16-bit BCD

The following code for ca65 converts a 16-bit unsigned integer to decimal digits, in roughly 700 cycles, without using the decimal mode that was removed from the 2A03.

To understand how curDigit is used, see Wikipedia:Ring counter.

; bcd16.s
; version 20060201
;
; Copyright (C) 2006 Damian Yerrick
;
; Copying and distribution of this file, with or without
; modification, are permitted in any medium without royalty provided
; the copyright notice and this notice are preserved in any source
; code copies.  This file is offered as-is, without any warranty.
;

.p02

.exportzp bcdNum, bcdResult
.export bcdConvert

; bcdConvert
;
; Given a number in bcdNum (16-bit), converts it to 5 decimal digits
; in bcdResult.  Unlike most 6502 binary-to-decimal converters, this
; subroutine doesn't use the decimal mode that was removed from the
; 2A03 variant of the 6502 processor.
;
; For each value of n from 4 to 1, it compares the number to 8*10^n,
; then 4*10^n, then 2*10^n, then 1*10^n, each time subtracting if
; possible. After finishing all the comparisons and subtractions in
; each decimal place value, it writes the digit to the output array
; as a byte value in the range [0, 9].  Finally, it writes the
; remainder to element 0.
;
; Extension to 24-bit and larger numbers is straightforward:
; Add a third bcdTable, increase BCD_BITS, and extend the
; trial subtraction.

; Constants _________________________________________________________
; BCD_BITS
;   The highest possible number of bits in the BCD output. Should
;   roughly equal 4 * log10(2) * x, where x is the width in bits
;   of the largest binary number to be put in bcdNum.
; bcdTableLo[y], bcdTableHi[y]
;   Contains (1 << y) converted from BCD to binary.
BCD_BITS = 19

; Variables _________________________________________________________
; bcdNum (input)
;   Number to be converted to decimal (16-bit little endian).
;   Overwritten.
; bcdResult (output)
;   Decimal digits of result (5-digit little endian).
; X
;   Offset of current digit being worked on.
; Y
;   Offset into bcdTable*.
; curDigit
;   The lower holds the digit being constructed.
;   The upper nibble contains a sentinel value; when a 1 is shifted
;   out, the byte is complete and should be copied to result.
;   (This behavior is called a "ring counter".)
;   Overwritten.
; b
;   Low byte of the result of trial subtraction.
;   Overwritten.
bcdNum = 0
bcdResult = 2
curDigit = 7
b = 2

;
; Completes within 670 cycles.
;

bcdConvert:
  lda #$80 >> ((BCD_BITS - 1) & 3)
  sta curDigit
  ldx #(BCD_BITS - 1) >> 2
  ldy #BCD_BITS - 5

@loop:
  ; Trial subtract this bit to A:b
  sec
  lda bcdNum
  sbc bcdTableLo,y
  sta b
  lda bcdNum+1
  sbc bcdTableHi,y

  ; If A:b > bcdNum then bcdNum = A:b
  bcc @trial_lower
  sta bcdNum+1
  lda b
  sta bcdNum
@trial_lower:

  ; Copy bit from carry into digit and pick up 
  ; end-of-digit sentinel into carry
  rol curDigit
  dey
  bcc @loop

  ; Copy digit into result
  lda curDigit
  sta bcdResult,x
  lda #$10  ; Empty digit; sentinel at 4 bits
  sta curDigit
  ; If there are digits left, do those
  dex
  bne @loop
  lda bcdNum
  sta bcdResult
  rts

bcdTableLo:
  .byt <10, <20, <40, <80
  .byt <100, <200, <400, <800
  .byt <1000, <2000, <4000, <8000
  .byt <10000, <20000, <40000

bcdTableHi:
  .byt >10, >20, >40, >80
  .byt >100, >200, >400, >800
  .byt >1000, >2000, >4000, >8000
  .byt >10000, >20000, >40000

See also

HexToDecimal.8

External links

Another 16-bit binary to decimal converter written in PIC assembly
Even faster converters by Omegamatrix

Categories: Arithmetic

6502 assembly optimisations

This page is about optimisations that are possible in assembly language, or various things one programmer has to keep in mind to make his code as optimal as possible.

There is two major kind of optimisations: Optimisation for speed (code executes in fewer cycles) and optimisation for size (the code takes fewer bytes).

There is also some other kinds of optimisations, such as constant-executing-time optimisation (code execute in a constant number of cycle no matter what it has to do), or RAM usage optimisation (use as few variables as possible). Because those optimisations have more to do with the algorithm than with its implementation in assembly, only speed and size optimisations will be discussed in this article.

Contents

1 Optimise both speed and size of the code

1.1 Avoid a jsr + rts chain
1.2 Split word tables in high and low components
1.3 Use Jump tables with RTS instruction instead of JMP indirect instruction
1.4 Use a macro instead of a subroutine which is only called once
1.5 Arithmetic shift right
1.6 Easily test 2 upper bits of a variable
1.7 Negating a value without temporaries
1.8 Avoiding the need for CLC/SEC with ADC/SBC
1.9 Test bits in decreasing order
1.10 Test bits in increasing order
1.11 Test bits without destroying the accumulator
1.12 Use opposite rotate instead of a great number of shifts

2 Optimise speed at the expense of size

2.1 Use identity look-up table instead of temp variable
2.2 Use look-up table to shift left 4 times

3 Optimise code size at the expense of cycles

3.1 Use the stack instead of a temp variable
3.2 Use an "intelligent" argument system
3.3 Using relative branch instruction instead of absolute

4 See also
5 Notes

Optimise both speed and size of the code

Avoid a jsr + rts chain

A tail call occurs when a subroutine finishes by calling another subroutine. This can be optimised into a JMP instruction:

MySubroutine
  lda Foo
  sta Bar
  jsr SomeRandomRoutine
  rts

becomes :

MySubroutine
  lda Foo
  sta Bar
  jmp SomeRandomRoutine

Savings : 9 cycles, 1 byte

Split word tables in high and low components

This optimisation is not human friendly, makes the source code much bigger, but still makes the compiled[1] size smaller and faster:

Example
  lda FooBar
  asl A
  tax
  lda PointerTable,X
  sta Temp
  lda PointerTable+1,X
  sta Temp+1
  ....

PointerTable
  .dw Pointer1, Pointer2, ....

Becomes :

Example
  ldx FooBar
  lda PointerTableL,X
  sta Temp
  lda PointerTableH,X
  sta Temp+1
  ....

PointerTableL
  .byt <Pointer1, <Pointer2, ....

PointerTableH
  .byt >Pointer1, >Pointer2, ....

Some assemblers may have a way to implement a macro to automatically make the table coded like this (Unofficial MagicKit Assembler is one such program).

Savings : 2 bytes, 4 cycles

Use Jump tables with RTS instruction instead of JMP indirect instruction

The so-called RTS Trick is a method of implementing jump tables by pushing a subroutine's entry point to the stack.

; This:

  ldx JumpEntry
  lda PointerTableL,X
  sta Temp
  lda PointerTableH,X
  sta Temp+1
  jmp [Temp]

; becomes this:

  ldx JumpEntry
  lda PointerTableH,X
  pha
  lda PointerTableL,X
  pha
  rts

Note that PointerTable entries must point to one byte before the intended target when the RTS trick is used, because RTS will add 1 to the offset.

Savings : 4 bytes, 1 cycle.

To squeeze slightly more, it's possible to combine this with the tail call optimization:

; This:

  jsr SomeOtherFunction  ; MUST NOT modify JumpEntry
  ldx JumpEntry
  lda PointerTableH,X
  pha
  lda PointerTableL,X
  pha
  rts

; Becomes this:

  ldx JumpEntry
  lda PointerTableH,X
  pha
  lda PointerTableL,X
  pha
  jmp SomeOtherFunction

Here, the CPU runs SomeOtherFunction, then returns to the function from the jump table, then returns to what called this dispatcher.

Use a macro instead of a subroutine which is only called once

What is the point to call a subroutine if you only call it at a single place? It would be more optimal to just insert the code where the subroutine is called. However this makes the code less structured and harder to understand. Inline expansion of a subroutine into another subroutine can be done with a macro. One drawback is that if the subroutine is called in a loop, it may require some JMPing to work around the 128-byte limit on branch length.

How macros are used depends on the assembler so no code examples will be placed here to avoid further confusion. In C, the static inline keyword acts as a hint to expand a function as a macro.

Savings : 4 bytes, 12 cycles.

Arithmetic shift right

Compact way to divide a variable by 2 but keep its sign:

   cmp #$80
   ror A

Easily test 2 upper bits of a variable

    lda FooBar
    asl A         ;C = b7, N = b6

Alternative:

    bit Foobar    ;N = b7, V = b6, regardless of the value of A.

This can be e.g. used to poll the sprite-0-hit flag in $2002.

Negating a value without temporaries

   eor #$FF
   clc
   adc #1

Avoiding the need for CLC/SEC with ADC/SBC

If you are using ADC #imm, and you know your carry is already cleared, you do not need to do CLC. However, if you know that carry is set (for example, your code is located in a branch that is only ever entered with a BCS instruction), you can still avoid using CLC by just doing ADC #(value-1). The PLOT subroutine in the Apple II Monitor uses this.

Similarly for SBC #imm: If you know know that carry is clear, you can still avoid using SEC by just doing SBC #(value+1).

Test bits in decreasing order

   lda foobar 
   bmi bit7_set 
   cmp #$40  ; we know that bit 7 wasn't set 
   bcs bit6_set 
   cmp #$20 
   bcs bit5_set 
             ; and so on

Or if you do not need to preserve the value of A:

   lda foobar 
   asl
   bcs bit7_set 
   asl
   bcs bit6_set 
   asl
   bcs bit5_set 
             ; and so on

This saves one byte per comparison, but 2 cycles more are used because of the extra ASL.

Test bits in increasing order

   lda foobar 
   lsr
   bcs bit0_set
   lsr
   bcs bit1_set
   lsr
   bcs bit2_set
             ; and so on

Note: This does not preserve the value of A.

Test bits without destroying the accumulator

The AND instruction can be used to test bits, but this destroy the value in the accumulator. The BIT can do this but it has no immediate adressing mode. A way to do it is to look for an opcode that has the bits you want to test, and use bit $xxxx on this opcode.

Example
   lda foobar
   and #$30
   beq bits_clear
   lda foobar
   ....

bits_clear
   lda foobar
   .....

becomes :

Example
   lda foobar
   bit _bmi_instruction ;equivalent to and #$30 but preserves A
   beq bits_clear
   ....

bits_clear
   .....

anywhere_in_the_code
    ....
_bmi_instruction    ;The BMI opcode = $30
    bmi somewhere

Savings : 2 cycles, 3 bytes

Use opposite rotate instead of a great number of shifts

To retrieve the 3 highest bits of a value in the low positions, you might be tempted to do 5 LSRs in a row. However, if you do not need the 5 top bits to be cleared, this is more efficient:

  lda value   ; got: 76543210 c
  rol         ; got: 6543210c 7
  rol         ; got: 543210c7 6 
  rol         ; got: 43210c76 5
  rol         ; got: 3210c765 4
  ; Only care about these ^^^

It works the same for replacing 5 ASLs with 4 RORs.

To replace 6 ASLs you can use 3 RORs:

  lda value   ; got: 76453210 c
  ror         ; got: c7654321 0
  ror         ; got: 0c765432 1
  ror         ; got: 10c76543 2
  and #$C0    ; got: 10------

Optimise speed at the expense of size

Those optimisations will make code faster to execute, but use more ROM. Therefore, it is useful in NMI routines and other things that need to run fast.

Use identity look-up table instead of temp variable

Example
    ldx Foo
    lda Bar
    stx Temp
    clc
    adc Temp    ;A = Foo + Bar

becomes :

Example
    ldx Foo
    lda Bar
    clc
    adc Identity,X    ;A = Foo + Bar

Identity
    .byt $00, $01, $02, $03, .....

If your program is very large, it is possible that this way uses slightly less ROM; also, it might save one byte of RAM in some circumstances.

Savings : 2 cycles

Use look-up table to shift left 4 times

Provided that the high nibble is already cleared, you can shift left by 4 by making a multiplication look-up table.

Example:
  lda rownum
  asl A
  asl A
  asl A
  asl A
  rts

becomes

Example:
  ldx rownum
  lda times_sixteen,x
  rts

times_sixteen:
  .byt $00, $10, $20, $30, $40, $50, $60, $70
  .byt $80, $90, $A0, $B0, $C0, $D0, $E0, $F0

In very large programs, this might save some ROM space. However, it will use up the X register, so it might not be ideal.

Savings: 4 cycles

Optimise code size at the expense of cycles

Those optimisations will produce code that is smaller but takes more cycles to execute. Therefore, it can be used in the parts of the program that do not have to be fast.

Use the stack instead of a temp variable

Example
   lda Foo
   sta Temp
   lda Bar
   ....
   ....
   lda Temp   ;Restores Foo
   .....

becomes:

Example
   lda Foo
   pha
   lda Bar
   ....
   ....
   pla   ;Restores Foo
   .....

Savings : 2 bytes.

Use an "intelligent" argument system

Each time a routine needs multiple bytes of arguments (>3) it's hard to code it without wasting a lot of bytes.

Example
   lda Argument1
   sta Temp
   lda Argument2
   ldx Argument3
   ldy Argument4
   jsr RoutineWhichNeeds4Args
   .....

Becomes something like:

Example
   jsr PassArguments
   .dw RoutineWhichNeeds4Args
   .db Argument1, Argument2, Argument3, Argument4
   .db $00
   ....

PassArguments
   pla 
   tay 
   pla 
   pha                    ; put the high byte back 
   sta pointer+1 
   ldx #$00 
   beq SKIP 
LOOP 
   sta parameters,x 
   inx 
SKIP 
   iny                    ; pointing one short first pass here fixes that 
   lda (pointer),y 
   bne LOOP      
   iny 
   lda (pointer),y 
   beq LOOP

   dey                    ; fix the return address guess we can't return to a 
                         ;  break        
   tya 
   pha 
   jmp (parameters)

Syscalls in Apple ProDOS[2] and FDS BIOS work this way.

Savings : Complicated to estimate - only saves bytes if the trick is used fairly often across the program, in order to compensate for the size of the PassArguments routine.

Using relative branch instruction instead of absolute

If the state of one of the processor flags is already known at this point and the branch target is not too far away, then you can use a condition branch instruction.

Savings : 1 byte.

See also

Synthetic instructions

Notes

↑ Pedants may complain that "compile" is incorrect terminology for "translate a program written in assembly language into object code". But it is the most familiar term meaning "translate a program, no matter the language, into object code", and the same issues apply to code generators within a compiler that targets the 6502 as to programs written in 6502 assembly language.
↑ ProDOS 8 Technical Reference Manual

Action 53 mapper/Reference implementations

These reference implementations of the PRG ROM bank formula in the Action 53 mapper (mapper 28) may be used to verify emulator or hardware implementations of this mapper.

Python

#!/usr/bin/env python3
from __future__ import print_function

bank_size_masks = [(2<<i)-1 for i in range(4)]  # 0x01, 0x03, 0x07, 0x0F

def calc_prg_bank(address, bank_mode, outer_bank, current_bank):
    """Calculate the 16K bank on A20-A14 for a given address.

address -- current address being accessed by the CPU,
    in range 0x8000-0xFFFF
bank_mode -- last value written to $80
outer_bank -- last value written to $81
current_bank -- last value written to $01

"""
    cpu_a14 = (address >> 14) & 0x01
    outer_bank = outer_bank << 1
    bank_mode >>= 2  # discard mirroring bits
    if (bank_mode ^ cpu_a14) & 0x03 == 0x02:  # in UNROM fixed bank?
        bank_mode = 0  # if so, treat as NROM
    if (bank_mode & 0x02) == 0:  # in 32K bank mode?
        current_bank = (current_bank << 1) | cpu_a14
    bank_size_mask = bank_size_masks[(bank_mode >> 2) & 3]
    return (current_bank & bank_size_mask) | (outer_bank & ~bank_size_mask)

def test_with_bank_mode_size(bank_mode, outer_bank):
    print("mode $%02x, outer bank $%02x" % (bank_mode, outer_bank))
    out80 = [calc_prg_bank(0x8000, bank_mode, outer_bank, current_bank)
         for current_bank in range(16)]
    print("$8000 banks:", " ".join("%02x" % i for i in out80))
    outC0 = [calc_prg_bank(0xC000, bank_mode, outer_bank, current_bank)
             for current_bank in range(16)]
    print("$C000 banks:", " ".join("%02x" % i for i in outC0))

for outer_bank in (0x00, 0x3C, 0x3F):
    test_with_bank_mode_size(0x28, outer_bank)
for outer_bank in (0x00, 0x03, 0x3F):
    test_with_bank_mode_size(0x2C, outer_bank)
for bank_mode in (0x00, 0x08, 0x0C, 0x10, 0x18, 0x1C,
                  0x20, 0x28, 0x2C, 0x30, 0x38, 0x3C):
    test_with_bank_mode_size(bank_mode, 0x2A)

6502 assembly

This routine appears in the test ROMs "test28" and "Holy Diver Batman".

;;
; Determines what 16 KiB PRG ROM bank ought to be mapped into a given
; CPU address with a given set of $80, $81, $00 values.
; For use in a test ROM that verifies mapper 28.
; @param A $80 value
; @param X $01 value
; @param Y $81 value
; @param C CPU A14 value: clear for $8000-$BFFF, set for $C000-$FFFF
; @return PRG bank number in A
.proc calc_prg_bank
bank_mode = 0
outer_bank = 1
current_bank = 2
  stx current_bank
  sty outer_bank
  rol outer_bank
  lsr a  ; discard mirroring bits
  lsr a
  sta bank_mode

  ; If the mode is UxROM (10 = mapper 180, 11 = mapper 2), and bit 0
  ; of the mode matches CPU A14, then the read is within the fixed
  ; bank.  For such reads, the mapper acts in 32K (NROM) mode.
  and #$02
  beq not_unrom
  lda outer_bank
  eor bank_mode
  ; If bit 0 of the eor result is false, there is a match, so
  ; fall through to the not-UNROM code.
  and #$01
  bne have_current_bank
  sta bank_mode

not_unrom:
  ; In 32K switched modes (NROM, CNROM, BNROM, AOROM),
  ; shift CPU A14 into the current bank
  lda outer_bank
  lsr a
  rol current_bank
  
have_current_bank:
  lda bank_mode
  lsr a
  lsr a
  and #$03
  tax
  lda current_bank
  eor outer_bank
  and bank_size_masks,x
  eor outer_bank
  rts
.endproc

.segment "RODATA"
bank_size_masks: .byt $01, $03, $07, $0F

APU

The NES APU is the audio processing unit in the NES console which generates sound for games. It is implemented in the RP2A03 (NTSC) and RP2A07 (PAL) chips. Its registers are mapped in the range $4000-$4013, $4015 and $4017.

Contents

1 Overview

1.1 Conditions for channel output
1.2 Notes

2 Specification

2.1 Registers
2.2 Pulse ($4000-4007)
2.3 Triangle ($4008-400B)
2.4 Noise ($400C-400F)
2.5 DMC ($4010-4013)

2.5.1 Other Uses

2.6 Status ($4015)
2.7 Frame Counter ($4017)

2.7.1 Length Counter

2.8 Mixer

3 Glossary
4 References

Overview

The APU has five channels: two pulse wave generators, a triangle wave, noise, and a delta modulation channel for playing DPCM samples.

Each channel has a variable-rate timer clocking a waveform generator, and various modulators driven by low-frequency clocks from the frame counter. The DMC plays samples while the other channels play waveforms. Each sub-unit of a channel generally runs independently and in parallel to other units, and modification of a channel's parameter usually affects only one sub-unit and doesn't take effect until that unit's next internal cycle begins.

The read/write status register allows channels to be enabled and disabled, and their current length counter status to be queried.

The outputs from all the channels are combined using a non-linear mixing scheme.

Conditions for channel output

The pulse, triangle, and noise channels will play their corresponding waveforms (at either a constant volume or at a volume controlled by an envelope) only when (and in the model given here, precisely when) their length counters are all non-zero (this includes the linear counter for the triangle channel). There are two exceptions for the pulse channels, which can also be silenced either by having a frequency above a certain threshold (see below), or by a sweep towards lower frequencies (longer periods) reaching the end of the range.

The DMC channel always outputs the value of its counter, regardless of the status of the DMC enable bit; the enable bit only controls automatic playback of delta-encoded samples (which is done through counter updates).

Notes

This reference describes the abstract operation of the APU. The exact hardware implementation is not necessarily relevant to an emulator, but the Visual 2A03 project can be used to determine detailed information about the hardware implementation.

The Famicom had an audio return loop on its cartridge connector allowing extra audio from individual cartridges. See Expansion audio for details on the audio produced by various mappers.

For a basic usage guide to the APU, see APU basics, or Nerdy Nights: APU overview.

The APU may have additional diagnostic features if CPU pin 30 is pulled high. See diagram by Quietust.

Specification

Registers

See APU Registers for a complete APU register diagram.

Registers | Channel | Units
$4000-$4003 | Pulse 1 | Timer, length counter, envelope, sweep
$4004-$4007 | Pulse 2 | Timer, length counter, envelope, sweep
$4008-$400B | Triangle | Timer, length counter, linear counter
$400C-$400F | Noise | Timer, length counter, envelope, linear feedback shift register
$4010-$4013 | DMC | Timer, memory reader, sample buffer, output unit
$4015 | All | Channel enable and length counter status
$4017 | All | Frame counter

Pulse ($4000-4007)

See APU Pulse

The pulse channels produce a variable-width pulse signal, controlled by volume, envelope, length, and sweep units.

$4000 / $4004 | DDLC VVVV | Duty (D), envelope loop / length counter halt (L), constant volume (C), volume/envelope (V)
$4001 / $4005 | EPPP NSSS | Sweep unit: enabled (E), period (P), negate (N), shift (S)
$4002 / $4006 | TTTT TTTT | Timer low (T)
$4003 / $4007 | LLLL LTTT | Length counter load (L), timer high (T)

The frequency of the pulse channels is a division of the CPU Clock (1.789773MHz NTSC, 1.662607MHz PAL). The output frequency (f) of the generator can be determined by the 11-bit period value (t) written to $4002-4003/$4006-4007. If t < 8, the corresponding pulse channel is silenced.

f = CPU / (16 * (t + 1))
t = (CPU / (16 * f)) - 1

The width of the pulse is controlled by the duty bits in $4000/4004. See APU Pulse for details.

The channel volume is a 4-bit value that is either constant, or controlled by an envelope (chosen by $4000/4004 bit 4). If using the envelope, the 4-bit value in $4000/4004 is the period of the envelope, otherwise it is the direct volume.

The length counter and envelope units are clocked by the frame counter. If the envelope is not looped, the length counter must be enabled (making it redundant if longer than the envelope). The length counter simply silences the channel when it counts down to 0. The envelope starts at a volume of 15 and decrements every time the unit is clocked, stopping at 0 if not looped.

Writing to $4003/4007 reloads the length counter, restarts the envelope, and resets the phase of the pulse generator. Because it resets phase, vibrato should only write the low timer register to avoid a phase reset click. At some pitches, particularly near A440, wide vibrato should normally be avoided (e.g. this flaw is heard throughout the Mega Man 2 ending).

Registers $4001/4005 control the sweep unit. Enabling the sweep causes the pitch to constantly rise or fall. When the frequency reaches the end of the generator's range of output the channel is silenced. See APU Sweep for details.

The two pulse channels are combined in a nonlinear mix (see mixer below).

Triangle ($4008-400B)

See APU Triangle

The triangle channel produces a quantized triangle wave. It has no volume control, but it has a length counter as well as a higher resolution linear counter control (called "linear" since it uses the 7-bit value written to $4008 directly instead of a lookup table like the length counter).

$4008 | CRRR RRRR | Length counter halt / linear counter control (C), linear counter load (R)
$4009 | ---- ---- | Unused
$400A | TTTT TTTT | Timer low (T)
$400B | LLLL LTTT | Length counter load (L), timer high (T)

The triangle wave has 32 steps that output a 4-bit value.

The linear counter control will silence the channel after a specified time with a resolution of 240Hz in NTSC (see frame counter below). It shares a control bit with the length counter in $4008, which means that they are always enabled at the same time, and whichever is longer is redundant. See APU Triangle for more linear counter details.

The pitch of the triangle channel is one octave below the pulse channels with an equivalent timer value (i.e. use the formula above but divide the resulting frequency by two).

Silencing the triangle channel merely halts it. It will continue to output its last value, rather than 0.

There is no way to reset the triangle channel's phase.

Noise ($400C-400F)

See APU Noise

The noise channel produces noise with a pseudo-random bit generator. It has a volume, envelope, and length counter like the pulse channels.

$400C | --LC VVVV | Envelope loop / length counter halt (L), constant volume (C), volume/envelope (V)
$400D | ---- ---- | Unused
$400E | L--- PPPP | Loop noise (L), noise period (P)
$400F | LLLL L--- | Length counter load (L)

The frequency of the noise is determined by a 4-bit value in $400E, which loads a period from a lookup table (see APU Noise).

If bit 7 of $400E is set, the period of the random bit generation is drastically shortened, producing a buzzing tone (e.g. the metalic ding during Solstice's gameplay). The actual timbre produced depends on whatever bits happen to be in the generator when it is switched to periodic, and is somewhat random.

DMC ($4010-4013)

See APU DMC

The delta modulation channel outputs a 7-bit PCM signal from a counter that can be driven by DPCM samples.

$4010 | IL-- RRRR | IRQ enable (I), loop (L), frequency (R)
$4011 | -DDD DDDD | Load counter (D)
$4012 | AAAA AAAA | Sample address (A)
$4013 | LLLL LLLL | Sample length (L)

DPCM samples are stored as a stream of 1-bit deltas that control the 7-bit PCM counter that the channel outputs. A bit of 1 will increment the counter, 0 will decrement, and it will clamp rather than overflow if the 7-bit range is exceeded.

DPCM samples may loop if the loop flag in $4010 is set, and the DMC may be used to generate an IRQ when the end of the sample is reached if its IRQ flag is set.

The playback rate is controlled by register $4010 with a 4-bit frequency index value (see APU DMC for frequency lookup tables).

DPCM samples must begin in the memory range $C000-FFFF at an address set by register $4012 (address = %11AAAAAA.AA000000).

The length of the sample in bytes is set by register $4013 (length = %LLLL.LLLL0001).

Other Uses

The $4011 register can be used to play PCM samples directly by setting the counter value at a high frequency. Because this requires intensive use of the CPU, when used in games all other gameplay is usually halted to facilitate this.

Because of the APU's nonlinear mixing, a high value in the PCM counter reduces the volume of the triangle and noise channels. This is sometimes used to apply limited volume control to the triangle channel (e.g. Super Mario Bros. adjusts the counter between levels to accomplish this).

The DMC's IRQ can be used as an IRQ based timer when the mapper used does not have one available.

Status ($4015)

The status register is used to enable and disable individual channels, control the DMC, and can read the status of length counters and APU interrupts.

$4015 write | ---D NT21 | Enable DMC (D), noise (N), triangle (T), and pulse channels (2/1)

Writing a zero to any of the channel enable bits will silence that channel and immediately set its length counter to 0.
If the DMC bit is clear, the DMC bytes remaining will be set to 0 and the DMC will silence when it empties.
If the DMC bit is set, the DMC sample will be restarted only if its bytes remaining is 0. If there are bits remaining in the 1-byte sample buffer, these will finish playing before the next sample is fetched.
Writing to this register clears the DMC interrupt flag.
Power-up and reset have the effect of writing $00, silencing all channels.

$4015 read | IF-D NT21 | DMC interrupt (I), frame interrupt (F), DMC active (D), length counter > 0 (N/T/2/1)

N/T/2/1 will read as 1 if the corresponding length counter is greater than 0. For the triangle channel, the status of the linear counter is irrelevant.
D will read as 1 if the DMC bytes remaining is more than 0.
Reading this register clears the frame interrupt flag (but not the DMC interrupt flag).
If an interrupt flag was set at the same moment of the read, it will read back as 1 but it will not be cleared.

Frame Counter ($4017)

See APU Frame Counter

$4017 | MI-- ---- | Mode (M, 0 = 4-step, 1 = 5-step), IRQ inhibit flag (I)

The frame counter is controlled by register $4017, and it drives the envelope, sweep, and length units on the pulse, triangle and noise channels. It ticks approximately 4 times per frame (240Hz NTSC), and executes either a 4 or 5 step sequence, depending how it is configured. It may optionally issue an IRQ on the last tick of the 4 step sequence.

The following diagram illustrates the two modes, selected by bit 7 of $4017:

mode 0:    mode 1:       function
---------  -----------  -----------------------------
 - - - f    - - - - -    IRQ (if bit 6 is clear)
 - l - l    l - l - -    Length counter and sweep
 e e e e    e e e e -    Envelope and linear counter

Both the 4 and 5-step modes operate at the same rate, but because the 5-step mode has an extra step, the effective update rate for individual units is slower in that mode (total update taking ~60Hz vs ~48Hz in NTSC). Writing to $4017 will restart the sequence almost immediately (2 or 3 CPU cycles delay). Writing $4017 with bit 7 set will immediately clock all of its controlled units at the beginning of the 5-step sequence, but with bit 7 clear only the sequence is reset without clocking any of its units.

Note that the frame counter is not exactly synchronized with the PPU NMI; it runs independently at a consistent rate which is approximately 240Hz (NTSC). Some games (e.g. Super Mario Bros., Zelda) manually synchronize it by writing $C0 or $FF to $4017 once per frame.

Length Counter

See APU Length Counter

The pulse, triangle, and noise channels each have their own length counter unit. It is clocked twice per sequence, and counts down to zero if enabled. When the length counter reaches zero the channel is silenced. It is reloaded by writing a 5-bit value to the appropriate channel's length counter register, which will load a value from a lookup table. (See APU Length Counter for the table.)

The triangle channel has an additional linear counter unit which is clocked four times per sequence (like the envelope of the other channels). It functions independently of the length counter, and will also silence the triangle channel when it reaches zero.

Mixer

See APU Mixer

The APU audio output signal comes from two separate components. The pulse channels are output on one pin, and the triangle/noise/DMC are output on another, after which they are combined. Each of these channels has its own nonlinear DAC. For details, see APU Mixer.

After combining the two output signals, the final signal may go through a lowpass and highpass filter. For instance, RF demodulation in televisions usually results in a strong lowpass. The NES' RCA output circuitry has a more mild lowpass filter.

Glossary

All APU channels have some form of frequency control. The term frequency is used where larger register value(s) correspond with higher frequencies, and the term period is used where smaller register value(s) correspond with higher frequencies.

In the block diagrams, a gate takes the input on the left and outputs it on the right, unless the control input on top tells the gate to ignore the input and always output 0.

Some APU units use one or more of the following building blocks:

A divider outputs a clock periodically. It contains a period reload value, P, and a counter, that starts at P. When the divider is clocked, if the counter is currently 0, it is reloaded with P and generates an output clock, otherwise the counter is decremented. In other words, the divider's period is P + 1.

A divider can also be forced to reload its counter immediately (counter = P), but this does not output a clock. Similarly, changing a divider's period reload value does not affect the counter.

A divider may be implemented as a down counter (5, 4, 3, ...) or as a linear feedback shift register (LFSR). The dividers in the pulse and triangle channels are linear down-counters. The dividers for noise, DMC, and the APU Frame Counter are implemented as LFSRs to save gates compared to the equivalent down counter.

A sequencer continuously loops over a sequence of values or events. When clocked, the next item in the sequence is generated.

A timer is used in each of the five channels to control the sound frequency. It contains a divider which is clocked by the CPU clock. The triangle channel's timer is clocked on every CPU cycle, but the pulse, noise, and DMC timers are clocked only on every second CPU cycle and thus produce only even periods.

References

Blargg's NES APU Reference.
Brad Taylor's 2A03 Technical Reference.

Categories: APU

APU DMC

The NES APU's delta modulation channel (DMC) can output 1-bit delta-encoded samples or can have its 7-bit counter directly loaded, allowing flexible manual sample playback.

Contents

1 Overview

1.1 Pitch table
1.2 Memory reader
1.3 Output unit

2 Conflict with controller and PPU read

2.1 Likely internal implementation of the read

3 Usage of DMC for syncing to video

3.1 Concept
3.2 Timing table
3.3 Number of scanlines to wait table

4 References

Overview

The DMC channel contains the following: memory reader, interrupt flag, sample buffer, timer, output unit, 7-bit output level with up and down counter.

                         Timer
                           |
                           v
Reader ---> Buffer ---> Shifter ---> Output level ---> (to the mixer)

$4010 | IL--.RRRR | Flags and Rate (write)
bit 7 | I---.---- | IRQ enabled flag. If clear, the interrupt flag is cleared.
bit 6 | -L--.---- | Loop flag
bits 3-0 | ----.RRRR | Rate index

Rate   $0   $1   $2   $3   $4   $5   $6   $7   $8   $9   $A   $B   $C   $D   $E   $F
      ------------------------------------------------------------------------------
NTSC  428, 380, 340, 320, 286, 254, 226, 214, 190, 160, 142, 128, 106,  84,  72,  54
PAL   398, 354, 316, 298, 276, 236, 210, 198, 176, 148, 132, 118,  98,  78,  66,  50

The rate determines for how many CPU cycles happen between changes in the output level during automatic delta-encoded sample playback. For example, on NTSC (1.789773 MHz), a rate of 428 gives a frequency of 1789773/428 Hz = 4181.71 Hz. These periods are all even numbers because there are 2 APU cycles in a CPU cycle. A rate of 428 means the output level changes every 214 APU cycles.

$4011 | -DDD.DDDD | Direct load (write)
bits 6-0 | -DDD.DDDD | The DMC output level is set to D, an unsigned value. If the timer is outputting a clock at the same time, the output level is occasionally not changed properly.[1]

$4012 | AAAA.AAAA | Sample address (write)
bits 7-0 | AAAA.AAAA | Sample address = %11AAAAAA.AA000000 = $C000 + (A * 64)

$4013 | LLLL.LLLL | Sample length (write)
bits 7-0 | LLLL.LLLL | Sample length = %LLLL.LLLL0001 = (L * 16) + 1

The output level is sent to the mixer whether the channel is enabled or not. It is loaded with 0 on power-up, and can be updated by $4011 writes and delta-encoded sample playback.

Automatic 1-bit delta-encoded sample playback is carried out by a combination of three units. The memory reader fills the 8-bit sample buffer whenever it is emptied by the sample output unit. The status register is used to start and stop automatic sample playback.

The sample buffer either holds a single 8-bit sample byte or is empty. It is filled by the reader and can only be emptied by the output unit; once loaded with a sample byte it will be played back.

Pitch table

| NTSC | PAL
$4010 | Period | Frequency | Note | Period | Frequency | Note
$0 | $1AC | 4181.71 Hz | C-8 -1.78c | $18E | 4177.40 Hz | C-8 -3.56c
$1 | $17C | 4709.93 Hz | D-8 +4.16c | $162 | 4696.63 Hz | D-8 -.739c
$2 | $154 | 5264.04 Hz | E-8 -3.29c | $13C | 5261.41 Hz | E-8 -4.15c
$3 | $140 | 5593.04 Hz | F-8 +1.67c | $12A | 5579.22 Hz | F-8 -2.61c
$4 | $11E | 6257.95 Hz | G-8 -3.86c | $114 | 6023.94 Hz | F#8 +30.2c
$5 | $0FE | 7046.35 Hz | A-8 +1.56c | $0EC | 7044.94 Hz | A-8 +1.22c
$6 | $0E2 | 7919.35 Hz | B-8 +3.77c | $0D2 | 7917.18 Hz | B-8 +3.29c
$7 | $0D6 | 8363.42 Hz | C-9 -1.78c | $0C6 | 8397.01 Hz | C-9 +5.16c
$8 | $0BE | 9419.86 Hz | D-9 +4.16c | $0B0 | 9446.63 Hz | D-9 +9.07c
$9 | $0A0 | 11186.1 Hz | F-9 +1.67c | $094 | 11233.8 Hz | F-9 +9.04c
$A | $08E | 12604.0 Hz | G-9 +8.29c | $084 | 12595.5 Hz | G-9 +7.11c
$B | $080 | 13982.6 Hz | A-9 -12.0c | $076 | 14089.9 Hz | A-9 +1.22c
$C | $06A | 16884.6 Hz | C-10 +14.5c | $062 | 16965.4 Hz | C-10 +22.7c
$D | $054 | 21306.8 Hz | E-10 +17.2c | $04E | 21315.5 Hz | E-10 +17.9c
$E | $048 | 24858.0 Hz | G-10 -15.9c | $042 | 25191.0 Hz | G-10 +7.11c
$F | $036 | 33143.9 Hz | C-11 -17.9c | $032 | 33252.1 Hz | C-11 -12.2c

(Deviation from note is given in cents, which are defined as 1/100 of a semitone.)

Note that on PAL systems, the pitches at $4 and $C appear to be slightly incorrect with respect to their intended A-440 tuning scheme[1].

Memory reader

When the sample buffer is emptied, the memory reader fills the sample buffer with the next byte from the currently playing sample. It has an address counter and a bytes remaining counter.

When a sample is (re)started, the current address is set to the sample address, and bytes remaining is set to the sample length.

Any time the sample buffer is in an empty state and bytes remaining is not zero (including just after a write to $4015 that enables the channel, regardless of where that write occurs relative to the bit counter mentioned below), the following occur:

The CPU is stalled for up to 4 CPU cycles to allow the longest possible write (the return address and write after an IRQ) to finish. If OAM DMA is in progress, it is paused for two cycles.[2]
The sample buffer is filled with the next sample byte read from the current address, subject to whatever mapping hardware is present.
The address is incremented; if it exceeds $FFFF, it is wrapped around to $8000.
The bytes remaining counter is decremented; if it becomes zero and the loop flag is set, the sample is restarted (see above); otherwise, if the bytes remaining counter becomes zero and the IRQ enabled flag is set, the interrupt flag is set.

At any time, if the interrupt flag is set, the CPU's IRQ line is continuously asserted until the interrupt flag is cleared. The processor will continue on from where it was stalled.

Output unit

The output unit continuously outputs a 7-bit value to the mixer. It contains an 8-bit right shift register, a bits-remaining counter, a 7-bit output level (the same one that can be loaded directly via $4011), and a silence flag.

The bits-remaining counter is updated whenever the timer outputs a clock, regardless of whether a sample is currently playing. When this counter reaches zero, we say that the output cycle ends. The DPCM unit can only transition from silent to playing at the end of an output cycle.

When an output cycle ends, a new cycle is started as follows:

The bits-remaining counter is loaded with 8.
If the sample buffer is empty, then the silence flag is set; otherwise, the silence flag is cleared and the sample buffer is emptied into the shift register.

When the timer outputs a clock, the following actions occur in order:

If the silence flag is clear, the output level changes based on bit 0 of the shift register. If the bit is 1, add 2; otherwise, subtract 2. But if adding or subtracting 2 would cause the output level to leave the 0-127 range, leave the output level unchanged. This means subtract 2 only if the current level is at least 2, or add 2 only if the current level is at most 125.
The right shift register is clocked.
As stated above, the bits-remaining counter is decremented. If it becomes zero, a new output cycle is started.

Nothing can interrupt a cycle; every cycle runs to completion before a new cycle is started.

Conflict with controller and PPU read

On the NTSC NES and Famicom, if a new sample byte is fetched from memory at the same time the program is reading the controller through $4016/4017, a conflict occurs corrupting the data read from the controller. Programs which use DPCM sample playback will normally use a redundant controller read routine to work around this defect.

A similar problem occurs when reading data from the PPU through $2007, or polling $2002 for vblank.

Likely internal implementation of the read

The following is speculation, and thus not necessarily 100% accurate. It does accurately predict observed behavior.

The 6502 cannot be pulled off of the bus normally. The 2A03 DMC gets around this by pulling RDY low internally. This causes the CPU to pause during the next read cycle, until RDY goes high again. The DMC unit holds RDY low for 4 cycles. The first three cycles it idles, as the CPU could have just started an interrupt cycle, and thus be writing for 3 consecutive cycles (and thus ignoring RDY). On the fourth cycle, the DMC unit drives the next sample address onto the address lines, and reads that byte from memory. It then drives RDY high again, and the CPU picks up where it left off.

This matters because on NTSC NES and Famicom, it can interfere with the expected operation of any register where reads have a side effect: the controller registers ($4016 and $4017), reads of the PPU status register ($2002), and reads of VRAM/VROM data ($2007) if they happen to occur in the same cycle that the DMC unit pulls RDY low.

For the controller registers, this can cause an extra rising clock edge to occur, and thus shift an extra bit out. For the others, the PPU will see multiple reads, which will cause extra increments of the address latches, or clear the vblank flag.

This problem has been fixed on the 2A07 and PAL NES is exempt of this bug.

Usage of DMC for syncing to video

DMC IRQs can be used for timed video operations. The following method was discussed on the forum in 2010.[2]

Concept

The NES hardware only has limited tools for syncing the code with video rendering. The VBlank NMI and sprite zero hit are the only two reasonably reliable flags that can be used, so only 2 synchronizations per frame are doable easily. In addition, only the VBlank NMI can trigger an interrupt, the sprite zero flag has to be polled, potentially wasting a lot of CPU cycles.

However, the DMC channel can hypothetically be used for syncing with video instead of using it for sound. Unfortunately it's a bit complicated, but used correctly, it can function as a crude scanline counter, eliminating the need for an advanced mapper.

The DMC's timing is completely separate from the video (obviously, it being an audio component). The DMC's timer is always running, and samples can only start every 8 clocks. However, because the DMC's timer isn't synchronized to the PPU in any way, these 8-clock boundaries occur on different scanlines each frame.

To achieve stable timing, this is what you do:

At a fixed time in rendering (we'll use the start of vblank as an example), start a dummy single-byte sample at rate $F. Due to a hardware quirk†, the sample needs to be started three times in a row like this:

sei
lda #$10 
sta $4015 
sta $4015 
sta $4015 
cli

Use any method to count how many cycles pass before the DMC IRQ happens (you can use an actual IRQ, or poll $4015).

At rate $F, there are 54 CPU cycles between clocks, so there are 432 CPU cycles (432 × 3 ÷ 341 = about 3.8 scanlines) between boundaries. In order to synchronize with vblank, after a DMC IRQ you should wait 432 CPU cycles minus the time you measured,

Start the actual sample that will be used for the timing.
When the IRQ happens, use your measurement from before to delay your program, and you'll synchronize the interrupt to vblank.

†Note: The hardware quirk mentioned above deals with how DMC IRQs are generated. Basically, the IRQ is generated when the last byte of the sample is read, not when the last sample of the sample plays. The sample buffer sometimes has enough time to empty itself between your writes to $4015, meaning your next write to $4015 will trigger an immediate IRQ. Fortunately, writing to $4015 three times will avoid this issue.

Still using vblank as an example, the measurement you take will tell you how far into the 8-clock boundary vblank occured, and by delaying after a DMC IRQ, you can perform a raster effect at the same point within the 8-clock boundary, aligning it with vblank. If you perform this same method each frame, your raster effect will have a reasonably stable timing to it. As a bonus, since you're mostly using IRQs, the CPU is free to do something else, instead of waiting in a timed loop.

It's possible to use more than one IRQ per frame - but you need to do the measurement part at the same time within each frame, before you use any of the IRQs.

You can only have one split-point per IRQ, with the shortest IRQ being 3.8 scanlines. If you want them closer together, you must use timed code.

You should also make sure your samples are made up of all $00 bytes, and that you've written $00 to $4011 at some point. Otherwise, you might unintentionally create audio. This is a sound channel, after all.

Timing table

This table converts sample length in scanline length (all values are rounded to the higher integer).

NTSC               Rate 
Length              $0    $1   $2   $3   $4   $5   $6   $7   $8   $9   $a   $b   $c   $d   $e   $f 
---------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------- 
1-byte (8 bits)     31    27   24   23   21   18   16   16   14   12   10   10   8    6    6    4 
17-byte (136 bits)  **    **   **   **   **   **   **   **   228  192  170  154  127  101  87   65 
33-byte (264 bits)  **    **   **   **   **   **   **   **   **   **   **   **   **   196  168  126 
49-byte (392 bits)  **    **   **   **   **   **   **   **   **   **   **   **   **   **   **   187 

PAL                Rate 
Length              $0    $1   $2   $3   $4   $5   $6   $7   $8   $9   $a   $b   $c   $d   $e   $f 
---------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------- 
1-byte (8 bits)     30    27   24   23   21   18   16   15   14   12   10   9    8    6    5    4 
17-byte (136 bits)  **    **   **   **   **   **   **   **   225  189  169  151  126  100  85   64 
33-byte (264 bits)  **    **   **   **   **   **   **   **   **   **   **   **   **   194  164  124 
49-byte (392 bits)  **    **   **   **   **   **   **   **   **   **   **   **   **   **   **   184

Number of scanlines to wait table

This table gives the best sample length and frequency combinations for all possible scanlines interval to wait. They are best because they are where the CPU will have to kill the less time. However it's still possible to use options to wait for fewer lines and kill more time during the interrupt before the video effect.

Because a PAL interrupt will always happen about the same time or a bit sooner than a NTSC interrupt, the NTSC table will be used to set the "best" setting here :

Scanlines  Best opt. for IRQ 
 
1-3        Timed code 
4-5        Length $0, rate $f 
6-7        Length $0, rate $d 
8-9        Length $0, rate $c 
10-11      Length $0, rate $a 
12-13      Length $0, rate $9 
14-15      Length $0, rate $8 
16-17      Length $0, rate $6 
18-20      Length $0, rate $5 
21-22      Length $0, rate $4 
23         Length $0, rate $3 
24-26      Length $0, rate $2 
27-30      Length $0, rate $1 
31-64      Length $0, rate $0 
65-86      Length $1, rate $f 
87-100     Length $1, rate $e 
101-125    Length $1, rate $d 
126        Length $2, rate $f 
127-153    Length $1, rate $c 
154-167    Length $1, rate $b 
168-169    Length $2, rate $e 
170-186    Length $1, rate $a 
187-191    Length $3, rate $f 
192-195    Length $1, rate $9 
196-227    Length $2, rate $d 
228-239    Length $1, rate $8

References

↑ Forum post: PAL DPCM frequency table contains 2 errors.
↑ Forum thread: DMC IRQ as a video timer.

Categories: APU

APU Envelope

In a synthesizer, an envelope is the way a sound's parameter changes over time. The NES APU has an envelope generator that controls the volume in one of two ways: it can generate a decreasing saw envelope (like a decay phase of an ADSR) with optional looping, or it can generate a constant volume that a more sophisticated software envelope generator can manipulate.

Each volume envelope unit contains the following: start flag, divider, and decay level counter.

                                   Loop flag
                                        |
               Start flag  +--------.   |   Constant volume
                           |        |   |        flag
                           v        v   v          |
Quarter frame clock --> Divider --> Decay --> |    | 
                           ^        level     |    v
                           |                  | Select --> Envelope output
                           |                  |
        Envelope parameter +----------------> |                   

Address | Bitfield | Description
$4000 | ddLC.VVVV | Pulse channel 1 duty and volume/envelope (write)
$4004 | ddLC.VVVV | Pulse channel 2 duty and volume/envelope (write)
$400C | --LC.VVVV | Noise channel volume/envelope (write)
bit 5 | --L- ---- | APU Length Counter halt flag/envelope loop flag
bit 4 | ---C ---- | Constant volume flag (0: use volume from envelope; 1: use constant volume)
bits 3-0 | ---- VVVV | Used as the volume in constant volume (C set) mode. Also used as the reload value for the envelope's divider (the period becomes V + 1).

$4003 | LLLL.Lttt | Pulse channel 1 length counter load and timer (write)
$4007 | LLLL.Lttt | Pulse channel 2 length counter load and timer (write)
$400F | LLLL.L--- | Noise channel length counter load (write)
Side effects | Sets start flag

When clocked by the frame counter, one of two actions occurs: if the start flag is clear, the divider is clocked, otherwise the start flag is cleared, the decay level counter is loaded with 15, and the divider's period is immediately reloaded.

When the divider is clocked while at 0, it is loaded with V and clocks the decay level counter. Then one of two actions occurs: If the counter is non-zero, it is decremented, otherwise if the loop flag is set, the decay level counter is loaded with 15.

The envelope unit's volume output depends on the constant volume flag: if set, the envelope parameter directly sets the volume, otherwise the decay level is the current volume. The constant volume flag has no effect besides selecting the volume source; the decay level will still be updated when constant volume is selected.

Each of the three envelope units' output is fed through additional gates at the sweep unit (pulse only), waveform generator (sequencer or LFSR), and length counter.

Categories: APU

APU Frame Counter

The NES APU frame counter (or frame sequencer) generates low-frequency clocks for the channels and an optional 60 Hz interrupt. The name "frame counter" might be slightly misleading because the clocks have nothing to do with the video signal.

The frame counter contains the following: divider, looping clock sequencer, frame interrupt flag.

The sequencer is clocked on every other CPU cycle, so 2 CPU cycles = 1 APU cycle. The sequencer keeps track of how many APU cycles have elapsed in total, and each step of the sequence will occur once that total has reached the indicated amount (with an additional delay of one CPU cycle for the quarter and half frame signals). Once the last step has executed, the count resets to 0 on the next APU cycle.

Address | Bitfield | Description
$4017 | MI--.---- | Set mode and interrupt (write)
Bit 7 | M--- ---- | Sequencer mode: 0 selects 4-step sequence, 1 selects 5-step sequence
Bit 6 | -I-- ---- | Interrupt inhibit flag. If set, the frame interrupt flag is cleared, otherwise it is unaffected.
Side effects | After 3 or 4 CPU clock cycles*, the timer is reset.
If the mode flag is set, then both "quarter frame" and "half frame" signals are also generated.

* If the write occurs during an APU cycle, the effects occur 3 CPU cycles after the $4017 write cycle, and if the write occurs between APU cycles, the effects occurs 4 CPU cycles after the write cycle.

TODO: describe PAL

The frame interrupt flag is connected to the CPU's IRQ line. It is set at a particular point in the 4-step sequence (see below) provided the interrupt inhibit flag in $4017 is clear, and can be cleared either by reading $4015 (which also returns its old status) or by setting the interrupt inhibit flag.

Mode 0: 4-Step Sequence (bit 7 of $4017 clear)

Step | APU cycles | Envelopes & triangle's linear counter (Quarter frame) | Length counters & sweep units (Half frame) | Frame interrupt flag
1 | 3728.5 | Clock |   |
2 | 7456.5 | Clock | Clock |
3 | 11185.5 | Clock |   |
4 | 14914 |   |   | Set if interrupt inhibit is clear
| 14914.5 | Clock | Clock | Set if interrupt inhibit is clear
| 0 (14915) |   |   | Set if interrupt inhibit is clear
|   | 240 Hz (approx.) | 120 Hz (approx.) | 60 Hz (approx.)

In this mode, the interrupt flag is set every 29830 CPU cycles, which is slightly slower than the 29780.5 CPU cycles per NTSC PPU frame.

Some Nintendo arcade boards, even those not directly based on the NES, use the 2A03 CPU as a sound processor. Examples include Punch-Out!! and Donkey Kong 3. This IRQ allows the CPU to keep time even if no PPU is connected to the bus.

Mode 1: 5-Step Sequence (bit 7 of $4017 set)

Step | APU cycles | Envelopes & triangle's linear counter (Quarter frame) | Length counters & sweep units (Half frame)
1 | 3728.5 | Clock |
2 | 7456.5 | Clock | Clock
3 | 11185.5 | Clock |
4 | 14914.5 |   |
5 | 18640.5 | Clock | Clock
| 0 (18641) |   |
|   | 192 Hz (approx.), uneven timing | 96 Hz (approx.), uneven timing

In this mode, the frame interrupt flag is never set.
Note: Writing to $4017 with bit 7 set will immediately generate a clock for both the quarter frame and the half frame units, regardless of what the sequencer is doing.

Categories: APU

APU Pulse

Each of the two NES APU pulse (square) wave channels generate a pulse wave with variable duty.

Each pulse channel contains the following: envelope generator, sweep unit, timer, 8-step sequencer, length counter.

                     Sweep -----> Timer
                       |            |
                       |            |
                       |            v 
                       |        Sequencer   Length Counter
                       |            |             |
                       |            |             |
                       v            v             v
    Envelope -------> Gate -----> Gate -------> Gate --->(to mixer)

Address | Bitfield | Description
$4000 | DDlc.vvvv | Pulse 1 duty, length counter halt, constant volume/envelope flag, and volume/envelope divider period (write)
$4004 | DDlc.vvvv | Pulse 2 duty, length counter halt, constant volume/envelope flag, and volume/envelope divider period (write)
bits 7-6 | DD-- ---- | The duty cycle is set (see table below). The sequencer's current position is not changed.

$4002 | LLLL.LLLL | Pulse 1 timer low (write)
$4006 | LLLL.LLLL | Pulse 2 timer low (write)
bits 7-0 | LLLL LLLL | Timer low 8 bits

$4003 | llll.lHHH | Pulse 1 length counter load and timer high (write)
$4007 | llll.lHHH | Pulse 2 length counter load and timer high (write)
bits 2-0 | ---- -HHH | Timer high 3 bits
Side effects | The sequencer is restarted at the first value of the current sequence. The envelope is also restarted.

Duty Cycle Sequences

Duty | Waveform sequence
0 | 0 1 0 0 0 0 0 0 (12.5%)
1 | 0 1 1 0 0 0 0 0 (25%)
2 | 0 1 1 1 1 0 0 0 (50%)
3 | 1 0 0 1 1 1 1 1 (25% negated)

The reason for these odd sequences is that the sequence counter is initialized to zero but counts downward rather than upward

The sequencer is clocked by an 11-bit timer. Given the timer value t = HHHLLLLLLLL formed by timer high and timer low, this timer is updated every APU cycle (i.e., every second CPU cycle), and counts t, t-1, ..., 0, t, t-1, ..., clocking the waveform generator when it goes from 0 to t. Since the period of the timer is t+1 APU cycles and the sequencer has 8 steps, the period of the waveform is 8*(t+1) APU cycles, or equivalently 16*(t+1) CPU cycles.

Hence

fpulse = fCPU/(16*(t+1)) (where fCPU is 1.789773 MHz for NTSC, 1.662607 MHz for PAL, and 1.773448 MHz for Dendy)
t = fCPU/(16*fpulse) - 1

A period of t < 8, either set explicitly or via a sweep period update, silences the corresponding pulse channel. The highest frequency a pulse channel can output is hence about 12.4 kHz for NTSC. (TODO: PAL behavior?)

The mixer receives the current envelope volume except when

The sequencer output is zero, or
overflow from the sweep unit's adder is silencing the channel, or
the length counter is zero, or
the timer has a value less than eight.

The behavior of the two pulse channels differs only in the effect of the negate mode of their sweep units.

Notice that a few Famiclone units have swapped APU duty cycles, as 12.5, 50, 25 and 25 negated instead.

Categories: APU

APU Triangle

The NES APU triangle channel generates a pseudo-triangle wave. It has no volume control; the waveform is either cycling or suspended. It includes a linear counter, an extra duration timer of higher accuracy than the length counter.

The triangle channel contains the following: timer, length counter, linear counter, linear counter reload flag, control flag, sequencer.

      Linear Counter   Length Counter
            |                |
            v                v
Timer ---> Gate ----------> Gate ---> Sequencer ---> (to mixer)

$4008 | CRRR.RRRR | Linear counter setup (write)
bit 7 | C---.---- | Control flag (this bit is also the length counter halt flag)
bits 6-0 | -RRR RRRR | Counter reload value

$400A | LLLL.LLLL | Timer low (write)
bits 7-0 | LLLL LLLL | Timer low 8 bits

$400B | llll.lHHH | Length counter load and timer high (write)
bits 2-0 | ---- -HHH | Timer high 3 bits
Side effects | Sets the linear counter reload flag

The sequencer is clocked by a timer whose period is the 11-bit value (%HHH.LLLLLLLL) formed by timer high and timer low, plus one. Given t = HHHLLLLLLLL, the timer counts t, t-1, ..., 0, t, t-1, ..., clocking the waveform generator when it goes from 0 to t. Unlike the pulse channels, this timer ticks at the rate of the CPU clock rather than the APU (CPU/2) clock. So given the following:

fCPU = the clock rate of the CPU
tval = the value written to the timer high and low registers
f = the frequency of the wave generated by this channel

The following relationships hold:

f = fCPU/(32*(tval + 1))
tval = fCPU/(32*f) - 1

Unlike the pulse channels, the triangle channel supports frequencies up to the maximum frequency the timer will allow, meaning frequencies up to fCPU/32 (about 55.9 kHz for NTSC) are possible - far above the audible range. Some games, e.g. Mega Man 2, "silence" the triangle channel by setting the timer to zero, which produces a popping sound when an audible frequency is resumed, easily heard e.g. in Crash Man's stage. At the expense of accuracy, these can be eliminated in an emulator e.g. by halting the triangle channel when an ultrasonic frequency is set (a timer value less than 2).

When the frame counter generates a linear counter clock, the following actions occur in order:

If the linear counter reload flag is set, the linear counter is reloaded with the counter reload value, otherwise if the linear counter is non-zero, it is decremented.
If the control flag is clear, the linear counter reload flag is cleared.

The sequencer is clocked by the timer as long as both the linear counter and the length counter are nonzero.

The sequencer sends the following looping 32-step sequence of values to the mixer:

15, 14, 13, 12, 11, 10,  9,  8,  7,  6,  5,  4,  3,  2,  1,  0
 0,  1,  2,  3,  4,  5,  6,  7,  8,  9, 10, 11, 12, 13, 14, 15

At the lowest two timer periods ($400B = 0 and $400A = 0 or 1), the resulting frequency is so high (over 20 kHz) that the mixer effectively receives a value half way between 7 and 8.
Note: If you're using this to silence the triangle channel, be aware that this makes a popping noise, because the triangle output is basically jumping to "7.5", from wherever it was before (could be 0 or 15). Mega Man 1 and 2 do this.

If that's undesirable, then there are three other ways to silence the triangle channel:

Use the linear counter to control the length of the note. This may be a bit limiting, because the linear counter doesn't allow for super-long notes.
Use $4015 to turn off the triangle channel when it needs to be silent (don't forget to turn it back on). However, writing to $4015 may cause problems if you're using the DMC.
Use the following writes when you want to silence the triangle channel:

Write $00 to $4008. This sets the linear counter to 0.
Write to $400B. This is to reload the linear counter with that 0. Be careful, because this register contains 3 bits of the triangle channel's period. You'd either need to rewrite the same value to this register, or write $07 to change the period to something low pitched and unnoticable.
Write to $4017 with bit 7 set. This will immediately clock the linear counter, reloading it, and silencing the triangle channel. This step is optional, but if you don't do this, there will be a random delay before the triangle channel is actually silenced, which is why it's important to pay attention to what you write to $400B in the previous step.

If you want to use the things that depend on the frame counter, you can simply write to $4017 every frame at the end of your music routine, instead of compulsively writing to $4017 only when you want to silence the triangle channel. This will keep the frame counter's sequencer consistent.

Categories: APU

Arkanoid controller

The Arkanoid Vaus controller was included with the Arkanoid game, and is only used for this game and Chase HQ. It has an control knob connected to a potentiometer and a single fire button. Under a small black plastic cover is another potentiometer to adjust the control knob's range.

            ,--------------------------------------.   |
            |                  %%                  |   |
            |   ,---.          %%                % |   |
            |  /     \         %%         ,-.   %% |   |
 Control  ->| |       |        %%        (   )  %% |<- Fire button
   knob     |  \     /         %%         `-'   %% |   |    
            |   `---'          %%                % |==/
Adjustment->|     ()           %%                  |
   screw    `--------------------------------------'

The Famicom version of this controller uses D1 (Famicom) on both ports. The NES version uses D3 and D4, usually in port 2 ($4017). The controller will not work in a Four Score.

Input ($4016 write)

7  bit  0
---- ----
xxxx xxxS
        |
        +- Control knob shift register strobe

Writing 1 to this bit will record the state of the control knob. Writing 0 afterwards will allow the position to be read back.

The analog to digital conversion takes about 7 ms, so strobing too fast will return bad data, especially at the right side of the range. A function that reads the controller multiple times in a row to avoid DPCM glitches may not work. Instead, check for spurious accelerations, where the second difference xt - 2xt - 1 + xt - 2 exceeds about eight units.

Output ($4016/$4017 read)

Famicom:

$4016:
7  bit  0
---- ----
xxxx xxBx
       |
       +-- Fire button (1: pressed)

$4017:
7  bit  0
---- ----
xxxx xxDx
       |
       +-- Serial control knob data

NES:

7  bit  0
---- ----
xxxD Bxxx
   | |
   | +---- Fire button (1: pressed)
   +------ Serial control knob data

Button status is returned in D3, and does not need to be latched. However, making sure it reads the same way eight times is a good way to distinguish it from a Power Pad, and reading it several times during a frame should distinguish it from the light sensor of a Zapper.

Control knob data is returned in D4, MSB first. The data is also inverted. The whole range is about 180 degrees, and returned in $A0 steps.

Variations in the analog to digital and pot physical range can vary the result slightly. With the trim pot at minimum the range returned is $0D-$AD. With the trim pot at maximum the range returned is $5C-$FC.

The Arkanoid game expects the range to be $54-$F4; the manual explains how to adjust the trimpot. New games can work at any trim pot setting by storing the maximum and minimum values seen during a play session and assuming values within ±80 units of the center of this range.

Test ROMs

Vaus Test shows adaptation to trimpot setting, repeated read rate, and first and second differences

Categories: Controllers

Bandai FCG board

Bandai FCG boards are used largely by Bandai for Dragon Ball and Gundam games, as well as a few others. One IREM title uses it as well.

Contents

1 Overview
2 Hardware Types
3 Banks
4 Registers

4.1 CHR bank select (BASE+0 … BASE+7)

4.1.1 Mappers 16 and 159:
4.1.2 Mapper 153 ($8000-$8003 only):
4.1.3 External Serial EEPROM Clock ($8000 … $8003)

4.2 PRG Bank select (BASE+8)
4.3 Mirroring Control (BASE+9)
4.4 IRQ Control (BASE+$A)
4.5 IRQ Counter (BASE+$B … BASE+$C)
4.6 EEPROM Control ($800D)
4.7 PRG RAM Enable ($800D)
4.8 Serial EEPROM ($6000-$7FFF)

5 Extra comments
6 Disch's notes
7 See Also

Overview

PRG ROM size: 256 KiB normally; 512KiB in one variant
PRG ROM bank size: 16 KiB
Nonvolatile memory: 0, 128, 256, or 8192 bytes
CHR capacity: Up to 256 KiB ROM or 8 KiB RAM
CHR bank size: 1 KiB
Nametable mirroring: Controlled by mapper
Subject to bus conflicts: No

Hardware Types

There are at least 6 different varieties of FCG board:

FCG-1 and FCG-2: Registers are at $6000-$7FFF. No persistent writable storage.
LZ93D50, sometimes erroneously known as FCG-3: Registers are at $8000-$FFFF. No persistent writable storage.
LZ93D50 with 24C01: Registers are at $8000-$FFFF. 24C01 128-byte serial EEPROM is attached to $6000-$7FFF.
LZ93D50 with 24C02: Registers are at $8000-$FFFF. 24C02 256-byte serial EEPROM is attached to $6000-$7FFF.
LZ93D50 with SRAM: Registers are at $8000-$FFFF. Conventional battery backed SRAM is at $6000-$7FFF. This board also exceeds the 256KiB PRG ROM limit by repurposing CHR select lines.
Datach Joint ROM System boards, which have a 24C02 serial EEPROM on the main board and the game itself on a daughterboard, possibly with another 24C01 serial EEPROM.

Mappers describe these boards as follow:

Four mappers are used to describe these boards:

iNES Mapper 016 is used for 1, 2, and 4.
iNES Mapper 153 is a rarely used assignment for 5.
iNES Mapper 157 is used for 6.
iNES Mapper 159 is used for 3.

You may encounter ROMs with the mapper assignments mixed up. There used to be no distinction when 016 was first assigned. The distinction was introduced later to distinguish the 128-byte boards from the 256-byte or no-EEPROM boards. In NES 2.0 format, only 157 differs, because the "battery backed PRG RAM size" field disambiguates these boards enough to run all known games that used them, though emulators MAY display a warning when the RAM size field is abnormal for a given mapper.

FCEUX does not emulate the EEPROM. It seems that returning 0x00 from EEPROM registers suffices to get most games booting.

Banks

CPU $6000-$7FFF: varies, see below
CPU $8000-$BFFF: 16 KiB switchable PRG ROM bank
CPU $C000-$FFFF: 16 KiB PRG ROM bank, fixed to the last bank
PPU $0000-$03FF: 1 KiB switchable CHR bank
PPU $0400-$07FF: 1 KiB switchable CHR bank
PPU $0800-$0BFF: 1 KiB switchable CHR bank
PPU $0C00-$0FFF: 1 KiB switchable CHR bank
PPU $1000-$13FF: 1 KiB switchable CHR bank
PPU $1400-$17FF: 1 KiB switchable CHR bank
PPU $1800-$1BFF: 1 KiB switchable CHR bank
PPU $1C00-$1FFF: 1 KiB switchable CHR bank

Registers

See the notes about hardware above. Because iNES Mapper 016 covers the capabilities of multiple differing boards, it must be emulated with the mapper's writable ports across all off $6000-$FFFF, and a 24C02 present at $6000-$7FFF. This configuration will run all known games that used one of these boards.

For iNES Mapper 153 (with SRAM), the writeable ports must only be mirrored across $8000-$FFFF.

Mappers 157 and 159 do not need to support the FCG-1 and -2 and so should only mirror the ports across $8000-$FFFF.

The registers are mirrored every 16 bytes, regardless of where they start.

CHR bank select (BASE+0 … BASE+7)

Mappers 16 and 159:

7  bit  0
---- ----
CCCC CCCC
|||| ||||
++++-++++-- Select 8KiB CHR ROM bank at appropriate PPU address.

Write to register offset | 1KiB CHR bank affected
0 | $0000-$03FF
1 | $0400-$07FF
2 | $0800-$0BFF
3 | $0C00-$0FFF
4 | $1000-$13FF
5 | $1400-$17FF
6 | $1800-$1BFF
7 | $1C00-$1FFF

Mapper 153 ($8000-$8003 only):

7  bit  0
---- ----
xxxx xxxP
        |
        +-- Select 256KiB PRG ROM outer bank

As this mapper has no CHR ROM and only 8KiB fixed CHR RAM, the CHR ROM selection lines are repurposed similarly to SUROM. So CHR A10 OUT is connected to PRG A18 out on the mapper IC. The mapper's PPU A12 and PPU A13 inputs are tied to ground, but the PPU A11 and PPU A10 inputs are still connected, so the first 4 CHR bank 'P' bits should be set to the same value, or the game will flip between 256KiB PRG outer banks while rendering.

External Serial EEPROM Clock ($8000 … $8003)

7  bit  0
---- ----
xxxx Cxxx
     |   
     +----- External I²C Clock

As with mapper 153, iNES Mapper 157 grounds the PPU A12 and A13 inputs. CHR A13 OUT is provided on the subcartridge header, and is used in one game as an external I²C clock. PPU rendering must either be disabled during traffic to the external EEPROM, or the same value must be written to all four registers. No CHR banking is available.

It's conceivable that a game could have used this extra signal to provide 512 KiB of PRG instead of a serial EEPROM, but none have been found.

PRG Bank select (BASE+8)

7  bit  0
---- ----
.... PPPP
     ||||
     ++++-- Select 16KiB PRG ROM bank mapped to CPU $8000-$BFFF

Mirroring Control (BASE+9)

7  bit  0
---- ----
.... ..MM
       ||
       ++-- 0: Vertical (A10), 1: Horizontal (A11), 2: Single screen 1 (ground), 3: Single screen 2 (VCC)

IRQ Control (BASE+$A)

7  bit  0
---- ----
.... ...C
        |
        +-- 1: Count down, 0: pause

Writes also acknowledge a currently-asserted interrupt.

IRQ Counter (BASE+$B … BASE+$C)

   $C         $B
7  bit  0  7  bit  0
---- ----  ---- ----
CCCC CCCC  CCCC CCCC
|||| ||||  |||| ||||
++++-++++--++++-++++-- The 16 bits of the current value of the counter (little-endian)

The IRQ counter is clocked by M2. There is no reload value, nor does it stop: after it becomes 0, it becomes 65535. Writes are not shadowed, so you either need to be careful about timing or pause the counter while you manually reload.

It is not known precisely which of the following are true:

Is /IRQ asserted while the timer is 0 ?
Is /IRQ asserted when the counter goes from 1 to 0 ?
Is /IRQ asserted when it changes from anything to 0 ?

EEPROM Control ($800D)

For games with serial EEPROMs:

7  bit  0
---- ----
RDC. ....
|||
||+-------- I²C SCL (Datach: internal EEPROM only)
|+--------- I²C SDA
+---------- Enable Read

PRG RAM Enable ($800D)

For games with PRG RAM:

7  bit  0
---- ----
RxE. ....
|||
||+-------- PRG RAM +CE
|+--------- don't care
+---------- probably should always be 0

Serial EEPROM ($6000-$7FFF)

Read-only; for games using the LZ93D50 but without PRG RAM.

7  bit  0
---- ----
xxxE Bxxx
|||| ||||
+++|-|+++- Open bus
   | +---- Data out from Barcode reader (or open bus)
   +------ Data out from I²C EEPROM

Extra comments

Some patterns observed in the games' save code:

Start I/O: $00 $40 $60 $20 $00
Write 0 bit: $00 $20 $00
Write 1 bit: $00 $40 $60 $40 $00
Acknowledge: $00 $20 $A0 Read $00
Read bit: $60 $E0 Read $40
Stop I/O: $00 $20 $60 $40 $C0

When implementing the EEPROM, use the datasheets for the 24C01 and 24C02 used by Bandai:

24C01, has no device address/uses device address as memory address: Xicor, Atmel

The 24C01 is NOT little endian, despite what Disch wrote below. This is due to a mistake at Bandai, not a deviation from the datasheet.

24C02, with device address: Xicor, Atmel

Disch's notes

Below, Disch was unfamiliar with I²C, so a number of his comments are solely from the point of view of someone unfamiliar with it.

 Here is a lightly-edited version of Disch's original notes:
 ========================
 =  Mapper 016          =
 =       + 153          =
 =       + 159          =
 ========================
 
 aka
 --------------------------
 Bandai (something or other)
 
 
 Example Games:
 --------------------------
 Dragon Ball - Dai Maou Jukkatsu      (016)
 Dragon Ball Z Gaiden                 (016)
 Dragon Ball Z 2                      (016)
 Rokudenashi Blues                    (016)
 Akuma-kun - Makai no Wana            (016)
 Famicom Jump II: Saikyou no 7 Nin    (153)
 Dragon Ball Z - Kyoushuu! Saiya Jin  (159)
 SD Gundam Gaiden                     (159)
 Magical Taruruuto Kun 1, 2           (159)
 
 
 Three Mappers:
 ---------------------------
 016 and 159 are mapped the exact same way.  Registers are all the same and whatnot.  And in fact, for a
 while, both mappers were assigned the same mapper number (016).  Therefore, you may come across mapper 159
 games that are still marked as mapper 016.
 
 The difference between the two is in the EEPROM.  These mappers don't have traditional SRAM (I couldn't tell
 you why).  Instead, they have an I²C EEPROM that has to be written to one bit at a time, resulting in very 
 strange-seeming register writes.
 
 Mapper 016 has 256 bytes of EEPROM, and is accessed high bit first
 Mapper 159 has 128 bytes of EEPROM, and is accessed low bit first
 Mapper 153 (as far as we know used exclusively for Famicom Jump II: Saikyou no 7 Nin) has SRAM instead of an EEPROM.
 
 For further details, see the section at the bottom.
 
 Apart from save mechanism, the mappers are 100% identical in function.
 
 
 Notes:
 ---------------------------
 Since there's EEPROM, there's no SRAM (EEPROM is used to save games).
 
 
 Registers:
 ---------------------------
 
 Range,Mask:   $6000-FFFF, $000F
 
 Note:  below regs are listed as $800x, but note they also exist at $6000-7FFF
 
 
   $8000-8007:   CHR Regs
   $8008:        PRG Reg (16k @ $8000)
 
   $8009:  [.... ..MM]   Mirroring:
     %00 = Vert
     %01 = Horz
     %10 = 1ScA
     %11 = 1ScB
 
   $800A:  [.... ...E]   IRQ Enable (0=disabled)
   $800B:                Low 8 bits of IRQ Counter
   $800C:                High 8 bits of IRQ Counter
 
   $800D:  EEPROM I/O
 
 another note:   since PRG is mapped to $8000-FFFF, EEPROM I/O reg can only be read via $6xxx or $7xxx.  To my
 knowledge no other registers are readable.  It also appears that reading from *ANY* address in $6xxx-7xxx
 will read the EEPROM I/O reg.  Rokudenashi Blues will poll $7F00 and will wait for bit 4 to be 0 before
 continuing (so if you're giving open bus @ 7F00, the game will deadlock)
 
 CHR Setup:
 ---------------------------
 
       $0000   $0400   $0800   $0C00   $1000   $1400   $1800   $1C00 
     +-------+-------+-------+-------+-------+-------+-------+-------+
     | $8000 | $8001 | $8002 | $8003 | $8004 | $8005 | $8006 | $8007 | 
     +-------+-------+-------+-------+-------+-------+-------+-------+
 
 
 PRG Setup:
 ---------------------------
 
       $8000   $A000   $C000   $E000  
     +---------------+---------------+
     |     $8008     |     { -1}     |
     +---------------+---------------+
 
 
 
 IRQs:
 ---------------------------
 IRQs are nice and simple.
 
 When enabled, the 16-bit IRQ counter counts down every CPU cycle, wrapping from $0000->FFFF.  When the
 counter makes the transition from $0001->$0000, an IRQ is generated.
 
 When disabled, the IRQ counter does not count.
 
 Any write to $800A will acknowledge the IRQ
 
 $800B and $800C change the IRQ counter directly -- not a reload value.
 
 
 EEPROM:
 ---------------------------
 EEPROM is a real nightmare.  Nobody knew exactly how it worked -- but by examining the game code,
 patterns surface.  Games do a series of extremely cryptic writes to $800D, and occasionally read a single
 bit from $800D.  By examining some logs I made of the games I've noticed a small bit of patterns which I
 list below, along with my guess as to what the game is attempting to do by performing that pattern:
 
 
   write $00
   write $40
   write $60     Start I/O
   write $20
   write $00
 
   write $00
   write $20     Output '0' bit
   write $00
 
   write $00
   write $40
   write $60     Output '1' bit
   write $40
   write $00
 
   write $00
   write $20
   write $A0    I have absolutly no clue
   Read
   write $00
 
   write $60
   write $E0    Read a single bit
   Read
   write $40
 
   write $00
   write $20
   write $60    Stop I/O
   write $40
   write $C0
 
 
 These likely aren't the only patterns that games perform.  I recall seeing occasional writes of $80 and
 other stuff thrown in there in some games.  Also -- not all games follow this pattern, so looking for these
 specific writes will not work for at least one other game.
 
 It seems that only bits 5-7 of the written value are relevent (hereon, they will be referred to as D5 - D7).
 Bit 4 ($10) is the only significant bit when read.  Other bits are most likely open bus.
 
 
 When writing bytes to EEPROM, games will generally perform 8 "output" patterns (either output 0 or output 1,
 depending on the bits it wants to write), followed by a 9th output pattern, which I would assume finalizes
 the write and/or possibly moves the 8 bits from a latch to EEPROM.
 
 When reading bytes, games will generally perform 8 "read" patterns, followed by a single output pattern
 (which I would assume finalizes the read).
 
 Sometimes when the game is writing bits, it's writing data to be stored on EEPROM, and other times it's
 setting the desired EEPROM address and/or read/write mode.  Knowing which it's doing involves keeping track
 of the state it's currently it and what it has done last, etc, etc.
 
 But again -- nobody *really* knows how it works.  The method I've employed in my emu is outlined below -- and
 it appears to work for every game I've tried, but I *KNOW* it's not accurate.  But, short of some hardware
 guru acquiring a handful of these carts and doing a thorough RE job, that's about the best anyone can do.
 
 
 Emulating EEPROM:
 -----------------------
 
 SUPER FAT IMPORTANT NOTE:  This is just the method of EEPROM emulation I employ in my emu.
 
      ***THIS IS NOT HOW THE ACTUAL HARDWARE WORKS***
 
 Do not use this as a final word or anything -- this is simply the product of lots of guesswork, speculation,
 and trial and error.
 
 
 D5 appears to be the "trigger" bit, and D6 appears to be the "signal" bit.  I have no clue what D7 does, and
 ignoring it completely has worked for me (though I'm sure it does have some purpose).  "Commands" are sent
 by toggling D5 (0->1->0).  Two states of D6 are observed -- one when D5 rises (0->1), and one when it falls
 (1->0).  Using these two observed states, you get 4 possible commands.  The command is sent when D5 falls.
 
 Example:
 
          byte  D6 D5 
   write: $00    0 0
   write: $40    1 0
   write: $60    1 1  <--  D5 rise:    D6=1
   write: $40    1 0  <--  D5 fall:    D6=1, command "1,1" sent here
   write: $00    0 0
 
 The above sequence would issue a "1,1" command.
 
 Commands:
 
   Name     rise,fall       example write sequence
   ------------------------------------------------
   Write 0     0,0          $00, $20, $00
   Write 1     1,1          $00, $40, $60, $40, $00
   Open        1,0          $00, $40, $60, $20, $00
   Close       0,1          $00, $20, $60, $40, $C0
 
 
 The unit can be in one of several modes:
 
   - Closed
   - Select
   - Address
   - Write
   - Read
 
 I also use an 8-bit temporary value, an 8-bit address (or 7-bit address, if 128 byte EEPROM) and 9-step bit
 counter.
 
 I would assume the unit is Closed on startup (and possibly reset).
 
 
 Basic Concept overview:
 
 
   "Write 0" and "Write 1" commands advance the 9-step bit counter.  The first 8 writes fill the appropriate
 bit in the temporary value.  The 9th write will take the temp value and move it to either the address (if in
 Address mode), or to the desired area in EEPROM (if in Write mode), and the mode will update accordingly.
 Basically the first 8 writes fill the temp value and the 9th moves it to where it needs to go.
 
   Reads operate similarly... but the temp buffer isn't affected by the writes, and the 9th step doesn't copy
 the temp value anywhere.  Note however that games will perform a write between each bit read (presumably to
 advance it to the next bit) -- so you should do nothing but return the appropriate bit when the game reads
 the EEPROM I/O Reg (do not advance it to the next bit on read).
 
   "Select" mode exists on 256 byte EEPROM only (mapper 016).  It is used to select between read/write mode.
 Bit 0 of the 8-bit value written when in Select mode determines read/write mode.  On 128 byte EEPROM (mapper
 159), the high bit of the address selects read/write mode.  In both cases, 1=read mode, 0=write mode.
 
   Remember that on 128 byte, values are written low bit first... but on 256 byte, they're written high bit
 first.  Bits are read the same order they're written.
 
   Doing anything but opening when the unit is closed has no effect.
 
 
 Logic Flow Details (256-byte ... mapper 016)
 --------------------------------------------
 
 Opening from Closed Mode:
   a) Enter Select Mode
 
 Opening from non-Closed Mode:
   a) if in Select Mode, increment address by 1
   b) enter Select Mode.
   c) Reset bit counter (next write is the first write in the 9-write sequence)
 
 Writing in Select Mode:
   a) If low bit of written value = 1
      -) Enter Read Mode
   b) otherwise...
      -) Enter Address Mode
 
 Writing in Address Mode:
   a) written value becomes address
   b) Enter Write mode
 
 Writing in Write Mode:
   a) written value moves to current address of EEPROM
   b) mode is not changed
 
 Writing in Read Mode:
   a) Enter Select Mode
 
 
 
 Logic Flow Details (128-byte ... mapper 159)
 --------------------------------------------
 
 Opening from Closed Mode:
   a) Enter Address Mode
 
 Opening from non-Closed Mode:
   a) increment address by 1 (wrap $7F->00)
   b) do not change mode
   c) Reset bit counter (next write is the first write in the 9-write sequence)
 
 Writing in Address Mode:
   a) written value becomes address (low 7 bits only)
   b) if high bit of written value is set...
      -) Enter Read Mode
   c) otherwise...
      -) Enter Write Mode
 
 Writing in Write Mode:
   a) written value moves to current address of EEPROM
   b) Enter Address mode
 
 Writing in Read Mode:
   a) Enter Address Mode

See Also

Bandai Mapper By goroh, translated by Sgt. Bowhack.
NES mapper list by Disch

Japanese only :

Bandai Mapper by goroh.
Naruko's notes:

http://w.livedoor.jp/famicomcartridge/d/Bandai%20FCG%20series
http://w.livedoor.jp/famicomcartridge/d/Bandai%20FCG-1
http://w.livedoor.jp/famicomcartridge/d/Bandai%20FCG-2
http://w.livedoor.jp/famicomcartridge/d/Bandai%20LZ93D50%20standard
http://w.livedoor.jp/famicomcartridge/d/Bandai%20BA-JUMP2 (iNES Mapper 153)
http://w.livedoor.jp/famicomcartridge/d/Bandai%20Datach (iNES Mapper 157)

Categories: Mappers with CHR RAM, In NesCartDB, ASIC mappers, Mappers with cycle IRQs

Battle Kid 2: Mountain of Torment

This game is the sequel to Battle Kid: Fortress of Peril. Like before, it is a platforming game, inspired from I Wanna be the Guy. It is done in a Metroidvania-style. Rather than having several levels, it is one large area that one can freely explore.

Overview

Project owner: Sivak
Developer: Sivak
Compiler : NESASM
Sound driver: Drag NSF 2.0
Soundtrack by: Sivak
Started on: July, 2010
Release date: December 15, 2012
Cart made: Yes
Mapper: Shipped on the Sealie UNROM 512 board (mapper 30) but uses only the subset compatible with oversize mapper 2
PRG Memory: 512 KB
CHR Memory: 0 KB

Gameplay

Gameplay is similar to the first game in that one controls Timmy and must navigate through the various sectors of the mountain base, seeking out items and bosses.

Unlike the first game, there are more types of blocks such as conveyor belts, ice, and sludge. Sludge is a liquid that makes one move at half speed while inside of it.

In this game, the upgrades include: Wall Grip, Feather Fall, X-Sludge, and Double Jump. Wall grip allows Timmy to cling onto special walls. Feather Fall lowers falling speed. X-Sludge makes sludge act like water. Double jump allows a second jump in the air. High Jump is phased out and you already jump at that height from the start. The Infinite Oxygen item was also removed and Timmy can simply be underwater indefinitely.

There will be varying levels of difficulty like before. Passwords and other bonuses will also be included.

External links

Sivak Games
Purchase page
Official trailer
Demo video #6 - Showcases revised intro stage and intro scenes
Demo video #5 - Showcases new features and artwork
Demo video #4 - Showcases intro stage and cutscenes
Demo video #3 - Showcases new features and another area
Demo video #2 - Showcases 3 areas
Demo video #1 - Old first area demo
General game engine demo video

Categories: Homebrew games, Games released in 2012, Games by Sivak

Blargg PPU

Just a rough attempt at striking the right detail level for the main PPU documentation. Posting here (rather than just previewing a local copy) in case someone wants to get an idea of what I'm trying.

Pattern tables

The background and sprites are drawn using small 8x8 pixel images called tiles. There are 512 tiles total, arranged in two pattern tables, each holding 256 tiles. A tile takes 16 bytes of memory, with 2 bits per pixel. The pixels are stored as two bit planes, each 8 bytes. Each byte of a plane represents one row of the tile, with the most significant bit representing the left-hand pixel. The first plane specifies the least significant bit of each pixel. A pixel value of 0 is transparent, while 1, 2, and 3 specify a color from one of the sub-palettes.

Palette

The colors of bckground and sprite pixels are determined by the palette. It consists of 8 sub-palettes; the first four for the background and the remaining four for the sprites. Each sub-palette specifies the colors for tile pixel values of 1 to 3.

The palette uses 32 bytes of VRAM starting at $3F00, with each sub-palette using 4 bytes. Normally the first entry of each sub-palette is ignored, except for the first entry of the first sub-palette, which specifies the backdrop color.

$3F00
Backdrop | $3F01
Color 1 | $3F02
Color 2 | $3F03
Color 3 | Background sub-palette 0
$3F04
Unused | $3F05
Color 1 | $3F06
Color 2 | $3F07
Color 3 | Background sub-palette 1
$3F08
Unused | $3F09
Color 1 | $3F0A
Color 2 | $3F0B
Color 3 | Background sub-palette 2
$3F0C
Unused | $3F0D
Color 1 | $3F0E
Color 2 | $3F0F
Color 3 | Background sub-palette 3
$3F10
Backdrop mirror | $3F11
Color 1 | $3F12
Color 1 | $3F13
Color 1 | Sprite sub-palette 0
$3F14
Unused | $3F15
Color 1 | $3F16
Color 2 | $3F17
Color 3 | Sprite sub-palette 1
$3F18
Unused | $3F19
Color 1 | $3F1A
Color 2 | $3F1B
Color 3 | Sprite sub-palette 2
$3F1C
Unused | $3F1D
Color 1 | $3F1E
Color 2 | $3F1F
Color 3 | Sprite sub-palette 3

Note that $3F00 and $3F10 both set the backdrop color; these two memory locations actually access the same byte of memory. This must be kept in mind when writing to sprite sub-palette 0.

Each palette entry is only 6 bits. The upper 2 bits specify brightness, and the lower 4 hue:

Palette entry | --BB HHHH | Brightness and Hue
bits 0-3 | ---- HHHH | Hue
bits 4-5 | --BB ---- | Brightness

[palette goes here, which shows palette and hex values for each color]

Note that a value of $0D should not be used (brightness=0, hue=13), as this results in a "blacker than black" color that causes stability problems on some televisions.

Background

The background is composed of 64x60 tiles, divided into four 32x30 nametables. Each nametable is 960 bytes, with 8-bit tile indicies into one of the two pattern tables as selected by PPUCTRL. Each nametable also has a corresponding 64-byte attribute table, which breaks the tiles into blocks of 2x2 and specifies which background sub-palette to use for each.

Normally there is only enough VRAM for two nametables and attribute tables; the other two are duplicates of these. Some mappers support other schemes, like having a single nametable duplicated in all four positions, or extra VRAM to allow four unique nametables. In the following table, A, B, C, and D refer to the underlying memory the nametables are stored in.

Arrangement | Name

A A
B B

| Horizontal

A B
A B

| Vertical

A A
A A

| One-screen

A B
C D

| Four-screen

Blargg SPC Upload

This covers the important points of uploading an SPC music file into the SNES SPC-700 sound module. See spc_loader.c for tested code in C. Thanks to Anti Resonance for much of the original algorithm. I've mostly streamlined and tweaked it.

The main tasks to play an SPC file are

Restore DSP registers
Restore 64K RAM
Restore CPU registers and other final values

DSP registers

We can't just restore all the registers directly, because some have effects that depend on the others, or cause RAM to be overwritten. Those must be restored at the end. We make a copy of the DSP registers and modify as follows:

Register | Value | Purpose
KOFF | $00 | There are no notes to stop, and if any bits were set, it would stop the first notes.
KON | $00 | We don't want notes to start before we've restored DSP registers and RAM.
FLG | $60 | Enables mute, and disables echo write. We can't have echo writing over memory while restoring.
EDL | $00 | Sets length of echo buffer, but not until after the current echo pointer reaches the end of the buffer. Since EDL might have been $0F previously, we must assume that this new EDL of $00 might take as long as 1/4 second to take effect. We write DSP registers first, then the 64K RAM, so during the time taken to write RAM, the echo pointer will have looped and taken on a new loop size of zero. To take less than 1/4 second uploading the 64K RAM, you'd have to upload each byte in less than 4 S-SMP cycles, an impossibility. After all this, with EDL and the internal echo position reliably at 0, we then restore the proper EDL from the SPC file, knowing exactly where it will first start writing echo samples.

With these modifications, we upload them to the DSP via a short SPC program:

       .org $0002
       mov x,#dsp_regs     ; pointer to table
       mov y,#0
next:  mov a,(x)+          ; copy to DSP
       mov $F2,y
       mov $F3,a
       inc y
       bpl next            ; stop when y > 127
       jmp !$FFC0          ; rerun bootrom
dsp_regs:
       .res 128            ; modified values to load

64K RAM

Again, we can't restore every byte of RAM directly, because some of the I/O locations have effects that we can't have just yet. We make a copy of the 64K RAM and modify it as follows:

Address | Value | Purpose
$0000 | $00 | The bootloader uses these locations to store a pointer to the current destination page, so when we overwrite them, we must overwrite with the same values.
$0001 | $00
$00F0 | $0A | Test register
$00F1 | $80 | Enables IPL ROM and stops timers. The IPL ROM must be enabled, because the bootloader is there. Note that having it enabled doesn't prevent storing values into RAM at $FFC0-$FFFF, so we can load those just fine.
$00F2 | $6C | DSP address
$00F3 | $60 | We just rewrite FLG with $60 again here, because we have to write something to the DSP.
$00F4 | $F4 | This is critical. This is the value the loader would have written here normally. If we write a different value, it will disrupt communication and hang the loader, but only very rarely, because the window of opportunity is small.
$00FD | $00 | Not really necessary to be zero, since the timer out registers are only readable, but why not.
$00FE | $00
$00FF | $00

Some final patching is necessary before sending the RAM.

Final restoration

With those values patched, we still need to insert some code to restore the final registers. We need to find some free space in RAM. Many have long stretches of $FF bytes, a good candidate. If the echo buffer is enabled, it could be used, though this will introduce a slight click. Some other SPC files have runs of the repeating pattern of 32 $FF bytes followed by 32 $00 bytes, aligned to a 32-byte boundary.

Once we've found space, we can patch in the following code. The notation spc.ram [n] refers to the RAM in the unpatched SPC file, spc.dsp [reg] to the unpatched DSP value, and spc.<register> to the processor register value in the SPC file.

   ; Restore first two bytes of RAM
   mov $00,#spc.ram [0]
   mov $01,#spc.ram [1]
   
   ; Restore CPU registers
   mov x,#spc.sp - 1   ; See below for why the -1
   mov sp,X
   mov y,#spc.y
   mov x,#spc.x
   mov a,#spc.a
   
   ; Restore SMP/DSP registers
   mov $F1,#spc.ram [$F1] AND $CF    ; Control

Note that we clear bits 4 and 5, because we don't want the input ports being cleared.

   mov $F3,#spc.dsp [FLG]

Now we restore the original FLG value, which might enable echo writing. Note that we don't need to set the DSP address, as it's already been set during RAM restore. Since we know the echo pointer will now be at the beginning of the echo buffer, writing is safe. If we put this final loader in the echo buffer, we should NOT place it at the very beginning, otherwise we'll be chased by the echo overwriting as we execute here, and might lose the race. So we should be at a small offset like 1024 (small enough to fit in case EDL is only $01).

   mov $F2,#$7D    ; EDL
   mov $F3,#spd.dsp [EDL]
   mov $F2,#$4C    ; KON
   mov $F3,#spd.dsp [KON]

No need to restore the original KOFF.

   mov $F2,#spc.ram [$F2]   ; DSP Address

Don't forget this, as the code might be expecting the address to already be set to something in particular.

   ; Restore PSW and PC
   pop psw
   mov spc.sp,#saved byte from stack

We pop the saved PSW we push on the stack before executing this final restore code. That saved PSW has the P flag set. Then we restore that byte on the stack to whatever it originally was. The SPC file could have been depending on that byte, even though it's outside the current stack. The P flag is set, so we can use direct-page addressing here.

   setp or clrp    ; depending on what's set in PSW in SPC file

Now we restore the P flag to what it should be.

   jmp !spc.pc

And finally jump to wherever the SPC was executing when the SPC file was captured.

The above code relies on the PSW being on the stack, so we must push that ourselves, saving the old byte so we can restore that too.

With the 64K RAM patched, we upload that to the SPC and execute our patch inside it, and away it goes. Immediately after that, we must do one final restoration: write the final values to the input ports that were there when the SPC was captured.

Categories: Super NES, Audio

BNROM

The designation BNROM refers to the Irem cartridge board "Irem I-IM" and to its NES workalike, the Nintendo cartridge board NES-BNROM. These boards were used only for one game: Deadly Towers (Japanese Mashou). The iNES format assigns mapper 34 to BNROM (as well as NINA-001).

Contents

1 Overview
2 Banks
3 Solder pad config
4 Registers

4.1 Bank select ($8000-$FFFF)

5 Hardware
6 Variants

Overview

PRG ROM size: 128 KB (mapper implementations may support up to 512 KB or 8 MB)
PRG ROM bank size: 32 KB
PRG RAM: None
CHR capacity: 8 KB RAM
CHR bank size: Not bankswitched
Nametable mirroring: Solder pads select vertical or horizontal mirroring
Subject to bus conflicts: Yes

Notes:

BNROM PRG uses the DIP-28 Nintendo pinout.
The bank number at power on is not defined.
The 6502's vectors must be present in all banks, along with the NMI, reset, and IRQ handlers.
iNES Mapper 034 implementations frequently support either a 4-bit or 8-bit PRG bank select register, allowing up to 512 KB or 8 MB of PRG ROM. This variant may be referred to as BxROM.

Banks

CPU $8000-$FFFF: 32 KB switchable PRG ROM bank

Solder pad config

Horizontal mirroring : 'H' disconnected, 'V' connected.
Vertical mirroring : 'H' connected, 'V' disconnected.

Registers

Bank select ($8000-$FFFF)

7  bit  0
---- ----
xxxx xxPP
       ||
       ++- Select 32 KB PRG ROM bank for CPU $8000-$FFFF

While the original BNROM board connects only 2 bits, it is recommended that emulators implement this as an 8-bit register allowing selection of up to 8 MB PRG ROM if present.

Hardware

The BxROM board contains a 74HC161 binary counter used as a quad D latch (4-bit register) to select the current PRG bank.

Variants

The iNES mapper used to implement this mapper also includes three additional registers at $7FFD-$7FFF for emulation of the NINA-001 board (using CHR ROM instead of RAM, as well as supporting 8KB of PRG RAM), which has caused many headaches for NES emulator authors. Emulator developers may consider switching between NINA-001 emulation and BxROM emulation based on the presence of CHR ROM.

AMROM is the same as BNROM except it uses bit 4 of the register to control a single screen mirroring configuration, instead of fixed mirroring.

The upper 2 bank select bits on the 74HC161 were left unconnected. These bits could have been used for an oversize variant of BNROM supporting up to 512 KB (4 Mbit) of PRG ROM. Some emulators support this oversize variation, as well as the PowerPak since a mapper update in June 2011. The Action 53 multicart used this oversize extension until mapper 28 was developed.

Theoretically the bank select register could be implemented with a 74HC377 octal latch, allowing up to 8 MB of PRG ROM.

Categories: Discrete logic mappers, Mappers with CHR RAM, Mappers with bus conflicts, Nintendo licensed mappers

Cartridge and mappers' history

1983 July 15th
The Nintendo Family Computer (Famicom) is released in Japan. The 3 launch games are : "Donkey Kong", "Donkey Kong Jr." and "Popeye". During the first year, only Nintendo released games for the system. All of them had 16 KiB PRG and 8 KiB CHR.
1984 June 21th
Family BASIC is released. It is the first special cart Nintendo made for the system: instead of being a game it allows the user to program the system using the BASIC programming language. It's also the first cart that uses 32 KiB of PRG. Additionally it provides 2 KiB of battery-backed PRG RAM. It is the first cart (for a long while) to use PRG RAM, let alone battery backup.
1984 July 28th/31st
Hudson's "Nuts & Milk" and "Lode Runner" appear to be the first third party games released on the Famicom. The cartridges were manufactured by Nintendo though.
1984 November 2nd/8th
Namco's "Pac Man" and "Xevious" appear to be the first releases for the Famicom that were entirely manufactured by a third party. "Xevious" appears to be the first 32 KiB PRG game for the system (as Family BASIC isn't a game). Because of the lack of any lockout chip, Namco and many other companies (Bandai, Irem, Jaleco, Konami, Sunsoft, Taito) will follow this trend and make their own cartridges instead of having Nintendo make them for them.
1985 June 21st
Konami's "Hyper Olympic Gentaiban!" is the first game to use hardware other than ROMs (not counting Family BASIC). The cartridge was made by Konami and uses some circuitry to allow 16 KB of CHR ROM, switching between two 8 KiB banks. Mappers were born.
1985 September 13th
Nintendo's "Super Mario Bros." is released in Japan. It is one of the first (if not the first) Famicom games that is not merely a port of another arcade or computer game. This will be a major factor in the console's success.
1985 September 27th
Jaleco released "City Connection", which uses the same circuit as Konami's above-mentioned CHR banking.
1985 October 18th
The Nintendo Entertainment System (NES) is released in the United States. The launch games are : "10-Yard Fight", "Baseball", "Clu Clu Land", "Donkey Kong Jr. Math", "Duck Hunt", "Excitebike", "Golf", "Gyromite", "Hogan's Alley", "Ice Climber", "Kung Fu", "Mach Rider", "Pinball", "Stack-Up", "Super Mario Bros.", "Tennis", "Wild Gunman", and "Wrecking Crew". Some of these contained 60-pin Famicom cartridge PCBs connected to an internal Famicom-to-NES adapter, while others used 72-pin cartridge PCBs designed specifically for the NES. This list already includes some third party games but this time the lockout chip inside the NES prevented them from building their own cartridges.
1986 February 21st
Nintendo released the Famicom Disk System (FDS) accessory, which vastly improved the capabilities of the console (as almost no games were yet using mappers). One disk can hold 128 KB of data (64KB per side), and was cheaper to produce. Additionally it provided extra sound and the disks could hold save data.
1986 April
Bandai, Konami and Nintendo appear to start producing CNROM games almost simultaneously. It's an improvement over Konami's circuit that uses only one chip instead of two.
1986 April 17th
Sunsoft's "Atlantis no Nazo" appears to be the first cartridge that uses a dedicated mapper chip (as opposed to 74 series logic chips). Other companies follow this trend promptly.
1986 June 6th
Nintendo's "Gumshoe" (released in USA) is the first GNROM game. It's the first game to bank PRG ROM, have 128 KiB of PRG ROM, and to support banking both PRG and CHR.
1986 June 13th
Capcom's "Maikamura" (a.k.a. "Ghosts 'n' Goblins") appears to be the first UNROM game. After the FDS, UNROM is the first game cartridge to use CHR RAM.
1986 June 20th
Namco's "Super Chinese" appears to be the first game that uses a complex ASIC mapper. Namco's 108 is the MMC3's predecessor.
1986 July 30th
Konami's VRC1 (the second ASIC mapper) is first used in "Ganbare Goemon! Karakuri Douchuu". After the FDS, the VRC1 is the first mapper that supports changing the nametable layout ("mirroring") at runtime.
1986 September 1st
The NES is released in PAL-B regions.
1986 December 15th
Irem's "Mashou" (a.k.a. "Deadly Towers") is the first game published to use a BNROM board.
1987 April 14th
Seta's "Morita Shougi" appears to be the first game to use the Nintendo MMC1 mapper. It's also the first game cartridge with 8 KiB of PRG RAM and battery backup.
1987 May 15th
The NES is released in PAL-A regions.
1987 June 30th
Taito's X1-005 is first used in "Mirai Shinwa Jarvas". The X1-005 is the first mapper to provide a small amount of extra RAM on-die, which was almost always used for saving.
1987 July 7th
Konami's VRC2 is first used in "Getsufuu Maden". The VRC2 is the first mapper to support eight independent CHR banks.
1987 September 25th
Konami's VRC3 is first and only used in "Salamander". After the FDS, the VRC3 is the first mapper that can generate IRQs.
1987 September
Nintendo's MMC2 is used in "Mike Tyson's Punch-out!!".
1987 December
Rare's "Wizards & Warriors" is the first game published to use an ANROM board.
1987 December 4th
Namco's "Star Wars" is the first game published to use their 129 mapper IC, which supported ROM nametables and expansion audio. (However, this game used neither)
1988 March 18th
Irem released "Napoleon Senki", the first game to have 4-screen mirroring, and to contain both CHR RAM and CHR ROM.
1988 August 12th
Namco's "Final Lap" is the first game to re-use the audio loop lines intended for the FDS to add expansion audio.
1988 September 27th
Seta's "8-Eyes" appears to be the first game to use the Nintendo MMC3 mapper.
1990 April
Rare's "Pin•Bot" is the first game that can bankswitch CHR-RAM, as well as both CHR-RAM and CHR-ROM independently.
1990 September
Hal Laboratory's "Uchuu Keibitai SDF" and Konami's "Castlevania 3" (released almost simultaneously) appear to be the first games to use the Nintendo MMC5 mapper.
1991 August 10th
Bandai's "Dragon Ball Z II: Gekishin Freeza!!" is the first game to save games in EEPROM.
1991 August 30th
HAL Labratory released "Metal Slader Glory", the largest licensed game with 512KB of PRG ROM and CHR ROM.
1994 June 24th
Hudson Soft's "Takahasi Meijin no Boukenjima (Adventure Islands) IV" is the last licensed game released for the Famicom.
1994 December
Nintendo's "Wario's Woods" is the last licensed game for the NES in USA.
2003 September 25th
Nintendo discontinued all manufacturing and support for the Famicom

Note: this list is not a citeable source for release dates; all dates either come from NEScartDB or Wikipedia.

Category talk:In NesCartDB

But why?

I'm curious what the goal/use of this category is?

I think an external link in the lead to the DB search entry might be very useful. You could click on it and go to that information. e.g.: http://bootgod.dyndns.org:7777/search.php?ines=3

This category, though, doesn't seem to offer any convenience or useful information. If you want to know NesDB information about the mapper, you still have to manually go to the site and search for it. What's the point of the category, exactly?

It's also woefully incomplete, but that's easy to address. I'm just thinking, if I were to go to the effort of tagging them all, wouldn't it be a better effort to remove the category entirely, and just add links? -- Rainwarrior (talk) 15:37, 18 April 2015 (MDT)

The reason I added it was it 1- counts as a loose score of verifiability, and 2- means I don't have to independently ask NesCartDB whether it has a given thing.—Lidnariq (talk) 09:47, 20 April 2015 (MDT)

I wonder if an "infobox" approach could improve things. A new template {{infobox iNES mapper}} with arguments like year, max_prg_rom, and in_nescartdb would put a mapper in the appropriate categories and generate a "Summary" that floats at the top right of a page. --Tepples (talk) 13:31, 20 April 2015 (MDT)

A lot of the mapper pages have an "overview" section that contains that kind of information. We could start adding an entry about NesCartDB to them (would also be a good place for the category tag, if you do find it useful, though I must admit I don't understand the use just described by Lidnariq). I don't know if an infobox template would work well, because there are so many special cases with mapper descriptions. Whether or not you want to try to use templates to help, having consistent overview information across the mapper pages would be great. - Rainwarrior (talk) 20:27, 20 April 2015 (MDT)

I'm reworking the overview into an infobox called {{Infobox iNES mapper}}. If you specify a game count, it'll add this category and make a link to search NesCartDB. See it at the top of Sunsoft FME-7. --Tepples (talk) 16:51, 21 April 2015 (MDT)

It's a good start. I left some notes on its talk page. - Rainwarrior (talk) 17:18, 21 April 2015 (MDT)

Another thing probably worth adding to the overview of each mapper page, the iNES mapper number. Where the page is the article about that iNES mapper, the number could just be bold, for pages like UxROM where it's a 1 to many relationship, link all the mappers (+ probably a clarifying note). The reason I'm a little iffy about templates for this is that it's difficult to write and modify template code when you need to handle a special case, and there will be lots. Writing wiki markup for an overview section anybody can do easily. - Rainwarrior (talk) 20:54, 20 April 2015 (MDT)

I created a template to easily make a box of NesDB links. Template:nesdbbox I guess this could appear directly beneath an infobox? I've placed the trial run at AxROM with this edit for now, please let me know if you have suggestions. (Might be better to answer at Template talk:Infobox iNES mapper.) - Rainwarrior (talk) 14:05, 22 April 2015 (MDT)

Category talk:Mappers with IRQs

Where to file fixed-timing IRQ-sources

I don't think it makes sense to say that "if it's clocked by M2, regardless of how general it is, it belongs in Category:Mappers with cycle IRQs". 1- With such a constraint, the only thing that could possibly make sense in the overarching category would be things that used analog effects for timing ... or the way IRQs are used on "real" computers, where they signal asynchronous events. 2- Because these are not general, it can't be used for arbitrary timing. At best, they're far more crippled than Tepples's demonstration of using the DPCM for mid-screen splits. —Lidnariq (talk) 13:10, 18 May 2015 (MDT)

Ah, I didn't understand why those 3 were left out of the cycle category. That sounds like a new category to me, then. Since they're all still cycle counters (even though the timing isn't configurable) I made that a subcategory of cycle IRQs for now, but we can move it back to the parent category if there are other kinds (you mention it on the scanline IRQ category description, but do any exist?). Better to just keep all the fixed ones in their own category, since that's a far more important property than either cycle or scanline counting. - Rainwarrior (talk) 14:06, 18 May 2015 (MDT)

For fixed PPU timing, there's iNES Mapper 091, and whatever board zxbdragon found here... —Lidnariq (talk) 14:28, 18 May 2015 (MDT)

Okay, I'll move the category up to the parent, then. The reason I thought it would be best to exclude them is that if you want list of "good" cycle/scanline IRQs you probably don't want them in there. Actually... maybe multiple-inheritence would solve this. I'll make two new subcategories, both additionally parented to the fixed-timing one. - Rainwarrior (talk) 14:44, 18 May 2015 (MDT)

Okay, that's done. I think this should make it easy to find "useful" IRQs, but also easy to find the various subcategories one might be interested in. - Rainwarrior (talk) 14:53, 18 May 2015 (MDT)

CHR ROM vs. CHR RAM

An NES cartridge has at least two memory chips on it: PRG (connected to the CPU) and CHR (connected to the PPU). There is always at least one PRG ROM, and there may be an additional PRG RAM to hold data. Some cartridges have a CHR ROM, which holds a fixed set of graphics tile data available to the PPU from the moment it turns on. Other cartridges have a CHR RAM that holds data that the CPU has copied from PRG ROM through a port on the PPU. (A few have both CHR ROM and CHR RAM.)

The PPU can see only 8 KiB of tile data at once. So once your game has more than that much tile data, you'll need to use a mapper to load more data into the PPU. Some mappers bankswitch the CHR ROM so that the PPU can see different "pages". Other mappers are designed for CHR RAM; they let the CPU switch to a PRG ROM bank containing CHR data and copy it to CHR RAM.

Contents

1 CHR ROM

1.1 Advantages
1.2 Applications

2 CHR RAM

2.1 Advantages
2.2 Applications

3 Effects possible with both types
4 Switching to CHR RAM
5 Notes

CHR ROM

Advantages

Takes less time and code for a beginner to get at least something displayed. The "hello world" program for a CHR ROM mapper is about 16 lines shorter.
Switching tiles is fast, needs no vblank time, and can be done mid-frame or even mid-scanline.
Can be used together with MMC3 and PRG RAM on a donor cartridge. Only six games have a board with MMC3 + PRG RAM + CHR RAM, and all are Japan-exclusive. Only three NES games use TGROM (MMC3 + CHR RAM) and two NES games use TQROM (MMC3 + CHR RAM + CHR ROM) even without PRG RAM. However, this should become less of a consideration as MMC3-compatible cartridges with all new parts hit the market.

Applications

Big static screens
Smash TV's title screen alone uses more than 8 KB of tile data.

Dedicated bank for status bar
A horizontal status bar might use a separate set of tiles from the playfield. This needs either a mapper with a raster interrupt or a sprite 0 overlap trigger. (e.g. Super Mario Bros. 3)

Artifact blanking
A game that scrolls in all four directions will often have artifacts on one side of the screen because the NES doesn't have enough VRAM to keep the "seam" where new map data is loaded clean. To hide this, a game such as Jurassic Park might display tiles from a blank pattern table for the first or last 8 to 16 scanlines.[1]

Pseudo texture mapping
In some pseudo-3D games, each row of the floor texture can be stored in a separate bank. Both CHR ROM and CHR RAM let the program switch the background between CHR banks in $0000 and $1000 using PPUCTRL,[2] but CHR ROM allows far more than two banks to be used, as seen in a forward-scrolling shooter called Cosmic Epsilon.

Workaround for PRG/CHR divide
A drawback of using CHR ROM is that the split between PRG ROM and CHR ROM fragments your data, but it can be worked around. If your PRG ROM is slightly bigger than a power of two, but you have a bit of spare CHR ROM left, you can stash the data in CHR ROM and read it out through PPUADDR/PPUDATA. For instance, Super Mario Bros. keeps its title screen map data at the end of CHR ROM and copies it into RAM to draw it. However, you can't read this data while rendering is turned on, and due to the DMA glitch, reading PPUDATA while playing sampled sound is unreliable.

CHR RAM

Advantages

Can switch tiles in small increments, and the granularity of switching does not depend on the mapper's complexity.
Tile data can be compressed in ROM.
Tile data can be otherwise generated in real time.
Only one chip to rewire and put on the board when replicating your work on cartridge.
All data is stored in one address space, as opposed to a small amount being inaccessible when rendering is on and unreliable when DPCM is on.

Applications

Compositing
Sometimes you need to draw piles of things that aren't aligned to an 8x8 pixel grid, and there are more of them than will fit into the limit of 8 sprites per scanline. Hatris, Shanghai II, Blockout, and its clone 3D Block have a large playfield containing large stacks of such objects. Cocoron creates the player character's animation frames by piecing together several customizable body parts.
Text flexibility
A font is a set of glyphs, or pictures that represent the characters of a script. Compositing these glyphs with CHR RAM allows drawing text in a proportional font (also called a variable-width font, or VWF). Not a lot of NES games used a VWF, but something like Word Munchers or Fraction Munchers might benefit. The Super NES version of Mario Is Missing uses a VWF, as do a lot of Super NES RPGs, the Action 53 menu, and text boxes in RHDE. It's also the most practical way to display characters in connected scripts such as Arabic or heavily accented scripts such as Vietnamese.
Compression
Compression refers to transforming a block of data to reduce its size in bits, so that another transformation on the compressed data can recover the original data. This is fairly common with tile data in games that use CHR RAM. The graphics in Konami games (Blades of Steel, the US version of Contra, and the Japanese version of Simon's Quest) and Codemasters games (such as Bee 52) are compressed using a run-length encoding scheme: Konami's codec works on bytes, while Codemasters' works on pixels. If your game has a lot of tile data, especially if it's just a shade over the power of two boundary between one ROM size and the next larger power of 2, consider compression.
Drawing
A few games allow the user to edit tiles. These include paint programs such as Videomation and Color a Dinosaur, or moddable titles such as the Japan-only shooter maker Dezaemon (whose stock sprites were reused in Recca).
Vector graphics
Qix has horizontal lines, vertical lines, and filled areas that aren't aligned to a tile grid. Graphics in Elite are wireframe 3D.
Juxtaposition
Some CHR ROM games restrict which objects can be seen together because of what bank their CHR data is stored in. CHR RAM has no such problem because any object's tile data can be loaded at any position. This proves useful in a game like Final Fantasy, where any player characters can meet any monsters, or in a game like Dizzy or RHDE or Animal Crossing, where the player can have any of several dozen items in his inventory. The extreme of this is Battletoads, which keeps only one frame of each player's animation loaded. To switch frames of animation, it copies them into CHR RAM. But then it has to turn off rendering at the top of the screen, creating a blank strip in the status bar, in order to fit the copy into blanking time. Whether you are using 8x8 or 8x16 pixel sprites, there is enough space in $1000-$1FFF to hold the current and next cel for all 64 sprites. This effect is used even more intensely in platforms with dual-ported VRAM (TurboGrafx-16, Game Boy Advance) and in platforms which have hardware-assisted memory copying to video ports other than OAM (Genesis, Super NES, Game Boy Color, Game Boy Advance). And it's required if you want to display text in a language whose script has more than 250 or so glyphs, such as the logographic characters in some Chinese games and the Japanese versions of Faxanadu and Bionic Commando.
One chip
CHR RAM means you don't need to program a separate flash chip to act as the CHR ROM.
Battery RAM
NES 2.0 supports CHR battery RAM. If not all of the memory is used for tiles, you can store save game data in there, which means you don't have to install CHR ROM or PRG RAM on the cartridge. (However not many mappers officially support this; as far as I know not many emulators do either.)

Effects possible with both types

Tile animation. Think of the animated ? blocks, coins, and conveyor belts in Super Mario Bros. 3 or the animated grass and quicksand in Super Mario Bros. 2, spinning fans or cogs in some games, or the independent parallax scrolling of distant repeating tile patterns in Batman: Return of the Joker, Crisis Force, and Metal Storm.

With CHR ROM, you'd make a separate bank for each frame of animation that you want to display, or for each offset between the distant pattern's scroll position and the foreground pattern's scroll position. It works best on a mapper with CHR banks smaller than 4 KB, such as MMC3.

With CHR RAM, you'd copy the tiles into VRAM as needed. Assuming moderately unrolled VRAM loading code, the NTSC vblank is long enough to copy about 160 bytes per frame plus the OAM display list without turning rendering on late. This is enough for 10 tiles alone, or 8 tiles plus a nametable row, nametable column, or entire palette.

In cases where player 1 and player 2 can select a character, and each character has his own frames of animation, the game needs to use either CHR RAM or a CHR ROM mapper with 1 KiB sprite banks so that both player 1's animation and player 2's animation can be loaded at once. According to an article in Nintendo Power, character selection in Pro Wrestling was the driving force behind the invention of UNROM.

Technically, juxtaposition isn't impossible with CHR ROM mappers, but almost no mappers support assigning a separate tile bank for each space in a nametable. MMC5 has an "ExGrafix" mode that allows this, regardless of page boundaries within the CHR ROM, as long as the game doesn't scroll vertically or uses the effect only in the playfield or only in the status bar. (MMC4 also supports automatically switching CHR ROM banks, although in a much more limited way than MMC5.) Thus only MMC5 can properly handle Chinese characters without needing each message to be rendered to a separate page.

Switching to CHR RAM

It's straightforward to change an existing project using NROM to use CHR RAM.

Start with an NROM-256 project, and make sure at least 8300 bytes are free in the PRG ROM. We want to make sure CHR RAM works before dealing with mapper bankswitch.
Remove the CHR ROM data from your build process, whether it be .incbin "mytiles.chr" after the IRQ vector or copy /b game.prg+mytiles.chr game.nes after assembly and linking.
In your program's iNES header, set the number of CHR banks to 0 (which signifies CHR RAM). (If you are using a NES 2.0 header, also set the CHR RAM amount.)
In your program's init code, after the PPU has stabilized but before you turn on rendering, jsr copy_mytiles_chr which is listed below (or you can inline the code).
Rebuild your project. The size should end up as 32,784 bytes (16 bytes of header and 32,768 bytes of PRG ROM).

; for ca65
PPUMASK = $2001
PPUADDR = $2006
PPUDATA = $2007

.segment "CODE"
.proc copy_mytiles_chr
src = 0
  lda #<mytiles_chr  ; load the source address into a pointer in zero page
  sta src
  lda #>mytiles_chr
  sta src+1

  ldy #0       ; starting index into the first page
  sty PPUMASK  ; turn off rendering just in case
  sty PPUADDR  ; load the destination address into the PPU
  sty PPUADDR
  ldx #32      ; number of 256-byte pages to copy
loop:
  lda (src),y  ; copy one byte
  sta PPUDATA
  iny
  bne loop  ; repeat until we finish the page
  inc src+1  ; go to the next page
  dex
  bne loop  ; repeat until we've copied enough pages
  rts
.endproc

.segment "RODATA"
mytiles_chr: .incbin "mytiles.chr"

The original NROM-256 board is designed to take a mask ROM or a JEDEC-pinout EPROM in the CHR ROM position, not a 6264 SRAM. Because the board needs to be rewired slightly for CHR RAM, a few emulators do not emulate iNES Mapper 000 (NROM) with CHR RAM. For these, you'll need to use iNES Mapper 034 (BNROM), which has CHR RAM and 32 KiB bank switching.

The next step after this is to switch to a mapper that allows switching PRG banks. See Programming UNROM and Programming MMC1.

Notes

Based on forum posts: 42576 and 61957

Clock rate

The clock rate of various components in the NES differs between consoles in the USA and Europe due to the different television standards used (NTSC M vs. PAL B). The color encoding method used by the NES (see NTSC video) requires that the master clock frequency be six times that of the color subcarrier, but this frequency is about 24% higher on PAL than on NTSC. In addition, PAL has more scanlines per field and fewer fields per second than NTSC. Furthermore, the PAL CPU's master clock could have been divided by 15 to preserve the ratio between CPU and PPU speeds, but Nintendo chose to keep the Johnson counter structure, which always has an even period, and divide by 16 instead.

So the main differences between the NTSC and PAL PPUs are depicted in the following table:

Property | NTSC (2C02) | PAL (2C07) | Dendy | RGB (2C03) | RGB (Vs. 4) | RGB (2C05)
Master clock speed | 21.477272 MHz ± 40 Hz
236.25 MHz ÷ 11 by definition | 26.601712 MHz ± 50 Hz
26.6017125 MHz by definition | Like PAL | Like NTSC
CPU | Ricoh 2A03 | Ricoh 2A07 | UMC 6527P | Ricoh 2A03
CPU clock speed | 21.47~ MHz ÷ 12 = 1.789773 MHz
Same as NTSC Amiga clock ÷ 4 | 26.60~ MHz ÷ 16 = 1.662607 MHz | 26.60~ MHz ÷ 15 = 1.773448 MHz
Same as PAL Amiga clock ÷ 4 | Like NTSC
APU Frame Counter rate | 60 Hz | 50 Hz[1] | 59 Hz[2] | Like NTSC
PPU | Ricoh 2C02 | Ricoh 2C07 | UMC 6538 | Ricoh 2C03 | Ricoh 2C04-0001 through 2C04-0004 | Ricoh 2C05
PPU clock speed | 21.477272 MHz ÷ 4 | 26.601712 MHz ÷ 5 | Like PAL | Like NTSC
PPU dots per CPU cycle | 3 | 3.2 | 3 | Like NTSC
Height of picture | 240 scanlines | 239 scanlines | Like PAL | Like NTSC
Nominal visible picture height (see Overscan) | 224 scanlines | 268 scanlines | Like PAL | Like NTSC
"Post-render" blanking lines between end of picture and NMI | 1 scanline | 1 scanline | 51 scanlines | Like NTSC
Length of vertical blanking after NMI | 20 scanlines | 70 scanlines | 20 scanlines | Like NTSC
Time during which OAM can be written | Vertical or forced blanking | Only during first 20 scanlines after NMI | Like NTSC | Like NTSC
"Pre-render" lines between vertical blanking and next picture | 1 scanline
Total number of dots per frame | 341 × 261 + 340.5 = 89341.5
(pre-render line is one dot shorter in every other frame) | 341 × 312 = 106392 | Like PAL | 341 × 262 = 89342
Vertical scan rate | 60.0988 Hz | 50.0070 Hz | Like PAL | 60.0985 Hz
Color of top and bottom borders | N/A | Always black ($1D) | Like PAL |  ? |  ? |  ?
Side borders | Palette entry at $3F00 | Always black ($1D), intruding on left and right 2 pixels and top 1 pixel of picture | Like PAL |  ? |  ? |  ?
Color emphasis
(with correlating bit in PPUMASK) | Blue (D7), green (D6), red (D5) | Blue (D7), red (D6), green (D5) | Like PAL | Blue, green, red (full scale)
Other quirks | | | | Missing $2D and $3D greys | Permutated palette | PPUCTRL and PPUMASK are swapped; revision ID in PPUSTATUS (D4-D0)

Some frequencies in the above table are rounded.

The 2C03, 2C04, and 2C05 PPUs were all found in Nintendo's Vs. System and PlayChoice-10 (a.k.a. PC10 or PC-10) arcade systems. Famicom Titler, Famicom TVs, and RGB-modded NES consoles would use either the 2C03 or a 2C05 with glue logic to unswap $2000 and $2001. (Later RGB mods used a 2C02 in output mode and faked out all palette logic.)

The color emphasis bits on the PAL NES have their red and green bits in PPUMASK swapped

The authentic NES sold in Brazil is an NTSC NES with an adapter board to turn the NTSC video into PAL-M video, a variant of PAL using NTSC frequencies but PAL's color modulation.

Dendy is a clone of the Famicom distributed by Steepler and sold in Russia. The chipset in Dendy and several other PAL famiclones (6527P+6538) is designed for compatibility with Famicom games, including games with CPU cycle counting mappers (e.g. VRC4) and games that use a cycle-timed NMI handler (e.g. Balloon Fight). This explains the faster CPU divider and longer post-render period vs. the authentic PAL NES.

To compensate for these differences, you can detect the TV system at power-on.

CNROM

CNROM

Company | Nintendo, others
Boards | CNROM
PRG ROM capacity | 32K
PRG ROM window | n/a
PRG RAM capacity | None
CHR capacity | 32K
CHR window | 8K
Nametable mirroring | Fixed H or V, controlled by solder pads
Bus conflicts | Yes
IRQ | No
Audio | No
iNES mappers | 003, 185

NESCartDB

iNES 003
iNES 185
CNROM

NES-CNROM (and its HVC counterpart) is a particular Nintendo cartridge board which uses uses discrete logic to provide up to four 8 KB banks of CHR ROM. The most common usage of this board, as well as other third-party compatible boards, is assigned to iNES mapper 3. (See iNES Mapper 003 for the suggested emulator implementation.) A small collection of non-bankswitching CNROM boards that have an incompatible copy-protection issue are assigned to iNES Mapper 185.

Contents

1 Banks
2 Registers

2.1 Bank select ($8000-$FFFF)

3 Hardware

3.1 Solder Pad Config

4 Variants
5 Notes
6 See Also

Banks

CPU $8000-$FFFF: 16 KB PRG ROM, fixed (if 16 KB PRG ROM used, then this is the same as $C000-$FFFF)
CPU $C000-$FFFF: 16 KB PRG ROM, fixed
PPU $0000-$1FFF: 8 KB switchable CHR ROM bank

For 16 KB PRG ROM testing, Joust (NES) makes a worthwhile test subject.

Registers

Bank select ($8000-$FFFF)

7  bit  0
---- ----
xxDD xxCC
  ||   ||
  ||   ++- Select 8 KB CHR ROM bank for PPU $0000-$1FFF
  ++------ Security diodes config

Hardware

The CNROM board contains a 74HC161 binary counter used as a quad D latch (4-bit register) to select the current CHR bank.

Early CNROM boards allow security diodes to be placed. If the latched bits 4 and 5 do not correspond to the configuration of the 2 diodes placed on the board while the PPU is rendering, the latched signal will conflict with some of the PPU's addresses bus and create bus conflicts. This system was probably created to make dumping cartridges harder, because the dumping device would have to write the correct value into the 74HC161 latch to dump the CHR ROM properly, or else bus conflicts will appear and possibly damage the dumping device. This anti-dump precaution wasn't very effective, and Nintendo quickly gave up on this. Only Japanese games released in 1986 are known to have these diodes present.

Some Japanese CNROM games combine the diode security with special CHR ROM where higher addresses are actually additional chip enable signals. This will cause the game's CHR ROM to be disabled at all if the wrong CHR bank is selected, making only one actual 8K CHR bank available (the games could in theory run in a NROM board without being affected). Those games typically turn the PPU off, switch in the wrong CHR bank (that return open bus) with wrong diode configuration, read a CHR byte in a specific place where the bus conflicts with the mapper will not appear even with the wrong diode config, then read the same byte with the correct bank and diode config latched, and enter in an infinite loop if the two reads matches. Those games have been assigned to iNES Mapper 185. Trying to dump them as regular NROM games will create bus conflicts with the dumping device, and even if this is bypassed the game will not run because the CHR ROM will be mirrored for all 8K bank select values.

Solder Pad Config

Horizontal mirroring : 'H' disconnected, 'V' connected.
Vertical mirroring : 'H' connected, 'V' disconnected.

16 KB PRG ROM : 'SL' connected, 'CL' disconnected.
32 KB PRG ROM : 'SL' disconnected, 'CL' connected.

Bit 4 security implemented to '0' : D2 cathode set to '3' (CHR A12) and D2 anode set to '4' (latch).
Bit 4 security implemented to '1' : D2 cathode set to '4' (latch) and D2 anode set to '3' (CHR A12).
Bit 5 security implemented to '0' : D1 cathode set to '1' (CHR A10) and D1 anode set to '2' (latch).
Bit 5 security implemented to '1' : D1 cathode set to '2' (latch) and D1 anode set to '1' (CHR A10).
Security unimplemented : D1 and D2 not present.

Variants

CNROM operates identically to a GNROM with one PRG bank.

The upper 2 bank select bits on the 74HC161 were connected to security diodes. If they were connected to CHR ROM address lines instead, this board could have theoretically supported up to 128 KB of CHR ROM. In fact, iNES Mapper 003 encompasses both CNROM and similar boards that used more CHR ROM, such as those made by Bandai and Panesian.

The Japanese version of Dance Aerobics adds a sound playback IC to a CNROM-like board. It adds a register mapped from $6000-$7FFF that can play one of eight voice recordings. However, the specifics of the compression are not yet known, and there is no standardized way to bundle audio data with iNES images.

Theoretically the bank select register could be implemented with a 74HC377 octal D latch, allowing up to 2 megabytes of CHR ROM.

Notes

Many CNROM games such as Milon's Secret Castle store data tables in otherwise unused portions of CHR ROM and access them through PPUDATA ($2007) reads. If an emulator can show the title screen of the NROM game Super Mario Bros., but CNROM games don't work, the emulator's PPUDATA readback is likely failing to consider CHR ROM bankswitching.

See Also

iNES Mapper 003 - The common emulator implementation used for this board, which includes some compatible additions.
iNES Mapper 185 - Emulation for a subset of CNROM boards that implement a weak form of copy protection.
Comprehensive NES Mapper Document by \Firebug\, information about mapper's initial state is inaccurate.

Categories: Expansion audio, CNROM-like mappers, Nintendo licensed mappers, In NesCartDB

Controller Reading

Contents

1 Basic Example
2 DPCM Safety using Repeated Reads
3 DPCM Safety using OAM DMA
4 Directional Safety
5 Calculating Presses and Releases
6 Button Flags
7 External Examples
8 References

Basic Example

This describes an efficient method of reading the standard controller using ca65 syntax.

The result byte buttons should be placed in zero page to save a cycle each time through the loop.

; we reserve one byte for storing the data that is read from controller
.zeropage
buttons .res 1

When reading from JOYPAD* what is read might be different from $01/$00 for various reasons. (See Controller port registers.) In this code the only concern is bit 0 read from JOYPAD*..

JOYPAD1 = $4016
JOYPAD2 = $4017

This is the end result that will be stored in buttons. 1 if the button was pressed, 0 otherwise.

bit:   	 7     6     5     4     3     2     1     0
button:	 A     B  Select Start  Up   Down  Left  Right

This subroutine takes 132 cycles to execute but ignores the Famicom expansion controller. Many controller reading subroutines use the X or Y register to count 8 times through the loop. But this one uses a more clever ring counter technique: $01 is loaded into the result first, and once eight bits are shifted in, the 1 bit will be shifted out, terminating the loop.

; At the same time that we strobe bit 0, we initialize the ring counter
; so we're hitting two birds with one stone here
readjoy:
  lda #$01
  ; While the strobe bit is set, buttons will be continuously reloaded.
  ; This means that reading from JOYPAD1 will only return the state of the
  ; first button: button A.
  sta JOYPAD1
  sta buttons
  lsr a        ; now A is 0
  ; By storing 0 into JOYPAD1, the strobe bit is cleared and the reloading stops.
  ; This allows all 8 buttons (newly reloaded) to be read from JOYPAD1.
  sta JOYPAD1
loop:
  lda JOYPAD1
  lsr a	       ; bit0 -> Carry
  rol buttons  ; Carry -> bit0; bit 7 -> Carry
  bcc loop
  rts

Adding support for controllers on the Famicom's DA15 expansion port and for player 2's controller is straightforward.

.zeropage
buttons1: .res 1
buttons2: .res 1

.code
readjoy:
  lda #$01
  sta JOYPAD1
  sta buttons2  ; player 2's buttons double as a ring counter
  lsr a         ; now A is 0
  sta JOYPAD1
loop:
  lda JOYPAD1
  and #$03      ; ignore bits other than controller
  cmp #$01      ; Set carry if and only if nonzero
  rol buttons1  ; Carry -> bit0; bit 7 -> Carry
  lda JOYPAD2   ; Repeat 
  and #$03
  cmp #$01
  rol buttons2  ; Carry -> bit0; bit 7 -> Carry
  bcc loop
  rts

DPCM Safety using Repeated Reads

If your code is intended to be used with APU DMC playback, this code will need to be altered. The NES occasionally glitches the controller port twice in a row if sample playback is enabled, and games using samples need to work around this. For example, Super Mario Bros. 3 reads each controller's data at least two times each frame. First it reads it as normal, then it reads it again. If the two results differ, it does the procedure all over. Because repeated rereads can take a long time, another way is to just use the previous frame's button press data if the results differ:

last_frame_buttons1 = $00
last_frame_buttons2 = $01
first_read_buttons1 = $02
first_read_buttons2 = $03

readjoy_safe:
  lda buttons2
  sta last_frame_buttons2
  lda buttons1
  sta last_frame_buttons1

  ; Read the controllers once and stash the result
  jsr readjoy
  lda buttons2
  sta first_read_buttons2
  lda buttons1
  sta first_read_buttons1

  ; Read the controllers again and compare
  jsr readjoy
  ldx #1
cleanup_loop:
  ; Ignore read values if a bit deletion occurred
  lda buttons1,x
  cmp first_read_buttons1,x
  beq not_glitched
    lda last_frame_buttons,x
    sta buttons1,x
  not_glitched:

  dex
  bpl cleanup_loop

  rts

Note that if the player presses or releases a button between the two reads, this will interpret that as a corrupt read. Unfortunately, there's no way for it to tell the difference.

DPCM Safety using OAM DMA

Because DPCM reads may only occur on an odd cycle, it is possible to get glitch-free controller reads by timing all $4016/$4017 reads to fall on even cycles. This is made possible by the behavior of OAM DMA: the first cycle after an OAM DMA is guaranteed to be an even cycle.[1]

This is a relatively new technique, and is not entirely supported by emulators.[2]

   lda #OAM
   sta $4014          ; ------ DMA ------
   ldx #1             ; even odd          <- strobe code must take an odd number of cycles total
   stx controller1    ; even odd even
   stx $4016          ; odd even odd even
   dex                ; odd even
   stx $4016          ; odd even odd even
 read_loop:
   lda $4017          ; odd even odd EVEN <- loop code must take an even number of cycles total
   and #3             ; odd even
   cmp #1             ; odd even
   rol controller2, x ; odd even odd even odd even (X = 0; waste 1 cycle and 0 bytes for alignment)
   lda $4016          ; odd even odd EVEN
   and #3             ; odd even
   cmp #1             ; odd even
   rol controller1    ; odd even odd even odd
   bcc read_loop      ; even odd [even]

Directional Safety

To reject opposing presses (Up+Down and Left+Right), which are possible on a worn Control Pad:

  lda buttons1,x
  and #$0A          ; Compare Up and Left...
  lsr a
  and buttons1,x    ; to Down and Right
  beq not_updown
    ; Use previous frame's directions
    lda buttons1,x
    eor last_frame_buttons1,x
    and #$F0
    eor last_frame_buttons1,x
    sta buttons1,x
  not_updown:

To instead reject all diagonal presses, simulating a 4-way joystick:

  lda buttons1,x
  and #$0F  ; If A & (A - 1) is nonzero, A has more than one bit set
  beq not_diagonal
  sec
  sbc #1
  and buttons1,x  ; to Down and Right
  beq not_updown1
    ; Use previous frame's directions
    lda buttons1,x
    eor last_frame_buttons1,x
    and #$F0
    eor last_frame_buttons1,x
    sta buttons1,x
  not_diagonal:

Calculating Presses and Releases

To calculate newly pressed and newly released buttons:

  lda buttons1,x
  eor #$FF
  and last_frame_buttons1,x
  sta released_buttons1,x
  lda last_frame_buttons1,x
  eor #$FF
  and buttons1,x
  sta pressed_buttons1,x

Button Flags

It is helpful to define the buttons as a series of bit flags:

BUTTON_A        = 1 << 7
BUTTON_B        = 1 << 6
BUTTON_SELECT   = 1 << 5
BUTTON_START    = 1 << 4
BUTTON_UP       = 1 << 3
BUTTON_DOWN     = 1 << 2
BUTTON_LEFT     = 1 << 1
BUTTON_RIGHT    = 1 << 0

And then buttons can be checked as follows:

  lda buttons
  and #BUTTON_A | BUTTON_B
  beq notPressingAorB
  ; Handle presses.
notPressingAorB:

External Examples

Forum post: Blargg's DMC-fortified controller read routine
Forum post: Rahsennor's OAM-synchronized controller read
Forum post: Drag's bitwise DMC-safe controller reading

References

↑ Forum post: Rahsennor's OAM-synchronized controller read
↑ Forum post: as of May 2016, Nintendulator and Nestopia do not accurately emulate OAM-synchronized controller reading.

CPU addressing modes

The NES CPU is a second-source version of MOS Technology 6502, manufactured by Ricoh. Addressing modes and instruction timings are the same as those in the standard 6502.

This page summarizes the 6502 addressing modes and explains some cases where certain modes might be useful.

Indexed addressing

Indexed addressing modes use the X or Y register to help determine the address. The 6502 has six main indexed addressing modes:

Abbr | Name | Formula | Cycles
d,x | Zero page indexed | val = PEEK((arg + X) % 256) | 4
d,y | Zero page indexed | val = PEEK((arg + Y) % 256) | 4
a,x | Absolute indexed | val = PEEK(arg + X) | 4+
a,y | Absolute indexed | val = PEEK(arg + Y) | 4+
(d,x) | Indexed indirect | val = PEEK(PEEK((arg + X) % 256) + PEEK((arg + X + 1) % 256) * 256) | 6
(d),y | Indirect indexed | val = PEEK(PEEK(arg) + PEEK((arg + 1) % 256) * 256 + Y) | 5+

Notes:

Abbreviations for addressing modes are those used in WDC's 65C816 data sheets.
+ means add a cycle for write instructions or for page wrapping on read instructions, called the "oops" cycle below.

The 6502 has one 8-bit ALU and one 16-bit upcounter (for PC). To calculate a,x or a,y addressing in an instruction other than sta, stx, or sty, it uses the 8-bit ALU to first calculate the low byte while it fetches the high byte. If there's a carry out, it goes "oops", applies the carry using the ALU, and repeats the read at the correct address. Store instructions always have this "oops" cycle: the CPU first reads from the partially added address and then writes to the correct address. The same thing happens on (d),y indirect addressing.

The (d),y mode is used far more often than (d,x). The latter implies a table of addresses on zero page. On computers like the Apple II, where the BASIC interpreter uses up most of zero page, (d,x) is rarely used. But the NES has far more spare room in zero page, and music engine might use X = 0, 4, 8, or 12 to match APU register offsets.

Other addressing

Abbr | Name | Notes
| Implicit | Instructions like RTS or CLC have no address operand, the destination of results are implied.
A | Accumulator | Many instructions can operate on the accumulator, e.g. LSR A. Some assemblers will treat no operand as an implicit A where applicable.
#v | Immediate | Uses the 8-bit operand itself as the value for the operation, rather than fetching a value from a memory address.
d | Zero page | Fetches the value from an 8-bit address on the zero page.
a | Absolute | Fetches the value from a 16-bit address anywhere in memory.
label | Relative | Branch instructions (e.g. BEQ, BCS) have a relative addressing mode that specifies an 8-bit signed offset relative to the current PC.
(a) | Indirect | The JMP instruction has a special indirect addressing mode that can jump to the address stored in a 16-bit pointer anywhere in memory.

CPU interrupts

This page covers detailed interrupt behavior for the MOS 6502 CPU and assumes basic familiarity with 6502 interrupts. For a basic introduction to 6502 interrupts, see e.g. the MOS 6502 Programming Manual.

Contents

1 Detailed interrupt behavior
2 Delayed IRQ response after CLI, SEI, and PLP
3 Branch instructions and interrupts
4 Interrupt hijacking

4.1 IRQ and NMI tick-by-tick execution

5 Notes

Detailed interrupt behavior

The NMI input is edge-sensitive (reacts to high-to-low transitions in the signal) while the IRQ input is level-sensitive (reacts to a low signal level). Both inputs are active low.

The NMI input is connected to an edge detector. This edge detector polls the status of the NMI line during φ2 of each CPU cycle (i.e., during the second half of each cycle) and raises an internal signal if the input goes from being high during one cycle to being low during the next. The internal signal goes high during φ1 of the cycle that follows the one where the edge is detected, and stays high until the NMI has been handled.

The IRQ input is connected to a level detector. If a low level is detected on the IRQ input during φ2 of a cycle, an internal signal is raised during φ1 the following cycle, remaining high for that cycle only (or put another way, remaining high as long as the IRQ input is low during the preceding cycle's φ2).

The output from the edge detector and level detector are polled at certain points to detect pending interrupts. For most instructions, this polling happens during the final cycle of the instruction, before the opcode fetch for the next instruction. If the polling operation detects that an interrupt has been asserted, the next "instruction" executed is the interrupt sequence.

Many references will claim that interrupts are polled during the last cycle of an instruction, but this is true only when talking about the output from the edge and level detectors. As can be deduced from above, it's really the status of the interrupt lines at the end of the second-to-last cycle that matters.

If both an NMI and an IRQ are pending at the end of an instruction, the NMI will be handled and the pending status of the IRQ forgotten (though it's likely to be detected again during later polling).

The interrupt sequences themselves do not perform interrupt polling, meaning at least one instruction from the interrupt handler will execute before another interrupt is serviced.

Delayed IRQ response after CLI, SEI, and PLP

The RTI instruction affects IRQ inhibition immediately. If an IRQ is pending and an RTI is executed that clears the I flag, the CPU will invoke the IRQ handler immediately after RTI finishes executing. This is due to RTI restoring the I flag from the stack before polling for interrupts.

The CLI, SEI, and PLP instructions on the other hand change the I flag after polling for interrupts (like all two-cycle instructions they poll the interrupt lines at the end of the first cycle), meaning they can effectively delay an interrupt until after the next instruction. For example, if an interrupt is pending and the I flag is currently set, executing CLI will execute the next instruction before the CPU invokes the IRQ handler.

Verification and testing of this behavior in emulators can be accomplished through test ROM images.

Branch instructions and interrupts

The branch instructions have more subtle interrupt polling behavior. Interrupts are always polled before the second CPU cycle (the operand fetch). Additionally, for taken branches that cross a page boundary, interrupts are polled before the PCH fixup cycle (see [1] for a tick-by-tick breakdown of the branch instructions). An interrupt being detected at either of these polling points (including only being detected at the first one) will trigger a CPU interrupt.

Interrupt hijacking

The MOS 6502 and by extension the 2A03/2A07 has a quirk that can cause one type of interrupt to partially hijack another type if they occur very close to one another.

For example, if NMI is asserted during the first four ticks of a BRK instruction, the BRK instruction will execute normally at first (PC increments will occur and the status word will be pushed with the B flag set), but execution will branch to the NMI vector instead of the IRQ/BRK vector:

Each [] is a CPU tick. [...] is whatever tick precedes the BRK opcode fetch.

Asserting NMI during the interval marked with * causes a branch to the NMI routine instead of the IRQ/BRK routine:

     ********************
[...][BRK][BRK][BRK][BRK][BRK][BRK][BRK]

In a tick-by-tick breakdown of BRK, this looks like

 #  address R/W description
--- ------- --- -----------------------------------------------
 1    PC     R  fetch opcode, increment PC
 2    PC     R  read next instruction byte (and throw it away),
                increment PC
 3  $0100,S  W  push PCH on stack, decrement S
 4  $0100,S  W  push PCL on stack, decrement S
*** At this point, the signal status determines which interrupt vector is used ***
 5  $0100,S  W  push P on stack (with B flag set), decrement S
 6   $FFFE   R  fetch PCL, set I flag
 7   $FFFF   R  fetch PCH

Similarly, an NMI can hijack an IRQ, and an IRQ can hijack a BRK (though it won't be as visible since they use the same interrupt vector). The tick-by-tick breakdown of all types of interrupts is essentially like that of BRK, save for whether the B bit is pushed as set and whether PC increments occur.

IRQ and NMI tick-by-tick execution

For exposition and to emphasize similarity with BRK, here's the tick-by-tick breakdown of IRQ and NMI (derived from Visual 6502). A reset also goes through the same sequence, but suppresses writes, decrementing the stack pointer thrice without modifying memory. This is why the I flag is always set on reset.

 #  address R/W description
--- ------- --- -----------------------------------------------
 1    PC     R  fetch opcode (and discard it - $00 (BRK) is forced into the opcode register instead)
 2    PC     R  read next instruction byte (actually the same as above, since PC increment is suppressed. Also discarded.)
 3  $0100,S  W  push PCH on stack, decrement S
 4  $0100,S  W  push PCL on stack, decrement S
*** At this point, the signal status determines which interrupt vector is used ***
 5  $0100,S  W  push P on stack (with B flag *clear*), decrement S
 6   A       R  fetch PCL (A = FFFE for IRQ, A = FFFA for NMI), set I flag
 7   A       R  fetch PCH (A = FFFF for IRQ, A = FFFB for NMI)

Notes

The above interrupt hijacking and IRQ response behavior is tested by the cpu_interrupts_v2 test ROM.
For more quirky behavior related to VBlank NMI's from the PPU, see PPU frame timing.
The B status flag doesn't physically exist inside the CPU, and only appears as different values being pushed for bit 4 of the saved status bits by BRK and NMI/IRQ.
For a more technical description of what causes the hijacking behavior, see Visual6502's writeup.

Detect TV system

The following code detects the TV system. A game can use it to compensate for differences in clock rate among various NES models. It has been tested on NTSC NES and Famicom, PAL NES, and PAL famiclones using the Dendy chipset, as well as emulators in NTSC, PAL, and Dendy modes.

;
; NES TV system detection code
; Copyright 2011 Damian Yerrick
;
; Copying and distribution of this file, with or without
; modification, are permitted in any medium without royalty provided
; the copyright notice and this notice are preserved in all source
; code copies.  This file is offered as-is, without any warranty.
;
.export getTVSystem
.importzp nmis

.align 32  ; ensure that branches do not cross a page boundary

;;
; Detects which of NTSC, PAL, or Dendy is in use by counting cycles
; between NMIs.
;
; NTSC NES produces 262 scanlines, with 341/3 CPU cycles per line.
; PAL NES produces 312 scanlines, with 341/3.2 CPU cycles per line.
; Its vblank is longer than NTSC, and its CPU is slower.
; Dendy is a Russian famiclone distributed by Steepler that uses the
; PAL signal with a CPU as fast as the NTSC CPU.  Its vblank is as
; long as PAL's, but its NMI occurs toward the end of vblank (line
; 291 instead of 241) so that cycle offsets from NMI remain the same
; as NTSC, keeping Balloon Fight and any game using a CPU cycle-
; counting mapper (e.g. FDS, Konami VRC) working.
;
; nmis is a variable that the NMI handler modifies every frame.
; Make sure your NMI handler finishes within 1500 or so cycles (not
; taking the whole NMI or waiting for sprite 0) while calling this,
; or the result in A will be wrong.
;
; @return A: TV system (0: NTSC, 1: PAL, 2: Dendy; 3: unknown
;         Y: high byte of iterations used (1 iteration = 11 cycles)
;         X: low byte of iterations used
.proc getTVSystem
  ldx #0
  ldy #0
  lda nmis
nmiwait1:
  cmp nmis
  beq nmiwait1
  lda nmis

nmiwait2:
  ; Each iteration takes 11 cycles.
  ; NTSC NES: 29780 cycles or 2707 = $A93 iterations
  ; PAL NES:  33247 cycles or 3022 = $BCE iterations
  ; Dendy:    35464 cycles or 3224 = $C98 iterations
  ; so we can divide by $100 (rounding down), subtract ten,
  ; and end up with 0=ntsc, 1=pal, 2=dendy, 3=unknown
  inx
  bne :+
  iny
:
  cmp nmis
  beq nmiwait2
  tya
  sec
  sbc #10
  cmp #3
  bcc notAbove3
  lda #3
notAbove3:
  rts
.endproc

What to change

PAL NES needs different music pitch from NTSC and Dendy.
NTSC needs different music speed from PAL NES and Dendy.
PAL NES needs different raster effects from NTSC and Dendy.
NTSC needs different scrolling and sprite movement speeds from PAL and Dendy.
PAL NES needs OAM DMA done first in vblank, while NTSC benefits from doing it last if using timed code to work around the DMC DMA glitch.
If you want to take advantage of PAL's longer vertical blank to load more tiles into CHR RAM, Dendy needs different detection of the end of rendering.

Division by a constant integer

Contents

1 Divide by a power of two
2 Division by a constant
3 Division of a constant by a variable ratio
4 Chain multiply by a variable

Divide by a power of two

In binary arithmetic, division by 2^n is equivalent to shifting right n times (technically this is true even if n is negative). For this reason, it is recommended that you design your NES project in a way that takes advantage of this fact. The rest of the division by 2^n can be easily obtainged by ANDing the original value by (2^n)-1.

For signed numbers, it is required that the bit shiting "in" the number at the left is the previous sign bit and not a '0'. This is commonly called an "arithmetic shift right" as opposed to a "logical shift right". Since the 6502 doesn't have any logical shift right instruction, it can be achevied that way :

    cmp #$80
    ror A

This will be true for all divisions discussed in this article, which focuses on unsigned numbers.

Division by a constant

When you want to divide 2 numbers, if the denominator is constant, it is possible take advantage of this to optimize code (as opposed to use the general purpose division by 2 variables).

First thing is to decompose the constant number into sum-of-power-of-two (i.e. write it in binary form). Then you'll need to know how many bits of the result you need, let's call this number n and let's call c your constant divisor. Take the variable number, and for each bit k, compare it to c<<k (= c*2^k) (in the order k = n-1, n-2, ... downto 0 included). If the comparaison bit is set, substract c<<k, and in all cases rotate the result left (note that after the substraction c will always be set). For example this division code divide the variable in A by 14 and keeps the lower 4 bit of results.

;Division by 14
      pha
      lda #$00
      sta Res      ;Init the res varialbe (needed because we're doing less than 8 shifts)
      pla
      cmp #$70     ;Compare to 14<<3 and set bit
      bcc + 
      sbc #$70 
+     rol Res 
      cmp #$38     ;14<<2
      bcc + 
      sbc #$38 
+     rol Res 
      cmp #$1c     ;14<<1
      bcc + 
      sbc #$1c 
+     rol Res 
      cmp #$0e     ;14<<0
      bcc + 
      sbc #$0e 
+     rol Res      ;A = remainder, Res = quotient

Of couse the result will only be correct if if fits in 4-bit in the above example (because it does 4 compare/shift operations), if you except a larger number of bits you should adapt your code to take that into account.

See also: Unsigned Integer Division Routines - NESDev forum post with a collection of efficient 8-bit division by constant routines.

Division of a constant by a variable ratio

When you divide 2 numbers, is it possible to optimize the algorithm if the numerator is constant and the denominator variable ? To be written.

Chain multiply by a variable

If you want to do an algorithm that does a really great number of divisions by a variable, but that the value of the variable is constant for the whole algorithm, it could be faster to write a code that generate the above code in RAM and execute it that way instead of doing the slower variable / variable code.

Errata

This page describes aspects of the NES hardware that may be considered an error in the implementation (errata), or just otherwise unintuitive or unexpected behaviour.

Many of these issues are poorly emulated, and can cause program compatibility problems, especially for homebrew games not tested on hardware.

Contents

1 Video

1.1 OAM and Sprites

2 Input
3 Audio

3.1 APU Pulse
3.2 APU DMC

4 CPU
5 References

Video

Setting the VRAM address using PPUADDR ($2006) corrupts the scroll position. (Workaround: Reset the scroll position using PPUSCROLL ($2005) and PPUCTRL ($2000) after finishing all background updates.)

Reading PPUSTATUS ($2002) at the exact same time that PPUSTATUS bit 7 goes high at the start of vertical blanking keeps $2002.D7 from going high at all that frame. (Workaround: Use NMI to wait for vertical blanking.)

If one enables NMIs (PPUCTRL bit 7) while PPUSTATUS bit 7 is set, it will immediately trigger a new NMI in the NES CPU. This can only happen during vertical blanking if the code has not yet read PPUSTATUS. (Workaround: Read PPUSTATUS immediately before enabling NMIs.)

When writing to PPUCTRL ($2000) at the exact start of horizontal blanking may cause the PPU to start reading from the left name table instead of the right. Workarounds:

Use horizontal or one-screen mirroring.
Don't write to PPUCTRL outside vertical or forced blanking except as part of a properly timed raster effect. If you are writing to PPUCTRL as a way of temporarily preventing the NMI handler from being called while it is already running, don't disable NMI through PPUCTRL. Instead, use a variable to lock out reentrant NMI, and check this variable at the beginning of your NMI handler.[1]

After reset ends (by CIC or reset button), the PPU refuses to accept data written to the registers at PPUCTRL, PPUMASK, PPUSCROLL ($2005), and PPUADDR ($2006) for about the length of one frame. NES startup code should wait at least this long after reset before using the PPU (see: Init code).

The VBlank flag in $2002.D7 is not cleared on reset, only power-up.

Some 6502 write instructions produce an extra read or write as part of their operation, which produces unexpected results when used with PPU registers OAMDATA ($2004) and PPUDATA ($2007). This includes all read-modify-write instructions (ASL, LSR, ROL, ROR, DEC, INC) as well as indexed addressing instructions (e.g. STA $2000, X). Spurious reads or writes that operate on these PPU registers are a problem, because they have the side effect of incrementing its internal write address.

[2C07 and Dendy only] The PAL red and green emphasis bits are swapped with respect to the 2C02 (NTSC).

[2A03] DMC DMA during reads from $2007 can cause an extra read signal, causing a lost byte. This issue can also affect $2002 vblank polling (though this is already unreliable, see above). Workaround: disable DMC while reading from PPU.

Setting bit 6 of PPUCTRL (EXTBG direction) on a stock NES to 1 (output) causes a bus conflict that can potentially damage the PPU. See master/slave_mode_and_the_EXT_pins.

A Y scroll position in 240-255 is treated as "negative", rendering the attribute table as two rows of garbage tiles.

Setting PPUADDR to a palette address while rendering is disabled will cause the PPU to render the color at that address. This means updating palettes outside of vblank can cause a flash even if rendering is disabled.

Color $0D in the palette is "blacker than black" and causes image stability problems on some TVs. Do not use this color.

OAM and Sprites

Sprite 0 hit does not trigger at x=255.

Sprite overflow is unreliable due to errors in its implementation. The internal copy to secondary OAM causes a diagonal fetch pattern, causing both false positives and false negatives in the sprite overflow bit. (Workaround: Make sure the ninth sprite immediately follows the eighth, and use sprite overflow only to time the top of the screen, not the bottom.) See: Sprite overflow bug.

Because OAM is DRAM, which needs to be refreshed frequently, the contents of OAM begin to decay quickly when rendering is turned off via PPUMASK ($2001). During rendering, sprite evaluation will continually refresh the OAM data. Caveats and workarounds:

The data remains reliably intact for about the length of NTSC's vblank, but longer than this and it will begin to corrupt itself.[2]
Using OAM DMA ($4014) during vblank is usually the best way to fill the entire OAM buffer during vblank.
Writes to OAMDATA ($2004) are usually too slow to fill the entire OAM buffer before it begins to decay. It can be used during vblank to update a few bytes of OAM.
PAL systems must execute OAM DMA early within vblank, because sprite evaluation begins partway through vblank to keep it refreshed during its extended duration.[3]

Reading from OAM is inconsistent or unusable depending on the hardware revision. This is due to differences in its DRAM controller, and its lack of reliability in edge cases:

[2C02 through 2C02E (early Famicoms and very early NESes)] OAM is simply never readable.
[2C02 only] Writes to OAMADDR ($2003) corrupt OAM. (Workaround: Rewrite entire OAM before rendering starts, possibly using DMA initiated by writes to $4014, or rely on OAMADDR being 0 at end of rendering.)
[2C07 only] OAM can only be accessed for the 20 scanlines after the NMI would have happened. (To compensate for PAL's longer vblank period, the 2C07 always enables the OAM refresh logic, regardless of whether rendering is enabled.)

Leaving the value in OAMADDR (either written or by autoincrement) at a value of eight or greater before rendering starts causes minor OAM corruption, copying the eight bytes at OAMADDR&~7 to the beginning of OAM.

Turning rendering off in PPUMASK ($2001) before the PPU has finished evaluating sprites for that line (x=192 for lines with no sprites, x=240 for lines with at least one sprite) can corrupt OAM, leading to sprite flicker.

Input

DMC DMA during a controller read ($4016/$4017) causes double clocking, which causes bits of the report to be skipped. A common symptom is spurious presses of Right. Workarounds:

Standard controller / Power Pad: read the controller multiple times to make sure valid input is read.
Four Score: check for signature.
Arkanoid controller: prevent a sudden single frame acceleration.
If already using DMC IRQ: read the controller in the DMC IRQ handler.

Audio

APU Pulse

In sweep decrease mode, the carry input differs between the two channels, causing a slightly different sweep rate.

Channels set to low frequencies can get silenced by the sweep unit if it is left in increase mode, even if the sweep is otherwise disabled. Workaround:

Write $08 to $4001 and $4005 to use decrease mode while disabling sweep.)

Writing to $4003 or $4007 to change the high byte of the period while a note is playing causes a click as the phase resets. Workarounds:

Write $4003 and $4007 only when they have changed.
The hardware sweep can be used to change the high period bits by clocking it immediately with a write to $4017.[4] (Advanced technique.)

APU DMC

The length counter for DPCM samples ends up reading 1 byte past the end of an otherwise 16 byte aligned sample. This creates a need for 15 bytes of padding between samples.
The sample playback frequency table contains a set of 16 pitches tuned to a standard A-440 scale. These appear to have been designed for a limited wavetable synthesis using looped samples, but because of the +1 modifier on sample length, the wavelength is detuned.
The frequency table on PAL systems contains 2 slight tuning errors ($4 and $C).[5]
Playback of samples generates occasional conflicts with controller reads through $4016/4017 (see above: Input), as well as PPU reads through $2007 (see above: Video). When using DPCM samples, the code must work around these conflicts.

CPU

The NES CPU has several hardware gotchas, most of which are inherited from the MOS 6502 it is derived from:[6][7]

JMP ($xxyy), or JMP indirect, does not advance pages if the lower eight bits of the specified address is $FF; the upper eight bits are fetched from $xx00, 255 bytes earlier, instead of the expected following byte.
All of the zero page addressing modes wrap within the zero page. The $xx,x , $xx,y, and ($xx,x) addressing modes all count 254,255,0,1…; none advance 254,255,256,257…
The ($xx),y addressing mode wraps when fetching the indirect address if the lower eight bits are stored at $FF (the upper eight bits are fetched from $0000, not $0100).
BRK, IRQ, or NMI can mask each other under certain conditions. (see Visual6502 wiki [1] and [2] ) Not all can happen on the NES.
Decimal mode was disconnected from the ALU in the NES's second-source 6502 to save on patent royalties. Some famiclones, however, use an authentic 6502 with a working decimal mode. (Workaround: Don't SED, and convert binary numbers to decimal when displaying them.)
The 6502 has several unofficial opcodes that were not part of its specification, but do reliably exist on the Famicom and NES. Code using these opcodes may not be portable to other variants of the 6502 CPU (e.g. SNES). Some games rely on the operation of these unofficial opcodes.
Page wrapping behavior is reliable on the Famicom/NES but may not be portable to other variants of the 6502 CPU.

References

↑ Forum: Random glitchy line in Super Mario Bros. on real hardware?
↑ Forum: Just how cranky is the PPU OAM?
↑ Forum: PAL OAM reliability during vblank.
↑ Forum: Vibrato on square without phase reset.
↑ Forum: PAL DPCM frequency table contains 2 errors.
↑ 6502.org forum: 6502 hardware gotchas.
↑ Wikipedia's article on the 6502.

Family Computer Disk System

The Famicom Disk System was a Japan-exclusive storage device for the Famicom, designed to reduce Nintendo's cost of making copies of games by switching from mask ROM chips to a storage medium based on Mitsumi's Quick Disk. Unfortunately for Nintendo, it also reduced the pirates' cost of making copies of games.

The iNES mapper #20 is assigned to FDS.

Contents

1 .FDS format
2 Overview
3 Hardware
4 FDS Disk Side format
5 Data not stored in the FDS image

5.1 Gaps
5.2 CRCs
5.3 True disc capacity

6 Block format

6.1 Disk info block (block 1)

6.1.1 Date format
6.1.2 Price
6.1.3 Manufacturer codes

6.2 File amount block (block 2)
6.3 File header block (block 3)
6.4 File data block (block 4)

7 Registers

7.1 IRQ timer low ($4020)
7.2 IRQ timer high ($4021)
7.3 IRQ timer enable ($4022)
7.4 Master I/O enable ($4023)
7.5 Write data register ($4024)
7.6 FDS Control ($4025)
7.7 External connector ($4026)
7.8 Disk Status Register 0 ($4030)
7.9 Read data register ($4031)
7.10 Disk drive status register ($4032)
7.11 External connector read ($4033)
7.12 Sound ($4040-$4092)

8 Pseudo-registers
9 BIOS calls

9.1 Disk access routines
9.2 Low-Level Disk access routines
9.3 Example code how to load files
9.4 Error list
9.5 Disk ID structure
9.6 File list structure
9.7 File header structure
9.8 Disk information structure

10 Other BIOS calls

10.1 VRAM write transfer structure
10.2 VRAM Buffer notes
10.3 Read routines and VRAM buffer
10.4 Load Tileset notes

11 References

.FDS format

fwNES was an NES emulator developed by Fan Wan Yang. Its most lasting contribution to the NES scene was its disk image file format, an image of the Quick Disk media.

The FDS format (file name suffix .fds) is a way to store Famicom Disk System disk data. It consists of the following sections, in order:

Header (16 bytes)
Disk data (65500 * x bytes)

The format of the header is as follows:

0-3: Constant $46 $44 $53 $1A ("FDS" followed by MS-DOS end-of-file)
4: Number of disk sides
5-15: Zero filled

Note: Most games are an even number of sides. Ports from NROM were one side. No commercial FDS game had an odd number of sides greater than 1. Disk sides comes in the following order :

Disc 1 Side A
Disc 1 Side B
Disc 2 Side A
Disc 2 Side B
etc...

Overview

PRG ROM : 8 KB BIOS at $E000-$FFFF
PRG RAM: 32 KB at $6000-$DFFF
CHR capacity: 8 KB RAM
Storage capacity : ~64 KB per disk side
Nametable mirroring: Controlled by mapper
Subject to bus conflicts: No

Games are stored on one or multiple disk sides. The FDS BIOS is used to load data from disks to PRG RAM or VRAM, and games can execute from there.

Hardware

The Famicom disk system comes in two parts : The disk drive and the RAM adapter.

The RAM adapter is a special shaped cartridge that contains the RAM chips, IRQ hardware, sound generation hardware, a serial interface for the disk drive and another (rarely used) serial port.

The Disk Drive has to be powered separately and is only connected to the Famicom/NES through the serial cable to the RAM adapter.

Most disk drives contains two motors: a rotation motor that spins the disk at a constant rate, and a tracking motor. However, the FDS only contains a single motor that does both at once. There is some mechanism that detects when the head reaches the end of the disc and make it return to the start, which makes a click sound.

Because of this limitation, random access to the disc is not possible, you can only spin the disc and wait until you detect the head is at the start of the disc, then wait until it reaches the desired access place. A complete cycle through the entire disc takes about 7 seconds.

The disc drives only contains basic electronics, there is no "intelligence" in it; therefore, the serial interface almost directly represents what is stored on the disc.

FDS Disk Side format

Each disk side must be structured into block as follows :

1, 2, 3, 4, 3, 4, ...., 3, 4

The 3, 4 pattern should be repeated once per file present on the disk.

From the last file, fill the side with all 0 so that the side has exactly 65500 is reached.

Data not stored in the FDS image

In addition to data stored in the FDS image, there is other data stored on the disc, but removed when the disc is dumped because such data wasn't meaningful for emulation.

Gaps

Physically on the disc, there are "gaps" of 0 recorded between blocks and before the start of the disc. Length of the gaps are as follows:

Before the start of the disc : At least 26150 bits, 28300 typical.
Gap between blocks : At least 480 bits, 976 bits typical.

Gaps are teminated by a single '1' bit. In terms of bytes, it would be $80, as the data is stored in little endian format.

CRCs

At the end of each block, a 16-bit CRC is stored. On loading, the CRC is *not* calculated by the 6502 in the BIOS, but by the RAM adapter, which monitors disc transfers and calculates the CRC. It will automatically send an error code if both CRCs doesn't match.

True disc capacity

Even if the FDS disc side image is always 65500 bytes, one WILL have to subtract all the bits taken by the gaps and CRCs to find the actual disc capacity. In this regard, the way the FDS image is made is not smart because all the bits that were saved by not dumping useless data should be wasted in zeroes at the end of the disc side. In addition to this, the programmer should be very careful for not using the whole disc side in FDS format, otherwise, the data might not fit the disc.

The actual disc capacity in bytes is (N = number of files):

65500 - 28300/8 - (2*N + 1)*(16 + 976)/8

For example, if you use 8 files, there's room for only 59854 bytes instead of the supposed 65500.

Block format

Disk info block (block 1)

Offset | Length (bytes) | Description | Details
0 | 1 | Block code | Raw byte: $01
1 | 14 | Disk verification | Literal ASCII string: *NINTENDO-HVC*
Used by BIOS to verify legitimate disk image
15 | 1 | Manufacturer code | See Manufacturer codes
16 | 3 | Game name | 3-letter ASCII code per game (e.g. LNK for The Legend of Zelda)
19 | 1 | Game type | $20 = " " — Normal disk
$45 = "E" — Event (e.g. Japanese national DiskFax tournaments)
$52 = "R" — Reduction in price via advertising
20 | 1 | Game version/revision number | Starts at $00, increments per revision
21 | 1 | Side number | $00 = Side A, $01 = Side B. Single-sided disks use $00
22 | 1 | Disk number | First disk is $00, second is $01, etc.
23 | 1 | Disk type | $00 = FMC ("normal card"), $01 = FSC ("card with shutter"). May correlate with FMC and FSC product codes
24 | 1 | Unknown | Speculative: (Err.10) Possibly indicates disk #; usually $00
Speculative: $00 = yellow disk, $01 = blue or gold disk, $FE = white disk, $FF = blue disk
25 | 1 | Boot read file code | Refers to the file code/file number to load upon boot/start-up
26 | 5 | Unknown | Raw bytes: $FF $FF $FF $FF $FF
31 | 3 | Manufacturing date | See Date format
34 | 1 | Country code | $49 = Japan
35 | 1 | Unknown | Raw byte: $61. Speculative: Region code?
36 | 1 | Unknown | Raw byte: $00. Speculative: Location/site?
37 | 2 | Unknown | Raw bytes: $00 $02
39 | 5 | Unknown | Speculative: some kind of game information representation?
44 | 3 | "Rewritten disk" date | See Date format. It's speculated this refers to the date the disk was formatted and rewritten by something like a Disk Writer kiosk. In the case of an original (non-copied) disk, this should be the same as Manufacturing date
47 | 1 | Unknown
48 | 1 | Unknown | Raw byte: $80
49 | 2 | Disk Writer serial number
51 | 1 | Unknown | Raw byte: $07
52 | 1 | Disk rewrite count | Value stored in BCD format. $00 = Original (no copies). Also see Price
53 | 1 | Actual disk side | $00 = Side A, $01 = Side B
54 | 1 | Unknown
55 | 1 | Price | See Price
56 | 2 | CRC

The *NINTENDO-HVC* string, stored in ASCII, proves that this is a FDS disk. If the string doesn't match, the BIOS will refuse to read the disk further.

If the FDS is started with a disk whose side number and disk number aren't both $00, it will be prompted to insert the first disk side. However, some games make this number $00, even for the second disk to make it bootable too.

All files with IDs smaller or equals to the boot read file code will be loaded when the game is booting.

The FDS also has a trademark security system similar to what Sega used on some of its consoles.

The 224-byte text at PPU $2800-$28DF must match the data in the BIOS, starting at $ED37. This data roughly translates into "produced by or under license from Nintendo" in the SMB1/Zelda character encoding. Traditionally, the first file on a disk is a nametable type file loaded into $2800, which is named KYODAKU- (きょだく or 許諾 means approval).

Date format

All bytes are stored in BCD format, in order of year, month, and day. To accurately calculate they year, add 1925 to the BCD value. For example, values of $63 $11 $28 would represent November ($11) 28th ($28), 1988 ($63 + 1925). The "magic year" of 1925 comes from the Japanese Shōwa period, despite the era only lasting from 1925 until 1989. Titles manufactured or updated later than 1989 are considered legitimate (e.g. $83 + 1925 = 2008).

Price

When the Disk rewrite count field is $00, the Price field represents the cost of a "new/original" disk. In this situation, a value of $01 means 3400円 (3400 yen), and a value of $03 also means 3400円 but includes peripherals. The example given by Enri in his Famicom Disk System documentation mentions the game とびだせ大作戦 (Tobidase Daisakusen/3D Worldrunner), where both sales of the game with and without the とびだせメガネ (Tobidase 3D glasses) cost 3400円. The reason for the delineation within the actual Price field is unknown.

When the Disk rewrite count field is $01, the Price field represents incurred costs of disk rewriting (such as that done by a Disk Writer kiosk). A value of $00 means 500円 (which appears to be specific to Mario Brothers via an in-box advertisement promising that all disk rewrites would only cost 500円), while a value of $01 means 600円.

Manufacturer codes

The manufacturer codes are similar (quite possibly identical) to that known on the GameBoy. There are some differences, however (for example, $A6).

Value | Company (English) | Company (Japanese)
$00 | <unlicensed> | <非公認>
$01 | Nintendo | 任天堂
$08 | Capcom | カプコン
$0A | Jaleco | ジャレコ
$18 | Hudson Soft | ハドソン
$49 | Irem | アイレム
$4A | Gakken | 学習研究社
$8B | BulletProof Software (BPS) | BPS
$99 | Pack-In-Video | パックインビデオ
$9B | Tecmo | テクモ
$9C | Imagineer | イマジニア
$A2 | Scorpion Soft | スコーピオンソフト
$A4 | Konami | コナミ
$A6 | Kawada Co., Ltd. | 河田
$A7 | Takara | タカラ
$A8 | Royal Industries | ロイヤル工業
$AC | Toei Animation | 東映動画
$AF | Namco | ナムコ
$B1 | ASCII Corporation | アスキー
$B2 | Bandai | バンダイ
$B3 | Soft Pro Inc. | ソフトプロ
$B6 | HAL Laboratory | HAL研究所
$BB | Sunsoft | サンソフト
$BC | Toshiba EMI | 東芝EMI
$C0 | Taito | タイトー
$C1 | Sunsoft / Ask Co., Ltd. | サンソフト アスク講談社
$C2 | Kemco | ケムコ
$C3 | Square | スクウェア
$C4 | Tokuma Shoten | 徳間書店
$C5 | Data East | データイースト
$C6 | Tonkin House/Tokyo Shoseki | トンキンハウス
$C7 | East Cube | イーストキューブ
$CA | Konami / Ultra / Palcom | コナミ
$CB | NTVIC / VAP | バップ
$CC | Use Co., Ltd. | ユース
$CE | Pony Canyon / FCI | ポニーキャニオン
$D1 | Sofel | ソフエル
$D2 | Bothtec, Inc. | ボーステック
$DB | Hiro Co., Ltd. | ヒロ
$E7 | Athena | アテナ
$EB | Atlus | アトラス

File amount block (block 2)

This block contains the total number of files recorded on disk.

SIZE   CONTENTS
1        $02
1       File Amount

More files might exist on the disk, but the BIOS load routine will ignore them, those files are called "hidden" files. Some games have a simple copy protection this way : They have their own loading routine similar to the one from the BIOS but hard-code the file amount to a higher number, which will allow for loading hidden files. This also allows the game to load faster because the BIOS will stop reading the disc after the last non-hidden file.

File header block (block 3)

SIZE     CONTENTS
1        $03
1        File Number  
1        File Indicate Code (file identification code)  
         ID specified at disk-read function call
8        File Name
2        File Address (16-bit little endian)
         the destination address when loading
2        File Size (16-bit little endian)
1        Kind of File  
         0:Program (PRAM)  
         1:Character (CRAM)  
         2:Name table (VRAM)

The file Number must go in increasing order, first file is 0. File IDs can be freely assigned, and this is the number which will decide which file is loaded from the disk (instead of the file number). An ID smaller than the boot number means the file is a boot file, and will be loaded on first start up.

File names are uppercase ASCII.

File data block (block 4)

SIZE      CONTENTS
1         $04
--        disk data

Registers

$402x registers are write-only $403x registers are read-only

IRQ timer low ($4020)

7  bit  0
---------
LLLL LLLL
|||| ||||
++++-++++- 8 LSB of IRQ timer

IRQ timer high ($4021)

7  bit  0
---------
LLLL LLLL
|||| ||||
++++-++++- 8 MSB of IRQ timer

IRQ timer enable ($4022)

7  bit  0
---------
xxxx xxEx
       |
       +-- Enable IRQ timer

Each CPU clock cycle the timer is decremented by one if the enable flag is set. When the counter reach 0, an IRQ is generated. Read $4030 to acknowledge the IRQ.

Note : Since the disk transfer routine also uses IRQs, it's very important to disable timer IRQs before doing any access to the disk.

Master I/O enable ($4023)

7  bit  0
---------
xxxx xxSD
       ||
       |+- Enable disk I/O registers
       +-- Enable sound I/O registers

This register sounds obscure. FDS bios just writes $00 then $83 to it.

Write data register ($4024)

The data that this register is programmed with will be the next 8-bit quantity to load into the shift register (next time the byte transfer flag raises), and to be shifted out and appear on pin 5 of the RAM adapter cable (2C33 pin 52).

FDS Control ($4025)

7  bit  0
---------
IS1B MRTD
|||| ||||
|||| |||+- Drive Motor Control  
|||| |||     0: Stop motor
|||| |||     1: Turn on motor
|||| ||+-- Transfer Reset
|||| ||        Set 1 to reset transfer timing to the initial state.
|||| |+--- Read / Write mode
|||| |     (0: write; 1: read)
|||| +---- Mirroring (0: horizontal; 1: vertical)
|||+------ CRC control (set during CRC calculation of transfer)
||+------- Always set to '1'
|+-------- Read/Write Start  
|            Turn on motor.  Set to 1 when the drive becomes ready for read/write
+--------- Interrupt Transfer  
             0: Transfer without using IRQ
             1: Enable IRQ when the drive becomes ready for 

A FDS game that wants to change mirroring probably don't want to touch motor related bits, so it should do a read-modify-write from the pseudo registers (see below).

External connector ($4026)

Output of expansion terminal where there's a shutter on the back of the ram card. The outputs of $4026 (open-collector with 4.7K ohm pull-ups (except on bit 7)), are shared with the inputs on $4033.

Disk Status Register 0 ($4030)

7  bit  0
---------
IExB xxTD
||||   ||
||||   |+- Timer Interrupt (1: an IRQ occurred)
||||   +-- Byte transfer flag. Set every time 8 bits have been transfered between the RAM adaptor & disk drive (service $4024/$4031). 
||||       Reset when $4024, $4031, or $4030 has been serviced.
|||+------ CRC control (0: CRC passed; 1: CRC error)
|+-------- End of Head (1 when disk head is on the most inner track)
+--------- Disk Data Read/Write Enable (1 when disk is readable/writable)

Read data register ($4031)

This register is loaded with the contents of an internal shift register every time the byte transfer flag raises. The shift register receives it's serial data via pin 9 of the RAM adapter cable (2C33 pin 51).

Disk drive status register ($4032)

7  bit  0
---------
xxxx xPRS
      |||
      ||+- Disk flag  (0: Disk inserted; 1: Disk not inserted)
      |+-- Ready flag (0: Disk read; 1: Disk not ready)
      +--- Protect flag (0: Not write protected; 1: Write protected or disk ejected)

External connector read ($4033)

7  bit  0
---------
BIII IIII
|||| ||||
|+++-++++- Input from expansion terminal where there's a shutter on the back of the ram card.
+--------- Battery status (0: Good; 1: Voltage is low).

When a bit is clear in $4026 port it will read back as '0' here (including battery bit) because of how open collector input works.

Sound ($4040-$4092)

For details on sound information, see FDS audio.

Pseudo-registers

Those registers are used by the FDS bios and FDS programs. They are used to overcome the problem that NES/FDS registers are write only, so it is effectively possible to modify only one bit of them without affecting other bits.

[$FF]:  value last written to PPUCTRL   $80 on reset.
[$FE]:  value last written to PPUMASK   $06 on reset
[$FD]:  value last written to PPUSCROLL#1 0'd on reset.
[$FC]:  value last written to PPUSCROLL#2 0'd on reset.
[$FB]:  value last written to $4016   0'd on reset.
[$FA]:  value last written to $4025   $2E on reset.
[$F9]:  value last written to $4026   $FF on reset.
$F5..$F8 : Used by controller read routines
$00..$0F is used as temporary memory for the BIOS. The main program can use it as temporary memory too.

Those values are used by the BIOS to determine action on interrupt.

($0102):	PC action on reset
[$0101]:	PC action on IRQ. set to $80 on reset
[$0100]:	PC action on NMI. set to $C0 on reset
($DFFE):	disk game IRQ vector    (if [$0101] = 11xxxxxxB)
($DFFC):	disk game reset vector  (if ($0102) = $5335, or $AC35)
($DFFA):	disk game NMI vector #3 (if [$0100] = 11xxxxxxB)
($DFF8):	disk game NMI vector #2 (if [$0100] = 10xxxxxxB)
($DFF6):	disk game NMI vector #1 (if [$0100] = 01xxxxxxB)

A few important notes :

After loading the boot files, $102 is set to $35 so that the ($DFFC) vector is used and the BIOS is skipped.
$103 indicate reset type : $AC = first boot of the game, $53 = the game was soft-reseted by the user
To use your own IRQ routine, you must manually write $c0 to $101
There is 3 possible NMI vectors, #3 is used by default.
On first start, the mirroring is set to horizontal, the stack pointer is $ff, and the I flag is clear. System RAM is filled with values used by the BIOS, and PRG RAM is uninitialized, except for parts of it which has files loaded in.

BIOS calls

Disk access routines

Routines takes one or two pointers as arguments. Those are placed directly after the JSR instruction: the subroutines uses the return address in stack to fetch the pointers and fix the return address.
Memory at $00-$0f will be affected by those routines
Unlike the vast majority of disk drives, the FDS lacks any kind of intelligent tracking system. All BIOS load and save functions will do access to the whole disk, no matter which data they load/save. A simple way to overcome this problem is to have your own loading routine, similar to the BIOS one but forcing the # of files to a smaller number than it actually is. That way the later files are not accessed at all and the earlier files load faster. Of course the maximal time is still taken when you have to load the files that are late on the disk.
All non-disk IRQ sources (timer, DMC and APU frame) should be properly disabled before calling any of these routines. The value at [$0101] however, is preserved on entry, and restored on exit.
On return of those routines, A = $00 means no error occurred, other number is error #. Main program should test if an error occurred with the BEQ or BNE instruction, BEQ will branch if no error, and BNE will branch if there is an error.
The structures defined below are used to identify files & disks in the access routines. The argument pointers should point to these structures in the program.

Address | Name | Input parameters | Output parameters | Description
$e1f8 | LoadFiles | Pointer to Disk ID, Pointer to File List | A = error #, Y = # of files loaded | Loads files specified by DiskID into memory from disk. Load addresses are decided by the file's header.
$e237 | AppendFile | Pointer to Disk ID, Pointer to File Header | A = error # | Appends the file data given by DiskID to the disk. This means that the file is tacked onto the end of the disk, and the disk file count is incremented. The file is then read back to verify the write. If an error occurs during verification, the disk's file count is decremented (logically hiding the written file).
$e239 | WriteFile | Pointer to Disk ID, Pointer to File Header, A = file # | A = error # | Same as "Append File", but instead of writing the file to the end of the disk, A specifies the sequential position on the disk to write the file (0 is the first). This also has the effect of setting the disk's file count to the A value, therefore logically hiding any other files that may reside after the written one.
$e2b7 | CheckFileCount | Pointer to Disk ID, A = # to set file count to | A = error # | Reads in disk's file count, compares it to A, then sets the disk's file count to A.
$e2bb | AdjustFileCount | Pointer to Disk ID, A = number to reduce current file count by | A = error # | Reads in disk's file count, decrements it by A, then writes the new value back.
$e301 | SetFileCount1 | Pointer to Disk ID, A = file count minus one = # of the last file | A = error # | Set the file count to A + 1
$e305 | SetFileCount | Pointer to Disk ID, A = file count | A = error # | Set the file count to A
$e32a | GetDiskInfo | Pointer to Disk Info | A = error # | Fills DiskInfo up with data read off the current disk.

Low-Level Disk access routines

Address | Name | Input parameters | Output parameters | Description
$e445 | CheckDiskHeader | Pointer to 10 byte string at $00 | | Compares the first 10 bytes on the disk coming after the FDS string, to 10 bytes pointed to by Ptr($00). To bypass the checking of any byte, a -1 can be placed in the equivelant place in the compare string. Otherwise, if the comparison fails, an appropriate error will be generated.
$e484 | GetNumFiles | | | Reads number of files stored on disk, stores the result in $06
$e492 | SetNumFiles | | A = number of files | Writes new number of files to disk header.
$e4a0 | FileMatchTest | Pointer to FileID list at $02 | | Uses a byte string pointed at by Ptr($02) to tell the disk system which files to load. The file ID's number is searched for in the string. If an exact match is found, [$09] is 0'd, and [$0E] is incremented. If no matches are found after 20 bytes, or a -1 entry is encountered, [$09] is set to -1. If the first byte in the string is -1, the BootID number is used for matching files (any FileID that is not greater than the BootID qualifies as a match).
$e4da | SkipFiles | Number of files to skip in $06 | | Skips over specified number of files.

Example code how to load files

Load
   jsr LoadFiles
   .dw DiskID
   .dw LoadList
   bne _Error        ;Check if there is an error
   rts
_Error
   jsr PrintError      ;If so print the error number and message to screen (include side/disk changing prompts)
_sideError
   lda $4032
   and #$01
   beq _sideError     ;Wait until disk is ejected
_insert
   lda $4032
   and #$01
   bne _instert      ;Wait until disk is inserted
   jmp Load

DiskID
   .db $01        ;Manufacturer code
   .db "NAME"     ;4-letter code of game
   .db $00        ;Version
   .db $01        ;Disk side
   .db $00        ;Disk number
   .db $00, $00   ;Extra disk IDs

LoadList          ;In this example the files with IDs equal to $02, $03 or $04 will be loaded into memory
   .db $02, $03, $04, $ff

Error list

Message in bold is the official BIOS message (if there is one) followed by an explanation

$00: no error
$01: disk set, ($4032.0) disk not set
$02: battery, ($4033.7) power supply failure
$03: ($4032.2) disk is write protected
$04: Wrong maker ID
$05: Wrong game
$06: Wrong game version
$07: a,b side, wrong side number
$08: disk no., wrong disk number
$09: wrong additional disk ID 1
$0a: wrong additional disk ID 2
$20: disk trouble, approval check failed
$21: disk trouble, '*NINTENDO-HVC*' string in block 1 doesn't match
$22: disk trouble, block type 1 expected
$23: disk trouble, block type 2 expected
$24: disk trouble, block type 3 expected
$25: disk trouble, block type 4 expected
$27: disk trouble, ($4030.4) block failed CRC
$28: disk trouble, ($4030.6) file ends prematurely during read
$29: disk trouble, ($4030.6) file ends prematurely during write
$30: disk trouble, ($4032.1) disk is full

Disk ID structure

This is a commonly used string. It consists of 10 bytes which are all compared directly against bytes 15..24 (right after the '*NINTENDO-HVC*' string) of the disk's header block (block type 1; always the first one on the disk). If any of the bytes fail the comparison, an appropriate error # is generated. Comparisons of immaterial data can be skipped by placing an $FF byte in the appropriate place in the DiskID string (for example, when the ROM BIOS boots a disk, it sets all the fields in the DiskID string to -1, except disk side #, and disk #, which are set to 0 (so these fields have to match 0)). The following chart describes the DiskID structure, and the error #'s returned when a comparison fails.

offset	size	error#	description
------	----	------	-----------
0	1	$04	game manufacturer code
1	4	$05	game ASCII name string
5	1	$06	game version
6	1	$07	disk side #
7	1	$08	disk #
8	1	$09	extra disk # data
9	1	$10	extra disk # data
A			-

File list structure

This is a list of 1-byte IDs of files to load. All files that matches any ID in the list are loaded. A list of up to 20 IDs is possible at a time, smaller lists should be terminated by a $ff byte (this implies a file ID can never be $ff).

Multiple files are loaded in the order as they exist on the disk, not in the order of the list.

File header structure

This structure is specified when a file is to be written to the disk. The first 14 bytes of this structure directly specify the data to use for generating a file header block (type 3, bytes [2..15]) to write to disk. The last 2 entries concern the file data to be written to disk (block type 4). The following is a table describing the FileHeader structure.

offset	size	description
------	----	-----------
00	1	file ID code
01	8	file name
09	2	load address
0B	2	file data size
0D	1	file type ($00 : Program; $01 : Character; $02 : Nametable)
0E	2	source address of file data (NOT written to disk)
10	1	source address type ($00 : RAM, $01 : VRAM)
11		-

Disk information structure

This is a data structure returned by a subroutine, of collected information from the disk (list of files on disk, disk size, etc.). The following table is a description of that structure.

offset	size
------  ----
0	1	game manufacturer code
1	4	game ASCII name string
5	1	game version
6	1	disk side #
7	1	disk #
8	1	extra disk # data
9	1	extra disk # data
A	1	# of files on disk

(the following block will appear for as many files as the "# of files on disk" byte indicates)

B	1	file ID code
C	8	file name (ASCII)

(the following is present after the last file info block. Disk size is equal to the sum of each file's size entry, plus an extra 261 per file.)

x	1	disk size high byte
x+1	1	disk size low  byte
x+2		-

Other BIOS calls

Address | Name | Input parameters | Output parameters | Affected RAM/Registers | Description
$e149 | Delay132 | | | | 132 clock cycle delay
$e153 | Delayms | | | X, Y | Delay routine, Y = delay in ms (approximate)
$e161 | DisPFObj | | | A, $fe | Disable sprites and background
$e16b | EnPFObj | | | A, $fe | Enable sprites and background
$e171 | DisObj | | | A, $fe | Disable sprites
$e178 | EnObj | | | A, $fe | Enable sprites
$e17e | DisPF | | | A, $fe | Disable background
$e185 | EnPF | | | A, $fe | Enable background
$e1b2 | VINTWait | | | $ff | Wait until next VBlank NMI fires, and return (for programs that does it the "everything in main" way). NMI vector selection at $100 is preserved, but further VBlanks are disabled.
$e7bb | VRAMStructWrite | Pointer to VRAM buffer to be written | | A, X, Y, $00, $01, $ff | Set VRAM increment to 1 (clear PPUCTRL/$ff bit 2), and write a VRAM buffer to VRAM. Read below for information on the structure.
$e844 | FetchDirectPtr | | $00, $01 = pointer fetched | A, X, Y, $05, $06 | Fetch a direct pointer from the stack (the pointer should be placed after the return address of the routine that calls this one (see "important notes" above)), save the pointer at ($00) and fix the return address.
$e86a | WriteVRAMBuffer | | | A, X, Y, $301, $302 | Write the VRAM Buffer at $302 to VRAM. Read below for information on the structure.
$e8b3 | ReadVRAMBuffer | X = start address of read buffer, Y = # of bytes to read | | A, X, Y | Read individual bytes from VRAM to the VRAMBuffer. (see notes below)
$e8d2 | PrepareVRAMString | A = High VRAM address, X = Low VRAM address, Y = string length, Direct Pointer = data to be written to VRAM | A = $ff : no error, A = $01 : string didn't fit in buffer | A, X, Y, $00, $01, $02, $03, $04, $05, $06 | This routine copies pointed data into the VRAM buffer.
$e8e1 | PrepareVRAMStrings | A = High VRAM address, X = Low VRAM address, Direct pointer = data to be written to VRAM | A = $ff : no error, A = $01 : data didn't fit in buffer | A, X, Y, $00, $01, $02, $03, $04, $05, $06 | This routine copies a 2D string into the VRAM buffer. The first byte of the data determines the width and height of the following string (in tiles): Upper nybble = height, lower nybble = width.
$e94f | GetVRAMBufferByte | X = starting index of read buffer, Y = # of address to compare (starting at 1), $00, $01 = address to read from | carry clear : a previously read byte was returned, carry set : no byte was read, should wait next call to ReadVRAMBuffer | A, X, Y | This routine was likely planned to be used in order to avoid useless latency on a VRAM reads (see notes below). It compares the VRAM address in ($00) with the Yth (starting at 1) address of the read buffer. If both addresses match, the corresponding data byte is returned exit with c clear. If the addresses are different, the buffer address is overwritten by the address in ($00) and the routine exit with c set.
$e97d | Pixel2NamConv | $02 = Pixel X cord, $03 = Pixel Y cord | $00 = High nametable address, $01 = Low nametable address | A | This routine convert pixel screen coordinates to corresponding nametable address (assumes no scrolling, and points to first nametable at $2000-$23ff).
$e997 | Nam2PixelConv | $00 = High nametable address, $01 = low nametable address | $02 = Pixel X cord, $03 = Pixel Y cord | A | This routine convert a nametable address to corresponding pixel coordinates (assume no scrolling).
$e9b1 | Random | X = Zero Page address where the random bytes are placed, Y = # of shift register bytes (normally $02) | | A, X, Y, $00 | This is a shift-register based random number generator, normally takes 2 bytes (using more won't affect random sequence). On reset you are supposed to write some non-zero values here (BIOS uses writes $d0, $d0), and call this routine several times before the data is actually random. Each call of this routine will shift the bytes right.
$e9c8 | SpriteDMA | | | A | This routine does sprite DMA from RAM $200-$2ff
$e9d3 | CounterLogic | A, Y = end Zeropage address of counters, X = start zeropage address of counters | | A, X, $00 | This decrements several counters in Zeropage. The first counter is a decimal counter 9 -> 8 -> 7 -> ... -> 1 -> 0 -> 9 -> ... Counters 1...A are simply decremented and stays at 0. Counters A+1...Y are decremented when the first counter does a 0 -> 9 transition, and stays at 0.
$e9eb | ReadPads | | $f5 = Joypad #1 data, $f6 = Joypad #2 data | A, X, $00, $01, | This read hardwired famicom joypads.
$ea1a | ReadDownPads | | $f5 = Joypad #1 up->down transitions, $f6 = Joypad #2 up->down transitions $f7 = Joypad #1 data, $f8 = Joypad #2 data | A, X, $00, $01 | This reads hardwired famicom joypads, and detect up->down button transitions
$ea1f | ReadOrDownPads | | $f5 = Joypad #1 up->down transitions, $f6 = Joypad #2 up->down transitions $f7 = Joypad #1 data, $f8 = Joypad #2 data | A, X, $00, $01 | This read both hardwired famicom and expansion port joypads and detect up->down button transitions.
$ea36 | ReadDownVerifyPads | | $f5 = Joypad #1 up->down transitions, $f6 = Joypad #2 up->down transitions $f7 = Joypad #1 data, $f8 = Joypad #2 data | A, X, $00, $01 | This reads hardwired Famicom joypads, and detect up->down button transitions. Data is read until two consecutive read matches to work around the DMC reading glitches.
$ea4c | ReadOrDownVerifyPads | | $f5 = Joypad #1 up->down transitions, $f6 = Joypad #2 up->down transitions $f7 = Joypad #1 data, $f8 = Joypad #2 data | A, X, $00, $01 | This read both hardwired famicom and expansion port joypads and detect up->down button transitions. Data is read until two consecutive read matches to work around the DMC reading glitches.
$ea68 | ReadDownExpPads | $f1-$f4 = up->down transitions, $f5-$f8 = Joypad data in the order : Pad1, Pad2, Expansion1, Expansion2 | | A, X, $00, $01 | This read both hardwired famicom and expansion port joypad, but stores their data separately instead of ORing them together like the other routines does. This routine is NOT DMC fortified.
$ea84 | VRAMFill | A = High VRAM Address (aka tile row #), X = Fill value, Y = # of tile rows OR attribute fill data | | A, X, Y, $00, $01, $02 | This routine does 2 things : If A < $20, it fills pattern table data with the value in X for 16 * Y tiles. If A >= $20, it fills the corresponding nametable with the value in X and attribute table with the value in Y.
$ead2 | MemFill | A = fill value, X = first page #, Y = last page # | | A, X, Y, $00, $01 | This routines fills RAM pages with specified value.
$eaea | SetScroll | | | A | This routine set scroll registers according to values in $fc, $fd and $ff. Should typically be called in VBlank after VRAM updates
$eafd | JumpEngine | A = Jump table entry | | A, X, Y, $00, $01 | The instruction calling this is supposed to be followed by a jump table (16-bit pointers little endian, up to 128 pointers). A is the entry # to jump to, return address on stack is used to get jump table entries.
$eb13 | ReadKeyboard | | | | Read Family Basic Keyboard expansion (detail is under analysis)
$eb66 | LoadTileset | A = Low VRAM Address & Flags, Y = Hi VRAM Address, X = # of tiles to transfer to/from VRAM | | A, X, Y, $00, $01, $02, $03, $04 | This routine can read and write 2BP and 1BP tilesets to/from VRAM. See appendix below about the flags.
$ec22 | unk_EC22 | | | | Some kind of logic that some games use. (detail is under analysis)

VRAM write transfer structure

The structure of VRAM buffers are as follows:

SIZE   CONTENTS
2      VRAM Address (big endian)
1      bit 0-5 length of data ($0 means a length of 64)
       bit 6 : 0 = copy, 1 = fill
       bit 7 : 0 = increment by 1, 1 = increment by 32
n      Data to copy to VRAM
.....  repeated as many times as needed
1      $ff

The main structure is terminated by a $ff byte (High address is always supposed to be in $00..$3f range)
$4c is a "call" command. The 2 bytes that follow is the address of a sub-VRAM structure. The sub-structure can call another sub-structure and so on.
$60 is a "return" command. It will terminate a sub-structure.
If Fill mode is used, the routine takes only 1 byte of data which is repeated.

VRAM Buffer notes

The VRAM buffer is located at $300-$3xx. $300 holds the size of the buffer (maximum), and $301 holds the end index of the buffer. The actual buffer lies at $302-$3xx, and is of variable length.

$300 is initialized to the value $7d, effectively making the buffer lie at $300-$37f. It's possible to change the value here to make it bigger or smaller, but the biggest possible value is $fd, making the buffer lie at $300-$3ff.
Format of the buffer is equivalent to the VRAM structure above, except that there are no sub-structures, no increment by 32 flag and no fill flag.
For this reason, the VRAM buffer at $302 can be used as a sub-structure.
A call to WriteVRAMBuffer will execute faster than a call to VRAMStructWrite with $302 as an argument, but both will have the same effect.

Read routines and VRAM buffer

Unlike the write routines which are very complete, the read routines are somewhat incomplete and their functionality have to be completed by the user (which limits their usefulness). Most of what follows is some sort of speculation about the usefulness of the incomplete read routines of the BIOS.

The read buffer is a part of the VRAM buffer at $300-$3xx, but the same location can't be used to transfer read and writes on the same frame (for example a RMW operation). Instead the user must manually split the buffer in two parts, the "read" buffer and the "write" buffer. The read buffer is probably supposed to always lies after the write buffer, so that when the read buffer is in use, the value in $300 (size of the write buffer) should be adjusted accordingly. The user should manually keep track of how many bytes are used for the read buffer, as well as the starting point of the read buffer (they are argument to the ReadVRAMBuffer function).

The structure of the read buffer itself is trivial - only single bytes are read (there's no runs of data). Very likely the purpose is to read one or a few individual attribute table data, in order to change the color mapping of individual 2x2 squares instead of whole 4x4 square (read-modify-write operation). All reads are mapped to a structure of 3 bytes in the read buffer :

SIZE   CONTENTS
2      VRAM Address (big endian)
1      data

Therfore, for each byte which is read from VRAM, 3 bytes have to be reserved in the read buffer. Once data from VRAM has been read, if it must be written back after a modification, the user need to copy it to the write buffer manually.

The GetVRAMBufferByte was probably designed to prevent reading attribute tables when it has already been read in the past by a call to ReadVRAMBuffer, for example if you don't know if you're modifying another area of the same 4x4 attribute byte as previously (no need to read again), or if you're modifying part of another 4x4 attribute byte (need to read from VRAM). If the routine return with C=0, the accumulator contains the attribute byte that was already read, but if C=1, it means we should first call ReadVRAMBuffer before getting the data we want.

Since reading VRAM for nothing is not a harmful operation, the user can call ReadVRAMBuffer every frame even if nobody has to be read (no need for check flags) which is probably why these routines are less complete than the write buffer related routines.

Load Tileset notes

The flags parameters are as follows:

7  bit  0
---------
AAAA MMIT
|||| ||||
|||| |||+- Fill bit
|||| ||+-- Transfer direction (0 = Write tiles, 1 = Read tiles)
|||| ++--- Bitplane type (see below)
++++------ Low VRAM Address (aka tile # within a row)

        1st bitplane	2nd bitplane     Description
        -----------	-----------      -----------
    0:  data	        data+8           Normal 2-bitplane graphics
    1:  data	        fill bit         Single bitplane graphics. Fill bit clear : Use colors 0&1  Fill bit set : Use colors 2&3
    2:  fill bit       data             Single bitplane graphics. Fill bit clear : Use color 0&2   Fill bit set : Use colors 1&3
    3:  data^fill bit	data             Single bitplane graphics. Fill bit clear : Use colors 0&3  Fill bit set : Use colors 1&2

This makes it possible for single bitplane tiles to take all possible color schemes when they end up in VRAM. However, it is not possible to (natively) load single bitplane graphics directly from the disk into VRAM; you have to load them into RAM before transferring the data into VRAM. In read mode, all non "data" bitplanes are replaced by dummy reads.

References

Enri's Famicom Disk System page (Japanese)
Enri's Famicom Disk System page (Japanese) (old/outdated)
http://nesdev.com/fds-nori.txt
http://nesdev.com/FDS%20technical%20reference.txt
FDS Lister by ccovell

Categories: Mappers using $4020-$5FFF, Mappers with cycle IRQs

FCEUX debugger

Tips for using the FCEUX debugger.

Contents

1 Memory
2 Inline assembler
3 Breakpoints
4 Conditional breakpoints

4.1 Example conditions
4.2 A story

5 References

Memory

The memory pane displays the current contents of the NES' RAM and ROM. The following memory ranges may display useful data for inspection:

0000-00FF - zero page
0100-01FF - stack
0200-07FF - ram
4018-FFFF - mapper controlled

Memory contents are displayed in this form:

0F:C0A8:24 1F     BIT $001F = #$80
bb:mmmm:dd dd dd  iiiiiiiiiiiiiiii

bb   - 16k iNES bank, designates which 16k bank from the iNES file is mapped here
mmmm - physical address on the NES CPU data bus
dd   - data bytes belonging to the instruction beginning at this address
iiii - description of the instruction

An instruction description with "= #$xx" at the end indicates the value currently in memory at the address referenced by the instruction (before that instruction executes).

When debugging an NSF program, the bank designation will be a 4k NSF bank instead of the 16k iNES bank.

There is an empty column to the left of the memory view. Hovering the mouse here will display at the bottom of the window more detailed information about the location of this code in the iNES file. Left clicking on this column will open the inline assembler, which allows you to patch the ROM at runtime. Right clicking on this column will open the hex editor, which allows you to directly edit the ROM.

Inline assembler

Open the inline assembler by clicking in the empty column to the left of the memory view.

The starting memory address is displayed in the PC field at the top of the inline assembler window. Type a line of assembly to add in the empty field just below this, and hit enter. The assembled code of your patch will appear line by line below.

Click apply to apply your patch to the ROM in memory. Click undo to remove the last assembled line. After applying a patch, clicking Save will allow you to save this patch directly to the ROM file.

Breakpoints

To create a breakpoint, click the Add button in the BreakPoints frame in the upper right corner of the debugger.

Each breakpoint has an address range to watch (use only the left address field if you wish to watch a single byte address). Check one or more of the options to watch for Read, Write, or Execute at an address. Note that fetching of code from an address will not break as a Read; use the Execute box for this.

Double click on a breakpoint in the BreakPoints frame to quickly disable or enable it.

The Forbid option creates an anti-breakpoint that will prevent the specified address from triggering any of the other breakpoints. These can also be enabled and disabled as needed.

Breakpoints are listed in the following form:

aaaa: EmRWXF : nnnn
aaaa-aaaa: EmRWXF : nnnn

aaaa - address of breakpoint
E    - enabled
m    - memory area C = CPU, P = PPU, S = sprite
R    - read
W    - write
X    - execute
F    - forbid
nnnn - name of breakpoint

When entering the address of a breakpoint, a small number of convenient strings may be used instead of the hexadecimal memory address:

NES special addresses:

NMI/VBL - non-maskable interrupt vector at FFFA
RST - reset vector at FFFC
IRQ - interrupt vector at FFFE

FDS special addresses:

NMI1 - non-maskable interrupt vector at DFF6
NMI2 - non-maskable interrupt vector at DFF8
NMI3 - non-maskable interrupt vector at DFFA
RST - reset vector at DFFC
IRQ - interrupt vector at DFFE

NSF special addresses:

LOAD - NSF LOAD address
INIT - NSF INIT address
PLAY - NSF PLAY address

Conditional breakpoints

Breakpoints may have a conditional statement that cause them to execute only if that statement evaluates to true. They can be used as runtime assertions: put the opposite of your assertion in the condition, and it will trigger only when your assertion fails. The conditional breakpoint grammar has this form:

* P         -> Connect
* Connect   -> Compare {('||' | '&&') Compare}
* Compare   -> Sum {('==' | '!=' | '<=' | '>=' | '<' | '>') Sum}
* Sum       -> Product {('+' | '-') Product}
* Product   -> Primitive {('*' | '/') Primitive}
* Primitive -> Number | Address | Register | Flag | PC Bank | '(' Connect ')'
* Number    -> '#' [1-9A-F]*
* Address   -> '$' [1-9A-F]* | '$' '[' Connect ']'
* Register  -> 'A' | 'X' | 'Y' | 'P'
* Flag      -> 'N' | 'C' | 'Z' | 'I' | 'B' | 'V'
* PC Bank   -> 'K'

The parser is very strict. All numbers are hexadecimal. Always prefix a number with # for an immediate value, or $ for a memory address. If a memory address needs to be calculated use $[] with the calculation inside the brackets. After entering a condition in the condition field, you should click Ok and then reopen the breakpoint with the Edit button. If there was a problem parsing your condition, it will have been erased.

Example conditions

break if register A is less than value at memory address $0005:

A < $0005

break if the program counter is 8123:

P == #8123

break if the value at the indirect address on zeropage $10 is not equal to FF:

#FF != $[$10+($11*#100)]

break if flag N is clear or A is not equal to 00:

(N==#0 || A!=#0)

A story

Once upon a time, an NES programmer was trying to determine where in the code a surprising value was being written to a specific memory location. Specifically, when the value $EE was being written to location $0028. To figure out what can be put into the "condition" text input field in the breakpoint dialog box, he dug into the source code for FCEUX and found the parser, whose grammar is listed near the top of the source file.

After the programmer had been staring at the problem for too long, a fox came and helped him.

Address: 28
Click "Write"
Memory: CPU (the default)
Condition: A == #ee || X == #ee || Y == #ee if you don't know what CPU register is used for the write or X == #ee if you know it's X. The # is important; leaving it out will screw it up.

References

FCEUX online debug documentation
FCEUX debugger usage guide
Forum post about conditional breakpoints

File talk:Neswires.jpg

It looks to me like the diagram for the RF Famicom (the description says NES, but I think it is clearly the RF Famicom, not the NES). I find this very helpful to me! It seems the audio from the microphone is also send to the cartridge, together with the square/triangle/noise/DPCM (does any mapper use this?), and now I can also see exactly how the expansion port is wired. It could help with many things, including to make a hardware clone (including one with a microphone). I suppose it means the device on the expansion port could read the inputs from the second controller, and I suppose as well as the expansion port to trigger IRQ, it can be used to communicate another signal directly between the expansion port and the cartridge. (If making a hardware clone, I suppose we can program the CPU, APU, PPU, and possibly some other components in Verilog, and then wire other things using discrete components, so it resembles this diagram; however, NES controller ports can then be added, and the microphone could be connected to an extra port. Of course, I suppose things like the Visual2A03 and so on can also help when making a hardware clone.) --Zzo38 (talk) 12:55, 22 May 2013 (MDT)

What are the direct output levels of the AUX A and AUX B of the 2A03 and video of the PPU (ignoring any resistors/etc which aren't in the IC)? What is the output level and impedance of the microphone (again, ignoring the resistors and so on shown in the schematic)? --Zzo38 (talk) 00:52, 26 May 2013 (MDT)

Output levels of the PPU are known: NTSC video. Otherwise, I can only give you ranges: the expected input impedence from the microphone is 5kΩ or less. Typical electric microphones have an impedence around 1-2kΩ, but the famicom amplifies it: http://atariusa.com/Famicom_Schematics/FC%20Control%20Pads%204021B%20RF%20and%20Power%20Schematics.png . The output of the 2A03's audio stage doesn't have a canonical voltage because it's a current-mode device: in the absence of the external 100Ω resistors it will "output" 5V always. —Lidnariq (talk) 12:18, 26 May 2013 (MDT)

Four Score

The NES Four Score and NES Satellite accessories allow four NES controllers to be connected to the NES's two controller ports. Controllers connected to this accessory are read using the same process as the standard controller. After the normal 8 reads from one port to get one controller data, 8 more are done to get another controller.

Note that the NES Four Score is not compatible with the Famicom 4-Players adapter, which connects the 3rd and 4th players to the 2s bit instead of the 1s bit; that functionality is described in greater detail on the standard controller article.

D3 and D4 are not connected on the Four Score, so accessories like the Zapper and Power Pad will not work.

Input ($4016 write)

7  bit  0
---- ----
xxxx xxxS
        |
        +- Controller shift register strobe

Writing 1 to this bit will record the state of each button on the controller. Writing 0 afterwards will allow the buttons to be read back, one at a time.

Output ($4016/$4017 read)

7  bit  0
---- ----
xxxx xxxD
        |
        +- Serial controller data

Read $4016 8 times to get the 8 buttons for controller #1.
Read $4016 8 more times to get the buttons for controller #3.
Read $4016 8 more times to get the signature, $10.
Read $4017 8 times to get the 8 buttons for controller #2.
Read $4017 8 more times to get the buttons for controller #4.
Read $4017 8 more times to get the signature, $20.

Button status for each controller is returned in the following order, as on the standard controller: A, B, Select, Start, Up, Down, Left, Right. 1 if pressed, 0 if not pressed.

The $10 and $20 signatures are sent most significant bit first. They can be used to detect 1. whether the Four Score switch is in the 4 player position and 2. whether a DMC sample fetch caused a bit deletion.

Controllers #3, #4, and the two signatures are only sent when the Four Score switch is in the 4 player position. When the switch is in the 2 player position those reads get the same result as a normal controller, either $00 or $FF depending on the controller.

Building new hardware from scratch

If you find yourself in the situation where you want to use the Four Score electrical interface for a project, but don't want to use up a four score, you can simply use six shift registers instead. Daisy-chain three shift registers together:

If using 4021s:

           IC1                 IC2                 IC3
          .-\/-.              .-\/-.              .-\/-.
       1A |1 16| Vcc       3A |1 16| Vcc      Vcc |1 16| Vcc
       nc |2 15| 1B        nc |2 15| 3B        nc |2 15| Vcc
NES P1 D0 |3 14| 1Sl       ZZ |3 14| 3Sl       YY |3 14| Vcc¹
      1Up |4 13| 1St      3Up |4 13| 3St      Vcc |4 13| Gnd²
      1Dn |5 12| nc       3Dn |5 12| nc       Vcc |5 12| nc
      1Lt |6 11| from ZZ  3Lt |6 11| from YY  Vcc |6 11| Gnd
      1Rt |7 10| NES CLK  3Rt |7 10| NES CLK  Vcc |7 10| NES CLK
      Gnd |8  9| NES OUT  Gnd |8  9| NES OUT  Gnd |8  9| NES OUT
          '----'              '----'              '----'

If using 74'165s:

         IC1                   IC2                 IC3
        .-\/-.                .-\/-.              .-\/-.
NES OUT |1 16| Vcc    NES OUT |1 16| Vcc  NES OUT |1 16| Vcc
NES CLK |2 15| Gnd    NES CLK |2 15| Gnd  NES CLK |2 15| Gnd
    1St |3 14| 1Up        3St |3 14| 3Up     ²Gnd |3 14| Vcc
    1Sl |4 13| 1Dn        3Sl |4 13| 3Dn     ¹Vcc |4 13| Vcc
     1B |5 12| 1Lt         3B |5 12| 3Lt      Vcc |5 12| Vcc
     1A |6 11| 1Rt         3A |6 11| 3Rt      Vcc |6 11| Vcc
     nc |7 10| from ZZ     nc |7 10| from YY   nc |7 10| Gnd
    Gnd |8  9| NES P1 D0  Gnd |8  9| ZZ       Gnd |8  9| YY
        '----'                '----'              '----'

For players 2 and 4, repeat the above, but change:

NES P1 D0 becomes NES P2 D0
1xx becomes 2xx
3xx becomes 4xx
IC3 pins denoted with ¹ and ² are swapped

Help:Editing pages

It's very easy to edit the contents of a wiki. It only takes a few clicks.

Click the “Edit” page tab at the top of the page.
Make changes to the text.
Click the “Save page” button.

Simple as that!

Contents

1 Editing rules, editing conventions, and formatting
2 Edit Summary
3 Preview
4 Other types of editing
5 Discussion

Editing rules, editing conventions, and formatting

The number one rule of wiki editing, is to be bold. Dive in and make changes. Other people can correct mistakes later, so have confidence, and give it a try! There can be all kinds of editing conventions, rules, and philosophy governing the editing of wiki pages, but the "be bold" rule overrides these!

In general try to write clearly and concisely and make sure you are always aiming to do something which improves the wiki contents. An edit might be to contribute whole paragraphs or pages full of information, or it could be as simple as fixing a typo or spelling mistake.

When you need to use some type of formatting e.g. new headings or bold text, you do this using wiki syntax. See Help:Formatting for some of the common types of formatting used.

Edit Summary

Before you save a change, you can enter a short note in the Summary: box describing your changes. Don't worry too much about this, or spend too much time thinking about it, but try to give a little description of what you just changed e.g. "fixed typo" or "added more information about sunflowers".

The summary gets stored alongside your edit, and allows people to track changes in the wiki more effectively.

Preview

It's a good idea to use the “Preview” button to see what your change will look like, before you save it. This is also related to tracking changes because every time you save, this is displayed to others as a separate change. This isn't something to worry about too much, but it's good to get into the habit of eliminating mistakes in your own work, by using a preview before saving, rather than saving several minor corrections afterwards.

Other types of editing

With wiki edits you can start a new page, move (or rename) a page, or even delete a page:

Help:Starting a new page
Help:Moving a page
Help:Deleting a page

Remember you should always aim to improve the overall contents of the wiki with your edits.

Discussion

Every article has its own "talk page" where you can ask questions, make suggestions, or discuss corrections. See Help:Talk pages

Help:Signatures

| Important note: When you edit this page, you agree to release your contribution into the public domain. If you don't want this or can't do this because of license restrictions, please don't edit. This page is one of the Public Domain Help Pages, which can be freely copied into fresh wiki installations and/or distributed with MediaWiki software.}} |

Users can easily sign their posts at the end of a comment. Signing is normally done on talk pages only, not on conjointly written articles.

Default signature options

There are three default options. Four tildes are standard (full signature). Typing three tildes results in a username-only signature (without timestamp). Typing five tildes results in a pure timestamp (without username).

Function | Wiki markup | Resulting code | Resulting display
Signature plus timestamp |

~~~~

|

[[User:Username|Username]] 12:34, 1 February 2008 (UTC)

| Username 12:34, 1 February 2008 (UTC)
Signature alone |

~~~

|

[[User:Username|Username]]

| Username
Timestamp alone |

~~~~~

| 12:34, 1 February 2008 (UTC) | 12:34, 1 February 2008 (UTC)

If you edit without logging in, your IP address will take the place of a username. Usernames and IP addresses are also stored in page histories as a record of who wrote what, so others can always verify signatures.

The common format to type a signature – two hyphens (or a dash) followed by four tildes (-- ~~~~) – is derived from the computer network Usenet, where two hyphens mark a signature block. The actual signature string, the tildes, automatically get substituted with username (linked to the appropriate user page) and timestamp (time/date), when you save a signed edit. This helps other users to follow the chronological order of discussions, and to identify the author of a particular comment.

If you don't find the tilde on your keyboard, you can use the signature button signature button of the default edit toolbar as a typing aid.

Signatures do not work in edit summaries (they do not translate from ~~~~ there).

Customized signatures

Registered users can customize their signature (the part between the two hyphens and the timestamp) by changing the field "New signature:" in their preferences. By default, anything you enter there will be wrapped with [[ ]]. To use a special linking (without this automatic link), you have to enable “Raw signatures.” Then you can add Wiki markup and also HTML (as far as allowed on the wiki) as you like, but the maximum length is 255 characters. Please note that striking signatures are often disliked by other users.

If you enable “Raw signatures” but don't add any customized signature string, you'll sign with your unlinked username.

The most common customizations are the following two:

Purpose | Raw signature | Resulting signature display
Adapting the displayed username |

[[User:Username|User Name]]

| -- User Name 12:34, 1 February 2008 (UTC)
Adding a talk page link |

[[User:Username|Username]] ([[User talk:Username|talk]])

| -- Username (talk) 12:34, 1 February 2008 (UTC)

. . . . . . . . . .

Categories: Help, Pages with broken file links

Help:Starting a new page

There are several ways to start a new page. These can vary based on the type of page started, as well as the wiki and namespace.

Contents

1 Using Wikilinks
2 Using the URL
3 From the search page
4 Create redirects to your new page

Using Wikilinks

MediaWiki makes it very easy to link wiki pages using a standard syntax (see Links). If you (or anyone else) creates a link to an article that doesn't exist yet, the link will be coloured red, like this.

Clicking a red link will take you to the edit page for the new article. Simply type your text, click save and the new page will be created.

Once the page has been created, the link will change from red to blue (purple for pages you've visited) indicating that the article now exists.

Usually this is the best way to create a new page, because it means that right from the start, the page will be linked from at least one other place on the wiki (and typically you will want to mesh it into other related pages later). If you are creating a new page without creating any link to it, you may need to ask yourself: Does this page really fit in with the topics already covered in the wiki? Also, how are you expecting visitors to find this page? Normally there is no reason to create a page without first creating a red link to it.

Using the URL

You can use the wiki's URL for creating a new page. The URL to an article of the wiki is usually something like this:

http://www.example.net/index.php/ARTICLE    or
http://www.example.net/wiki/ARTICLE

If you replace ARTICLE with the name of the page you wish to create, you will be taken to a blank page which indicates that no article of that name exists yet. Clicking the "Edit" page tab at the top of the page will take you to the edit page for that article, where you can create the new page by typing your text, and clicking submit.

From the search page

If you search for a page that doesn't exist (using the search box and “Go” button on the left of the page) then you will be provided with a link to create the new page. (Note that this technique doesn't work if you use the “Search” button).

Create redirects to your new page

Don't forget to setup redirects when you create a page. If you think another person may search for the page you've created by using a different name or spelling, please create the proper redirect(s). See Help:Redirects

Help:Talk pages

| Important note: When you edit this page, you agree to release your contribution into the public domain. If you don't want this or can't do this because of license restrictions, please don't edit. This page is one of the Public Domain Help Pages, which can be freely copied into fresh wiki installations and/or distributed with MediaWiki software.}} |

Every wiki page has an associated talk page which can be used for discussion and communicating with other users. Talk pages can be accessed by clicking the “discussion” tab at the top of the page. Simply edit the page as normal to add your comment.

A talk page is actually very similar to any other wiki page, but it is in the “Talk” namespace, to keep it separate from the articles in the “(Main)” namespace (See Help:namespaces). As with any wiki page, you can edit it, link to it, and view the editing history.

Contents

1 Editing conventions on talk pages

1.1 Example

2 Editing discussions
3 Building articles - Discussing articles
4 User talk pages

Editing conventions on talk pages

Having discussions on a free-form wiki page will seem strange at first. It helps if everyone follows some simple editing conventions:

Always sign your name after your comments. Use the four tildes “~~~~” wiki syntax (or the signature button signature button in the toolbar above editing textbox). For more information see Help:Signatures.
Start a new discussion with a ==level 2 heading== at the bottom of the page (or use the “+” tab)
Indent replies with colons (:) at the beginning of the line.

Example

Here is an example discussion, following the talk page conventions:

Wiki text | Rendered talk page

== More spiders information needed ==
This page has a lot of detail about the web, but I really dont understand a single word of it, and it doesn't mention the spider once -- [[User:Example|Bob Smith]] 18:07, 26 August 1991 (UTC)
: No no. This page is talking about the "world wide web". I have added a clarification at the top - [[User:Example|Simon Brown]] 11:21, 28 August 1991(UTC)
:: Oh I see... So what's the big deal about hyperlinked documents? Seems like a stupid idea to me. -- [[User:Example|Bob Smith]] 14:11, 3 September 1991 (UTC)
::: Well I think we should have some information about it here on our wiki, but you're probably right. It'll never catch on. -- [[User:Example|Simon Brown]] 21:55, 3 September 1991 (UTC)</pre>

|

More spiders information needed

This page has a lot of detail about the web, but I really dont understand a single word of it, and it doesn't mention the spider once -- Bob Smith 18:07, 26 August 1991 (UTC)

No no. This page is talking about the "world wide web". I have added a clarification at the top - Simon Brown 11:21, 28 August 1991(UTC)

Oh I see... So what's the big deal about hyperlinked documents? Seems like a stupid idea to me. -- Bob Smith 14:11, 3 September 1991 (UTC)

Well I think we should have some information about it here on our wiki, but you're probably right. It'll never catch on. -- Simon Brown 21:55, 3 September 1991 (UTC)

Editing discussions

Having discussions on a free-form wiki page will seem strange at first. It has some advantages over the conventional rigid forum format, but it can get a little messy. As with other wiki pages, anyone can help with tidying up discussions, to conform to the editing conventions e.g. add signatures and headings where they are missing.

Clearly we also have the opportunity to edit other people's comments. It is generally bad etiquette to modify somebody else's wording (Better to just add your own comment with your corrections) But it can be acceptable to...

Modify discussion headings
Change wording or append words to the discussion headings, to better describe the topic of discussion. Note that good descriptive headings become important when many discussions start to fill the page.
Move discussions to a different page
If discussions are put in the wrong place on the wiki, and are better associated with different talk page, then you could just move the discussion by cut & paste. This is potentially confusing, for the people posting, but can be important for keeping things tidy. You could leave the discussion in the wrong place for a few days/weeks grace before tidying it. You could leave a link behind explaining that a discussion was moved, or if not, you should link within the edit summary.
Delete discussions when they are out-of-date
Discussions can often get left lying around on a talk page long after the issue is no longer relevant. It's usually a good idea to reply to saying "I think this is now resolved", but sooner or later it's time to just blow away the old discussions (they are of course preserved in the editing history).
Split a post into several discussions
It may be appropriate to do this, if somebody has raised several points which need to be answered separately. However you should always be respectful to other people's words. Does their post still make sense if you split it up?

Building articles - Discussing articles

It is usually best to keep focused on the task of building a wiki article, and use discussion pages only to support this process. The topic of conversation should generally revolve around what needs to be done to make the associated article better. Remember that editing the article itself is often a more effective means of communicating. It can be more difficult, requiring you to balance your views alongside those of others, but it can also be more rewarding. This is how the community of wiki editors will make progress. Often it will feel more natural to engage in heated debate on a talk page (or indeed any other contact channel) but in fact the wiki article itself can offer a powerful means of reaching middle-ground. Think about how to portray both sides of the argument (e.g. listing advantages and disadvantages) and you may find the debate evaporates.

User talk pages

A "User talk page" is a talk page associated with somebody's "User page" (See Help:User page). This is a place to leave messages for a particular wiki user.

This can function as a kind of messaging system. Users receive a prominent notification when new messages have been left on their talk page. They may be notified by email as well, although this cannot always be relied upon (since the email notification feature must be activated by supplying a valid email address, and clicking a confirmation link). If you don't get a response to your user talk page message, try looking for other contact details which they may have supplied on their user page.

Note that the messages are not private, and others can join in the conversation.

. . . . . . . . . .

Categories: Help, Pages with broken file links

Help:User page

| Important note: When you edit this page, you agree to release your contribution into the public domain. If you don't want this or can't do this because of license restrictions, please don't edit. This page is one of the Public Domain Help Pages, which can be freely copied into fresh wiki installations and/or distributed with MediaWiki software.}} |

A user page is a page about a wiki user; someone who registered on the wiki, and is (most probably) a contributor.

If you have registered, you can create your own user page. Your user page is linked in the top right. More importantly, others will see links to your user page from various places which assist wiki collaboration. This includes the “Recent changes” and “page history” displays (See Help:Tracking changes). You can also link to your user page within text of a wiki page, which is mainly useful on talk pages when you sign your name.

Contents

1 What to put on your user page

1.1 User scratchpad / development area

2 Other people's user pages

2.1 User Contributions
2.2 Editing someone else's page
2.3 User talk pages

What to put on your user page

User pages are just as flexible as any other wiki page, and it's a page all about you, so generally people will leave you to freely write your user page in whatever format you like. It's a feature to help other people know who you are, and to bring the online community closer together. Think of it as a “profile” page. You might like to mention where you are from and what your job is. You can also state what your main areas of interest are in relation to the topic of the wiki, and describe contributions you have made or areas where you are interested in contributing.

User scratchpad / development area

You can use your user page as a scratchpad. An area for developing ideas without cluttering the main namespace (see Help:Namespaces). If subpages are enabled (see Help:Subpages), you may find them useful for creating sub pages under your user page. However you should avoid expending too much effort within your own area of the wiki. Be bold! Edit the main wiki articles! If your wiki has a shared Sandbox page, you can also use it for quick (non-permanent) wiki experimentation.

Other people's user pages

As mentioned above, you will see links to other people's user pages, in various places throughout the wiki.

User Contributions

When viewing another person's user page, an additional link “user contributions" appears in the “tools” of the sidebar. This takes you to a list of all of this user's wiki edits. Use this to get an idea of how prolific a contributor somebody is, or to track down edits made by a user who is causing trouble/making bad wiki edits.

Editing someone else's page

It's generally considered bad etiquette to rewrite or reword another person's user page. Editing is not disallowed, but you should avoid adding information (or especially opinions) which might be misinterpreted as coming from that user, in situations where this could potentially cause upset. Some types of edit are widely acceptable, and unlikely to cause upset:

Fixing internal links, when a page has been moved or deleted
Fixing broken external links
Categorizing or fixing categories of user pages.

User talk pages

Every user page has an associated talk page; a "user talk page". This is a special kind of talk page, for leaving messages directed at a particular user. See Help:Talk pages#User Talk pages.

. . . . . . . . . .

Categories: Help

INES Mapper 012

This mapper is an MMC3 variant with a simple twist. Writing to $4020-5FFF will set an additional bit for each half of CHR to allow an extra 256K of ROM to be addressed. For example, the mapped page for the left half would be %Lxxxxxxxx where %xxxxxxxx is the result of the typical MMC3 logic.

Otherwise all operations appear to be typical for MMC3A.

Maybe the only game that uses this mapper is Dragon Ball Z 5. It depends on this mapper operating as MMC3A variant. Choosing otherwise will result in the game hanging at boot-up as it gets stuck in an infinite loop with the IRQ reload set to 0 and continually getting re-triggered.

 Registers:
 ---------------------------
 
 Range:   $4020-5FFF
 
 $4020:  [...R ...L]
   L = 256K CHR block for left (low) half of CHR (<$1000)
   R = 256K CHR block for right (high) half of CHR (>=$1000)

Note: FCEUX instead uses the range $4100-$5FFF. DBZ5 itself seems to always write to $4132.

If the CHR ROM is 256K or smaller, CHR A18 isn't connected to anything, and thus this behaves as an ordinary MMC3A.

Mapper 12 is also used for FFE disk images. See Mapper 6 for some additional details. (FIXME: does the FFE usage comply with the above info, or is there a conflict between different mapper 12 definitions?)

See also: Forum thread about adding parts to an MMC3A board to make this mapper

Categories: INES Mappers, Mappers using $4020-$5FFF, MMC3-like mappers

INES Mapper 021

iNES Mapper 021 is used to represent the VRC4a (PCB 352398) and VRC4c (PCB 352889) variants of the Konami VRC4 mapper.

 ========================
 =  Mapper 021          =
 =       + 023          =
 =       + 025          =  
 ========================
 
 aka
 --------------------------
 VRC4
 
 
 
 Example Games:
 --------------------------
 Wai Wai World 2          (021)
 Ganbare Goemon Gaiden 2  (021)
 Boku Dracula-kun         (023)
 Tiny Toon Adventures (J) (023)
 Gradius 2 (J)            (025)
 Bio Miracle Bokutte Upa  (025)
 
 
 
 Multiple numbers, just one mapper:
 --------------------------
 These three mapper numbers (021, 023, 025) collectively represent different wiring variations of the same mapper:
 VRC4.  Each variation operates exactly the same, only the registers used are different because they all use
 different address lines.  Some lines are even reversed from the norm.
 
    variant   lines     registers                       Mapper Number
    =================================================================
    VRC4a:    A1, A2    $x000, $x002, $x004, $x006      021
    VRC4b:    A1, A0    $x000, $x002, $x001, $x003      025
    VRC4c:    A6, A7    $x000, $x040, $x080, $x0C0      021
    VRC4d:    A3, A2    $x000, $x008, $x004, $x00C      025
    VRC4e:    A2, A3    $x000, $x004, $x008, $x00C      023
    VRC4f:    A0, A1    $x000, $x001, $x002, $x003      023
      VRC4f may not exist, see Talk:VRC4
 
 
 This doc will use the 'VRC4a' registers (0,2,4,6) in all following register descriptions.  For other
 variants, use the above chart to convert.
 
 Registers:
 --------------------------
 Some registers are mirrored across several addresses.  For example, writing to $9004 has the same effect as
 writing to $9006.
 
 $8000-$8006:  [...P PPPP]   PRG Reg 0
 $9000,$9002:  [.... ..MM]   Mirroring:
    %00 = Vert
    %01 = Horz
    %10 = 1ScA
    %11 = 1ScB
 
 $9004,$9006:  [.... ..M.]   PRG Swap Mode Select
 $A000-$A006:  [...P PPPP]   PRG Reg 1
 $B000-$E006:  [...C CCCC]   CHR Regs (see CHR Setup)
 
 $F000+$F002:  [.... IIII]   IRQ Reload Value (see IRQ section)
 $F004         [.... .MEA]   IRQ Control (see IRQ section)
 $F006         [.... ....]   IRQ Acknowledge (see IRQ section)
 
 
 PRG Setup:
 --------------------------
 There are two PRG modes, which can be seleted via $9004.
 
                $8000   $A000   $C000   $E000  
              +-------+-------+-------+-------+
 PRG Mode 0:  | $8000 | $A000 | { -2} | { -1} |
              +-------+-------+-------+-------+
 PRG Mode 1:  | { -2} | $A000 | $8000 | { -1} |
              +-------+-------+-------+-------+
 
 
 CHR Setup:
 --------------------------
 The VRC4 only has 5 data pins.  To compensate, two CHR regs are combined
 to form a single page number.  One reg contains the high 5 bits and the
 other reg contains the low 4 bits (allowing for 9-bit page numbers)
 
 Example:  $B000+$B002  select 1k CHR page @ $0000
     if   $B000=$03
     and  $B002=$01
     then use page $13
 
 
       $0000   $0400   $0800   $0C00   $1000   $1400   $1800   $1C00 
     +-------+-------+-------+-------+-------+-------+-------+-------+
     |$B000+2|$B004+6|$C000+2|$C004+6|$D000+2|$D004+6|$E000+2|$E004+6|
     +-------+-------+-------+-------+-------+-------+-------+-------+
 
 
 --------------------------------------------------
 --------------------------------------------------
 
 
 VRC IRQs:
 --------------------------
 VRC IRQ logic is shared by VRC4, VRC6, and VRC7.  IRQs for all of those mappers operate exactly the same way.
 Therefore, this section applies to all of those mappers (other docs refer here).
 
 One thing in paticular to note with VRC4 that is different from VRC6, VRC7 is that the reload register is
 split in two just as CHR regs are.  $F000 specifies the low 4 bits of the reload value, and $F002 specfies
 the high 4 bits.  This only happens in VRC4.   VRC6 and VRC7 have a single 8-bit register to specify the
 reload value.  The rest of this doc will refer to this reload value as a single register.
 
 
 Notes:
 --------------------------
 VRC IRQs are unique in that they simulate a scanline counter, without actually counting scanlines.  The IRQ
 counter is actually a CPU cycle counter, with a prescaler that divides clocks by 113⅔ CPU cycles (one
 NTSC scanline).  This results in the IRQ counter being clocked once per scanline -- however unlike true
 scanline counters, it will be clocked even when the PPU is inactive, and even during VBlank!
 
 
 
 Registers:
 --------------------------
 
 There are 3 registers relevant to VRC IRQs.  See respective mapper doc for which register corresponds to
 which address:
 
   IRQ Reload:       [IIII IIII]
      This register specifies the counter reload value.  It does not affect the counter itself.
 
   IRQ Control:      [.... .MEA]
      M = IRQ Mode (0=scanline mode, 1=CPU cycle mode)
      E = Enable (0=disabled, 1=enabled)
      A = Enable-on-acknowledge (see below)
 
      - If 'E' is written as set, the IRQ counter will be immediately reloaded with the 
         reload value, and the prescaler will be reset.  IRQs will also be enabled.
      - If 'E' is written as clear, the IRQ counter and prescaler are not changed, and IRQs are disabled.
      - Any write to this register will acknowledge the IRQ.
 
 
   IRQ Acknowledge:  [.... ....]
      Any write to this register will acknowledge the IRQ.  In addition, the 'A' control bit is copied to the
 'E' control bit (enabling or disabling IRQs).  No write to this register will change the state of the IRQ
 counter or prescaler.
 
 
 Operation:
 --------------------------
 
 When in scanline mode ('M' control bit clear), a prescaler divides the passing CPU cycles by 114, 114, then
 113 (and then repeats that pattern).  This averages 113 + 2/3 CPU cycles (1 NTSC scanline).  When the
 prescaler is reset, the sequence is reset, and it will be 114 CPU cycles until the next IRQ counter clock.
 
 A simple way to emulate prescaler behavior is to have it reset to 341, and subtract 3 every CPU cycle.  When
 it drops to or below 0, increment it by 341 and clock the IRQ counter once.  This will produce the
 114,114,113 repeating pattern.
 
 When in cycle mode ('M' control bit set), the prescaler is effectively bypassed, and the IRQ counter gets
 clocked every CPU cycle.  In this mode, the prescaler remains unchanged by passing CPU cycles.
 
 If IRQs are disabled, neither the prescaler nor IRQ counter get clocked.
 
 
 When the IRQ counter is clocked:
  - If IRQ counter = $FF...
     a) reload IRQ counter with reload value
     b) trip IRQ
 
  - otherwise...
     a) increment IRQ counter by 1

Categories: NES 2.0 mappers with submappers, INES Mappers, In NesCartDB, Mappers with cycle IRQs

INES Mapper 027

iNES Mapper 027 is believed to be an pirate variant of the VRC4 mapper.

GoodNES thinks this is used for World Hero. We should discover whether this mapper number is used for any other unlicensed/pirate/multicart VRC2/4 games.

This is supported by BizHawk as of r3975 and FCEUX for some time prior but definitely as of 26-nov-2012.

Formerly FCEUX emulated this with unique code, but as of r2722 CaH4e3 asserts that it is a duplicate of INES Mapper 023. This means the only difference between 27 and the other VRC4 mappers (21, 23, and 25) is the way the board wires up the address lines. However, FCEUX's VRC2/4 emulation is filled with hacks for pirate and multicart games which are otherwise similar to VRC2/4.

In particular, World Hero depends on the VRC4's 9-bit CHR bank numbers, where the most significant nibble of the CHR banks are actually 5 bits.

The below notes are left until the author agrees they are describing VRC4:

IRQ behavior: does it match that of VRC family or that of MMC3?
$9002 behavior: is it 3x8+8F PRG banking or VRC4/MMC3 style PRG banking?

Additionally, Nestopia adds a register at $9080 that is a duplicate of $9002.

Mask = F00F

Writes:
9002: ......x. = If bit 2 is set, next write to register 8000 affects PRG C000-BFFF instead of PRG 8000-AFFF
8000: xxxxxxxx = Switches 8k PRG bank 8000-9FFF (or C000-DFFF)
9000: ......xx = Select mirroring (0 = Vertical, 1 = Horizontal, 2 = Single screen 0, 3 = Single screen 1)
A000: xxxxxxxx = Switches 8K PRG bank A000-BFFF
B000-E003: CHR banks.  They appear to have 9 bits.  If address written to is even (least significant bit is zero), sets the low 4 bits of the value.
  If address is odd (least significant bit is one), sets the 5 high bits of the value.
  CHR Bank number affected = Top nibble of address - B, times 2, plus 1 if address & 2.
  (B000 = 4 low bits of bank 0, B001 = 5 high bits of bank 0, B002 = 4 low bits of bank 1, B003 = 5 high bits of bank 1, C000 = 4 low bits of bank 2, etc...)
  Selects the 1K CHR bank.
F000: 4 low bits of IRQ latch
F001: 4 high bits of IRQ latch
F002: ......ER = 2 bit IRQ register, bit E = enable, bit R = enable on next acknowledgement (retrigger), then sets value of IRQ counter to IRQ latch - 1.
F003: Writing here acknowledges the IRQ, and sets bit E (enable) to bit R (retrigger).

IRQ behavior:
IRQ counter is triggered by A12, just like MMC3, and happens once per scanline.
If enabled, IRQ counter counts up to FF.  If it would count up when the counter is at FF, it triggers an interrupt, then resets the IRQ counter to IRQ Latch + 1.
If disabled, IRQ does not count at all.

PRG E000-FFFF is probably fixed to the last bank.

In FCEUX r2947, Санчез subsequently reallocated this mapper to a set of games that the source refers to has "Mi Hun Che", a very simple (if conflated) mapper:

$8000: [.... ...X] - Select both 4 KiB CHR-ROM bank (mirrored across both PPU $0xxx and $1xxx) and 1scA/1scB mirroring.
$8001-$FFFF: A~[1... .... .... ...X] - same

Categories: INES Mappers

INES Mapper 028

iNES Mapper 028 is assigned to a multicart mapper developed by Tepples and Infiniteneslives in October 2012, as an extension of the Action 53 project to cover CNROM and UNROM games. It is used for STREEMERZ: Action 53 Function 16 Volume One and Double Action 53.

Implemented in FCEUX as of r2739 (tracking bug) but appears to have been dropped sometime between 2.2.0 and 2.2.1. Implemented in Bizhawk as of r3680.

Disch

Aping Disch's style:

========================
=  Mapper 028          =
========================

aka
--------------------------
Multi-discrete


Example Games:
--------------------------
Action 53 series


Notes:
--------------------------
This mapper is designed for making multicarts of games that
use NROM, CNROM, UNROM, BNROM, or AOROM.  It looks like the
love child of MMC3, MMC1, and the Nintendo discrete mappers.
It has separate address and data ports like MMC3 (and FME-7),
its mode register is laid out in a way reminiscent of MMC1,
and it has the data port at $8000-$FFFF for compatibility with
the discrete mappers that it is designed to simulate.

Registers:
--------------------------

Range,Mask:   $5000-$5FFF, $F000

  $5000:  [A... ...A]   Address for use with $8000

Range,Mask:   $8000-$FFFF, $8000

  $8000:  [..DD DDDD]   Data port
    R:$00 ->  CHR Reg
    R:$01 ->  PRG Reg
    R:$80 ->  Mode
    R:$81 ->  Outer PRG Reg

These registers are internal, written through the data port:

  R:$00:  [...M ..CC]
    C = CHR Reg
    M = Mirroring
        This bit overwrites bit 0 of R:$80, but only if bit 1 of
        R:$80 is clear

  R:$01:  [...M PPPP]
    P = PRG Reg
    M = Mirroring
        This bit overwrites bit 0 of R:$80, but only if bit 1 of
        R:$80 is clear

  R:$80:  [..GG PSMM]
    G = Game Size (0=32K, 1=64K, 2=128K, 3=256K)
    P = PRG Size (0=32k mode, 1=16k mode)
    S = Slot select:
        0 = $C000 swappable, $8000 fixed to bottom of 32K outer bank
        1 = $8000 swappable, $C000 fixed to top of 32K outer bank
        This bit is ignored when 'P' is clear (32k mode)
    M = Mirroring control:
        %00 = 1ScA
        %01 = 1ScB
        %10 = Vert
        %11 = Horz

  R:$81:  [..BB BBBB]
    Outer PRG Reg


CHR Setup:
---------------------------

    $0000   $0400   $0800   $0C00   $1000   $1400   $1800   $1C00 
  +---------------------------------------------------------------+
  |                             R:$00                             |
  +---------------------------------------------------------------+


PRG Setup:
---------------------------

There is 1 PRG reg and 3 PRG modes, corresponding to mappers 34, 2,
and 180. When 32K PRG mode is used (P = 0), R:$01 specifies a 32K
bank number between 0 and 7 (i.e., the high bit is ignored). When
16K PRG mode is used (P = 1), R:$01 specifies a 16K bank number
between 0 and F.

                     $8000   $A000   $C000   $E000
                   +-------------------------------+
  P = 0:           |             R:$01             |
                   +-------------------------------+
  P = 1, S = 0:    |    "Fixed"    |     R:$01     |
                   +---------------+---------------+
  P = 1, S = 1:    |     R:$01     |    "Fixed"    |
                   +---------------+---------------+

The "fixed" banks aren't really fixed.  They represent the first and
second half of the currently selected outer bank, as if temporarily
forcing P=0 and G=0 for a single read.

The 4-bit output I (Inner) from this phase tells which 16K bank within a
single game is being read.  The value is fed into the multicart logic.
The game size G controls how many bits of I are kept, the rest being
replaced with bits of the outer bank number O = 2 * R:$81.  This can
be thought of as an inner-AND and outer-AND value controlled by G.
I is ANDed with inner-AND, O is ANDed with outer-AND, and the results
are ORed to form a 16K page number.

  'G'   Block size   Inner-AND   Outer-AND
  ----------------------------------------
   0        32K         $01        $7E
   1        64K         $03        $7C
   2       128K         $07        $78
   3       256K         $0F        $70

This 16K page number is concatenated with bits A13-A0 to form the
PRG ROM address.

An easy way to visualize the 16K bank number in 16K PRG mode is as
follows:

           |        
B5 B4 B3 B2|B1 B0       Outer PRG bits from R:$81
         P3|P2 P1 P0    Inner PRG bits from R:$01
           |

The location of the separator is determined by the game size selected
in R:$80. The above separator location corresponds to 128K. Moving
the separator one step to the left or right would be 256K and 64K,
respectively. The 16K bank number is formed by the outer PRG bits to
the left of the separator and the inner PRG bits to the right, giving
the bank number B5 B4 B3 B2 P2 P1 P0 in this example.

The only difference in 32K PRG mode is that the inner PRG bits are
shifted one step to the left:

           |        
B5 B4 B3 B2|B1 B0       Outer PRG bits from R:$81
      P3 P2|P1 P0 x     Inner PRG bits from R:$01
           |

This gives the 16K bank number B5 B4 B3 B2 P1 P0 x, where x = 0 is
the lower 16K part of the 32K bank and x = 1 the higher 16K part.
 
Powerup and Reset:
---------------------------

The last 16K PRG bank is switched into $C000-$FFFF on powerup.
Registers are unchanged on reset.

References

Forum post announcing reservation of #28
Forum post announcing implementation in NESICIDE

Categories: INES Mappers, Mappers using $4020-$5FFF

INES Mapper 036

iNES Mapper 036 is assigned to TXC's PCB 01-22000-400, featuring a 74138, a 74175, and usually a 24-pin ASIC labeled 05-00002-010. Two games are currently known to require this definition.

Strike Wolf
Policeman

Even though these games can evidently be emulated as a weird kind of GNROM, the hardware does something quite different:

The CHR banking is definitely implemented using the two 7400-series ICs:

Mask: $E200
write $4200: [.... CCCC] - Select 8 KiB CHR bank

The PRG banking is part of the ASIC:

Mask: $E103
 read $4100-4103: [xxRR xxxx]
                   |||| ||||
                   ||++------ reads show the internal state.
                   ++---++++- open bus
 write $4100: when M=0, copy PP to RR. When M=1, RR=RR+1
 write $4101: no visible effect
 write $4102: [..PP ....] - Request 32 KiB PRG bank
 write $4103: [...M ....] - PRG banking mode (0: copy, 1: increment)
 write $8000-$FFFF: copy RR to PRG banking pins

This PRG behavior is confusing but seems to be complete.

The 05-00002-010 ASIC is connected as:

                .--\/--.
         ¹NC <- |01  24| -> NC
 (r) PRG A16 <- |02  23| -> NC
 (r) PRG A15 <- |03  22| -> NC
         GND ?? |04  21| <- CPU A13 (rn)
          5V ?? |05  20| <- CPU A14 (rn)
          NC <> |06  19| ?? GND
          5V ?? |07  18| <- CPU R/W (n)
          NC <> |08  17| <- /ROMSEL (rn)
          NC <> |09  16| <- M2 (n)
         ¹NC <> |10  15| <- CPU A8 (rn)
 (rn) CPU D5 <> |11  14| <- CPU A1 (rn)
 (rn) CPU D4 <> |12  13| <- CPU A0 (rn)
                '------'

 ¹: pins 1 and 10 could respectively function as PRG A17 and CPU D6 if they were connected
    However, none of pins 6, 8, or 9 behave like CPU D7. Perhaps they were intended for CHR banking?

Three additional games published by Gluk use the same PCB, with no ASIC. They were also released in other regions on different hardware, and only Gluk's editions are compatible with the above-mentioned CHR banking.

F-15 City War
Volley ball
Puzzle

Compatibility code left in means that all editions of these three games are emulatable as NINA-06.

See also:

http://forums.nesdev.com/viewtopic.php?p=167180#p167180 Thread about dumping Policeman starts here

Categories: GNROM-like mappers, INES Mappers

INES Mapper 037

iNES Mapper 037 represents the Nintendo of Europe multicart "Super Mario Bros. + Tetris + Nintendo World Cup". It glues together 3 MMC3-compatible games in a single pak.

Contents

1 Overview
2 Registers

2.1 Outer Bank Select ($6000-$7FFF)
2.2 All other registers ($8000-$FFFF)

3 Hardware

Overview

PRG ROM size: 256 KiB
PRG ROM bank size: 8 KiB inner / 64 or 128 KiB outer
PRG RAM: Impossible
CHR capacity: 256 KiB ROM
CHR bank size: 1 and 2 KiB inner / 128 KiB outer
Nametable mirroring: Controlled by mapper.
Subject to bus conflicts: No

Registers

This game, like Super Spike V'Ball + Nintendo World Cup, replaces PRG RAM with a single register to enforce multiple "jail cells" containing each game.

The Outer Bank Select register is cleared by the CIC reset line, so if this multicart is used in a console without a functioning lockout chip, only a full power cycle will get back to the menu.

Outer Bank Select ($6000-$7FFF)

7  bit  0
xxxx xQBB
      │││
      │└┴── If 3, forces PRG A16 high regardless of Q bit; otherwise
      └──── the MMC3's PRG A16 is ANDed with this bit before going to PRG ROM.
             Additionally connected to A17 on both PRG and CHR ROM.

In case that wasn't clear:

Value written | PRG window | 128kB CHR window
0,1,2 | $00000-$0FFFF (64kB) | $00000-$1FFFF
3 | $10000-$1FFFF (64kB) | $00000-$1FFFF
4,5,6 | $20000-$3FFFF (128kB) | $20000-$3FFFF
7 | $30000-$3FFFF (64kB) | $20000-$3FFFF

As far as the MMC3 is concerned, this is the PRG-RAM, so you will need to enable writes to PRG-RAM to update it. Despite that the MMC3 thinks this register is RAM, the register itself does not, so it is not readable and attempting to read it will return open bus.

All other registers ($8000-$FFFF)

See MMC3.

Hardware

Since this pak was only ever released with epoxy covering wirebonded silicon dice, the following is guesswork:

It is very likely that the support hardware is a 74HC161 latch and a 74HC00 quad NAND gate, based on the specific order that the traces enter the epoxy blob. The latch, just like in the discrete logic mappers that use it, latches the bottom 3 bits of the data bus when it is written to. (Below, we call the latched form of D0→Q0, D1→Q1, and D2→Q2). The NAND gates are arranged to calculate

(MMC3 PRG A16 out) = M16 (for brevity)
(PRG ROM A16 in) = Q0·Q1 + Q2·M16 = Q̿0̿·̿Q̿1̿ ̅·̅ ̅Q̿2̿·̿M̿1̿6̿
(PRG ROM A17 in) = (CHR ROM A17 in) = Q2

Further testing has indicated that the internal products (Q0 NAND Q1, Q2 NAND M16) are brought out to test pads for factory verification.

The fourth NAND gate is used to invert CIC +RESET to generate 74'161 /CLEAR.

Categories: Mappers with scanline IRQs, INES Mappers, In NesCartDB, MMC3-like mappers, Multicart mappers

INES Mapper 045

 Here are Disch's original notes:  
 ========================
 =  Mapper 045          =
 ========================
 
 Example Games:
 --------------------------
 Super 8-in-1
 Super 4-in-1
 Super 1000000-in-1
 
 
 Notes:
 ---------------------------
 
 This mapper is another MMC3 multicart, only it works a bit strangely.  The multicart selects PRG/CHR blocks
 independently through 4 internal registers (accessed via $6000-7FFF).  MMC3 registers then operate normally
 within the current block.
 
 For info on MMC3, see mapper 004.
 
 
 Registers:
 ---------------------------
 
   $6000-7FFF:  Multicart regs
   $8000-FFFF:  Same as MMC3 for selected blocks
 
 When Multicart regs are locked, writes to $6000-7FFF proceed to PRG-RAM, as normal.
 
 Where the game writes in the $6000-7FFF range doesn't matter.  An internal counter selects which reg gets
 written to.  ie:
 
   LDA #$00
   STA $6000 ; first write, goes to reg 0
   STA $6000 ; second write, goes to reg 1
   STA $6000 ; reg 2
   STA $6000 ; reg 3
   STA $6000 ; back to reg 0, etc
 
 
   Reg 0:  [CCCC CCCC]   Low 8 bits of CHR-OR
   Reg 1:  [PPPP PPPP]   PRG-OR
   Reg 2:  [CCCC SSSS]
           S = CHR-AND block size
           C = High 4 bits of CHR-OR
   Reg 3:  [.LAA AAAA]
           L = Lock Multicart regs (1=locked)
           A = Inverted PRG-AND
 
 Once multicart regs are locked, the only way to unlock is to Reset the system.
 
 
 CHR Setup:
 --------------------------
 
 'S' bits are somewhat strange.  They seem to select the size of the CHR block to mask out:
   'S'   Block size     CHR-AND
   ----------------------------
   $F       256k          $FF
   $E       128k          $7F
   $D        64k          $3F
        ...
   $8         2k          $01
   7-0        1k          $00
 
 
 An easy way to emulate this:
 
    chr_and = 0xFF >> ~S_bits;
 
 CHR-OR is straightforward
 
 
 
 PRG Setup:
 -------------------------
 
 PRG-OR is straightforward.
 
 PRG-AND is inverted.  XOR written value with $3F for actual PRG-AND.
 
 
 
 Odd game behavior:
 -------------------------
 
 Games seem to set the multicart registers in a loop that runs 256 times.  Why it does this isn't known,
 neither is whether or not it is actually necessary.
 
 
 
 Powerup and reset:
 -------------------------
 
 Block 0 must be selected on powerup and reset.  Regs must be unlocked, as well... and they must be reset so
 that the next write will write to reg 0.

Categories: INES Mappers, MMC3-like mappers

INES Mapper 072

iNES Mapper 072 describes games released on Jaleco's JF-17 board.

Pinball Quest will require bus conflicts to be emulated if this mapper is emulated this way.

Contents

1 Overview
2 Registers

2.1 PRG Bank select ($8000-$FFFF, 128s bit)
2.2 CHR Bank select ($8000-$FFFF, 64s bit)
2.3 Audio playback control ($8000-$FFFF, 32s and 16s bits)

3 Hardware
4 Emulator oversize support
5 In Disch's style

Overview

PRG ROM size: 128 KiB
PRG ROM bank size: 16 KiB
PRG RAM: None
CHR capacity: 128 KiB ROM
CHR bank size: 8 KiB
Nametable mirroring: Cuttable trace selects vertical or horizontal mirroring
Subject to bus conflicts: Yes

Registers

PRG Bank select ($8000-$FFFF, 128s bit)

 7  bit  0
 Pxxx .DDD
 |     |||
 |     +++- 16 KB PRG ROM bank for CPU $8000-$BFFF
 +--------- When a 1 is written after a 0 was previously written, load the bank specified by D

CHR Bank select ($8000-$FFFF, 64s bit)

 7  bit  0
 xCxx DDDD
  |   ||||
  |   ++++- 8 KB CHR ROM bank for PPU $0000-$1FFF
  +-------- When a 1 is written after a 0 was previously written, load the bank specified by D

Audio playback control ($8000-$FFFF, 32s and 16s bits)

 15   11 address   0  7 data  0
 ---- ---- ---- ----  ---- ----
 1... .... ...A AAAA  xxRS ....
              | ||||    ||
              | ||||    |+------ While 0 and no previous sound is playing, start playing
              | ||||    |        sound specified by A.
              | ||||    +------- While 0, the µPD7756C sound IC is held in reset and unable
              | ||||             to make sound.  Hold this low for at least 34 cycles.
              +-++++------------ The sound to play when triggered by S bit

Hardware

A 74161 is attached to the top 4 bits of the data bus, in the exact same way as in all of Nintendo's discrete logic mappers.
The top two output bits of the '161 connect to the CLOCK pins of two different 74174s.
The '174 latches the contents of the bottom 4 bits of the data bus when its CLOCK pin goes from 0 to 1.
Three of a 7432's OR gates are used to make the PRG act like UNROM. (The last is used to allow for a 28-pin 128kB CHR ROM)
The bottom two output bits of the '161 connect to the /RESET and /START pins of the µPD7756C sound IC.

A design that replaced the '161 with a 74139 could have the side effect of preventing bus conflicts. However, the µPD7756 requires that its /RESET signal be low for at least 19µs and its /START timing requirements may be too strict for the NES also, so Jaleco used a latch instead of a demultiplexer.

Emulator oversize support

Both Nestopia-1.4.0h and FCEUX-2.1.5 support 256KiB PRG and 128KiB CHR.

The hardware could easily be generalized to 1 MiB PRG and 512KiB CHR by repurposing the sound control bits.

See also: Oversize

In Disch's style

 ========================
 =  Mapper 072          =
 ========================
 
 Example Games:
 --------------------------
 Pinball Quest (J)
 Moero!! Pro Tennis
 Moero!! Juudou Warriors
 
 
 Registers (**BUS CONFLICTS**):
 ---------------------------
 
   $8000-FFFF:  [PCRS DDDD]
     P = When a 1 is written after a 0 was previously written,
         the bottom three bits of the data bus are copied to the PRG bank select
     C = When a 1 is written after a 0 was previously written,
         the bottom four bits of the data bus are copied to the CHR bank select
     R = For games that have add-on sound, while 0,
         the ADPCM playback IC is held in reset and unable to make sound
     S = For games that have add-on sound, when the value written here changes
          (direction unknown because the datasheet contradicts itself), 
         the sound specified by the bottom 5 bits of the address bus is played.
         Leaving the value at 0 will probably result in erratic audio playback.
     D = the three- or four- bit bank number to switch to, as appropriate.
 
 
 Notes:
 ---------------------------
 
 Commands pass through a latch.  Rather than writing to the regs directly, you write the
 desired page number and command to the latch, then send another command that readies it for the next time.
 
    Commands (PC bits together):
      %00 = Do nothing (prepare for next write)
      %01 = Set CHR Page
      %10 = Set PRG page
      %11 = Set both simultaneously
 
    Example:
      If a game wanted to select CHR page 3, it would first write $43, then $03.  The $43 fills the latch with command 
      bits $4, which instruct bank $3 to be used for CHR; then the write of $03 prepares for the next write by
      resetting the command bits to $0. The $03 should be able to be any value from $00 to $0F, because the command
      bits are what is crucial.
 
 No current theory explains why games go to any effort to put the bank's nybble in the second byte, although perhaps
 it has to do with not disturbing the bank registers while the logic propagates.
 
 CHR Setup:
 ---------------------------
 
       $0000   $0400   $0800   $0C00   $1000   $1400   $1800   $1C00 
     +---------------------------------------------------------------+
     |                            CHR Reg                            |
     +---------------------------------------------------------------+
 
 
 PRG Setup:
 ---------------------------
 
       $8000   $A000   $C000   $E000  
     +---------------+---------------+
     |    PRG Reg    |     { -1}     |
     +---------------+---------------+

Categories: Discrete logic mappers, Expansion audio, INES Mappers, In NesCartDB

INES Mapper 096

iNES Mapper 096 was used with the two games that use the Oeka Kids tablet. It is specifically designed to turn the PPU into an all-points-addressable 2bpp bitmap without needing timed code, a scanline counter, or audio channel abuse.

Games:

Oeka Kids: Anpanman no Hiragana Daisuki
Oeka Kids: Anpanman to Oekaki Shiyou!!

Contents

1 Overview
2 Banks
3 Registers

3.1 Outer Bank Control (CPU $8000-$FFFF), bus conflicts
3.2 Inner Bank Control (PPU $2000-$2FFF)

4 Hardware
5 Disch's Notes
6 See Also

Overview

PRG ROM size: 128 KiB
PRG ROM bank size: 32 KiB
PRG RAM: No
CHR capacity: 32 KiB RAM
CHR bank size: 4 KiB inner / 16 KiB outer
Nametable mirroring: Hardwired
Subject to bus conflicts: partly

Banks

CPU $8000-$FFFF: 32 KiB switchable PRG ROM bank
PPU $0000-$0FFF: 4 KiB switchable CHR RAM bank
PPU $1000-$1FFF: 4 KiB semi-fixed CHR RAM bank (banks 3 or 7 only)

Registers

Outer Bank Control (CPU $8000-$FFFF), bus conflicts

7  bit  0
xxxx xCPP
      |||
      |++- Select 32KiB PRG bank
      +--- Select 16KiB outer CHR bank

Inner Bank Control (PPU $2000-$2FFF)

No bus conflicts:

13  PPU address  0
 DD xxCC xxxx xxxx
 ||   ||
 ||   ++---------- Select 4 KiB inner CHR RAM bank for PPU $0000-$0FFF
 ++--------------- Latch CC bits when 'DD' changes from anything else to '10'

Note that this effect does not pay attention to the PPU read or write strobes; it reacts continuously to all changes of the PPU's address bus.

Sprites fetched from PPU $0000-$0FFF will always come from banks 0 or 4 because the CC bits are clear for the sprite dummy nametable fetches.

Hardware

The game uses a 74161, 7402, and 7474. The 74161 is wired exactly the same as in all of Nintendo's discrete logic mappers, complete with bus conflicts.

The 7402 generates the clock signal for the 7474 by calculating (PPU /A13) NOR (PPU A12), which is equivalent to (PPU A13) AND (PPU /A12). On a rising edge of this signal, the 7474 latches the value of PPU A9 and PPU A8, i.e. when the PPU fetches the nametable after having fetched from the pattern tables. Because PPU /RD isn't involved and attribute fetches are immediately after nametable fetches, attribute fetches are ignored. Another two NOR gates take these two latched values and produce 4+4F CHR banking.

Technically, this banking is NOR logic, not OR logic. This difference is invisible to the software, however. (This means that the fixed bank is actually bank 0 or 4, and that reading from $2000 actually selects bank 3 or 7. The outer bank is not inverted: mapping the 3 C bits above to what actually appears on the RAM's address lines provides the order 3,2,1,0,7,6,5,4)

To rephrase: it is the act of changing the PPU address from $0xxx, $1xxx, or $3xxx to $2xxx that latches A9 and A8. There is no special logic that guarantees attribute fetches don't cause bankswitching, and Y scroll values greater than 240 will choose the same bank as reads from any of the rest of $23xx. It is only because of the PPU's fetch pattern that attribute fetches have no impact.

Disch's Notes

 Excerpt from Disch's original notes:  

 Long story short:
 
   A nametable spans from $2000-$23BF   ($23C0-$23FF are the attribute table).
   The mapper breaks the NT up like so:
 
      $2000-20FF = use CHR page 0
      $2100-21FF = use CHR page 1
      $2200-22FF = use CHR page 2
      $2300-23BF = use CHR page 3
 
   the other nametables at $2400, $2800, $2C00 are broken up in the same fashion.
 
 
 
 
 Long story long:
 
   PPU Address lines are modified as the PPU fetches tiles, and also when the game manually changes the PPU
 address (via the second write to $2006 --- or by the increment after read/writing $2007).  The mapper
 monitors every change to the PPU Address lines, and when it lies within a certain range, it swaps the
 appropriate CHR page in.
 
   It will only swap CHR when the address falls between $2000-2FFF (or mirrored regions like $6000-6FFF,
 $A000-AFFF, $E000-EFFF).  $3xxx will not trigger a swap.
 
   When in that range, it checks to make sure the address is not attribute tables ((Addr AND $03FF) < $03C0).
 Note I'm not 100% sure if the mapper really does this or not.  It's very possible that attribute fetches will
 also swap CHR... this would not really disrupt anything other than making the game be more careful about its
 PPU writes.
 
   When all that checks out, bits 8 and 9 (Addr AND $0300) select the 4k CHR page to swap in to $0000.
 
 
   Note that the mapper does not distinguish between PPU driven line changes and game driven line changes.
 This means that games can manually swap the CHR page by doing specific writes to $2006:
 
 
 LDA #$20
 STA $2006
 STA $2006   ; Addr set to $20xx -- CHR page 0 selected
 
 LDA #$21
 STA $2006
 STA $2006   ; Addr set to $21xx -- CHR page 1 selected
 
   And in fact, games would HAVE to do that to select CHR, since that's the only way to fill CHR RAM with the
 desired data.  So make sure your emu supports this.

See Also

NES Mapper list by Disch [1]

Categories: Discrete logic mappers, Mappers with CHR RAM, INES Mappers, In NesCartDB

INES Mapper 116

These boards appear to have been researched by CaH4e3. They're used for some chinese games and bootlegs. He has described them in fceu-mm sources as:

* SL12 Protected 3-in-1 mapper hardware (VRC2, MMC3, MMC1)
* the same as 603-5052 board (TODO: add reading registers, merge)
* SL1632 2-in-1 protected board, similar to SL12 (TODO: find difference)

The following PCBs are listed as examples:

* Garou Densetsu Special (G0904.PCB, Huang-1, GAL dip: W conf.)
* Kart Fighter (008, Huang-1, GAL dip: W conf.)
* Somari (008, C5052-13, GAL dip: P conf., GK2-P/GK2-V maskroms)
* Somari (008, Huang-1, GAL dip: W conf., GK1-P/GK1-V maskroms)
* AV Mei Shao Nv Zhan Shi ()
* Samurai Spirits (Full version) (Huang-1, GAL dip: unk conf. GS-2A/GS-4A maskroms)
* Contra Fighter (603-5052 board, C5052-3, GAL dip: unk conf. SC603-A/SCB603-B maskroms)

These documents were verified by implementation into bizhawk based solely on the fceu-mm sources. FCEUX also possesses fceu-mm's sources for this mapper.

This equipment is much simpler to operate than you might expect, considering that it is a combination of VRC2 + MMC3 + MMC1. The supervisor register controls which mapper's address and IRQ outputs and write enable inputs are enabled:

 Range,Mask:   $4000-7FFF, $4100
   $4100:  [.... .CMM]
     MM = Mapper mode
          %00 = VRC2b
          %01 = MMC3
          %02, %03 = MMC1
      C = 256K CHR ROM base (AV Girl Fighting uses this)

This control register supposedly occupies the WRAM address range, so there can be no WRAM. However, it only answers to $41xx.

The Mapper mode bits control which of the mapper circuits are connected to the NES. All of the PRG-based registers and IRQ signals are connected or disconnected accordingly. This means that in order to configure one of the mapper circuits, it must be connected.

The VRC2 is wired as a VRC2b. Though Konami games using VRC mappers write to only the canonical address of each port, games using this mapper such as Garou Densetsu Special tend to rely on being able to write to mirrors of $8xxx, $9xxx, and $Axxx. And SOMARI-W depends on the CHR bank registers being $FF at power on.

The MMC3 acts exactly as a stock TxROM. It has not been determined which MMC3 variant this MMC3 is acting as. Fceu-mm makes it seem as if the mmc3 CHR regs must be initialized at power-on in a certain pattern; it is unknown why this would be important.

The MMC1 acts exactly as a stock SxROM. Fceu-mm contained "hacky hacky" logic to do a reset of sorts on the MMC1 whenever the low bit of $41xx's address was set, claiming it was necessary for SOMARI-W.

The C bit of the m116's control reg controls CHR ROM A18, which provides a CHR ROM base offset for the VRC2 and MMC3 modes. Whether and how this applies to the MMC1 mode has not been tested.

Categories: INES Mappers, Mappers using $4020-$5FFF, MMC3-like mappers

INES Mapper 118

TxSROM is used to designate TKSROM and TLSROM boards, both of which use the Nintendo MMC3 in a nonstandard way. The only known difference between these boards and TKROM and TLROM is the mirroring configuration. The CHR A17 line connects directly to CIRAM A10 line instead of MMC3's CIRAM A10 output, to compensate for the MMC3's lack of single-screen mirroring. The iNES format assigns iNES Mapper 118 to these boards.

Example games:

Armadillo
Pro Sport Hockey

Contents

1 Registers

1.1 Bank data ($8001-$9FFF, odd)
1.2 Mirroring ($A000-$BFFE, even)

2 Variants
3 References

Registers

The behavior of these boards differs from that of a typical MMC3 board in the use of the upper CHR address line. This board relies on the fact that the MMC3's CHR bank circuit ignores A13 when calculating CHR A10-A17, responding to nametable fetches from $2000-$2FFF the same way as fetches from the first pattern table at $0000-$0FFF. This means that the 1KB/2KB banking scheme used for CHR bankswitching is active even during nametable fetches while the CHR ROM/RAM is disabled.

However, on these particular boards, the CHR bankswitching directly affects the mirroring mapping the nametable RAM. This allows programs to select which nametable is mapped to each slot, much like CHR banks are mapped to pattern table slots, in either two 2KB banks (allowing only single-screen or horizontal mirroring) or four 1KB banks (allowing all mirroring modes one can think of, because this is equal to the size of a nametable) at the price of mapping the 1KB CHR banks to the first pattern table by setting bit 7 of $8000. If the IRQ counter is being used in a standard way, this involves having sprites bankswitched in 2KB banks and backgrounds in 1KB banks.

Bank data ($8001-$9FFF, odd)

7  bit  0
---- ----
MDDD DDDD
|||| ||||
|+++-++++- New bank value, based on last value written to Bank select register
|          0: Select 2 KB CHR bank at PPU $0000-$07FF (or $1000-$17FF);
|          1: Select 2 KB CHR bank at PPU $0800-$0FFF (or $1800-$1FFF);
|          2: Select 1 KB CHR bank at PPU $1000-$13FF (or $0000-$03FF);
|          3: Select 1 KB CHR bank at PPU $1400-$17FF (or $0400-$07FF);
|          4: Select 1 KB CHR bank at PPU $1800-$1BFF (or $0800-$0BFF);
|          5: Select 1 KB CHR bank at PPU $1C00-$1FFF (or $0C00-$0FFF);
|          6, 7: as standard MMC3
|
+--------- Mirroring configuration, based on the last value
           written to Bank select register
           0: Select Nametable at PPU $2000-$27FF
           1: Select Nametable at PPU $2800-$2FFF
           Note : Those bits are ignored if corresponding CHR banks
           are mapped at $1000-$1FFF via $8000.
           
           2 : Select Nametable at PPU $2000-$23FF
           3 : Select Nametable at PPU $2400-$27FF
           4 : Select Nametable at PPU $2800-$2BFF
           5 : Select Nametable at PPU $2C00-$2FFF
           Note : Those bits are ignored if corresponding CHR banks
           are mapped at $1000-$1FFF via $8000.

Mirroring ($A000-$BFFE, even)

7  bit  0
---- ----
xxxx xxxM
        |
        +- Mirroring
           This bit is bypassed by the configuration described above, so writing here has no effect.

Note: In theory, the CHR limitation is 256 KB like all MMC3 boards. But because CHR A17 has another usage, having a CHR greater than 128 KB would require very careful CHR ROM layout because CHR bankswitching and mirroring will be linked through the same selection bits. Probably for this reason, official Nintendo TLSROM boards doesn't allow for 256 KB CHR-ROMs. However, a mapper 118 game that uses a third party MMC3/board, using 1-screen mirroring could draw the playfield with the lower 128 KB of CHR ROM and the lower nametable, and draw the status bar and menus with the upper 128 KB of CHR ROM and the upper nametable. Sprite tile banks could go in whatever space remains in either or both halves.

Variants

Mappers 158 and 207 do the exact same thing but with Tengen's RAMBO-1 and Taito's X1-005, respectively. Mapper 95 is almost the same thing, but with a reduced MMC3 made by Namco instead of a full MMC3 and with the nametable select bit on A15 instead of A17 because the Namco mapper has only six CHR bank bits.

References

NES Mapper list by Disch.

Categories: Mappers with scanline IRQs, INES Mappers, In NesCartDB, MMC3-like mappers, Nintendo licensed mappers

INES Mapper 164

These notes are not very good. There is more information to be got. Check some emulator sources and please elaborate here.

 Those are **not** Disch's original notes:  
 ========================
 =  Mapper 164          =
 ========================
 
 Example Games:
 --------------------------
 Final Fantasy V
 Pokémon Red [宠物红](Waixing)
 
 
 Registers:
 ---------------------------
 
 Range,Mask:   $5000-FFFF, $F300
 
    $5000, $D000:  PRG reg (32k @ $8000)
 
 $6000-7FFF may have SRAM (not sure)
 
 
 On Reset
 ---------------------------
 Reg seems to contain $FF on powerup/reset
 
 
 Notes:
 ---------------------------
 
 Swapping is really simple -- the thing that is funky is the register range/mask.  $5000 and $D000 will access
 the register, however $5100, $5200, etc will not.

 FCEUX implements mapper 164 as:
 $5000: [.... LLLL]
 $5100: [.... HHHH]
 $5300: 8-bit latch
 Writing to either $5000 or $5100 immediately switches a 32kB or 512kB chunk.
 Reading from $5100 or $5900 returns the value of the latch, but not $5500 or $5D00

 Nestopia implements mapper 164 as:
 $5000: [.ABC DLLL]
 $5100: [.... ...H]
 Writing to either immediately switches banks. The interpretation of the address depends on ABC:
 C=0: Switch 16kB at $8000, address specified by HBDLLL; 16kB at $C000 switched to H11111.
 A=0 C=1: undefined (noop)
 ABC=5: Switch 32kB at $8000, address specified by HDLLL
 ABC=7: Switch 16kB at $8000, address specified by HDDLLL; 16kB at $C000 switched to H11111. (Yes, D appears twice)

 Note that the copy of Final Fantasy V in GoodNES does not work correctly in Nestopia. This should not be taken as an indication that Nestopia's implementation is necessarily wrong.

Categories: INES Mappers

INES Mapper 178

VirtuaNesEX sources call this mapper "Education / WaiXing / HengGe". However, virtuanes is among most other emulators in not supporting it fully; a game "Pet Family ES-1081" has a larger PRG than this mapper was originally supposed to handle, and only Nestopia 1.40u4 has been supporting it. The rest of the emulators will manifest a bug in the nametables when the main game engine starts. With r2536, FCEUX supports it; bizhawk does as well.

This is a simple mapper.

  $4800:  [.... ...M]
     M = Mirror mode
         %0 = Vertical
         %1 = Horizontal
  
  $4801:  [...P PPP.]
     P = Some bits of the selected 32K PRG bank
  
  $4802:  [pppp pppp]
     p = Some more bits of the selected 32K PRG bank

The selected 32K PRG bank (mapped to $8000) is P + (p<<2). The older emulators are masking this result by & 0xF which is what breaks the larger PRG games. It is unclear whether this mask is necessary for some games to work.

This addition is unusual but would be expected from a multicart if $4802 originally meant "start of program" and $4801 "address within program". Pet Family seems to boot up and get past the nametable bug using an OR instead of a + which strikes me as much more likely.

The new PRG bank is only committed when $4801 is written. Therefore, you should write $4802 first and then $4801 to complete the remapping.

Categories: INES Mappers, Mappers using $4020-$5FFF

INES Mapper 206

Namco 118, Tengen MIMIC-1
DxROM

Company | Namco, Tengen, others
Games | 39 in NesCartDB
Complexity | ASIC
Boards | 34xx, DxROM
PRG ROM capacity | 128K
PRG ROM window | 8K + 8K + 16K fixed
PRG RAM capacity | None
CHR capacity | 64K
CHR window | 2Kx2 + 1Kx4
Nametable mirroring | Fixed H/V, or 4
Bus conflicts | No
IRQ | No
Audio | No
iNES mappers | 206, 76, 88, 154, 95

iNES Mapper 206 is the simpler predecessor of the MMC3, and was used by Tengen and Namco.

Chips used include "Tengen MIMIC-1" and "Namcot 118", and the boards made by Nintendo of America that used this mapper are NES-DxROM. Many ROMS using this mapper are incorrectly listed as using MMC3, but will usually work if emulated with MMC3, and the mirroring is correct, as if they were on a TEROM or TFROM board.

Compared to MMC3:

There are no IRQs
There is no WRAM support
PRG always has the last two 8KiB banks fixed to the end.
CHR always gives the left pattern table (0000-0FFF) the two 2KiB banks, and the right pattern table (1000-1FFF) the four 1KiB banks.
Mirroring is hardwired, one game uses 4-screen mirroring (Gauntlet, DRROM).
CHR size limit is 64KiB, PRG size limit is 128KiB.
The two registers are repeated across the entire address space from $8000-$FFFF, not just $8000-$9FFF

Naruko asserts that this is not true.
Naruko additionally observed a bug where writes to RAM (i.e. $0000-$1FFF) while executing code from $8000-$9FFF will cause erratic mapper writes. It is not known whether all five ICs (108, 109, 118, 119, MIMIC-1) have this same bug.

Registers:

$8000: 00000xxx - Select which internal register gets written by $8001
$8001: 00xxxxxx - Value written to the internal register. PRG registers use only 4 bits.

Internal registers:

0, 1: 2k CHR banks at 0000, 0800. Least significant bit is ignored.
2, 3, 4, 5: 1k CHR banks at 1000, 1400, 1800, 1C00.
6, 7: 8k PRG banks at 8000, A000.

Warning

The game Babel no Tou, on the PCB 3401, is the only game with 32 KiB PRG that allows—and uses!—PRG banking. All other games with 32 KiB PRG connect CPU A13 and CPU A14 directly to the PRG ROM, but fortunately they initialize their PRG registers to work on a normal board. Because all six games can be correctly emulated by respecting the PRG banking registers, it seems no submapper needs to be allocated for this variation.

Variants

Mapper 76 increases CHR to 128KiB by inflating the 1KiB CHR banks to 2KiB and making the originally-2KiB banks inaccessible.

Mapper 88 increases CHR to 128KiB by connecting PPU's A12 line to the CHR ROM's A16 line, making tiles in $0000 and $1000 come from disjoint sections of ROM. Because an undersize ROM on a mapper 88 board behaves identically to mapper 206, emulators may treat these mapper numbers as synonymous.

Mapper 154 has the same as mapper 88, plus mapper-controlled one-screen mirroring.

Mapper 95 uses the MSB to control mirroring by connecting CHR A15 to CIRAM A10, much as CHR A17 controls CIRAM A10 in TxSROM.

References

FCEUX source code
Enri's reverse-engineered schematic of PCBs 3407 and 3416: http://www43.tok2.com/home/cmpslv/Famic/Fcmp206.htm
Naruko's forum thread about mapper register range

Categories: INES Mappers, In NesCartDB, ASIC mappers, MMC3-like mappers, Nintendo licensed mappers

INES Mapper 233

 Here are Disch's original notes:  
 ========================
 =  Mapper 233          =
 ========================
 
 
 Example Game:
 --------------------------
 ???? "42-in-1"  ????
 
 
 Notes:
 ---------------------------
 Sources report this mapper as "42-in-1" with description layed out below.  I did not test this,
 since I could not find a copy of the ROM in question.  The only ROM I have that's marked as
 233 is "Unknown Multicart 1", and it does *not* follow the description in this doc at all.
 
 There is a "Super 42-in-1"... but that is mapper 226.  226, by the way, is strikingly similar
 to the below description.  I wonder if below description really applies to 233?
 
 
 
 Registers:
 ---------------------------
 
  $8000-FFFF:  [MMOP PPPP]
     M = Mirroring
     O = PRG Mode
     P = PRG Page
 
 
 PRG Setup:
 ---------------------------
 
               $8000   $A000   $C000   $E000  
             +-------------------------------+
 PRG Mode 0: |            <$8000>            |
             +-------------------------------+
 PRG Mode 1: |     $8000     |     $8000     |
             +---------------+---------------+
 
 
 Mirroring:
 ---------------------------
 
   'M' mirroring bits:
      %00 = See below
      %01 = Vert
      %10 = Horz
      %11 = 1ScB
 
 
   Mode %00 (almost, but not quite 1ScA):
     [  NTA  ][  NTA  ]
     [  NTA  ][  NTB  ]
 
 
 
 -----------------------------------------------
 --------------------------
 "Unknown Multi Cart 1"
 --------------------------
 -----------------------------------------------
 
 
 
 Notes:
 --------------------------
 
 This ROM is a mystery.
 
 It consists of 32 individual mapper 0 games, each 16k PRG + 8k CHR.
 
 Games do not use compatible mirroring modes -- the ROM includes Ice Climber (which uses H mirroring) and
 Excitebike (V mirroring).  
 
 No games seem to be modified to make any kind of writes to $8000-FFFF, so I didn't find any clue as to what
 mapper registers are being written to (if any).
 
 There does not appear to be *ANY* game selection screen for the multicart.  I have paged through every 16k
 of PRG and they all run the individual games straight up.  So unless the mapper aligns to 8k (or smaller) pages
 on startup and there's some crap hidden in there, I don't see how these games are held together.
 
 Could it be that this ROM dump is bad or incomplete?  The *only* other thing I can think of is that this cart might
 be reset based (a la mapper 060) -- but that is complicated by the fact that games use conflicting mirroring modes.
 So perhaps the mapper sets the mirroring mode based on what game is selected?
 
 
 More weirdness:  games seem to have mismatching PRG/CHR pages.  Ice Climber's PRG is on page $1F, but its CHR is
 on page $17.  It seems that you need to subtract 8 from the PRG page to get the matching CHR page (and wrap where
 appropriate)
 
 Even more weirdness:  despite each game only having 16k PRG, some of the games in the package normally have 32k!
 I don't know if the games were just hacked and had a bunch of stuff removed for what.
 
 It's possible this ROM dump is bogus and/or bad.  It might even be assigned the wrong mapper number.
 
 
 
 At any rate... here are the games.
 
 
 
 Game name          PRG page  CHR Page  Mirroring
 ----------------------------------------------------------
 Galaxian              $00      $18        Horz
 10 Yard Fight         $01      $19        Horz
 DKJ Math              $02      $1A        Vert
 Antarctic Adventure   $03      $1B        Horz
 Balloon Fight         $04      $1C        Horz
 Baseball              $05      $1D        Horz
 Battle City           $06      $1E        Horz
 Binary Land           $07      $1F        Horz
 Burger Time           $08      $00        Horz
 Chack 'n Pop          $09      $01        Horz
 Clu Clu Land          $0A      $02        Horz
 Lode Runner           $0B      $03        Vert
 ?? Go / Othello ??    $0C      $04        ????
 Field Combat          $0D      $05        Horz   ** really 32k PRG? **
 Devil World           $0E      $06        Horz
 Dig Dug               $0F      $07        Horz
 Donkey Kong           $10      $08        Horz
 Donkey Kong Jr.       $11      $09        Horz
 Donkey Kong 3         $12      $0A        Vert
 Door Door             $13      $0B        Vert
 Duck Hunt             $14      $0C        Vert
 Excitebike            $15      $0D        Vert
 Exerion               $16      $0E        Horz
 F1-Race               $17      $0F        Vert
 Formation Z           $18      $10        Horz
 Front Line            $19      $11        Horz
 Galaga                $1A      $12        Horz   ** really 32k PRG? **
 Golf                  $1B      $13        Vert
 Hogan's Alley         $1C      $14        Vert
 Hyper Olympic         $1D      $15        Vert
 ?? some gun game ??   $1E      $16        ????
 Ice Climber           $1F      $17        Horz

Categories: INES Mappers

INES Mapper 234

iNES Mapper 234 represents the Maxi 15 multicart, which allows the combination of slightly-modified 32k/32k CNROM and 64k/64k NINA-03 games. The only instance of this board was released with 512k/512k, but seems to be laid out in a way that would support a total of 1M/1M in 4 512k ROMs.

Contents

1 Overview
2 Registers

2.1 Outer Bank Control ($FF80-$FF9F)
2.2 Lockout defeat control ($FFC0-$FFDF)
2.3 Inner Bank Control ($FFE8-$FFF7)

Overview

PRG ROM size: 512 KiB or 1MiB
PRG ROM bank size: 32 KiB inner / 32 or 64 KiB outer
PRG RAM: No
CHR capacity: 512 KiB or 1MiB ROM
CHR bank size: 8 KiB inner / 32 or 64 KiB outer
Nametable mirroring: Controlled by mapper.
Subject to bus conflicts: Yes

Registers

Typical for the Atari 2600, but strange for the NES: Registers lie at $FF80-$FFF7 but bankswitching happens on the value that was read. Bus conflicts are thus avoided by storing the library of desired bankswitch values in ROM. Writes to the registers will produce bus conflicts.

All registers are cleared on reset.

Outer Bank Control ($FF80-$FF9F)

7  bit  0
MOQq BBBb  
││││ ││││
││││ └┴┴┴── Block selection
│││└─────── ROMs 3+4 Disable (0=normal, 1=disable ROMs 3+4 even if selected by Q)
││└──────── ROM switch (0=select ROMs 1+2, 1=select ROMs 3+4)
│└───────── Mode (0=CNROM, 1=NINA-03)
└────────── Mirroring (0=Vertical, 1=Horizontal)

Since the cartridge was distributed with only ROMs 1+2 populated, the Q and q bits are irrelevant.

The q bit seems to have been intended to have been an extra address line for ROMs 3+4, enabling a total of 1.5M/1.5M in the cartridge, but instead of just being routed to the A19 line for ROMs 3+4, it instead also is ORed with the Output Enable signal and so disables them.

Once any of the Q, q, BBB, or b bits are set, neither this register nor the Lockout defeat register can be updated. However, the Inner Bank Control Register can be set even when updates to the other registers are disabled.

Lockout defeat control ($FFC0-$FFDF)

7  bit  0
.... ..LL
       ││
       └┴── Lockout defeat (charge pump drive)

Emulators do not need to implement the lockout defeat control register.

Inner Bank Control ($FFE8-$FFF7)

7  bit  0
.cCC ...P
 │││    │
 │││    └── PRG page
 └┴┴─────── CHR page

Both CNROM and NINA-03 modes select a 32kB bank of PRG ROM at $8000 and an 8kB bank of CHR ROM at $0000.

In CNROM mode, the 32kB PRG ROM bank is BBBb and the 8kB CHR ROM bank is BBBbCC.

In NINA-03 mode, the 32kB PRG ROM bank is BBBP and the 8kB CHR ROM bank is BBBcCC.

Categories: Discrete logic mappers, INES Mappers, In NesCartDB, Multicart mappers

INES Mapper 243

iNES Mapper 243 describes Sachen's “74LS374N” mapper IC, which in no way resembles its namesake.

The IC as described by Санчез neither supports games with more than 64 KiB PRG, nor do any exist as images in GoodNES, so it's unclear why he specifies three bits for PRG banking.

 Example Games:
 --------------------------
 Honey
 Poker III 5-in-1
 
 Registers:
 ---------------------------
 Mask: $C101
 
 Both variants-
   $4100:  [.... .AAA]   Address for use with $4101
 
 Variant one (Nestopia calls "374b", FCEUmm calls S74LS374N, both meaning iNES Mapper 150, but what Санчез specified for m243) :
   $4101:   Write only- Data port
      R:2 -> [.... ...B]  High bit of CHR reg AND ALSO sets PRG reg to B.
      R:4 -> [.... ...C]  Middle bit of CHR reg
      R:5 -> [.... .PPP]  PRG reg  (32k @ $8000)
      R:6 -> [.... ..DE]  Low bits of CHR reg
      R:7 -> [.... .MM.]  Mirroring
          %00 = Horz
          %01 = Vert
          %10 = L-shaped; see below
          %11 = 1ScA
   $4100 reads: [.... .aaa]
             aaa = ~AAA XOR (counter & 1)   - where counter toggles on every reset
 
  Variant two (Nestopia calls "374a", FCEUmm calls S74LS374NA, Nocash's specification, all meaning m243) :
   $4101:   Data port
      R:0 -> [.... ....]  Writes reset CHR bank to 3 and PRG bank to 0
      R:2 -> [.... ...B]  High bit of CHR reg
      R:4 -> [.... ...E]  Low bit of CHR reg
      R:5 -> [.... ...P]  PRG reg  (32k @ $8000)
      R:6 -> [.... ..CD]  Middle bits of CHR reg
      R:7 -> [.... ...M]  Mirroring
           0 = Horz
           1 = Vert
 
 Mirroring:
 ---------------------------  
 Mirroring mode %10 is not quite 1ScB:
   [  NTA  ][  NTB  ]
   [  NTB  ][  NTB  ]
 
 CHR Setup:
 ---------------------------  
 8k CHR page @ $0000 is selected according to the BCDE bits.

Of all the images marked as mapper 243 in GoodNES 3.1.4, Nestopia's database leaves ONLY Poker III (Sachen) [!] and Poker III (Sachen) [a1].nes as variant 374a, and refiles the rest as variant 374b (m150).

There are two different dumps of "Poker III" in GoodNES, both marked with [!]. This has caused some confusion. There is no difference in the PRG of these two images! The only difference seems to be the different interpretation of CHR order. Given that Санчез described the pinout, and so presumably actually figured out which pin connected to which pin on the ROMs, it seems likely that his interpretation is the true one.

This still doesn't address the difference in mirroring behavior. Nocash says that no game ever wrote anything other than $05 to the register anyway.

Given the above, it seems that mapper 243 should possibly be deprecated, and all existing dumps either discarded or refiled to mapper 150.

Reference: Санчез, Nestopia's source, Nocash, FCEUmm source

Categories: INES Mappers, Mappers using $4020-$5FFF

INES Mapper DischDocs

This article clarifies the terminology used in Disch's detailed list of over 50 mappers at romhacking.net

      ******************************************
      *     iNES Mappers by Mapper Number      *
      *               v0.6.1                   *
      *              by Disch                  *
      ******************************************
 
 
 Read this doc
 --------------------------
 
   The mapper pages use charts and symbols and abbreviations and stuff which aren't clarified in each
 individual doc, but are covered here.  You could probably get away with just skimming this doc and/or only
 coming back to it if something in a specific mapper doc seems unclear.
 
 
 
 RAM Names
 --------------------------
 
   "WRAM", "SRAM", and "PRG-RAM" are used synonymously and inconsistently in these docs.  Kind of sloppy of
 me, I know.  All three terms refer to on-cartridge RAM.
 
 
 
 Mirroring
 --------------------------
 
   The NES only has two physical nametables.  These nametables are referred to as "NTA" and "NTB".  There are
 4 "slots" for nametables to be accessed:  $2000 (upper-left), $2400 (upper-right), $2800 (lower-left), and
 $2C00 (lower-right)
 
   Mappers which can customize the nametable layout may have a chart like the below to illustrate which
 nametable goes to which slot:
 
    [  $2000  ][  $2400  ]
    [  $2800  ][  $2C00  ]
 
 
   Most mappers which control mirroring usually pick from 2 to 4 standard mirroring configurations:
 Horizontal ("Horz"), Vertical ("Vert"), 1-Screen A ("1ScA"), and 1-Screen B ("1ScB").  These arrange the
 nametables like so:
 
        Vert              Horz
   --------------    --------------
   [ NTA ][ NTB ]    [ NTA ][ NTA ]
   [ NTA ][ NTB ]    [ NTB ][ NTB ]
 
        1ScA              1ScB
   --------------    --------------
   [ NTA ][ NTA ]    [ NTB ][ NTB ]
   [ NTA ][ NTA ]    [ NTB ][ NTB ]
 
 
   A few mappers also support 4-screen mirroring, which uses 4 full nametables so that each slot has its own
 unique nametable.  Since the NES only has 2k for nametables, for a game to have 4-screen mirroring,
 additional VRAM must be present on the cartridge.  I only know of a grand total of three games which use
 4-screen mirroring, and they will be mentioned in their respective docs.
 
 
 
 Swap Charts
 ----------------------------
 
   PRG/CHR swapping schemes are generally outlined in a chart.  A PRG chart might look like so:
 
       $8000   $A000   $C000   $E000  
     +-------+-------+-------+-------+
     | $7EFA | $7EFC | $7EFE | { -1} |
     +-------+-------+-------+-------+
 
   This indicates which register is used to select a PRG page for which region.  In this example, the register
 at $7EFA selects an 8k page for $8000-9FFF.
 
   Numbers surrounded by {curly braces} mean the page is fixed.  Here, $E000-FFFF is fixed to page -1.
 Negative pages indicate the last pages are used.  IE:  "-1" means to use the last page of PRG, "-2" would be
 the second last, etc.
 
   CHR charts work similarly:
 
       $0000   $0400   $0800   $0C00   $1000   $1400   $1800   $1C00 
     +---------------+---------------+-------+-------+-------+-------+
     |    <$7EF0>    |    <$7EF1>    | $7EF2 | $7EF3 | $7EF4 | $7EF5 |
     +---------------+---------------+-------+-------+-------+-------+
 
   
   Here, the register at $7EF3 selects a 1k CHR page for $1400-17FF, while $7EF0 selects a 2k CHR page for
 $0000-07FF.
 
   Numbers surrounded by <> symbols indicate the low bits of the given page number are ignored.  This is
 typical where a mapper deals with several different page sizes.  For example, $7EF0 selects a 2k page, but
 its low bit is ignored (effectively, you must right-shift its value by 1 for the actual page number).
 
   Example:  if $7EF0=$05, 2k page $02 would be selected ($05 right shift 1 = $02)
 
   Double <>'s (example:  "<<$7EF0>>") would mean the low 2 bits are ignored (right shift the value by 2).
 
   Numbers without <> symbols are referred to as "actual" page numbers.
 
   Charts may have multiple rows if there are multiple swapping modes.
 
 
 
 Erroneous noob swapping
 ----------------------------
   Some newbies tend to make an understandable, but incorrect assumption about how swapping works.  Given the
 following CHR chart:
 
                $0000   $0400   $0800   $0C00   $1000   $1400   $1800   $1C00 
              +---------------+---------------+-------+-------+-------+-------+
 CHR Mode 0:  |     <R:0>     |     <R:1>     |  R:2  |  R:3  |  R:4  |  R:5  |
              +---------------+---------------+---------------+---------------+
 CHR Mode 1:  |  R:2  |  R:3  |  R:4  |  R:5  |     <R:0>     |     <R:1>     |
              +-------+-------+-------+-------+---------------+---------------+
 
   A newbie might think that they can cleverly manipulate modes to select 1k pages across the board, rather
 than having those two 2k chunks in there.  IE:  They think that they can set R:2-R:5 in mode 0, then switch
 to mode 1, set R:2-R:5 again... and that would select each 1k page individually.
 
   This, of course, is not now it works.  "Swapping" isn't actually swapping.  What's actually happening is
 when the NES reads from a certain address the high bits of the address are being replaced by the contents
 of a mapper register.  Because of this, mapper registers (and swapping modes) are accessed constantly at
 runtime... not just when the value is written.
 
   For example... setting R:2 in mode 0, then switching to mode 1 will have the exact same effect as switching
 to mode 1 first, then setting R:2.  Both methods end up in mode 1, and both set only R:2... meaning the end
 result is selecting a 1k page at $0000.
 
   You might say a second "swap" occurs when the mode is changed.  That is... if a game were to change modes,
 they would see the pattern tables "flip", even though they didn't swap anything.
 
 
 
 Register bit layouts
 ----------------------------
 
   Registers often have different bits of the written value do different things.  Or sometimes only some bits
 are significant and others are ignored.  In these situations, bitfields are indicated by a pair of brackets.
 Example:
 
   $8000:  [CP.. .AAA]
 
   The above shows 3 seperate things ('A', 'P', and 'C') that the register controls, and which bits are
 assigned to those things.  Bits marked as '.' are irrelevent and unused.  These bits are listed high bit
 first (here, 'C' would be bit 7)
 
   Some mappers (usually multicarts) also take bits from the address written to -- not just the value
 written.  These instances will be marked with brackets with "A~" before them.  A good example of this:
 
   $8000-FFFF:    [.... ..CC]
                A~[..MH HPPP PPO. CCCC]
 
   The first bracket represents the value written, and the second bracket (with the A~) represents the address
 written to.
 
 
 Address/Data ports
 ----------------------------
 
   Many mappers have several registers which are accessed by writing an address to one area, then writing the
 data you want to write to the reg to another area.  The most common example of this is MMC3 (mapper 004).
 $8000 is the address port, and $8001 is the data port.
 
   Since $8001 actually accesses 8 different registers, $8001 can't appear in charts and descriptions and
 stuff.  So for address/data ports like this, the accessed registers are referred to as "R:#"  (where # is the
 hex address by which they're accessed).  For example MMC3's 8 regs would be "R:0" through "R:7".
 
   For example, if a game wanted to change R:4, it would do the following:
 
 LDA #$04
 STA $8000  ; set address to $04
 LDA whatever
 STA $8001  ; since address is $04, this sets R:4
 
 
 
 Timing / Dots
 ----------------------------
 
   When discussing the timing of PPU triggered IRQs, I refer to 'dots'.  IE:  "The IRQ will fire on dot 260 of
 the scanline".  'Dots' are otherwise known as PPU Cycles.  Each scanline consists of 341 dots -- and on NTSC,
 there are 3 dots to every 1 CPU cycle.
 
 
 
 Bus Conflicts
 -----------------------------
 
   Some simple mappers suffer from bus conflicts.  This means that when registers share CPU space with PRG,
 the value you write to the address must match what is read from that address or bad things will happen!
 
 
 Many games do this by having a LUT of common values somewhere and indexing it:
 
      Swap_LUT:
      .db $00, $01, $02, $03, $04, $05, $06, $07
 
      PRG_Swap:
          ;  assume A is the desired page to swap to (00-07)
        TAX
        STA Swap_LUT,X
        RTS
 
 This ABSOLUTELY NEEDS TO BE DONE for these mappers!  Do not try to shortcut this!  You will break your ROM!
 
 I'm sure I missed some mappers that have bus conflicts -- but I tried to mark all the ones I know do, and
 suspect might.
 
 When a bus conflicting write occurs, the result is usually an AND of the two potential values -- but such
 behavior should not be relied on.
 
 
 
 
 Register Masking / Ranges
 ------------------------------
 
   Many times, a single register can be accessed by several addresses.  For example when you see something
 like:
 
   $8000-FFFF:   PRG Reg
 
   That means a write to anywhere between $8000-FFFF will access the PRG Reg.
 
   In that same vein, sometimes not all address lines are used when decoding which register is to be accessed.
 That is, some bits of the address don't matter.  This creates a masking effect where registers are mirrored
 in a semi-weird fashion accross an address range.  This would be marked in docs with something like:
 
 
 Range,Mask:   $8000-FFFF, $E001
 
 
 This would mean that within the range $8000-FFFF, you'd use $E001 as a mask for determining which register to
 use.  IE:  $D3F7 would mirror $C001, because $D3F7 AND $E001 = $C001.
 
 
 
 PRG/CHR Masking
 ------------------------------
 
   When a game selects a page higher than there is ROM for, the page number would be masked to select an
 appropriate page.  For example... if a game only has $08 pages of CHR, and it selects page $0A, then it would
 actually select page $02 (because $0A AND ($08-1) = $02).
 
   In that same vein... fixed "last pages" {-1}, {-2}, etc are really pages $FFFF, $FFFE, etc -- and the mask
 happens to make that select the last or second last page.
 
   This is why PRG/CHR sizes must always be a power of 2, except in extremely rare cases where there's an odd
 number of chips (and those cases are handled specially by the mapper).
 
 
 
 Powerup/Reset
 -----------------------------
 
   Do not assume the state of anything at startup.  Mapper registers, like RAM, contain pseudo-random garbage
 on system powerup, except in special cases, which will be noted in the appropriate docs.
 
   If no such note is made, you cannot assume anything.
 
 
 
 PRG-AND, PRG-OR, Blocks, etc
 -----------------------------
 
   Multicarts (and even some single game carts) employ a type of block system which lets the game choose a
 block, and then will only swap to pages within that block.  In these docs I often illustrate this with PRG-OR
 and PRG-AND values.
 
   For an example, let's say you have a game with the following PRG pages selected:
 
       $8000   $A000   $C000   $E000  
     +-------+-------+-------+-------+
     |  $02  |  $16  | { -2} | { -1} |
     +-------+-------+-------+-------+
 
   And let's say the PRG-AND is $0F, and the PRG-OR is $20.  This would result in the following pages being
 selected:
 
       $8000   $A000   $C000   $E000  
     +-------+-------+-------+-------+
     |  $22  |  $26  |  $2E  |  $2F  |
     +-------+-------+-------+-------+
 
   simply, it's  "(desiredpage AND PRGAND) OR PRGOR".  Note that even the fixed pages are affected by this.
 
   CHR-AND and CHR-OR operate the same way, but with CHR pages.
 
   Always apply these values *before* any downshifting caused by <> symbols.

It was clarified later that Disch appreciates corrections.

Init code

When the NES is powered on or reset, the program should do the following within a fixed bank:

Set IRQ ignore bit (not strictly necessary as the 6502 sets this flag on all interrupts, including RESET, but it allows program code to simulate a reset by JMP ($FFFC))
Disable PPU NMIs and rendering
Initialize stack pointer
Initialize the mapper (if any)

The init code after this point may be placed either in the fixed bank or in a separate bank using a bankswitch followed by a JMP:

Disable decimal mode (not strictly necessary as the 2A03 has no decimal mode, but it maintains compatibility with generic 6502 debuggers)
If using a mapper that generates IRQs, disable APU timer IRQs
Disable DMC IRQs [1]
Set all RAM that your program uses to a known state. This often involves clearing internal RAM (@ $0000-$07FF) (and PRG RAM if needed (@ $6000-$7FFF)), except that which is intended to survive a reset (such as high scores). However, you don't need to set up an area of RAM that only one part of a program uses; you can set that in the same part where it's used, and in many cases, you'll need to set it up multiple times as part of the program is run multiple times.
Wait at least 30,000 cycles (see PPU power up state) before reading or writing registers $2003 through $2007. This is commonly done by waiting for the PPU to signal the start of vertical blank twice through $2002.

Some mappers have no fixed bank because they switch all 32 KB of PRG at a time. These include AxROM, BxROM, GxROM, and some configurations of MMC1. You'll have to put the interrupt vectors and the code up to the end of the JMP in a separate section that is duplicated in each bank. Often, the 256-byte page $FF00-$FFFF contains the vectors, the start of the init code, and a "trampoline" for jumps from code in one bank to code in another.

Sample implementation:

reset:
    sei        ; ignore IRQs
    cld        ; disable decimal mode
    ldx #$40
    stx $4017  ; disable APU frame IRQ
    ldx #$ff
    txs        ; Set up stack
    inx        ; now X = 0
    stx $2000  ; disable NMI
    stx $2001  ; disable rendering
    stx $4010  ; disable DMC IRQs

    ; Optional (omitted):
    ; Set up mapper and jmp to further init code here.

    ; If the user presses Reset during vblank, the PPU may reset
    ; with the vblank flag still true.  This has about a 1 in 13
    ; chance of happening on NTSC or 2 in 9 on PAL.  Clear the
    ; flag now so the @vblankwait1 loop sees an actual vblank.
    bit $2002

    ; First of two waits for vertical blank to make sure that the
    ; PPU has stabilized
@vblankwait1:  
    bit $2002
    bpl @vblankwait1

    ; We now have about 30,000 cycles to burn before the PPU stabilizes.
    ; One thing we can do with this time is put RAM in a known state.
    ; Here we fill it with $00, which matches what (say) a C compiler
    ; expects for BSS.  Conveniently, X is still 0.
    txa
@clrmem:
    sta $000,x
    sta $100,x
    sta $300,x
    sta $400,x
    sta $500,x
    sta $600,x
    sta $700,x  ; Remove this if you're storing reset-persistent data

    ; We skipped $200,x on purpose.  Usually, RAM page 2 is used for the
    ; display list to be copied to OAM.  OAM needs to be initialized to
    ; $EF-$FF, not 0, or you'll get a bunch of garbage sprites at (0, 0).

    inx
    bne @clrmem

    ; Other things you can do between vblank waits are set up audio
    ; or set up other mapper registers.
   
@vblankwait2:
    bit $2002
    bpl @vblankwait2

At this point, the program can fill the nametables, fill the pattern tables (if the board uses CHR RAM), fill the palette, and start displaying things.

See also

APU basics covers how to initialize the APU

Jump table

A jump table is a table of code addresses, meant to be indexed by a selector value. For example, a game script might specify an action to be performed via an index, which is then used to select a routine from a jump table of available scripting actions. The alternative to a jump table is a long string of comparisons with each possible selector value. This approach is tedious to set up and maintain, and slow:

; Jumps to routine selected by A
do_action:
       cmp #0
       bne not0
       jmp action0
not0:  cmp #1
       bne not1
       jmp action1
not1:  cmp #2
       bne not2
       jmp action2
not2:  ...

Indirect jumping

The NES doesn't have a JMP (addr,X) instruction, as other members of the 65xx family do. If it had one, a jump table would be trivial to implement, as in the following 65C02/Hu6280/65C816 code:

; Jumps to routine selected by A, from 0 to 127. High bit of A is ignored.
do_action:
       asl a           ; A = A * 2
       tax
       jmp (table,x)

table:
       .word action0, action1, action2 ; ...

The NES does support a JMP (addr) instruction, so a jump table can be implemented by copying the address to a temporary variable, then jumping through it:

; Jumps to routine selected by A, from 0 to 127. High bit of A is ignored.
do_action:
       asl a
       tax
       lda table,x
       sta temp
       lda table+1,x
       sta temp+1
       jmp (temp)

To call a routine via a selector, load the selector into A, then JSR do_action. This will then JMP to the appropriate routine, which will eventually RTS back to the routine that did JSR do_action. Essentially, you have JSR do_action, which then does JMP routine, which then does RTS; the JMP in the middle has no effect on the call stack. Note that the above code cannot be used without a JSR to it, since without that it's just a glorified JMP. That is, do_action must never be inlined in the code that uses it; it must always be called with JSR like a normal routine.

Like most temporary variables, the temp variable in this routine should not be used by both main thread code and an interrupt/NMI. If this routine is interrupted in the middle and the interrupt code modifies temp, the wrong address will be jumped to when it resumes after the interrupt. If a reentrant jump table subroutine is needed, the stack can be used instead (see below).

Stack-based dispatch

Main article: RTS Trick

RTI and RTS allow use of the stack for holding the temporary address. These are normally used to return to some calling/interrupted code, but at their core they pull an address from the stack then jump to it. This is the behavior we need. We push the address on the stack, then execute RTI or RTS to jump to it. It's roundabout, but it solves the interrupt problem.

Even though RTI is meant for returning from an interrupt, it happens to be simpler to use for this technique, since it doesn't adjust the address it pulls from the stack:

do_action:
       asl a
       tax
       lda table+1,x ; high byte first
       pha
       lda table,x
       pha
       php
       rti

RTS is more tricky, because it adds one to the address it pulls from the stack. This requires that every entry in the jump table have one subtracted from it. This could be done by the code, but it's tedious because the low byte must be decremented first, while the high byte needs to be pushed first. Thus, it's preferable to simply subtract one from each entry in the assembly source text:

do_action:
       asl a
       tax
       lda table+1,x
       pha
       lda table,x
       pha
       rts

table:
       .word action0-1, action1-1, action2-1 ; ...

The benefit of the RTS version is that it's three clock cycles faster than the RTI version, due to not having to push the flags. The disadvantage is that you must adjust every table entry by -1.

JY Company

JY Company was a publisher of pirate-original Famicom games, including many by Hummer Team.

The following is adapted from Disch's notes:

 ========================
 =  Mapper 090          =
 =       + 209          =
 =       + 211          =
 ========================
 
 aka
 --------------------------
 Tekken 2 Pirate Cart
 a big fat pile of ass
 
 
 Example Games:
 --------------------------
 Tekken 2                (090)
 Mortal Kombat 2         (090)
 Super Contra 3          (090)
 Super Mario World       (090)
 Shin Samurai Spirits 2  (209)
 Donkey Kong Country 4   (211)
 
 
 Rants:
 ---------------------------
 Disch hated this mapper with a passion.  It was used for poorly balanced games with poorly tuned music.
 But overall it isn't too much more complicated than, say, MMC5 without ExGrafix.
 
 
 090 vs. 209 vs. 211
 ---------------------------
 209 and 211 split from 090 somewhere along the line, but at some time, 090 was shared by both.
 Therefore you may come across ROMs mislabelled as 090 that are actually 209.
 
 The two mappers are exactly the same.  The only difference is a jumper setting which controls the extended
 nametable control.  090 has extended NT control permanently disabled, 209 has it enabled.  This jumper
 setting keeps games designed for older versions of the IC from inadvertently enabling it.
 
 This doc, as a whole, applies to both 090 and 209 -- with the exception of the Mirroring section, which draws
 the distinctions between the two.
 
 
 Notes:
 ---------------------------
 This mapper has no PRG-RAM, which is unusual for an ASIC mapper,
 
 In addition to the above mentioned jumper setting that controls mirroring, there are 2 other DIP switch
 settings which can be read back by the game via reg $5000.  Changing the DIP switch can change details
 of the played in some ROMs.
 
 
 This document's organization:
 ---------------------------
 Since there are so many registers for this mapper, registers will be listed and outlined as the features are
 explained.  The overall registers section will be extremely brief, serving primarily as a very quick
 reference or checklist.
 
 
 
 PRG Setup:
 ---------------------------
 
  $8000-8003 are PRG regs.  $8004-8007 are mirrors of them.
     $8000-$8003:  [.PPP PPPP]
 
  $D000 is the PRG mode select (among other things):
     $D000:  [SRNC CPPP]
       R,N = Relate to Mirroring (see mirroring section for details)
       C = Relate to CHR Setup (see chr setup for details)
       S = Put PRG @ $6000-7FFF
       P = PRG Mode Select
 
 If 'S' is clear, $6000-7FFF is always open bus.  It is only when 'S' is set, that $6000 reflects the page
 indicated in the setup chart below.
 
 Notice that page numbers are "actual" pages.
 
 Some modes are bit reversed (as marked below).  This means that the PRG registers are to be interpretted
 backwards:
 
   [.ABC DEFG]  normal order
   [.GFE DCBA]  bit reversed order
 
 
                       $6000        $8000   $A000   $C000   $E000  
                +-----------------+-------------------------------+
 PRG Mode %000  |  ($8003 * 4)+3  |             { -1}             |
                +-----------------+-------------------------------+
 PRG Mode %001  |  ($8003 * 2)+1  |     $8001     |     { -1}     |
                +-----------------+---------------+---------------+
 PRG Mode %010  |      $8003      | $8000 | $8001 | $8002 | { -1} |
                +-----------------+-------+-------+-------+-------+
 PRG Mode %011  |      $8003      | $8000 | $8001 | $8002 | { -1} |  *BIT REVERSE*
                +-----------------+-------------------------------+
 PRG Mode %100  |  ($8003 * 4)+3  |             $8003             |
                +-----------------+-------------------------------+
 PRG Mode %101  |  ($8003 * 2)+1  |     $8001     |     $8003     |
                +-----------------+---------------+---------------+
 PRG Mode %110  |      $8003      | $8000 | $8001 | $8002 | $8003 |
                +-----------------+-------+-------+-------+-------+
 PRG Mode %111  |      $8003      | $8000 | $8001 | $8002 | $8003 |  *BIT REVERSE*
                +-----------------+-------+-------+-------+-------+
 
 
 In case you don't see the patterns:
  - PRG modes %1xx are the same as %0xx, only $8003 is used for the last page instead of {-1}
  - $6000 is always swapped to the last 8k in the block specified by $8003.  In %1xx modes, this means $6000
 will always mirror $E000.
 
 
 CHR Setup:
 ---------------------------
 
    $9000-9007 are CHR regs -- each specifies the low 8 bits of the CHR page
    $A000-A007 -- specifies the high 8 bits of the CHR page (work with above regs)
 
 The rest of this section refers to above regs as $900x only -- but note that it all includes $900x and $A00x.
 
 CHR Mode is set by the following:
 
    $D000:  [SRNC CPPP]
      R,N = Relate to Mirroring (see mirroring section for details)
      S,P = Relate to PRG (see prg setup for details)
      C = CHR Mode
 
    $D003:  [M.BH HHHH]
      M = Mirror CHR (very strange, see below)
      B = CHR Block mode (0=enabled, 1=disabled)
      H = CHR Block (when in block mode)
 
 
 In CHR Block mode ('B' clear), $A00x is ignored, and instead, the H bits selects a 256k block for all CHR.
 $9000-9007 select a page within that block.
 
 In normal mode ('B' set), $9000-9007 select a page from the entire CHR.
 
 Mirror CHR mode ('M' set), only takes effect when in 1k or 2k mode ('C' = %10 or %11).  In this mode,
 $0800-$0FFF always mirrors $0000-07FF.  ($1800 is unaffected, however).  This is relatively easily
 emulatable by using $9000+$9001 in place of $9002+$9003 in the chart below.
 
 Note that page numbers are in "actual" pages.
 
                  $0000   $0400   $0800   $0C00   $1000   $1400   $1800   $1C00 
                +---------------------------------------------------------------+
 CHR Mode %00:  |                             $9000                             |
                +---------------------------------------------------------------+
 CHR Mode %01:  |             $9000             |             $9004             |
                +-------------------------------+-------------------------------+
 CHR Mode %10:  |     $9000     |     $9002     |     $9004     |     $9006     |
                +---------------+---------------+---------------+---------------+
 CHR Mode %11:  | $9000 | $9001 | $9002 | $9003 | $9004 | $9005 | $9006 | $9007 |
                +-------+-------+-------+-------+-------+-------+-------+-------+
 
 
 
 Mirroring:
 ---------------------------
 
 At first glance, mirroring appears simple, using the same values as FME-7 register 12:
 
   $D001:  [.... ..MM]
     %00 = Vert
     %01 = Horz
     %10 = 1ScA
     %11 = 1ScB
 
 However there is a special setting to complicate this, of course.
 
    $D000:  [SRNC CPPP]
      S,P = Relate to PRG (see prg setup for details)
      C = Relates to CHR (see chr setup for details)
      N = Enable advanced NT control (0=disabled, 1=enabled)
      R = disable NT RAM (0=NT can be RAM or ROM, 1=NT ROM only)
 
 When 'N' is clear, $D001 controls mirroring, and all other mirroring regs are ignored (including 'R' bit of
 $D000).  When 'N' is set, $D001 is ignored, and the below regs control mirroring.
 
 Mapper 211 behaves as though N were always set (1), and mapper 090 behaves as though
 N were always clear (0).
 
 
    $D002:  [A... ....]   NT RAM select bit
    $B000-B003   NT Regs (low 8 bits)
    $B004-B007   NT Regs (high 8 bits)
 
 Just like with normal CHR Regs, NT CHR regs are 16-bits... $B000-B003 specify the low bits, and $B004-B007
 specify the high bit.  They are arranged in the following:
 
    [ $B000 ][ $B001 ]
    [ $B002 ][ $B003 ]
 
 When 'R' is set, $D002 is ignored, and CHR-ROM is always used as NT (with page selected by appropriate reg).
 When 'R' is clear... CHR-ROM is only used if bit 7 of the NT Reg does not match the 'A' bit of $D002.  If the
 bits match, then NES internal NT RAM is used instead (either NTA or NTB, depending on bit 0 of the NT reg)
 
 Typical Examples:

           $B000 $B001 $B002 $B003
           -----------------------
    Horz:   $00   $00   $01   $01
    Vert:   $00   $01   $00   $01
    1ScA:   $00   $00   $00   $00
    1ScB:   $01   $01   $01   $01
 
 
 IRQs
 ---------------------------
 
 IRQs on this mapper are generated by a fairly flexible if somewhat obfuscated programmable interval timer.
 
 IRQs are triggered by any one of 4 sources:
  1) CPU Cycles
  2) A12 Rises
  3) PPU Reads (which happen 170 times per active scanline)
  4) CPU Writes (wtf, I know, but it's true)
 
 I *think* the only method used by any games is the A12.  CPU Cycles may also be used... and I really doubt
 the other two are used anywhere.
 
 A12 rises operate just like they do for MMC3 (mapper 004 -- see that doc for details).  One key difference:
 Unlike the MMC3, nearby rises are not ignored.  This means that under "normal" conditions, this IRQ counter
 is clocked 8 times per scanline (not just once).
 
 Clocks are first run through a prescaler, which divides the clocks by either 256 or 8.  Prescaling by 8
 is useful with A12 source, and prescaling by 256 is handy with CPU cycle or PPU read source.  For example,
 if the source is PPU reads prescaled by 256, a value of 64 causes a wait of just under 96 lines.
 
 Also.. the counter can be configured to count up, or count down!  Among other oddities.
 
 Related regs are as follows:
 
   $C001:  [DD.. FPSS]
     D = Count direction (10=down, 01=up, 00/11=pause counter)
     F = Funky mode (0=disabled, 1=enabled) -- see below
     P = Prescaler size (0=256, 1=8)
     S = IRQ source:
       %00 = CPU Cycles
       %01 = PPU A12 rising edges
       %10 = PPU Reads
       %11 = CPU Writes
 
 
   $C002:  [.... ....]   Any write here will acknowledge and disable IRQs
   $C003:  [.... ....]   Any write here will enable IRQs
   $C000:  [.... ...E]   Alternate method:
      writing to this reg with E=0:  same as writing to $C002
      writing to this reg with E=1:  same as writing to $C003
 
   $C004:  [PPPP PPPP]  Prescaler.  Any write here will set the prescaler to 'P' XOR $C006
   $C005:  [IIII IIII]  IRQ Counter.  Any write here will set the IRQ counter to 'I' XOR $C006
   $C006:  [XXXX XXXX]  This value is used as a XOR when writing to $C004/5
 
   $C007:  Funky Mode Reg
 
 
 
 $C004 and $C005 directly change the IRQ counter/prescaler.  They do not change a reload value.
 
 When the prescaler is in 3-bit mode (divide by 8), the high 5 bits of the prescaler remain unchanged when
 clocked and only the low 3 bits are used.  When the low 3 bits wrap, the IRQ counter is clocked.  8-bit mode
 (divide by 256) works as you'd expect.
 
 When the IRQ counter wraps (either $FF->00 or $00->FF, depending on whether it's incrementing or
 decrementing), an IRQ is tripped (if enabled).
 
 Disabling IRQs does not stop the counter or prescaler from counting, it simply stops the IRQ from being
 generated.  Only setting the count direction to 00 (neither down nor up) or 11 (both down and up)
 stops the counting.
 
 
 
 Funky Mode:
 
 When 'F' in $C001 is clear, $C007 is ignored.  When set, exact operation is unknown.  It appears to funkify
 the prescaler.  $C007 containing any value other than $FF will result in the IRQ counter not being clocked at
 all... and $FF will result in the prescaler dividing by strange amounts (sometimes 8?  sometimes 12?
 sometimes 257?).  Details are unknown.  Fortunately, no games use this funky mode.
 
 
 Other crap:
 ---------------------------
 
   $5000:  [DD.. ....]   DIP switch settings (readable only)
     These bits can be read back as any value depending on DIP switch settings on the cart.  The high bit, in
 paticular, has an effect in some games.
 
 
   $5800, $5801:   8*8->16 multiplication reg.  (read+write)
     These are similar to the multiplication registers on the MMC5 and the Super NES.  You write two unsigned
 8-bit values you want multiplied to $5801 and $5800, then the 16-bit product can be read back ($5800 has low
 8 bits, $5801 has high 8 bits).  Multiplication appears to need 8 CPU cycles of processing time.
 
   $5803:  a single byte of RAM (read+write)
 
 
   $5804-$5807 may also be RAM -- it's unknown.
 
 
 
 Registers:
 ---------------------------
 Registers were all covered in detail in previous sections.  This section is just an overall
 reference/checklist.
 
 
 
 Range, Mask:  $5000-FFFF, $F007
 
 
   $5000:        DIP switch         (read only)
   $5800-5801:   8*8->16 multiplier (read+write)
   $5803:        RAM                (read+write)
   $5804-5807:   ???                (possibly RAM)
 
   $8000-8003:   PRG Regs
   $8004-8007:   Mirror of PRG Regs
 
   $9000-9007:   CHR Regs (low bits)
   $A000-A007:   CHR Regs (high bits)
 
   $B000-B003:   NT Regs (low bits)
   $B004-B007:   NT Regs (high bits)
 
   $C000-C007:   IRQ Regs
 
   $D000-D003:   Control/Mode Regs
   $D004-D007:   mirror $D000-D003

External links

wikia:c:bootleggames:JY Company

Categories: Mappers with ROM nametables, ASIC mappers

Limitations

Some of the limitations of NES hardware and common mapper hardware severely limit the system's capability to perform well in some genres. This could be part of why these genres took off after 1991 when more powerful hardware became more readily available.

To clarify something: Some of these limitations don't mean "can't" as much as "too expensive". In a commercial game project, managers have to balance the cost of solving technical problems like those listed below with the cost of exploring, implementing, refining, and balancing the game rules. A game for a powerful system will often be programmed inefficiently because it gets the game out the door faster. Building your own clone (or emulation device) of mappers and other external devices is also possible, although this may also be expensive and/or time consuming.

A clone or a port to a less powerful system keeps most of the game design, which is already paid for, and cuts down the design in ways that the porting team thinks the players won't care about. A team of amateurs with no deadline can eventually squeeze more capability out of a system than can a commercial game developer bound by opportunity cost and return on investment. Even commercial developers in a country with a low cost of living, such as China or Brazil compared to Japan or the United States, have a time-money tradeoff biased toward time: witness the "Hong Kong Original" Famicom reductions of 16-bit fighting games, platformers, and RPGs, and the Brazilian ports of games to Sega Master System and Sega Genesis.

Contents

1 Simulation
2 Creation
3 Driving
4 Puzzle
5 Fighting
6 Bullet hell shooter
7 Party multiplayer
8 Music
9 External links

Simulation

Limitations: 8 KiB PRG RAM; no 3D graphics hardware

Some kinds of simulator games, like SimCity, The Sims, Harvest Moon, and Animal Crossing, have large grid-based world maps and tend to need 8 KiB just to store this map, let alone the rest of the world's state. Very few NES cartridge boards (such as SXROM and EWROM) provided more than 8 KiB, and most of them were rare and/or Japan-only. Nintendo has been known to cancel finished products such as the NES port of SimCity and the English version of Mother because replication cost would kill the return on investment. Games would have to be planned carefully to fit their state into a cheap chip. Nowadays, it's possible to make a custom mapper on a CPLD that bankswitches a large work RAM and saves to an unused area of the PRG flash.

Games that allow the player to customize his appearance extensively, as in Animal Crossing and The Sims, typically rely on 3D texture mapping so that the changes to the appearance can be seen from all angles. Tony Hawk series for Game Boy Advance soft-rendered a 3D player character in real time, but the GBA CPU is also fast enough to emulate the NES CPU. An NES game with customizable characters, such as Cocoron, has to store each animation of each body part seen from each angle and composite them at runtime, either drawing them into CHR RAM or overlaying numerous sprites (and risking flicker).

By the Super NES era: Several games were 32 KiB or larger battery RAM, and a game using the GSU might barely be able to soft-render a 3D player character, though at a reduced frame rate.

Creation

Limitations: Input devices, mostly

Games that allow for modification, such as modified game graphics, maps, and scripts, tend to be extremely limited. Part of this has to do with input limits: the NES never had an official alphabetic keyboard or precise pointing device. In Japan, Family BASIC shipped with a keyboard, and the Oeka Kids paint program shipped with a graphics tablet, but these use the Famicom's DA15 expansion port, which the NES doesn't have. Videomation, a paint program for the NES with a unique cartridge board, has to use a clunky control scheme similar to the speed control in Image Fight. (Its animation is also severely limited compared to Mario Paint for Super NES, and it can't save.) In 2011, some NES software was written to use the Super NES Mouse through a Super NES controller to NES adapter.

There are some external devices which can be used for extended save data: the Famicom Disk System, the Family BASIC Data Recorder, the Battle Box, and the Turbo File. However, all are Japan-only, exceptionally rare, and the latter two only hold 8KiB of data anyway.

By the Super NES era: Support for the Super NES Mouse was common, and Mario Paint and the Japan-only Dezaemon led the way.

Driving

Limitations: No 3D graphics

There are two ways to do a driving game: behind-the-car with a Pole Position style track (as seen in F-1 Race and Rad Racer) and overhead/isometric style (as seen in RC Pro-Am and Micro Machines). In a behind-the-car view, the car can't turn all the way around. The "morphmation" technique used to bend the racetrack limits the variety of scenery and track layout: for example, the track can't have hairpin turns or narrow segments without using an obscenely large multi-bank CHR ROM like that seen in Cosmic Epsilon. Overhead view severely limits how far ahead one player can see, resulting in usually slower movement, and the camera generally has to follow one player or the other. (Micro Machines uses the screen edge as a game mechanic.)

By the Super NES era: Limit broken using mode 7 and later the GSU.

Puzzle

Limitations: 16x16 pixel attribute tiles

A lot of tile-matching games, such as Columns (ported to NES as Magic Jewelry and Mystic Pillars), Yoshi's Cookie, Puyo Puyo, Wario's Woods, and Palamedes, have 16x16 pixel tiles. This limits each player's playfield to about 6x12 cells. Games with smaller tiles typically can't go over three unique colors, as seen in Dr. Mario and Tetris 2. One compromise involves drawing tiles in both players' playfields as a dithered combination of orange, green, and blue, much as CGA graphics were limited to three colors plus the backdrop. It's not as clean as a Sega Master System game, but it gets the job done without having to destroy one of 13 donor games to use the 8x8 pixel color areas of MMC5 ExGrafix. Another workaround would be to make a custom mapper on a CPLD that simulates some subset of ExGrafix. Klax uses a mapper with a scanline counter to change the scroll position in mid-frame, making its 16-pixel-wide attribute areas less than 8 scanlines tall.

Yet another thing that can be done is to make the single-player playfield wider than the 2-player playfield. This was tried in things like Magical Drop 2, Wario's Woods, and the 4-player "Familiss" mode of BPS's Super Tetris 3. Lumines for PSP borrows the mechanic of two players fighting over space in a single playfield from FantaVision for PS2, and at least one fan-made clone of the single-player game Zoop makes the game cooperative with two shooters on one big field.

By the Super NES era: Limit suffered comminuted fracture. Super NES has 8x8 pixel color areas, HDMA to change the vertical scroll position, lots of sprites with lots of overdraw, the 12x12 trick in mode 1, and a 256-color playfield in mode 3.

Fighting

Limitations: Overdraw

If both players' graphics are drawn as sprites, characters will have to be no wider than 32 pixels. Otherwise, they'll flicker like crazy when you cross the 8-sprite limit. You can get away with wider jumping poses because it's less likely that both characters will be in the air at once. Shaq-Fu was poor in execution, but its core idea of smaller characters could be made to work well on an NES. You could aim for something like Super Smash Bros., using platforms in the playfield as an additional source of tactics.

The other way to do this, allowing big characters like in Street Fighter, is to draw one character as 8x16 pixel sprites and the other as background tiles. This allows up to 64-pixel-wide characters, or slightly smaller counting projectile attacks. But you have to design the game such that only one player faces either direction, so that you can draw the other player with mirrored sprites. That means you can't easily jump behind or roll past the other player and attack from behind unless the frames for facing the other player's back have dedicated cels. In addition, backgrounds will be plain, and you'll probably need an advanced mapper with a scanline timer to perform multiple scroll splits at the status bar, play area, and ground.

By the Super NES era: Limit scarred across the chest with a Shoryuken. A competent port of Street Fighter II was a system seller. However, by Street Fighter Alpha 2, the Super NES was showing its age. Games like Killer Instinct and Samurai Shodown also had to have camera zooming cut out because of limits of mode 7.

Bullet hell shooter

Limitations: Overdraw, CPU speed, 5-line OAM DMA delay

Shoot-em-ups can be hard, like Recca, but they can't have more than 64 things in the air at once. Some platforms (like GBA and Neo Geo) can rewrite part of the sprite table during rendering to expand the sprite capability, but the NES can't. And even then, more than 8 on a line will flicker so bad that bullets will be invisible half the time.

By the Super NES era: Boss and bullet patterns became more complex, but the need for constant access to OAM outside of vertical or forced blanking meant shmups still couldn't overcome the 128-sprite capacity of OAM.

Party multiplayer

Limitations: Sprite palettes; overdraw

An NES Four Score hub provides four controller ports, one for each of the four palettes. If each player's car, uniform, etc. has the same graphics with a palette swap, there are no palettes left for anything else. If each player uses one palette, other things like projectiles and enemies would need to use the same palette as a player, or they would have to be background objects. It might be easier if the player sprites leave one color unused or if the game splits the players into two teams whose characters aren't palette swaps. Four 16x16 or 16x32 pixel sprites will also hit the 8-sprite limit with no room for projectiles unless the game is designed not to encourage them to be at the same vertical position.

Memory accesses during sample playback occasionally cause a bit from the controllers to be skipped. It takes longer to read 16 bits than 8, making rereading less practical, but the Four Score's signature bits help detect bit deletions.

By the Super NES era: Limit blown to bits by Super Bomberman. Overdraw increased to 32 sprites with 34 tiles and sprite palettes increased to eight, leaving plenty of room for players and their projectiles. And no more sample playback glitch.

Music

Limitations: Audio hardware, storage

A music game for the Famicom could put a digital audio player on the PCB. In fact, the JF-13 board in the Japanese version of Bases Loaded does just this for the umpire's voiceover. But unlike the 60-pin Famicom cart edge, the 72-pin NES cart edge lacks a pair of pins for an audio signal. Instead it has ten pins connected directly to the NES-001 Control Deck's expansion port. A 47 kΩ resistor from one of the cart pins to an audio pin on the expansion port enables audio out of the expansion port as on a Famicom, but Nintendo never released an accessory with this resistor, and top-loading NES-101 consoles don't even have this port. So NES games usually have to use the 2A03's internal APU channels. A mapper could trigger an IRQ when each sample is ready and offer a digital output on $4011 so that dec $4011 to read a sample from the mapper and write it back to the APU, but it was determined that OAM DMA would audibly interfere with that approach.[1]

Music games such as Beatmania, Dance Dance Revolution, and Amplitude use CD-quality audio played from a disc. Though the NES APU is capable of competent covers of popular music, as seen in D-Pad Hero, a lot of players demand the original studio recordings, or at least an electric guitar that sounds like an electric guitar and chords that don't sound warbly. Witness poor sales of the Game Boy Color versions of Beatmania and DDR.

Apart from DDR: Disney Dancing Museum for the Japanese N64 and games on Nintendo handhelds, most music games have come out on platforms with hundreds of megabytes of cheap storage: PCs and disc-based consoles. A lot of music games especially for consoles use a custom controller, shaped like a musical instrument or like the Power Pad. Because cartridges were much more expensive to replicate, bundling a controller with your game cartridge was cost prohibitive. Did anyone actually buy the Miracle Piano Teaching System?

Disc-based games using a standard controller, like Parappa the Rapper and Frequency, came on discs 600 MB to 4 GB in size and thus could afford to store the music tracks as two long samples: one for background music and one for the foreground instrument. (This pattern is called "keysound" in the Beatmania simulation community.) Guitar Hero On Tour games for Nintendo DS are 128 MB each after several Moore's law doublings of ROM density. But with a typical NES ROM size of 128 to 512 KiB, a big fat sample like that is out of the question.

By the Super NES era: The audio subsystem supports streaming vocals from ROM through HDMA, but ROM was still limited to 4096 KiB with a handful of largely Japan-only exceptions.

External links

Forum: Easier and harder game genre to code/developp
Forum: The essence of great games on the NES
Preliminary analysis of what would have to be cut to put Animal Crossing on the NES
Forum: Proposed SRAM layout for port of The Sims to NES

List of games with expansion audio

The following is a list of games that use the Famicom's expansion audio.

Contents

1 Nintendo FDS
2 Namco 163
3 Nintendo MMC5
4 Konami VRC6
5 Konami VRC7
6 Sunsoft 5B (YM2149F)
7 NEC µPD7756C (Jaleco)
8 Mitsubishi M50805 (Bandai)
9 References

Nintendo FDS

See FDS audio.

Ai Senshi Nicol
Aki to Tsukasa no Fushigi no Kabe
Apple Town Monogatari - Little Computer People
Arumana no Kiseki
Backgammon
Big Challenge! Go! Go! Bowling
Big Challenge! Dogfight Spirit
Bio Miracle Bokutte Upa
Bishoujo Hanafuda Club Vol. 1 - Oichokabu-hen
Bishoujo Hanafuda Club Vol. 2 - Koikoi Bakappana-hen
Bishoujo Sexy Derby
Chinou Game Series 3 - Chisoko Tairiku Orudora
Chinou Game Series 2 - Super Boy Allan
Chinou Game Series 1 - Adian no Tsue
Chitei Tairiku Orudoora
Cleopatra no Mahou
Dead Zone
Deep Dungeon 2 - Yuushi no Monshou
Dirty Pair - Project Eden (SFX only)
Doki Doki Panic
Dracula 2 - Noroi no Fuuin (Castlevania 2)
Egger Land
Vs. Excitebike
Exciting Baseball
Exciting Basket
Exciting Billiard
Exciting Soccer - Konami Cup
Falsion
Famicom Grand Prix II - 3D Hot Rally
Famicom Golf - Japan Course
Famicom Golf - US Course
Famicom Mukashi Banashi - Shin Onigashima
Famicom Mukashi Banashi - Yuuyuuki
Famicom Tantei Club - Kieta Koukeisha
Famicom Tantei Club II - Ushiro ni Tatsu Shoujo
Family Composer
Fire Bam
Gall Force - Eternal Story
Ginga Denshou - Galaxy Odyssey
Gyruss
Hao-kun no Fushigi na Tabi
I am a Teacher - Super Mario no Sweater
I am a Teacher - Teami no Kiso
Idol Hotline - Nakayama Miho no Tokimeki High School
Kaettekita Mario Bros.
Kalin no Tsurugi
Kick and Run
Kiki Kaikai - Dotou-hen
Knight Move
Link no Bouken (Zelda 2)
Lutter
Matou no Houkai - The Hero of Babel
Meikyuu Jiin Dababa
Metroid
Monty no Doki Doki Daisassou - Monty on the Run
Nankin no Adventure
Nazo no Magazine Disk - Nazoler Land Dai 2 Gou
Nazo no Magazine Disk - Nazoler Land Dai 3 Gou
Nazo no Magazine Disk - Nazoler Land Soukan Gou
Nazo no Murasamejou
19 Neunzehn
Otocky
Parutena no Kagami (Kid Icarus)
Pulsar no Hikari - Space Wars Simulation
Risa no Yousei Densetsu
Santa Claus no Takarabako
Seiken Psycho Calibur - Maju no Mori Densetsu
Sexy Invaders
Suishou no Ryuu
Super Mario Bros. 2
Tarot Uranai
Time Twist
Tobidase Daisakusen
Transformers - The Head Masteres
Zelda no Densetsu (Zelda)

Namco 163

See Namco 163 audio.

Final Lap (4 channel)
Mappy Kids (4)
Megami Tensei II: Digital Devil Story (4)
Namco Classic 2 (4)
Rolling Thunder (4)
Sangokushi - Chuugen no Hasha (4)
Sangokushi 2 - Haou no Tairiku (4)
Youkai Douchuuki (4, SFX only)
King of Kings (8 channel)
Erika to Satoru no Yumebouken (8)

Nintendo MMC5

See MMC5 audio.

Just Breed
Metal Slader Glory (very sparingly, mostly in SFX)
Shin 4-Nin Uchi Mahjong (uses PCM)
Uchuu Keibitai SDF (SFX only)

Konami VRC6

See VRC6 audio.

Akumajou Densetsu
Esper Dream 2
Madara

Konami VRC7

See VRC7 audio.

Lagrange Point

Sunsoft 5B (YM2149F)

See Sunsoft 5B audio.

Gimmick! (does not use envelope or noise)

NEC µPD7756C (Jaleco)

See mappers 18, 72, 86, and 92.

Moe Pro! '90: Kandou-hen
Moe Pro!: Saikyou-hen
Moero!! Pro Tennis
Moero!! Pro Yakyuu
Moero!! Pro Yakyuu '88: Kettei Ban
Shin Moero!! Pro Yakyuu
Terao no Dosukoi Oozumou

Mitsubishi M50805 (Bandai)

Family Trainer 3: Aerobics Studio

References

http://forums.nesdev.com/viewtopic.php?f=6&t=9757 - Famicom games with expansion audio - complete list
http://forums.nesdev.com/viewtopic.php?f=6&t=8639 - Famicom expansion hardware recordings
http://forums.nesdev.com/viewtopic.php?f=9&t=9449 - Mitsubishi M50805
Cartridge connector

Categories: Expansion audio

Make sram

This program make_sram.py creates .sav files for all iNES format ROMs in a folder and its subfolders that have the battery bit turned on. It's useful for users of PowerPak, which can't create files by itself. It is written in Python and has been tested on Python 2.6 on Ubuntu Karmic and (to a lesser extent) Python 2.5 on Windows. If you have trouble getting to run under your copy of Python, tell me about it here or on the forum.

#!/usr/bin/env python
"""
make_sram
See versionText below for copyright information.

Change log:
0.02 (2009-12-30): fixed a 'with' statement that I missed
0.01 (2009-12-29): initial release
"""
import os
# I'd use python 2.5's with statement, but the last time I posted a
# python program on pocket heaven, people were complaining about not
# being able to run my program on python 2.4.


helpText = """Usage: make_sram [foldername]
Makes empty 8192 byte .sav files for .nes files that need it.
"""
versionText = """make_sram 0.02 (2009-12-30)

Copyright 2009 Damian Yerrick
Copying and distribution of this file, with or without modification,
are permitted in any medium without royalty provided the copyright
notice and this notice are preserved.  This file is offered as-is,
without any warranty.
"""

def findAllRoms(folder='.'):
    pathnames = []
    for (root, folders, files) in os.walk(folder):
        for filename in files:
            if filename.lower().endswith('.nes'):
                pathnames.append(os.path.join(root, filename))
    return pathnames

def getINESBatteryBit(filename):
    infp = None
    try:
        infp = open(filename, 'rb')
        infp.seek(6)
        c = ord(infp.read(1))
        return (c & 0x02) != 0
    finally:
        if infp is not None:
            infp.close()

def getSavName(filename):
    (folder, filename) = os.path.split(filename)
    (filename, ext) = os.path.splitext(filename)
    return os.path.join(folder, filename + '.sav')

def processFolder(folder='.', dry=False):
    # First find the corresponding .sav filename for each .nes rom
    # with a battery bit
    savFiles = [getSavName(filename)
                for filename in findAllRoms(folder)
                if getINESBatteryBit(filename)]
    # Then find the ones that don exits (like tires)
    savFiles = [filename
                for filename in savFiles
                if not os.path.exists(filename)]
    blankSavData = chr(0) * 8192
    for filename in savFiles:
        print filename
        if not dry:
            r = open(filename, 'wb')
            r.write(blankSavData)
            r.close()

def main(argv=None):
    if argv is None:
        import sys
        argv = sys.argv
    if len(argv) > 1:
        folderName = argv[1]
        if folderName in ('--help', '-?', '/?', '-h'):
            print helpText
            return
        elif folderName == '--version':
            print versionText
            return
    else:
        folderName = '.'
    processFolder(folderName)

if __name__=='__main__':
    main()

MMC1

MMC1
SxROM

Company | Nintendo, others
Games | 390 in NesCartDB
Complexity | ASIC
Boards | SKROM, SLROM,
SNROM, others
PRG ROM capacity | 512K
PRG ROM window | 16K + 16K fixed or 32K
PRG RAM capacity | 32K
PRG RAM window | 8K
CHR capacity | 128K
CHR window | 4K + 4K or 8K
Nametable mirroring | H, V, or 1, switchable
Bus conflicts | No
IRQ | No
Audio | No
iNES mappers | 001, 105, 155

The Nintendo MMC1 is a mapper ASIC used in Nintendo's SxROM and NES-EVENT Game Pak boards. Most common SxROM boards are assigned to iNES Mapper 1. This chip first appeared in the April of 1987.

Contents

1 Banks
2 Registers

2.1 Load register ($8000-$FFFF)
2.2 Control (internal, $8000-$9FFF)
2.3 CHR bank 0 (internal, $A000-$BFFF)
2.4 CHR bank 1 (internal, $C000-$DFFF)
2.5 PRG bank (internal, $E000-$FFFF)

3 Hardware
4 Variants

4.1 SNROM

4.1.1 CHR bank 0 (internal, $A000-$BFFF)
4.1.2 CHR bank 1 (internal, $C000-$DFFF)

4.2 SOROM, SUROM and SXROM

4.2.1 CHR bank 0 (internal, $A000-$BFFF)
4.2.2 CHR bank 1 (internal, $C000-$DFFF)

5 iNES Mapper 001

5.1 Heuristic disambiguation
5.2 NES 2.0 combined implementation

6 References
7 See also

Banks

CPU $6000-$7FFF: 8 KB PRG RAM bank, fixed on all boards but SOROM and SXROM
CPU $8000-$BFFF: 16 KB PRG ROM bank, either switchable or fixed to the first bank
CPU $C000-$FFFF: 16 KB PRG ROM bank, either fixed to the last bank or switchable
PPU $0000-$0FFF: 4 KB switchable CHR bank
PPU $1000-$1FFF: 4 KB switchable CHR bank

Through writes to the MMC1 control register, it is possible for the program to swap the fixed and switchable PRG ROM banks or to set up 32 KB PRG bankswitching (like BNROM), but most games use the default setup, which is similar to that of UxROM.

Registers

Unlike almost all other mappers, the MMC1 is configured through a serial port in order to reduce pin count. CPU $8000-$FFFF is connected to a common shift register. Writing a value with bit 7 set ($80 through $FF) to any address in $8000-$FFFF clears the shift register to its initial state. To change a register's value, the CPU writes five times with bit 7 clear and a bit of the desired value in bit 0. On the first four writes, the MMC1 shifts bit 0 into a shift register. On the fifth write, the MMC1 copies bit 0 and the shift register contents into an internal register selected by bits 14 and 13 of the address, and then it clears the shift register. Only on the fifth write does the address matter, and even then, only bits 14 and 13 of the address matter because the mapper registers are incompletely decoded like the PPU registers. After the fifth write, the shift register is cleared automatically, so a write to the shift register with bit 7 on to reset it is not needed.

When the CPU writes to the serial port on consecutive cycles, the MMC1 ignores all writes but the first. This happens when the 6502 executes read-modify-write (RMW) instructions, such as DEC and ROR, by writing back the old value and then writing the new value on the next cycle. At least Bill & Ted's Excellent Adventure resets the MMC1 by doing INC on a ROM location containing $FF; the MMC1 sees the $FF written back and ignores the $00 written on the next cycle.[1] The reason for this is that resetting and shifting happen on a falling edge of R/W, and RMW instructions hold R/W low for both writes.[2]

To switch a bank, a program will execute code similar to the following:

;
; Sets the switchable PRG ROM bank to the value of A.
;
              ;  A          MMC1_SR  MMC1_PB
setPRGBank:   ;  000edcba    10000             Start with an empty shift register (SR).  The 1 is used
  sta $E000   ;  000edcba -> a1000             to detect when the SR has become full.
  lsr a       ; >0000edcb    a1000
  sta $E000   ;  0000edcb -> ba100
  lsr a       ; >00000edc    ba100
  sta $E000   ;  00000edc -> cba10
  lsr a       ; >000000ed    cba10
  sta $E000   ;  000000ed -> dcba1             Once a 1 is shifted into the last position, the SR is full.
  lsr a       ; >0000000e    dcba1             
  sta $E000   ;  0000000e    dcba1 -> edcba    A write with the SR full copies D0 and the SR to a bank register
              ;              10000             ($E000-$FFFF means PRG bank number) and then clears the SR.
  rts

But because only the fifth write sets the destination register, the following equivalent (if obfuscated) subroutine changes the PRG ROM bank in the same manner:

setPRGBank:
  sta $8765
  lsr a
  sta $FACE
  lsr a
  sta $BA11
  lsr a
  sta $AD2E
  lsr a
  sta $EAD5
  rts

Load register ($8000-$FFFF)

7  bit  0
---- ----
Rxxx xxxD
|       |
|       +- Data bit to be shifted into shift register, LSB first
+--------- 1: Reset shift register and write Control with (Control OR $0C),
              locking PRG ROM at $C000-$FFFF to the last bank.

Control (internal, $8000-$9FFF)

4bit0
-----
CPPMM
|||||
|||++- Mirroring (0: one-screen, lower bank; 1: one-screen, upper bank;
|||               2: vertical; 3: horizontal)
|++--- PRG ROM bank mode (0, 1: switch 32 KB at $8000, ignoring low bit of bank number;
|                         2: fix first bank at $8000 and switch 16 KB bank at $C000;
|                         3: fix last bank at $C000 and switch 16 KB bank at $8000)
+----- CHR ROM bank mode (0: switch 8 KB at a time; 1: switch two separate 4 KB banks)

CHR bank 0 (internal, $A000-$BFFF)

4bit0
-----
CCCCC
|||||
+++++- Select 4 KB or 8 KB CHR bank at PPU $0000 (low bit ignored in 8 KB mode)

MMC1 can do CHR banking in 4KB chunks. Known carts with CHR RAM have 8 KiB, so that makes 2 banks. RAM vs ROM doesn't make any difference for address lines. For carts with 8 KiB of CHR (be it ROM or RAM), MMC1 follows the common behavior of using only the low-order bits: the bank number is in effect ANDed with 1.

CHR bank 1 (internal, $C000-$DFFF)

4bit0
-----
CCCCC
|||||
+++++- Select 4 KB CHR bank at PPU $1000 (ignored in 8 KB mode)

PRG bank (internal, $E000-$FFFF)

4bit0
-----
RPPPP
|||||
|++++- Select 16 KB PRG ROM bank (low bit ignored in 32 KB mode)
+----- PRG RAM chip enable (0: enabled; 1: disabled; ignored on MMC1A)

Hardware

At least 6 different versions of the MMC1 are known to exist: MMC1, MMC1A, MMC1B1, MMC1B2, MMC1B3, and MMC1C. The known differences are as follows:

MMC1A: PRG RAM is always enabled. Two games abuse this lack of feature: they have been allocated to iNES Mapper 155.
MMC1B: PRG RAM is enabled by default.
MMC1C: PRG RAM is disabled by default.

The MMC1 most commonly exists in a 24-pin shrink-DIP package.

Boards using an MMC1 may contain a battery connected to the PRG RAM's power line to preserve the data. Boards doing so will allow extra circuitry to be used, with 2 diodes and 2 resistors. A diode is needed from both voltage sources: The battery and the NES 5V, so that one cannot supply current to the other, and there is a resistor in series with the battery so that no current is drained from the battery when 5V is present. A pull-down resistor is needed on the CE line so that the SRAM is disabled when the MMC1 isn't powered. Finally, the battery powered SRAMs have an additional larger decoupling capacitor to make sure voltage transitions are smooth. Very early NES-SNROM-03 and lower revisions lacks that capcity, and saves are lost much more easily on those boards.

Nintendo transitioned from the original MMC1 (manufactured by ROHM) to the MMC1A (manufactured probably by Ricoh) around the 39th week of 1988. (Based on comparison of otherwise identical SMB/DH/WCTM carts from 38th and 39th weeks of '88)

Variants

Because the higher CHR lines aren't used when the MMC1 mapper is used with a 8KB CHR RAM, those lines are sometimes put to other uses depending on the board :

SNROM

CHR bank 0 (internal, $A000-$BFFF)

4bit0
-----
ExxxC
|   |
|   +- Select 4 KB CHR RAM bank at PPU $0000 (ignored in 8 KB mode)
+----- PRG RAM disable (0: enable, 1: open bus)

CHR bank 1 (internal, $C000-$DFFF)

4bit0
-----
ExxxC
|   |
|   +- Select 4 KB CHR RAM bank at PPU $1000 (ignored in 8 KB mode)
+----- PRG RAM disable (0: enable, 1: open bus) (ignored in 8 KB mode)

Both the E bit and the R bit (in standard MMC1 registers) should be clear in order for the PRG RAM to be writable or readable. This bit is more "reliable" on authentic hardware as it is implemented even in older boards with older MMC1's, while the R bit was only introduced later. But because the E bit wasn't confirmed by the homebrew community until October 2010[3], emulators tend not to implement it.

SOROM, SUROM and SXROM

CHR bank 0 (internal, $A000-$BFFF)

4bit0
-----
PSSxC
||| |
||| +- Select 4 KB CHR RAM bank at PPU $0000 (ignored in 8 KB mode)
|++--- Select 8 KB PRG RAM bank
+----- Select 256 KB PRG ROM bank

CHR bank 1 (internal, $C000-$DFFF)

4bit0
-----
PSSxC
||| |
||| +- Select 4 KB CHR RAM bank at PPU $1000 (ignored in 8 KB mode)
|++--- Select 8 KB PRG RAM bank (ignored in 8 KB mode)
+----- Select 256 KB PRG ROM bank (ignored in 8 KB mode)

The SOROM board only implements the upper S bit, while the SUROM board only implements the P bit. For SXROM, the upper S (bit 3) selects the SRAM's A14, and the lower S (bit 2) selects A13[4].

The 256 KB PRG bank selection applies to all the PRG area, including the supposedly "fixed" bank.

In 4KB CHR bank mode, the P, S and E bits in both CHR bank registers must be set to the same values, or the PRG ROM and/or RAM will be bankswitched/enabled as the PPU renders, in a similar fashion as MMC3's scanline counter. As there is not much of a reason to use 4 KB bankswitching with CHR RAM, it is wise for programs to just set 8 KB bankswitching mode in the Control register.

iNES Mapper 001

iNES Mapper 001 is used to designate the SxROM boardset, all of which use Nintendo's MMC1.

This has proven to be problematic for boards (such as SOROM, SUROM and SXROM) which use the upper CHR bank select lines to select additional PRG ROM or PRG RAM data; games which use SOROM or SXROM often must be handled individually based on the ROM checksum.

Heuristic disambiguation

In the absence of data beyond basic iNES header data, an emulator may follow the following procedure to guess a board type useful for emulation:

Determine whether PRG ROM is "large" (512 KiB) or "small" (256 KiB or less) and whether CHR is "large" (16-128 KiB CHR ROM) or "small" (8 KiB CHR ROM or CHR RAM).
When PRG ROM is large, the highest CHR line (CHR A16) switches 256 KiB PRG ROM banks as in SUROM.
When CHR is large, MMC1 registers act "normal".
When CHR is small, the MMC1's CHR bank registers switch PRG RAM banks as in SXROM. If the battery bit is present, only banks which are written to are saved to the disk when the game is quit. When loading a game with the battery bit set, if a 8KB .sav file is present, it is repeated equally across all banks. This will lead to data being saved when it wasn't supposed to for SOROM games, but 8KB of hard disk space isn't a problem, and no known NES game had the copy protection based on PRG RAM size that was common in the Super NES era.
When both PRG ROM and CHR are small, CHR A16 disables PRG RAM when turned on.

NES 2.0 combined implementation

Because NES 2.0 can disambiguate the variant function by PRG ROM, PRG RAM, and CHR RAM sizes, the alternate function of the CHR banking registers can be described together:

$A000 and $C000:
4bit0
-----
EDCBA
|||||
||||+- CHR A12
|||+-- CHR A13, if extant (CHR >= 16k)
||+--- CHR A14, if extant; and PRG RAM A14, if extant (PRG RAM = 32k)
|+---- CHR A15, if extant; and PRG RAM A13, if extant (PRG RAM >= 16k)
+----- CHR A16, if extant; and PRG ROM A18, if extant (PRG ROM = 512k)

The E bit also acts as a PRG RAM disable for SNROM (PRG ROM <= 256k, CHR RAM = 8k, PRG RAM = 8k), though this is merely for write protection and not strictly required for compatible emulation.

The D and C lines are swapped for SXROM (32k PRG RAM) here; the D line actually selects the upper SRAM address line, though this reversal might be irrelevant to an emulator's implementation.

References

↑ 6502_cpu.txt. See the section labelled Instruction Timing, subsections Absolute addressing, Read-Modify-Write instructions
↑ #nesdev IRC chat, 2015/05/23. kevtris: "I think I figured out why the MMC1 ignores the second write. It seems to be because it uses R/W as a clock, and it stays low for 2 cycles, instead of pulsing so only the first is written."
↑ Form topic: NES SNROM to 512K cart?
↑ Forum post: tracing the SXROM PCB

See also

Programming MMC1
MMC1 pinout
"Nintendo MMC1 info for 8-bit NES carts" by Matthew J. Richey
MMC1 doc by Kevin Horton
Comprehensive NES Mapper Document by \Firebug\, information on SUROM/SXROM carts (512k carts, 1024k carts) is inaccurate
US Patent 4,949,298

Categories: Nintendo licensed mappers, In NesCartDB, ASIC mappers, Mappers with large PRG RAM

MMC3

MMC3
TxROM

Company | Nintendo, others
Games | 300 in NesCartDB
Complexity | ASIC
Boards | TSROM, others
PRG ROM capacity | 512K
PRG ROM window | 8K + 8K + 16K fixed
PRG RAM capacity | 8K
PRG RAM window | 8K
CHR capacity | 256K
CHR window | 2Kx2 + 1Kx4
Nametable mirroring | H or V, switchable, or 4 fixed
Bus conflicts | No
IRQ | Yes
Audio | No
iNES mappers | 004, 118, 119

NESCartDB

iNES 004
TxROM

The Nintendo MMC3 is a mapper ASIC used in Nintendo's TxROM Game Pak boards. Most common TxROM boards, along with the NES-HKROM board (which uses the Nintendo MMC6) are assigned to iNES Mapper 004.

Some less common MMC3 boards required alternative iNES mapper implementations:

iNES Mapper 118 - TKSROM and TLSROM
iNES Mapper 119 - TQROM

This chip first appeared in the fourth quarter of 1988.

Contents

1 Banks
2 Registers

2.1 Bank select ($8000-$9FFE, even)

2.1.1 CHR Banks
2.1.2 PRG Banks

2.2 Bank data ($8001-$9FFF, odd)
2.3 Mirroring ($A000-$BFFE, even)
2.4 PRG RAM protect ($A001-$BFFF, odd)
2.5 IRQ latch ($C000-$DFFE, even)
2.6 IRQ reload ($C001-$DFFF, odd)
2.7 IRQ disable ($E000-$FFFE, even)
2.8 IRQ enable ($E001-$FFFF, odd)

3 Hardware
4 iNES Mapper 004 and MMC6
5 Variants
6 Pirate variants
7 See also

Banks

CPU $6000-$7FFF: 8 KB PRG RAM bank
CPU $8000-$9FFF (or $C000-$DFFF): 8 KB switchable PRG ROM bank
CPU $A000-$BFFF: 8 KB switchable PRG ROM bank
CPU $C000-$DFFF (or $8000-$9FFF): 8 KB PRG ROM bank, fixed to the second-last bank
CPU $E000-$FFFF: 8 KB PRG ROM bank, fixed to the last bank
PPU $0000-$07FF (or $1000-$17FF): 2 KB switchable CHR bank
PPU $0800-$0FFF (or $1800-$1FFF): 2 KB switchable CHR bank
PPU $1000-$13FF (or $0000-$03FF): 1 KB switchable CHR bank
PPU $1400-$17FF (or $0400-$07FF): 1 KB switchable CHR bank
PPU $1800-$1BFF (or $0800-$0BFF): 1 KB switchable CHR bank
PPU $1C00-$1FFF (or $0C00-$0FFF): 1 KB switchable CHR bank

Registers

The MMC3 has 4 pairs of registers at $8000-$9FFF, $A000-$BFFF, $C000-$DFFF, and $E000-$FFFF - even addresses ($8000, $8002, etc.) select the low register and odd addresses ($8001, $8003, etc.) select the high register in each pair. These can be broken into two independent functional units: memory mapping ($8000, $8001, $A000, $A001) and scanline counting ($C000, $C001, $E000, $E001).

Bank select ($8000-$9FFE, even)

7  bit  0
---- ----
CPMx xRRR
|||   |||
|||   +++- Specify which bank register to update on next write to Bank Data register
|||        0: Select 2 KB CHR bank at PPU $0000-$07FF (or $1000-$17FF);
|||        1: Select 2 KB CHR bank at PPU $0800-$0FFF (or $1800-$1FFF);
|||        2: Select 1 KB CHR bank at PPU $1000-$13FF (or $0000-$03FF);
|||        3: Select 1 KB CHR bank at PPU $1400-$17FF (or $0400-$07FF);
|||        4: Select 1 KB CHR bank at PPU $1800-$1BFF (or $0800-$0BFF);
|||        5: Select 1 KB CHR bank at PPU $1C00-$1FFF (or $0C00-$0FFF);
|||        6: Select 8 KB PRG ROM bank at $8000-$9FFF (or $C000-$DFFF);
|||        7: Select 8 KB PRG ROM bank at $A000-$BFFF
||+------- Nothing on the MMC3, see MMC6
|+-------- PRG ROM bank mode (0: $8000-$9FFF swappable,
|                                $C000-$DFFF fixed to second-last bank;
|                             1: $C000-$DFFF swappable,
|                                $8000-$9FFF fixed to second-last bank)
+--------- CHR A12 inversion (0: two 2 KB banks at $0000-$0FFF,
                                 four 1 KB banks at $1000-$1FFF;
                              1: two 2 KB banks at $1000-$1FFF,
                                 four 1 KB banks at $0000-$0FFF)

CHR Banks

When $8000 & #$80 | is 0 | is #$80
PPU Bank | Value of MMC3 register
$0000-$03FF | R0 AND $FE | R2
$0400-$07FF | R0 OR 1 | R3
$0800-$0BFF | R1 AND $FE | R4
$0C00-$0FFF | R1 OR 1 | R5
$1000-$13FF | R2 | R0 AND $FE
$1400-$17FF | R3 | R0 OR 1
$1800-$1BFF | R4 | R1 AND $FE
$1C00-$1FFF | R5 | R1 OR 1

PRG Banks

Because the values in R6, R7, and $8000 are unspecified at power on, the reset vector must point into $E000-$FFFF, and code must initialize these before jumping out of $E000-$FFFF.

When $8000 & #$40 | is 0 | is #$40
CPU Bank | Value of MMC3 register
$8000-$9FFF | R6 | (-2)
$A000-$BFFF | R7 | R7
$C000-$DFFF | (-2) | R6
$E000-$FFFF | (-1) | (-1)

(-1) : the last bank, in a proper MMC3, the 63rd
(-2) : the penultimate bank; properly the 62nd

Bank data ($8001-$9FFF, odd)

7  bit  0
---- ----
DDDD DDDD
|||| ||||
++++-++++- New bank value, based on last value written to Bank select register (mentioned above)

The PRG banks are 8192 bytes in size, half the size of an iNES PRG bank. If your emulator or copier handles PRG data in 16384 byte chunks, you can think of the lower bit as selecting the first or second half of the bank:[1]

7  bit  0  When $8000 AND #$06 == #$06
---- ----
xxBB BBBH
  || ||||
  || |||+- 0: Select first half of this bank;
  || |||   1: Select second half of this bank
  ++-+++-- Select 16 KB PRG bank at $8000-$9FFF, $A000-$BFFF, or $C000-$DFFF

Writes to registers 6 and 7 always ignore bits 6 and 7, as the MMC3 has only 6 PRG ROM address output lines.

Writes to registers 0 and 1 always ignore bit 0, loading the value AND #$FE into the first half and the value OR #$01 into the second half of the 2 KiB bank.

Some romhacks rely on an 8-bit extension of registers 6 and 7 for oversized PRG-ROM, but this is deliberately not supported by many emulators. See iNES Mapper 004 below.

Mirroring ($A000-$BFFE, even)

7  bit  0
---- ----
xxxx xxxM
        |
        +- Nametable mirroring (0: vertical; 1: horizontal)

This bit has no effect on Rad Racer II, which uses the TVROM board, because TVROM is hardwired to 4-screen VRAM. In the iNES and NES 2.0 formats, TVROM can be identified through bit 3 of byte $06 of the header.

PRG RAM protect ($A001-$BFFF, odd)

7  bit  0
---- ----
RWXX xxxx
||||
||++------ Nothing on the MMC3, see MMC6
|+-------- Write protection (0: allow writes; 1: deny writes)
+--------- PRG RAM chip enable (0: disable; 1: enable)

Disabling PRG RAM through bit 7 causes reads from the PRG RAM region to return open bus.

Though these bits are functional on the MMC3, their main purpose is to write-protect save RAM during power-off. Many emulators choose not to implement them as part of iNES Mapper 4 to avoid an incompatibility with the MMC6.

See iNES Mapper 004 and MMC6 below.

IRQ latch ($C000-$DFFE, even)

7  bit  0
---- ----
DDDD DDDD
|||| ||||
++++-++++- IRQ latch value

This register specifies the IRQ counter reload value. When the IRQ counter is zero (or a reload is requested through $C001), this value will be copied to the IRQ counter at the NEXT rising edge of the PPU address, presumably at PPU cycle 260 of the current scanline.

IRQ reload ($C001-$DFFF, odd)

7  bit  0
---- ----
xxxx xxxx

Writing any value to this register reloads the MMC3 IRQ counter at the NEXT rising edge of the PPU address, presumably at PPU cycle 260 of the current scanline.

IRQ disable ($E000-$FFFE, even)

7  bit  0
---- ----
xxxx xxxx

Writing any value to this register will disable MMC3 interrupts AND acknowledge any pending interrupts.

IRQ enable ($E001-$FFFF, odd)

7  bit  0
---- ----
xxxx xxxx

Writing any value to this register will enable MMC3 interrupts.

Hardware

The MMC3 most commonly exists in a 44-pin TQFP package. Three revisions are known to exist - MMC3A, MMC3B, and MMC3C. No major behavioral differences are known, except for the IRQ counter.

The MMC3 scanline counter is based entirely on PPU A12, triggered on rising edges (after the line remains low for two rising edges of M2).

The counter is based on the following trick: whenever rendering is turned on in the PPU, it fetches nametable and BG pattern tiles from dots 0-255 and 320-340 of a scanline and fetches sprite patterns from dots 256-319, even if no sprites are visible. Because of this, if BG uses the left pattern table ($0000), and if sprites always use the right pattern table ($1000), A12 will remain low during all nametable and BG pattern fetches, and high during all sprite pattern fetches, causing it to oscillate exactly one time per scanline and 241 times per frame. It may oscillate more if the program uses registers $2006 and $2007 to access PPU $1000-$1FFF during vblank, but this is rare because very few games have MMC3 and CHR RAM (two on TQROM and three on TGROM among NES games, and a couple more Famicom-only games). The scanline counter will also work when the BG uses the right pattern table ($1000) and the sprites use the left pattern table ($0000), but this is less common. The MMC3 IRQ has two revisions that work slightly different [2].

Counter operation:

When the IRQ is clocked (PPU A12 0->1), the counter value is checked - if zero or the reload flag is true, it's reloaded with the IRQ latched value at $C000; otherwise, it decrements.
If the IRQ counter is zero and IRQs are enabled ($E001), an IRQ is triggered. The "alternate revision" checks the IRQ counter transition 1->0, whether from decrementing or reloading.

Regarding PPU A12:

If the BG uses $0000, and the sprites use $1000, the IRQ counter should decrement on PPU cycle 260,268,276... or 315 (as in, a little after the visible part of the target scanline has ended).
If the BG uses $1000, and the sprites use $0000, the IRQ counter should decrement on PPU cycle 324 or 332 of the previous scanline (as in, right before the target scanline is about to be drawn).
For 8x16 sprites: if there are less than 8 sprites on a scanline, the PPU makes a dummy fetch to tile $FF (right pattern table $1000) for each leftover sprite. So, games with background and sprites from PPU $0000 watches the sprite tile pattern selection.

Important points:

The scanline counter cannot be stopped. It will continue to decrement and reload as long as PPU A12 on the PPU bus toggles.
There is no direct access to the counter! The best you can do is update the reload value and immediately request a reload.
Writing to $E000 will only prevent the MMC3 from generating IRQs - the counter will continue to run.
Writing to $E001 will simply allow the MMC3 to generate IRQs - the counter remains unaffected.
Writing to $C001 will cause the counter to be cleared, and set reload flag to true. It will be reloaded on the NEXT rising edge of the PPU A12.
Writing to $C000 does not immediately affect the value within the counter - this value is only used when the counter is reloaded, whether from reaching 0 or from writing to $C001.
The exact number of scanlines between IRQs is N+1, where N is the value written to $C000. 1 (Sharp MMC3B, MMC3C) or 2 (MMC3A, Non-Sharp MMC3B) to 256 scanlines are supported.
The counter will not work properly unless you use different pattern tables for background and sprite data. The standard configuration is to use PPU $0000-$0FFF for background tiles and $1000-$1FFF for sprite tiles, whether 8x8 or 8x16.
The counter is clocked on each rising edge of PPU A12, no matter what caused it, so it is possible to (intentionally or not) clock the counter by writing to $2006, regardless of whether PPU is/is not rendering.

There's a slight discrepancy with what happens when you set $C000 to $00, and so far, two behaviors are known to exist:

All MMC3A's and non-Sharp MMC3B's will generate only a single IRQ when $C000 is $00. This is because this version of the MMC3 generates IRQs when the scanline counter is decremented to 0. In addition, writing to $C001 with $C000 still at $00 will result in another single IRQ being generated. In the community, this is known as the "alternate" or "old" behavior.
All MMC3C's and Sharp MMC3B's will generate an IRQ on each scanline while $C000 is $00. This is because this version of the MMC3 generates IRQs when the scanline counter is equal to 0. In the community, this is known as the "normal" or "new" behavior.

Acclaim's MC-ACC chip is their own variant of the MMC3, that they used for their own boards (for industrial money-saving purposes). It comes in a standard 600 mil 40-pin DIP package. It is not known if it has SRAM support. The only known difference is that the scanline counter triggers on falling edges instead of rising edges.

iNES Mapper 004 and MMC6

The unfortunate conflation of MMC3 and MMC6 into the same iNES mapper can be resolved by the use of an NES 2.0 header, but since the new header is not yet well adopted among emulators or ROM sets, an approach that supports both MMC3 and MMC6 may be desired when an NES 2.0 header is not used.

The MMC6 has a smaller PRG-RAM, and a different register scheme for write protecting it.

Because write protection is generally only used to guard against corruption during power off, many implementations of iNES Mapper 004 simply omit the write protection. Leaving PRG-RAM always write-enabled removes most of the incompatibility between MMC3 and MMC6, and is sufficient to support the popular MMC6 games StarTropics and StarTropics II. These games do not rely on the smaller PRG-RAM size of the MMC6, so the larger 8k RAM addressed by the MMC3 is not a problem.

The less well known game Low G Man is problematic. It used an MMC3 board with no PRG-RAM. Because of a bug in its music code, it relies on open-bus behaviour in the RAM's address range to function correctly. The game does use the MMC3 mechanism to disable RAM, so it may function on an MMC3 board with PRG-RAM, but implementing the MMC3 RAM disable may conflict with the effort to support MMC6 games. Alternatively, NES 2.0 could be used to specify a PRG-RAM size of 0, or the problem can be resolved by patching the Low G Man ROM to work around the conflict: patch.

Some romhacks attempt to increase the available PRG-ROM size beyond the MMC3's hard 512k limit (e.g. Translation of Final Fantasy III). Full 8-bit banking registers could theoretically support up to 2048K PRG-ROM, but very few emulators implement this extension.

Variants

The TKSROM and TLSROM boards, assigned to INES Mapper 118, connect the upper bank select line directly to VRAM A10, allowing more flexible control over nametable mirroring.

The TQROM board, assigned to INES Mapper 119, uses both CHR ROM and CHR RAM simultaneously, using the 2nd-highest CHR bank select line to choose between them (on a per-bank basis).

The DxROM board, assigned to iNES Mapper 206 has a custom mapper developed by Namco before the MMC3 existed. It has no IRQ or mirroring control. Tengen used it for some of their games under the name MIMIC-1. It exists both in a 400 mil 28-pin Shrink-DIP (found in licensed DxROM boards) and in a larger 600 mil 28-pin DIP (found in unlicensed Tengen cartridges).

The Namco 108/MIMIC-1 does the basic ROM banking exactly like the MMC3, but it only implements the low 3 bits of $8000 and the low 6 bits of $8001. Compared to the MMC3, it lacks mirroring control, SRAM support and an IRQ counter. The TEROM and TFROM boards have been developed with backward compability with DxROM in mind, featuring solder pads to have hardwired H/V mirroring instead of MMC3 controlled mirroring, and allow the hardware to disable IRQs.

IRQ behavior when reload is set to 0 differs among different MMC3 chips. MMC3 chips with the "new behavior" generate an IRQ every scanline. (These include at least MMC3B chips bearing a bold S before the date code.) MMC3 chips with the "old behavior" cease to generate IRQs. (These include MMC3B chips lacking the S and having a date code of the form nnnnPKnnn, and an MMC3A 8940EP chip.) Some games have been manufactured with both versions, and during the transition, relying on old or new behavior might at first have been one of the things that caused Nintendo lot check to reject a program. A few later games developed after Nintendo had run out of the old chips, such as Star Trek: 25th Anniversary, are reported to rely on the new behavior (source: Nestopia 1.30 changelog).

There's an anecdotal report that Felix the Cat needs MMC3A, but it's necessarily not related to the IRQ behavior since the game works correctly in emulators that only implement the MMC3C behavior.

Nintendo made at least two MMC3-based multicart mappers: mappers 37 and 47.

Pirate variants

Mapper 245 increases PRG to 1024K by losing CHR ROM.

Mappers 205, 52, 49, 45, and 44 force unmodified games together in a multicart.

Mapper 189 loses the MMC3's 8+8+16F banking scheme in exchange for 32k-at-a-time banking like AxROM, BxROM, or GxROM

Mapper 182's registers are only in a different order.

Mapper 115 increases CHR to 512K by losing PRG RAM and contains an UxROM emulation mode.

Mappers 194, 192, 191, and 74, are like TQROM in that they combine CHR ROM and CHR RAM by replacing some CHR pages with CHR RAM.

See also

MMC3-like mappers
NES Mapper list by Disch.
Nintendo MMC3 by goroh.
Comprehensive NES Mapper Document by \Firebug\. Information on mapper's initial state is innacurate.

Categories: Mappers with scanline IRQs, Nintendo licensed mappers, In NesCartDB, ASIC mappers, MMC3-like mappers

Mouse

Recent homebrew has adapted the SNES mouse to be used with the NES.

A famiclone made by the Subor company also had a mouse.

SNES Mouse

The Super NES Mouse (SNS-016) is a peripheral for the Super NES that was originally bundled with Mario Paint. It can be used with an NES through an adapter, made from an NES controller extension cord and a Super NES controller extension cord, that connects the respective power, ground, clock, latch, and data pins.

As with the standard controller, the mouse is read by turning the latch ($4016.d0) on and off, and then reading bit 0 or bit 1 of $4016 or $4017 several times, but its report is 32 bits long as opposed to 8 bits. Bit 0 goes to the standard controller ports on an NES or AV Famicom; bit 1 goes to the Famicom 4-player adapter.

Some documents about interfacing with the mouse recommend reading the first 16 bits at one speed, delaying a while, and reading the other 16 bits at another speed, following logic analyzer traces from a Super NES console. However, these different speeds are merely an artifact of the main loop of Mario Paint, and the mouse will give a correct report when read at any reasonable speed. For example, a program could read 8 bits, wait a couple thousand cycles, and then read the other 24.

The first byte of the report is all zeroes and may be ignored. The other three bytes are sent most significant bit first:

76543210  Second byte of report
||||++++- Signature: 0001
||++----- Current sensitivity (0: low; 1: medium; 2: high)
|+------- Left button (1: pressed)
+-------- Right button (1: pressed)

76543210  Third byte of report
|+++++++- Vertical displacement since last read
+-------- Direction (1: up; 0: down)

76543210  Fourth byte of report
|+++++++- Horizontal displacement since last read
+-------- Direction (1: left; 0: right)

The displacements are in sign-and-magnitude, not two's complement. For example, $05 represents five mickeys (movement units) in one direction and $85 represents five mickeys in the other. To convert these to two's complement, use negation:

  ; Convert to two's complement
  lda third_byte
  bpl :+
  eor #$7F
  sec
  adc #$00
:
  sta y_velocity

  lda fourth_byte
  bpl :+
  eor #$7F
  sec
  adc #$00
:
  sta x_velocity

The mouse can be set to low, medium, or high sensitivity. To change the sensitivity, send a clock while the latch ($4016.d0) is turned on:

  ldy #1
  sty $4016
  lda $4016,x
  dey
  sty $4016

Some revisions of the mouse's microcontroller reportedly power up in an unknown state and may return useless values before the sensitivity is changed for the first time. A mouse detection routine should cycle through the sensitivities anyway to ensure that the connected device is in fact a mouse. Failure to do so is likely to cause things that are not a mouse to be detected as a mouse, such as half of a Four Score if player 3 or 4 is holding Right.

Using more than two mice on an AV Famicom is not recommended for two reasons:

A mouse draws 50 mA, which is much more current than the standard controller draws. Drawing too much current is likely to cause the voltage regulator to overheat.
Changing player 1's sensitivity also affects player 3's, and changing player 2's sensitivity also affects player 4's.

A program that reads the mouse while playing DPCM samples must proceed very carefully. Sample playback causes occasional double reads on $4016 and $4017, deleting a bit from the stream read back. The re-reading solution that can be used for the standard controller fails here because each latch pulse sent to a mouse will clear its count of accumulated movement, and there is no known way to reliably detect corrupted data. Only the OAM DMA sync trick reliably avoids these glitches.

A program could read the mouse while using the DMC as a interval timer, as long as the mouse is read in the IRQ handler so that the mouse reading subroutine can avoid the sample fetch.

Example games:

Thwaite

Subor Mouse

This came with Subor's SB2000 famiclone system.

Example games:

Educational Computer 2000

Reference: Nocash's EveryNES documentation

Categories: Super NES, Controllers

Namco 163 audio

The Namco 163 offers up to 8 additional sound channels that play wavetable samples while the 175 and 340 do not. Each waveform can be of a configurable length, and each channel has linear volume control. It has $80 bytes of sound RAM shared by channel registers and wavetable samples; at least $40 bytes are dedicated to samples, with more available if not all channels are used.

Like the Ensoniq DOC in the Apple IIGS, the chip is unable to clock every channel at once, so it cycles though channels, updating one every 15 CPU cycles. Because of this, the chip allows the game to configure the number of enabled channels. When fewer channels are enabled, the channels are clocked more often, allowing for higher tones with longer, more detailed waveforms. When more channels are enabled, clocking slows down since each channel has to wait its turn, resulting in lower tones and a high-pitched whining noise at the switching frequency. Most games using this IC used only 4 channels.

Contents

1 Registers

1.1 Sound Enable ($E000-E7FF)
1.2 Address Port ($F800-$FFFF)
1.3 Data Port ($4800-$4FFF)

1.3.1 Sound RAM $78 - Low Frequency
1.3.2 Sound RAM $79 - Low Phase
1.3.3 Sound RAM $7A - Mid Frequency
1.3.4 Sound RAM $7B - Mid Phase
1.3.5 Sound RAM $7C - High Frequency and Wave Length
1.3.6 Sound RAM $7D - High Phase
1.3.7 Sound RAM $7E - Wave Address
1.3.8 Sound RAM $7F - Volume
1.3.9 Other Channels

2 Waveform
3 Channel Update
4 Frequency
5 Mixing
6 References

Registers

Sound Enable ($E000-E7FF)

7  bit  0
---- ----
.SPP PPPP
 ||| ||||
 |++-++++- Select 8KB page of PRG-ROM at $8000
 +-------- Disables sound if set.

Sound is enabled on the 163 by writing a clear bit 6 to this register (0 is sufficient).

Address Port ($F800-$FFFF)

7  bit  0   (write only)
---- ----
IAAA AAAA
|||| ||||
|+++-++++- Address
+--------- Auto-increment

Writing to this register sets the internal address. If the 'I' bit is set, the address will increment on writes and reads to the Data Port ($4800), wrapping $7F->$00 (address is 7 bits wide)

Data Port ($4800-$4FFF)

7  bit  0   (read / write)
---- ----
DDDD DDDD
|||| ||||
++++-++++- Data

This Port accesses the 163's internal $80 bytes of sound RAM. Which of the $80 bytes is determined by the Address register ($F800). When read, the appropriate byte is returned. When written, the appropriate byte is set.

This RAM is used primarily for wavetables. The sound channel control registers are also set by writing to certain addresses in sound RAM:

Sound RAM $78 - Low Frequency

7  bit  0
---------
FFFF FFFF
|||| ||||
++++-++++- Low 8 bits of Frequency

Sound RAM $79 - Low Phase

7  bit  0
---------
FFFF FFFF
|||| ||||
++++-++++- Low 8 bits of Phase

Sound RAM $7A - Mid Frequency

7  bit  0
---------
FFFF FFFF
|||| ||||
++++-++++- Middle 8 bits of Frequency

Sound RAM $7B - Mid Phase

7  bit  0
---------
FFFF FFFF
|||| ||||
++++-++++- Middle 8 bits of Phase

Sound RAM $7C - High Frequency and Wave Length

7  bit  0
---------
LLLL LLFF
|||| ||||
|||| ||++- High 2 bits of Frequency
++++-++--- Length of waveform ((64-L)*4 4-bit samples)

Sound RAM $7D - High Phase

7  bit  0
---------
FFFF FFFF
|||| ||||
++++-++++- High 8 bits of Phase

The high byte of the 24-bit phase value directly determines the current sample position of the channel. Every time a channel is updated, the 18-bit frequency value is added to the 24-bit phase accumulator, which is stored in these three registers.

The phase registers may be written to immediately set the phase of the wave. It is good practice to set the frequency to 0 before doing so.

Sound RAM $7E - Wave Address

7  bit  0
---------
AAAA AAAA
|||| ||||
++++-++++- Address of waveform (in 4-bit samples)

Sound RAM $7F - Volume

7  bit  0
---------
.CCC VVVV
 ||| ||||
 ||| ++++- Linear Volume
 +++------ Enabled Channels (1+C)

Note 'C' is available on register $7F ONLY. Those bits have no effect in other registers.

When C=0, only channel 8 enabled
When C=1, channels 8 and 7 enabled
When C=2, channels 8, 7, 6 enabled
etc...

Other Channels

Above Sound RAM register descriptions ($78-$7F) are for the 8th channel. The other 7 channels are accessed via the same pattern, but each 8 bytes before the last:

Channel 8:  $78-$7F
Channel 7:  $70-$77
Channel 6:  $68-$6F
Channel 5:  $60-$67
Channel 4:  $58-$5F
Channel 3:  $50-$57
Channel 2:  $48-$4F
Channel 1:  $40-$47

Again note that the 'C' bits in the final register is only available at address $7F.

When channels are disabled, their registers are unused, and can be used for waveform data instead.

Waveform

Each enabled channel cycles through its waveform at a rate determined by the 18-bit frequency value 'F'. Each step in the waveform is 4-bits wide, and the number of steps is determined by the 'L' bits ((64-L)*4). Two samples are stored to a byte, which is little-endian (unlike the Game Boy's wavetable channel).

The 'A' bits dictate where in the internal sound RAM the waveform starts. 'A' is the address in 4-bit samples, therefore a value of $02 would be the low 4 bits of address $01. A value of $03 would be the high 4 bits of address $01.

For a visual example, assume you have the following sound RAM:

$00:    00 00 00 A8 DC EE FF FF EF DE AC 58 23 11 00 00
$10:    10 21 53 00 00 00 00 00 00 00 00 00 00 00 00 00

And assume a channel has a 'A' value of $06, and a 'L' value of $39. That channel's waveform would be a sine wave, looking like the following:

F -       *****
E -     **     **
D -    *         *
C -   *           *
B -
A -  *             *
9 - 
8 - *               *
7 - 
6 -
5 -                  *             *
4 -
3 -                   *           *
2 -                    *         *
1 -                     **     **
0 -                       *****

Channel Update

Namco's 163 does not internally mix its channels. Instead, each channel is output one at a time. It takes exactly 15 CPU cycles to update and output one channel. When multiple channels are used it will cycle between them. With 6 or fewer channels, the time to update all channels is a rate faster than any audible frequency, and the difference between this serial output and mixing cannot be heard, but for 8 channels it creates a very loud and apparent noise at the update rate. For a Famicom through RF output, this noise is attenuated during demodulation (which performs a lowpass filter), but through A/V output to a TV that does not filter high frequencies, it can be very unpleasant. Only two games used all 8 channels: King of Kings and Erika to Satoru no Yume Bouken.

Channels | Update Rate
1 | 119318 Hz
2 | 59659 Hz
3 | 39773 Hz
4 | 29830 Hz
5 | 23864 Hz
6 | 19886 Hz
7 | 17045 Hz
8 | 14915 Hz

The following is a speculative version of a single channel update, occurring every 15 CPU cycles:

* w[$80] = the 163's internal memory
* sample(x) = (w[x/2] >> ((x&1)*4)) & $0F
* phase = (w[$7D] << 16) + (w[$7B] << 8) + w[$79]
* freq = ((w[$7C] & $03) << 16) + (w[$7A] << 8) + w[$78]
* length = 256 - (w[$7C] & $FC)
* offset = w[$7E]
* volume = w[$7F] & $0F

phase = (phase + freq) % (length << 16)
output = (sample(((phase >> 16) + offset) & $FF) - 8) * volume

The output will be held until the next channel update. The 24-bit phase value will be stored back into w[$7D/$7B/$79].

The sample value is biased by -8, meaning that a waveform value of 8 represents the centre voltage. This means that volume changes have no effect on a sample of 8, will tend negative if <8 and positive if >8.

Frequency

The wave position is driven by the high 8 bits of a 24-bit accumulator. Every 15 CPU clocks, one channel will add its 18-bit frequency to the accumulator. Because only one channel is updated per tick, the output frequency is thus divided by the number of channels enabled.

f = wave frequency
l = wave length
c = number of channels
p = 18-bit frequency value
n = CPU clock rate (≈1789773 Hz)

f = (n * p) / (15 * 65536 * l * c)

Mixing

The relative volume of the IC varies from game to game, unfortunately.

A 163 with a single channel enabled is somewhere between ~3.6x and ~8.5x as loud as the APU square at max volume. The two 8-channel games have a louder mix, probably to compensate for the quieter volume when more channels are enabled. Some 4-channel games have a quieter mix. The polarity of the 163 is reversed from the 2A03.

The volume comparison measured on various cartridges: (Values in parentheses are estimated based on listening/balance.)

4-Channel Game | Volume | Samples
Final Lap | 3.6x | 1
Mappy Kids | (~6x) | 0
Megami Tensei II | 4.0x | 1
Namco Classic 2 | (~6x) | 0
Rolling Thunder | 6.5x | 2
Sangokushi | (~6x) | 0
Sangokushi 2 | (~4x) | 0
8-Channel Game | Volume | Samples
Erika to Satoru no Yumebouken | 8.5x | 1
King of Kings | 7.3x | 1

Since the mix appears to be arbitrarily chosen per-game, how to handle this is a difficult choice for an emulator author. It should probably be adjustable. You may choose to simply boost the volume when 8-channels are used. You may try to use a value in between (~6.0x sounds well for all games except Final Lap and Sangokushi 2). You may keep a table of 163 games and their volumes (ignoring potential homebrew), though more data needs to be collected . It should be noted that the 8-channel games do not significantly use the 2A03 for music, except the noise channel, so an accurate mix may be less important.

Because the high frequency generated by the channel cycling can be unpleasant, and emulation of high frequency audio can be difficult, it is often preferred to simply sum the channel outputs, and divide the output volume by the number of channels. To compensate for less drop in apparent volume once the switching frequency crosses the threshold of audibility, it may be desired to slightly increase the volume for >5 channels (perhaps always dividing the output by 6 for 6, 7 or 8 channels).

References

Namcot 106 Mapper Information by Goroh, ZW4, nori
NES Music Format Spec by Kevin Horton, N106 info by Mamiya

Categories: Expansion audio

Nerdy Nights: Square 1

Square 1 Channel

Let's make a beep. This week we'll learn how to produce a sound on the Square 1 channel. The Square channels are everybody's favorites because you can control the volume and tone and perform sweeps on them. You can produce a lot of interesting effects using the Squares.

Square 1 is controlled via ports $4000-$4003. The first port, $4000, controls the duty cycle (ie, tone) and volume for the channel. It looks like this:

7654 3210  SQ1_ENV ($4000)
|||| ||||
|||| ++++- Volume
|||+------ Saw Envelope Disable (0: use internal counter for volume; 1: use Volume for volume)
||+------- Length Counter Disable (0: use Length Counter; 1: disable Length Counter)
++-------- Duty Cycle

For our purposes, we will focus on Volume and Duty Cycle. We will set Saw Envelope Disable and Length Counter Disable to 1 and then forget about them. If we leave Saw Envelopes on, the volume of the channel will be controlled by an internal counter. If we turn them off, WE have control of the volume. If WE have control, we can code our own envelopes (much more versatile). Same thing with the Length Counter. If we disable it, we have more control over note lengths. If that didn't make sense, don't worry. It will become clearer later. For now we're just going to disable and forget about them.

Volume controls the channel's volume. It's 4 bits long so it can have a value from 0-F. A volume of 0 silences the channel. 1 is very quiet and F is loud.

Duty Cycle controls the tone of the Square channel. It's 2 bits long, so there are four possible values:

00 = a weak, grainy tone. Think of the engine sounds in RC Pro-Am. (12.5% Duty)
01 = a solid mid-strength tone. (25% Duty)
10 = a strong, full tone, like a clarinet or a lead guitar (50% Duty)
11 = sounds a lot like 01 (25% Duty negated)

The best way to know the difference in sound is to listen yourself. I recommend downloading FamiTracker and playing with the different Duty settings in the Instrument Editor.

For those interested, Duty Cycle actually refers to the percentage of time that the wave is in "up" position vs. "down" position. Here are some pictures:

[diagram missing]

Don't sweat it if graphs and waves aren't your thing. Use your ears instead.

Here's a code snippet that sets the Duty and Volume for the Square 1 channel:

   lda #%10111111; Duty 10 (50%), volume F (max!)
   sta $4000

$4001 controls sweeps for Square 1. We'll skip them for now.

Setting the note

$4002 and $4003 control the period of the wave, or in other words what note you hear (A, C#, G, etc). Periods are 11-bits long. $4002 holds the low 8-bits and $4003 holds the high 3-bits of the period. We'll get into more detail in a future tutorial, but for now just know that changing the values written to these ports will change the note that is played.

7654 3210  SQ1_LO ($4002)
|||| ||||
++++-++++- Low 8-bits of period

7654 3210  SQ1_HI ($4003)
|||| ||||
|||| |+++- High 3-bits of period
++++-+---- Length Counter

The Length Counter, if enabled, controls how long the note is played. We disabled it up in the $4000 section, so we can forget about it for now.

Here is some code that will produce an eternal beep on the Square 1 channel:

   lda #%00000001
   sta $4015 ;enable square 1

   lda #%10111111 ;Duty 10, Volume F
   sta $4000

   lda #$C9    ;0C9 is a C# in NTSC mode
   sta $4002
   lda #$00
   sta $4003
   

Putting it all together

Download and unzip the square1.zip sample files. All the code above is in the square1.asm file. Make sure square1.asm and square1.bat are all in the same folder as NESASM3, then double click square1.bat. That will run NESASM3 and should produce the square1.nes file. Run that NES file in FCEUXD SP to listen to your beep! Edit square1.asm to change the Volume (0 to F), or to change the Duty Cycle for the square wave. Try changing the period to produce different notes.

Categories: APU

NES 2.0

NES 2.0 is an extension to the iNES ROM format, originally proposed by Kevin Horton on 2006-09-18.

It adds extra header information to disambiguate ROMs that incompatibly require the same iNES mapper, or supplemental information for ROMs that are otherwise inadequately described by the original format.

This extension is backwards compatible with the original format, identified by two bits in byte 7 of the header.

Contents

1 Overview
2 Existing header

2.1 Byte 6 (Flags 6)
2.2 Byte 7 (Flags 7)

3 The problem cases

3.1 Vs. Unisystem
3.2 Big ROMs
3.3 Submappers
3.4 Mapper number exhaustion
3.5 WRAM

4 The proposed solution

4.1 Byte 8 (Mapper variant)
4.2 Byte 9 (Upper bits of ROM size)
4.3 Byte 10 (RAM size)
4.4 Byte 11 (Video RAM Size)
4.5 Byte 12 (TV system)
4.6 Byte 13 (Vs. hardware)
4.7 Byte 14 and 15 (Reserved)

5 Emulator support
6 See also
7 References

Overview

Written by K.Horton
Thanks to Quietust for ideas and proofing and help

NES 2.0 is an addition to the standard .NES file format that most emulators use. It is designed to disambiguate certain ROMs that formerly could have been only be discerned via a CRC-32 or similar hash check. Naturally, this caused problems for new ROMs that are not in the database but need special handling, such as fan translations, other ROM hacks, and new homebrew on compatible boards.

There are four goals for this specification:

Retain 100% backwards compatibility with existing emulators/ROMs/etc. (*this includes "dirty ROMs" with crap such as "DiskDude!" in the header and other atrocities*)
The format must be "future proof".
The changes made must be very carefully documented and make sense.
Said changes must make sense from both a hardware and software standpoint.

The name of this specification is "NES 2.0". Do not confuse with "iNES 2.0" which is an emulator that does not support extended features of NES 2.0 headers.

Existing header

The standard specification as popularized by the iNES emulator is presented below:

 0-3: string    "NES"<EOF>
   4: byte      Number of 16384 byte program ROM pages
   5: byte      Number of 8192 byte character ROM pages (0 indicates CHR RAM)
   6: bitfield  Flags 6
   7: bitfield  Flags 7
8-15: byte      These bytes are not used, and should be 00h.

The PRG ROM size is in 16384 byte units, and the CHR ROM size is in 8192 byte units. If the actual game's data is smaller, such as 8192-byte PRG for Galaxian or 4096-byte CHR for Slappin', double it up and call it a day. For example, if the PRG ROM data is 16384 bytes long, and the first 8192 bytes of the PRG ROM data match the second 8192 bytes, the PRG ROM is an 8Kx8 chip.

Byte 6 (Flags 6)

7       0
---------
NNNN FTBM

N: Lower 4 bits of the mapper number
F: Four screen mode. 0 = no, 1 = yes. (When set, the M bit has no effect)
T: Trainer.  0 = no trainer present, 1 = 512 byte trainer at 7000-71FFh
B: SRAM at 6000-7FFFh battery backed.  0= no, 1 = yes
M: Mirroring.  0 = horizontal, 1 = vertical.

None of this changes in NES 2.0. KH discovered that very few existing ROMs have a trainer, and most of these aren't real trainers at all but subroutines used by a mapper hack.

Byte 7 (Flags 7)

Later versions of the iNES emulator introduced a second byte of flags.

7       0
---------
NNNN xxPV

N: Upper 4 bits of the mapper number
P: Playchoice 10.  When set, this is a PC-10 game
V: Vs. Unisystem.  When set, this is a Vs. game
x: these bits are not used in iNES.

Early ROM processing tools were not aware of Flags 7 because the earliest emulators ignored it. For example, one tool put 0x44 (ASCII for 'D', the first character of "DiskDude!") here. This confuses newer emulators, which combine the nibbles from Flags 6 and Flags 7 to form an incorrect mapper number. NES 2.0 redefines the unused bits to always equal binary 10, which happens not to match any of the patterns used by these ROM processing tools:

7       0
---------
NNNN SSPV

N: Upper 4 bits of the mapper number
S: When equal to binary 10, use NES 2.0 rules; otherwise, use other rules.
P: Playchoice 10.  When set, this is a PC-10 game
V: Vs. Unisystem.  When set, this is a Vs. game

That is the "how" of determining whether we are dealing with a valid NES 2.0 file. Now that that is done, the desired aspects of such a thing need to be considered. Kevin has tested over 4000 ROMs and have dumped at least a thousand more, and reverse engineered probably 60-70 different mappers. This has given him a front row seat into the shortcomings of the original, and a good idea of where additional information is needed.

The problem cases

The new specification needs to clarify five areas:

Vs. Unisystem

The Vs. Unisystem is one of the two Nintendo arcade machine series produced which use "mostly NES/famicom" hardware. These games will run fine on emulators if a little extra things are stored in the header.

Nintendo wanted to make life difficult for arcade operators when it came to copy protection. Three main schemes were devised. (See the "Vs. system byte" description below for a detailed analysis)

Big ROMs

PRG ROM has already surpassed 2 MiB, and CHR ROM has already surpassed 1 MiB, especially on pirate multicarts. So far, the hack has been to set PRG ROM to 00h to indicate 4Mbytes of ROM (since FFh is 16K short of 4Mbytes). And in the case of exceeding the 2Mbyte-8K CHR barrier, ROMs have been allocating the CHR in the PRG space. This can get very messy for an emulator to sort out, especially by 2015 now that pirates are making monstrosities like the CoolBoy 400 in 1 Real Game multicart[1] dumped by TeamEurope, which is 32 MB.[2].

Submappers

See: NES 2.0 submappers

Occasionally, two mappers get one number. Sometimes, an emulator can distinguish them easily: 34 covers both NINA-001 and BNROM, but NINA-001 has CHR ROM, and BNROM has CHR RAM. But other mappers are messier: mapper 83 (two styles of CHR ROM banking), mapper 1 (various ROM/RAM hacks), mapper 16 (EEPROM/WRAM/light pen/etc).

Currently, the only fix for this is to CRC the games and then hack the mapper if the CRC or other hash matches. This of course fails if the game is not in the database, especially newly developed homebrew games.

Mapper number exhaustion

Face it: we're running out. In the early days of iNES, 16 mappers seemed like it would be enough, but they were quickly exhausted. Then 256 mappers seemed like a vast space to work on. But now, we are getting near the end of the line, and running out of mapper numbers. Mr. Horton alone has assigned at least 50 or 60 of them, which is almost a quarter of the total mapper space.

WRAM

Not all carts that support PRG RAM support 8K of it. Some support less, some support more, and some by Bandai even have EEPROM! Heck, some carts even battery backed the stupid CHR RAM. This last one was a very recent find at the time NES 2.0 was first written and goes to show that a workable extension needs to reasonably cover all possible bases.

The proposed solution

Byte 8 (Mapper variant)

7       0
---------
SSSS MMMM

S: Submapper number.  Mappers not using submappers set this to zero.
M: Bits 11-8 of mapper number.

Submappers are used to disambiguate iNES 1 mappers that require multiple incompatible implementations. Most mappers will not use submappers; they set S to 0.

It's not recommended yet as of 2015 to assign mapper numbers greater than 255. There were still a couple dozen existing numbers left in the current iNES mapper space as of 2013. Mapper numbers up to 511 should hold us until they stop making Ice Age films; mapper numbers up to 4095 should hold us until the next literal ice age.

In 2013, there was a proposal on the BBS to break up the expanded mapper space into "planes", much like those of Unicode when it expanded past UCS-2. Each M value would thus correspond to one plane:

Plane 0 (0-255): Basic Multilingual Plane, the current mess
Plane 1 (256-511): Mostly for new homebrew mappers.
Plane 2 (512-767): For new dumps of East Asian games.
Plane 15: Private use area (not for publicly distributed dumps)

Byte 9 (Upper bits of ROM size)

7       0
---------
CCCC PPPP

C: 4 more CHR ROM size bits
P: 4 more PRG ROM size bits

These combine with the existing 8 bits of each to form 12 bits total for the number of PRG and CHR banks... this is enough for 64Mbytes-16K of PRG data and 32Mbytes-8K of CHR data.

Only a few mappers, mostly multicart mappers, support non-power-of-two sizes for PRG and CHR. The behavior of a ROM with a Nintendo MMC and a non-power-of-two ROM size is undefined.

Byte 10 (RAM size)

7       0
---------
pppp PPPP

p: Quantity of PRG RAM which is battery backed (or serial EEPROM, see below)
P: Quantity of PRG RAM which is NOT battery backed

The PRG RAM need not be actual RAM; it may also be EEPROM. Serial EEPROMs are familiar to developers of Game Boy Advance and Nintendo DS emulators. But they're older than that: some mapper 16 (Bandai) games use serial EEPROMs to store the game data, rather than a battery backed SRAM. They most often used the 24C01 (with 128 bytes) or 24C02 (with 256 bytes), but there's no practical limitation on total size. Both ICs use the I²C bus.

Some games on SOROM or ETROM have two PRG RAM chips, one battery-backed and one not. Which chip appears earlier in PRG RAM address space depends on the mapper. For example, SOROM (mapper 1, no CHR ROM, 8192 byte CHR RAM, 8192+8192 byte PRG RAM) puts the battery-backed chip at bank 2 and the other chip at bank 0.

Most discrete logic mappers lacked specific support for PRG RAM. For these mappers, emulators should continue the iNES tradition of extending the stock mappers' functionality in the same way that Family BASIC extended that of mapper 0. A cartridge can have up to 8192 bytes of either battery-backed or non-battery-backed RAM at $6000-$7FFF,[3] decoded with an 74HC20 or 74LS139. But some mappers have registers in $6000-$7FFF and do not define a mapping for PRG RAM or serial EEPROM, such as Jaleco's JF-13. Headers for ROMs using these mappers MUST specify 0 for both PRG RAM sizes.

Bytes 10 and 11 of the header define the size of the RAM segments exponentially using 4-bit values:

value | RAM size in bytes
0 | 0
1 | 128
2 | 256
3 | 512
4 | 1024
5 | 2048
6 | 4096
7 | 8192
8 | 16384
9 | 32768
10 | 65536
11 | 131072
12 | 262144
13 | 524288
14 | 1048576
15 | Reserved; do not use

Sizes that are not a power of two, such as the 5120 byte battery-backed RAM of Taito's X1-017, are rounded up.

Byte 11 (Video RAM Size)

7       0
---------
cccc CCCC

c: Quantity of CHR RAM which is battery backed (yes it exists! see below)
C: Quantity of CHR RAM which is NOT battery backed

The majority of games with no CHR ROM will have $07 (8192 bytes, not battery backed) in this byte. Use of $00 with no CHR ROM implies that the game is wired to map nametable memory in CHR space. The value $00 MUST NOT be used if a mapper isn't defined to allow this.

Battery-backed CHR RAM exists. The RacerMate Challenge II cartridge has 64K of CHR RAM total: 32K is battery backed, and 32K of it is not. They store all the stats and such in it. KH traced out the circuit and couldn't believe it. It probably simplified the routing or power off protection.

For backward compatibility, the battery bit in the original iNES header (byte 6, bit 1) MUST be true if the upper nibble of byte 10 or 11 is nonzero or false otherwise.

Byte 12 (TV system)

Different TV systems have different clock rates, and a game's raster effects and difficulty tuning might expect one or the other.

7       0
---------
xxxx xxBP

P: 0 indicates NTSC mode; 1 is for PAL mode.

NTSC mode
262 lines, NMI on line 241, 3 dots per CPU clock
PAL mode
312 lines, NMI on line 241, 3.2 dots per CPU clock
Dendy PAL mode
312 lines, NMI on line 291, 3 dots per CPU clock, designed for maximum compatibility with NTSC ROMs, but NES 2.0 does not yet indicate that a game is designed for this mode

B: When set, indicates this ROM works on both PAL and NTSC machines. Some of the Codemasters games actually will adjust the game depending on if it detects you running on a PAL or NTSC machine - it adjusts the timing of the game and transposes the music. Not many games would have this B flag set; those that do would be labeled (UE) or the like in GoodNES.

Byte 13 (Vs. hardware)

7       0
---------
MMMM PPPP

This byte is reserved for the Vs. system only.  If this is not
a Vs. system ROM, the value of this byte must be $00, which
signifies RP2C03B (used in PlayChoice, Famicom Titler, and a
few TVs with built-in Famicom) and no Vs.-specific submapper.

P: PPU.  There are 13 Vs. PPUs that can be found on the games:

 0 - RP2C03B     (bog standard RGB palette)
 1 - RP2C03G     (similar pallete to above, might have 1 changed colour)
 2 - RP2C04-0001 (scrambled palette + new colours)
 3 - RP2C04-0002 (same as above, different scrambling)
 4 - RP2C04-0003 (similar to above)
 5 - RP2C04-0004 (similar to above)
 6 - RC2C03B     (bog standard palette, seems identical to RP2C03B)
 7 - RC2C03C     (similar to above, but with 1 changed colour or so)
 8 - RC2C05-01   (all five of these have the normal palette...
 9 - RC2C05-02   (...but with different bits returned on 2002)
10 - RC2C05-03
11 - RC2C05-04
12 - RC2C05-05
13 - not defined (do not use these)
14 - not defined
15 - not defined

KH has a good cross-section of Vs. games and has dumped bit-for-bit
palettes from all thirteen of these PPUs.  The last 5 PPUs (RC2C05)
have the standard NES palette in them, however they return a specific
word in the lower 5 bits of PPUSTATUS ($2002), and the PPUCTRL ($2000)
and PPUMASK ($2001) ports are flipped around (PPUMASK at $2000 and 
PPUCTRL at $2001).

Nocash and MESS report:
 RC2C05-01 (with ID ([2002h] AND ??h)=1Bh)
 RC2C05-02 (with ID ([2002h] AND 3Fh)=3Dh)
 RC2C05-03 (with ID ([2002h] AND 1Fh)=1Ch)
 RC2C05-04 (with ID ([2002h] AND 1Fh)=1Bh)
 and cannot find the 2C05-05


M: Vs. mode:

 0 - Normal- no special mode(s)
 1 - RBI Baseball  (protection hardware at port 5E0xh)
 2 - TKO Boxing    (other protection hardware at port 5E0xh)
 3 - Super Xevious (protection hardware at port 5xxxh)
 4 - ...

Nintendo did a few things to make piracy difficult for arcade operators:

Different PPUs
There are 13 different PPU chips found on Vs. arcade boards.
Different controller pinouts
Some games came with new control panels you had to install with the game. This was pretty basic stuff and just remapped a few of the buttons. (FIXME: which games do use what special control panels?)

Byte 14 and 15 (Reserved)

Reserved, these two bytes must be zero.

Emulator support

BizHawk as of r6313
FCEUX as of r3071
Nintendulator 0.975 Beta
MESS (per BBS post 62428)
no$nes v1.1
PowerMappers v23 for PowerPak
puNES v.0.90

See also

NES 2.0 header for ca65

References

↑ SomeRussianMarioDude's review
↑ CaH4e3's Dumping 2015
↑ possibly a dumb iNES 2.0 header question :-): http://forums.nesdev.com/viewtopic.php?p=77288#p77288

Categories: File formats

NES 2.0 header for ca65

This macro pack for ca65 constructs a 16-byte NES 2.0 header.

;
; NES 2.0 header generator for ca65 (nes2header.inc)
; 
; Copyright 2016 Damian Yerrick
; Copying and distribution of this file, with or without
; modification, are permitted in any medium without royalty provided
; the copyright notice and this notice are preserved in all source
; code copies.  This file is offered as-is, without any warranty.
;

;;
; Puts ceil(log2(sz / 64)) in logsz, which should be
; local to the calling macro.  Used for NES 2 RAM sizes.
.macro _nes2_logsize sz, logsz
  .assert sz >= 0 .and sz <= 1048576, error, "RAM size must be 0 to 1048576"
  .if sz < 1
    logsz = 0
  .elseif sz <= 128
    logsz = 1
  .elseif sz <= 256
    logsz = 2
  .elseif sz <= 512
    logsz = 3
  .elseif sz <= 1024
    logsz = 4
  .elseif sz <= 2048
    logsz = 5
  .elseif sz <= 4096
    logsz = 6
  .elseif sz <= 8192
    logsz = 7
  .elseif sz <= 16384
    logsz = 8
  .elseif sz <= 32768
    logsz = 9
  .elseif sz <= 65536
    logsz = 10
  .elseif sz <= 131072
    logsz = 11
  .elseif sz <= 262144
    logsz = 12
  .elseif sz <= 524288
    logsz = 13
  .else
    logsz = 14
  .endif
.endmacro

;;
; Sets the PRG ROM size to sz bytes. Must be multiple of 16384;
; should be a power of 2.
; example: nes2prg 131072
.macro nes2prg sz
.local sz1
  sz1 = (sz) / 16384
_nes2_prgsize = <sz1
_nes2_prgsizehi = >sz1
.endmacro

;;
; Sets the CHR ROM size to sz bytes. Must be multiple of 8192;
; should be a power of 2.
; example: nes2chr 32768
.macro nes2chr sz
.local sz1
  sz1 = (sz) / 8192
_nes2_chrsize = <sz1
_nes2_chrsizehi = >sz1
.endmacro

;;
; Sets the (not battery-backed) work RAM size in bytes.
; Default is 0.
.macro nes2wram sz
.local logsz
  _nes2_logsize sz, logsz
  _nes2_wramsize = logsz
.endmacro

;;
; Sets the battery-backed work RAM size in bytes.  Default is 0.
.macro nes2bram sz
.local logsz
  _nes2_logsize sz, logsz
  _nes2_bramsize = logsz
.endmacro

;;
; Sets the (not battery-backed) CHR RAM size in bytes.  Default is 0
; if CHR ROM or battery-backed CHR RAM is defined; otherwise 8192.
.macro nes2chrram sz
.local logsz
  _nes2_logsize sz, logsz
  _nes2_chrramsize = logsz
.endmacro

;;
; Sets the battery-backed CHR RAM size in bytes.  Default is 0.
.macro nes2chrbram sz
.local logsz
  _nes2_logsize sz, logsz
  _nes2_chrbramsize = logsz
.endmacro

;;
; Sets the mirroring to one of these values:
; 'H' (horizontal mirroring, vertical arrangement)
; 'V' (vertical mirroring, horizontal arrangement)
; '4' (four-screen VRAM)
.macro nes2mirror mir
.local mi1
  mi1 = mir
  .if mi1 = 'h' .or mi1 = 'H'
    _nes2_mirror = 0
  .elseif mi1 = 'v' .or mi1 = 'V'
    _nes2_mirror = 1
  .elseif mi1 = '4'
    _nes2_mirror = 8
  .else
    .assert 0, error, "Mirroring mode must be 'H', 'V', or '4'"
  .endif
.endmacro

;;
; Sets the mapper (board class) ID.  For example, MMC3 is usually
; mapper 4, but TLSROM is 118 and TQROM is 119.  Some mappers have
; variants.
.macro nes2mapper mapperid, submapper
.local mi1, ms1
  mi1 = mapperid
  .assert mi1 >= 0 .and mi1 < 4096, error, "Mapper must be 0 to 4095"
  .ifnblank submapper
    .assert ms1 >= 0 .and ms1 < 16, error, "Submapper must be 0 to 15"
    ms1 = submapper
  .else
    ms1 = 0
  .endif
  _nes2_mapper6 = (mi1 & $0F) << 4
  _nes2_mapper7 = mi1 & $F0
  _nes2_mapper8 = (mi1 >> 8) | (ms1 << 4)
.endmacro

;;
; Sets the ROM's intended TV system:
; 'N' for NTSC NES/FC/PC10
; 'P' for PAL NES
; 'N','P' for dual compatible, preferring NTSC
; 'P','N' for dual compatible, preferring PAL NES
.macro nes2tv tvsystem, dual_compatible
.local tv1, tv2
  tv1 = tvsystem
  .ifnblank dual_compatible
    tv2 = $02
  .else
    tv2 = $00
  .endif
  .if tv1 = 'n' .or tv1 = 'N'
    _nes2_tvsystem = $00 | tv2
  .elseif mi1 = 'p' .or mi1 = 'P'
    _nes2_tvsystem = $01 | tv2
  .else
    .assert 0, error, "TV system must be 'N' or 'P'"
  .endif
.endmacro

;;
; Writes the header configured by previous nes2 macros.
.macro nes2end
.local battery_bit
  ; Apply defaults
  .ifndef _nes2_chrsize
    nes2chr 0
  .endif
  .ifndef _nes2_mirror
    nes2mirror 'H'
  .endif
  .ifndef _nes2_wramsize
    nes2wram 0
  .endif
  .ifndef _nes2_bramsize
    nes2bram 0
  .endif
  .ifndef _nes2_chrbramsize
    nes2chrbram 0
  .endif
  .ifndef _nes2_chrramsize
    .if _nes2_chrsize .or _nes2_chrsizehi .or _nes2_chrbramsize
      nes2chrram 0
    .else
      nes2chrram 8192
    .endif
  .endif
  .ifndef _nes2_tvsystem
    nes2tv 'N'
  .endif
  .if _nes2_bramsize .or _nes2_chrbramsize
    battery_bit = $02
  .else
    battery_bit = $00
  .endif

  .pushseg
  .segment "INESHDR"
  .byte "NES",$1A
  .byte _nes2_prgsize, _nes2_chrsize
  .byte _nes2_mapper6 | _nes2_mirror | battery_bit
  .byte _nes2_mapper7 | $08  ; not supporting vs/pc10 yet

  .byte _nes2_mapper8
  .byte (_nes2_chrsizehi << 4) | _nes2_prgsizehi
  .byte (_nes2_bramsize << 4) | _nes2_wramsize
  .byte (_nes2_chrbramsize << 4) | _nes2_chrramsize

  .byte _nes2_tvsystem, 0, 0, 0
  .popseg
.endmacro

Linker script requirement

Your linker configuration file will need to have a segment called INESHDR in the first ROM memory area.

MEMORY {
  HEADER: start = 0, size = $0010, type = ro, file = %O, fill=yes, fillval=$00;
  # Other memory area definitions appropriate for your board
}
SEGMENTS {
  INESHDR:  load = HEADER, type = ro, align = $10;
  # Other segment definitions appropriate for your board
}

Examples

A CNROM board with horizontal mirroring (V pad) for NTSC systems:

.include "nes2header.inc"
nes2mapper 3
nes2prg 32768
nes2chr 32768
nes2mirror 'H'
nes2tv 'N'
nes2end

An SLROM board with 128 KiB PRG ROM, 128 KiB CHR ROM, 8 KiB battery-backed WRAM, and PAL-preferred but dual-compatible program:

.include "nes2header.inc"
nes2mapper 1
nes2prg 131072
nes2chr 131072
nes2bram 8192
nes2tv 'P','N'
nes2end

An MMC3 board with 512 KiB PRG ROM, 32 KiB CHR RAM, and NTSC-only program:

.include "nes2header.inc"
nes2mapper 4
nes2prg 524288
nes2chrram 32768
nes2tv 'N'
nes2end

NES 2.0 submappers/Proposals

This page collects proposals for NES 2.0 submappers that are not yet ready for implementation.

Explain what game or ROM is incompatible with existing submappers.
Explain how the proposed submapper should be implemented.
Allow one or more other members of the community to independently verify that both 1 and 2 are correct. (We'll perform peer review, commentary, and possible revision/iteration here.)
Allocate and document the new submapper, listing the relevant game/ROM.

When allocating new submappers, please consult kevtris' original proposal before choosing a number. If it is something he already assigned that we have just not adopted yet, use his existing assignment: submappers.txt

If there is no existing game or ROM that requires a submapper, it should not yet be allocated. There is no end to possible variations of hardware, and there is no need to speculate on the future. If you want to work on a project that will require a new mapper, engage the community and/or seek help from others. Do not pre-emptively add a new mapper to the spec until there is something we can run with it. The spec will still be here when you're finished your project.

Contents

1 021, 023, 025: VRC2 / VRC4

1.1 Submapper assignment
1.2 Alternative Submapper Assignment
1.3 021 / 023 / 025: 0
1.4 021 / 023 / 025: 1, 3, 8, 9, 10, 14 VRC4
1.5 023: 8 VRC4f
1.6 023: 15 VRC2b
1.7 025: 15 VRC2c

2 005: MMC5
3 019: Namco 129 and 163
4 083: Cony

4.1 083: 0
4.2 083: 1
4.3 083: 2

5 iNES Mapper 185
6 References

021, 023, 025: VRC2 / VRC4

these submappers are fully specified, allocation is pending the existence of test ROMs

additional review and consensus for the allocation numbering scheme is requested

These three mappers collect various configurations of VRC2 and VRC4 boards.

VRC2 is mostly a subset of VRC4, with differences including:

VRC2 has a single bit of memory mapped at $6000-6FFF that the VRC4 does not[1], though it is redundant if WRAM is used.
VRC4 has an interrupt device that VRC2 does not.

Additionally, different boards connect the address lines for the registers in various arrangements. The three iNES mappers 21, 23, and 25 each combine multiple boards whose addresses overlap. This is enough for game compatibility, but it creates an ugly combination that does not accurately describe the original hardware of either board.

Submapper assignment

Konami's VRC4 mapper has five known variations (and one additional pirate variation) of how the board connects low CPU address lines among A7-A0 to the port select lines of the mapper. These are spread across three mappers: two for 21, two for 25, and one for 23. There are theoretically 8 * 7 = 56 ways to wire these, but in all five extant possibilities, two adjacent address lines are used: A2 and A1, A0 and A1, A7 and A6, A2 and A3, and A3 and A2. All 14 ways to pick two subsequent integers easily fit in a submapper number:

3210
||||
|+++- Which address line corresponds is wired to the A1 in the VRC4a
+---- 0: Use next lower address line for VRC4a A2; 1: use next higher line

The values 0 (A0 and next lower) and 15 (A7 and next higher) are impossible. 15 is used to indicate VRC2 for the two mappers that it shares with VRC4.

The VRC4 article describes the ports by mapping them to the variant called "VRC4a" on that page, which uses A2 and A1, putting the four VRC IRQ ports (IRQ Latch low, IRQ Latch high, IRQ Control, and IRQ Acknowledge) at $F000, $F002, $F004, and $F006.

Nickname | A2 | A1 | Registers | iNES mapper | NES 2.0 submapper
VRC4a | A2 | A1 | $x000, $x002, $x004, $x006 | 21 | 9
VRC4b | A0 | A1 | $x000, $x002, $x001, $x003 | 25 | 1
VRC4c | A7 | A6 | $x000, $x040, $x080, $x0C0 | 21 | 14
VRC4d | A2 | A3 | $x000, $x008, $x004, $x00C | 25 | 3
VRC4e | A3 | A2 | $x000, $x004, $x008, $x00C | 23 | 10
VRC4f | A1 | A0 | $x000, $x001, $x002, $x003 | 23 | 8

There are three variations of the VRC2 boards:

Nickname | A2 | A1 | Registers | iNES mapper | NES 2.0 submapper
VRC2a* | A1 | A0 | $x000, $x002, $x001, $x003 | 22 | 0
VRC2b | A0 | A1 | $x000, $x001, $x002, $x003 | 23 | 15
VRC2c | A1 | A0 | $x000, $x002, $x001, $x003 | 25 | 15

* Note that VRC2a is exclusively assigned to mapper 22, because it has an CHR bank select implementation that is incompatible with the others.

Alternative Submapper Assignment

Each of the 3 mappers represents only 2 addressing schemes. Any new addressing schemes are not backward compatible with iNES anyway so don't need their own submapper numbers. A newly discovered board would be a new mapper, not a submapper. There's no need to make space for future boards, the only potential variants for existing boards is VRC2 vs VRC4.

I would instead propose:

021: 1 VRC4a (A2, A1)
021: 2 VRC4c (A7, A6)
021: 3 unseen VRC2 (A2, A1)
021: 4 unseen VRC2 (A7, A6)
023: 1 VRC4f (A1, A0)
023: 2 VRC4e (A3, A2)
023: 3 VRC2b (A1, A0)
023: 4 unseen VRC2 (A3, A2)
025: 1 VRC4b (A0, A1)
025: 2 VRC4d (A2, A3)
025: 3 VRC2c (A0, A1)
025: 4 unseen VRC2 (A2, A3)

This covers all known variants, and any potential undiscovered VRC2 variants that could fit the existing iNES mappers.

021 / 023 / 025: 0

The default implementation acts as a VRC4 (mostly compatible superset of VRC2), and responds to register writes in one or more configurations simultaneously (supporting both boards at once).

021 / 023 / 025: 1, 3, 8, 9, 10, 14 VRC4

These allocations each request a single specific addressing scheme for VRC4, rather than the combined version used by submapper 0.

Test ROMs:

021: 9 VRC4a - please create a test ROM before allocating this submapper
025: 1 VRC4b - please create a test ROM before allocating this submapper
021: 14 VRC4c - please create a test ROM before allocating this submapper
025: 3 VRC4d - please create a test ROM before allocating this submapper
023: 10 VRC4e - please create a test ROM before allocating this submapper
023: 8 VRC4f - please create a test ROM before allocating this submapper

023: 8 VRC4f

Some second-source VRC4 clones used a memory layout that was identical to the VRC2b (the simplest contiguous in-order interpretation: 0,1,2,3). This was used in World Hero.

Test ROM:

please create a test ROM before allocating this submapper

023: 15 VRC2b

Some games rely on a single bit of memory mapped in the region from $6000-$6FFF on VRC2. These games were previously supported with submapper 0 by implementing WRAM in this region (despite these games not having WRAM). Additionally, VRC2 does not implement VRC4's interrupts. This board was used in Contra (J) and Ganbare Goemon 2.

Test ROM:

please create a test ROM before allocating this submapper

025: 15 VRC2c

Ganbare Goemon Gaiden: Keita Ougon Kiseru uses VRC2c. It is compatible with submapper 0, but VRC4 has an additional interrupt capability (unused by this game).

Test ROM:

please create a test ROM before allocating this submapper

005: MMC5

Status: Wishlist

Vertical split mode:
0: SL (all known hardware)
1: CL

If only one kind (battery or non-battery) of PRG-RAM present:
0: PRG-RAM is contiguous (EKROM, EWROM)
2: PRG-RAM is not contiguous; is split in half across two chips

If both kinds of PRG-RAM present:
0: Chip 0 is battery-backed (ETROM (note: verify this))
2: Chip 1 is battery-backed

Pulse waves volume:
0: R1 is 6.8kΩ (as in all games that use expansion audio)
4: R1 is 15kΩ (the nominal value of this resistor)

It is safe to leave the submapper number at 0 for all known games.

019: Namco 129 and 163

Status: Problem outline

Mapper 19 designates the Namco 129 and 163, which supports expansion sound, IRQs, and ROM nametables.

Different 163-using PCBs used a different resistor to change the volume of the expansion audio relative to the internal 2A03 audio. It is unclear if this variation warrants a submapper.

KH allocated a submapper specifically for the N163-using game Mindseeker. It is not known what is different about this game.

Tentative suggestion:
Mapper 19:
1: N163, expansion audio unused (mixing resistor: 0Ω)
2: N163, mixing resistor: 4.7kΩ
3: N163, mixing resistor: 10kΩ
4: N163, mixing resistor: 15kΩ
9: N129. Expansion audio is known buggy relative to N163, but other differences are not known.

Source: KH's submappers

083: Cony

There's actually three different versions of the hardware, all assigned to the same mapper.

Unfortunately, we have no idea which is which.

Here's Kevtris's assignments:

083: 0

"Bog-standard Cony mapper. 1K CHR ROM banks, no WRAM."

083: 1

"Same, but with 2K CHR ROM banks instead."

083: 2

"This is the standard Cony mapper with the following changes:

1K CHR ROM banks (like 83.0)

a 4 bit 256K CHR/PRG bank select register:

B000h: bits 6 and 7 select the 256K superbank

1 byte of RAM at 5103h (stores the last game played) Game will not start without this RAM byte.

WRAM at 6000-7FFFh. WRAM is banked with the PRG/CHR superbank. This gives a total of 32K. It is battery backed.

iNES Mapper 185

Status: Draft

A few NROM-like games were released on CNROM boards where all four bits of the latch were solely used as an anti-piracy measure. While a documented heuristic exists for which values were used, we tentatively suggest that the submapper here indicate the value to be written to the latch for normal operation (submapper = (latch&0x30)/4+(latch&3))

3210  
||||
|||+- Bit 0 (bank number)
||+-- Bit 1 (bank number)
|+--- Bit 4 (diode config)
+---- Bit 5 (diode config)

In the case that any of the bits are "don't care", use 0.

On second thought, lidnariq would be happier with

3210
xxCC
||||
|||+- Bit 0 (bank number)
||+-- Bit 1 (bank number)
++--- Always "01", so that submapper 0 (use heuristic) doesn't collide with "write 0 for correct operation"

References

↑ http://forums.nesdev.com/viewtopic.php?t=8274 VRC2 memory bit at $6000-$6FFF

NESdev IRC channel

Contents

1 Connecting
2 Topic
3 Conduct
4 Bot

Connecting

Our IRC channel is located on the EFnet network. A list of servers is available.

Find yourself an IRC client and drop by to #nesdev for assistance with your code or hardware related inquiries or interests.

Occasionally, EFnet's round-robin DNS may put you on a server that has blocked (G-lined or K-lined) your IP address for some server-specific reason, or it might have the annoying "/QUOTE PONG :cookie" CAPTCHA. You may want to connect to a specific server instead, such as the following:

North America: irc.servercentral.net, irc.blessed.net, irc.prison.net, irc.igs.ca
Europe: irc.efnet.ch, efnet.xs4all.nl, irc.swepipe.se, irc.efnet.ru
Middle East: irc.inter.net.il
Africa: irc.ac.za

Tip: Some IRC servers won't K-line you if you get ident (RFC1413/931) working. Ident is a protocol to associate an IRC connection to a specific user name/account on a computer. Many IRC clients (ex. mIRC) have built-in ident servers that run on TCP port 113; make sure that's enabled. If you have a firewall or NAT router, these will probably block ident requests until you tell your firewall/router to allow them/port forward them. On the router, you can use use port triggering (outbound TCP 6667 -> inbound TCP 113) or set up a static port forward to your computer (TCP port 113). If using a software firewall, allow your IRC client to accept inbound connections to TCP port 113.

Topic

The channel attempts to follow a standard
Voiced (+v) individuals are either friends of operators, respected regulars, or known to have an understanding of the NES/Famicom and its architecture. Not all of these people will be able to answer questions, but questions will eventually get answered.
Code or hardware related questions are better suited for most operators
The operators (or ops, +o) of the channel -- like most channels -- were chosen for specific reasons by other operators; mainly that they are trusted with the authority of managing the channel, keeping the bot (LittleMac) opped, having a basic to advanced understanding of 6502, NES/Famicom architecture, and knowledge of other platforms.
#nesdev is not the official support channel for PowerPak and other RetroZone products, but when its inventor is on (under nick bunnyboy or retrousb), you can bring up your support issues in channel or through a private message.

In summary: #nesdev as a channel exists as a community to casually discuss hardware, software, and NES/Famicom related topics (mainly pertaining to development or hacking). Off-topic conversation is not discouraged, so long as it does not affect any conversation in the channel related to these topics.

Conduct

As a channel we try to stay casual, informative, and helpful.
Users that undesiredly use the help of others as a crutch or talk off-topic much too often will receive negative attention. ...Just because disapproval isn't publicly expressed, doesn't mean it does not exist or matter intensely. So don't be Mr. "I vant to suck your help." TL;DR - people are flexible, within reason.
Please be considerate of the majority of our users that log or lurk until insightful discussion has germinated.
We don't have rigid rules for bannable offenses; operators may do as they please.
#nesdev is not considered a safe for work environment.
As discussions started by voices or ops are capable of running to any which direction; unless moderation is necessary. Please use your own discretion.

Bot

We're on our third bot. "LittleMac" is an Eggdrop bot that maintains user privileges.

To set your password (only necessary after an user account has been added):

/msg LittleMac pass <password>

To identify yourself from a new host:

/msg LittleMac ident <password>

To get ops (if you have +o rights on the bot):

/msg LittleMac op <password>

To gain help:

/msg LittleMac help

Welcome!

Nesdev wiki:Manual of Style/RFC 2119

MUST
SHOULD
MAY | The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as described in RFC 2119. (what's this?)

"RFC 2119: Key words for use in RFCs to Indicate Requirement Levels" is a RFC memorandum published by the Internet Engineering Task Force that describes the standard meanings of modal verbs and some other words used in Internet standards documents. Documents that use RFC 2119 indicate that RFC 2119 applies to a given word by writing the word with all capital letters.

The most common key words are

MUST or MUST NOT
Something is absolutely required.
SHOULD or SHOULD NOT
Something is strongly recommended.
MAY
Something is allowable either way.

Not all pages on this wiki need to indicate requirement levels. Pages that are descriptive rather than prescriptive, that is, those that describe what is rather than what ought to be, need not use this convention. But pages that do indicate requirement levels SHOULD use this convention and SHOULD use the template {{RFC 2119}}, which produces a notice that floats to the right, lest readers confuse these all-capital words with shouting.

Nesdev wiki talk:Manual of Style/RFC 2119

This should be deprecated or deleted

After Bregalad left a comment about the use of MUST, I ended up taking a look at the use of this template across the wiki.

This should not be part of our manual of style for this wiki (do we even have one? this seems to be the only page in this namespace). All of these words have perfectly normal English meanings, and those are the meanings that new users come in expecting. Putting them in ALLCAPS and insisting that they have some specific meaning (which is only obscurely different from their normal English meaning) creates confusion and slows comprehension of the article. An infobox wasting 100 words to try to explain that "MUST" means "must, but pedantically" is counter-productive. The capitalization style of RFC 2119 is jargon used only by a few particular groups of people; the vast majority of users are not familiar with it, and it wastes our time.

I looked through the wiki and found no use of this template that I thought contributed to better understanding of the meaning of the words in question, and I found several cases where MUST was being used incorrectly. I'd recommend deleting this page, though this wiki doesn't seem to have a deletion request process. - Rainwarrior (talk) 11:49, 26 May 2015 (MDT)

Why in hell does typing RFC 2119 automatically create an external link??? - Rainwarrior (talk) 11:51, 26 May 2015 (MDT)

Mediawiki feature(?): http://www.mediawiki.org/wiki/Manual:RFC —Lidnariq (talk) 13:15, 26 May 2015 (MDT)

See RfcKeywords on W3C Wiki. If MUST was being misused, it should be fixed. But just because something can be misused doesn't mean it's useless. For example, look at all the other RFCs that cite this RFC in the same way the {{RFC 2119}} template does; is it useless there? And if it's useless, why is the delusion that it's useful so widespread? Should I reword all uses of all-caps MUST along the lines "Failure to do so causes undefined behavior"? --Tepples (talk) 16:55, 26 May 2015 (MDT)

No, absolutely DO NOT redefine what "MUST" is supposed to mean and try to impose this new personal definition of the word on others. That's my primary issue with this! You're creating nonstandard meanings for words and then expecting others to read some documentation to keep up with you. The word "must" is perfectly fine already; just use English words as they already exist. I don't care if some people have a use for RFC 2119 elsewhere, it's not helping here. - Rainwarrior (talk) 17:30, 26 May 2015 (MDT)

"personal definition"--The IETF is hardly a person creating a personal definition; RFC 2119 is a standard set by the organisation eighteen years ago. (As for tepples creating a "personal definition" he is just suggesting a rephrasing this particular meaning of MUST into the vernacular; not redefining it.) "perfectly normal"? English (well, language in general) is fairly extensively ambiguous. I think it is[/was] useful for distinguishing these particular meanings. The group that uses these...is those creating technical computer document specifications, which we are/do; I find it useful to discriminate advice for complying with the specification from requirements of the specification. Furthermore, not all of our readers are native English speakers. Defining the difference between should and must is a useful thing. (And one doesn't have to click if one doesn't find it necessary to be clarified, meaning no time lost!)(Perhaps better to contend a wide adoption to counter "particular groups of people", than its usefulness? Using it to imply usefulness is an argumentum ad populum.)Myask (talk) 17:43, 26 May 2015 (MDT)

Perhaps more saliently, "If you don't carefully and clearly define the words you use in communications, you will fail to communicate. Standards documents are – first and foremost – about clear communication of an agreement on how to do a thing." http://www.quora.com/Whats-the-story-behind-RFC-2119 Myask (talk) 17:47, 26 May 2015 (MDT)

Sorry, I misread what tepples said. (I thought he was suggesting editing the template to define MUST = otherwise undefined behaviour, which would have been even worse.) I'm saying that we should not encumber our text with unnecessary definitions. I don't disagree with RFC 2119 as a practice on how to personally use these words, but I absolutely disagree with an annoying and intrusive infobox to explain them everywhere they appear, and with UNNECESSARY capitalizations of PARTICULAR words for NO REASON other than they're relevant to some ESSAY you once read about how to USE them. If you think the word "must" is used ambiguosly in an article fix the text to resolve the ambiguity, don't slap ugly formatting an an infobox and a link to some 5000 word essay about how to use these words on it! We don't need to offer definitions for every use of a word, we should present the words clearly so they can be understood in context. - Rainwarrior (talk) 18:02, 26 May 2015 (MDT)

The capitalization is intended to distinguish the RFC 2119 readings from the far less precise dictionary readings. --Tepples (talk) 18:35, 26 May 2015 (MDT)

I wouldn't mind at all if you included this template on talk pages, if you wanted to use it as part of a comment suggest to an editor how it may be helpful to use these words (if some editor were consistently misusing them), but I am very strongly opposed to suggesting to the reader how they are supposed to read them by placing it within articles. When editing you should acknowledge the naive reading of your words, and accomodate that by using them well, not by telling the reader to get with the program and read this essay first. - Rainwarrior (talk) 18:15, 26 May 2015 (MDT)

"The naive reading" of the word bit is "a small portion", not "an individual switch that can be set to a low or high value". --Tepples (talk) 18:35, 26 May 2015 (MDT)

Just, please do not propose an infobox explaining the word "BIT", capitalizing it wherever it is used with a link to a 10 page essay about what it means. - Rainwarrior (talk) 18:51, 26 May 2015 (MDT)

For what it's worth, I'm in agreement with Rainwarrior on this matter. I've no issue with RFC2119 or its purpose, but adding an infobox (or anything else similar in concept) to pages to add nothing more than clarification of what English words mean is, quite literally, excessively pedantic. As someone who has (obviously) written technical documentation for decades, know that pedantry of this sort ends up making the documentation more confusing to readers. (For sake of comparison, the same goes for excessive linking). The purpose of a piece of technical documentation (re: NES/Famicom) is not to reassert dictionary definitions, it's to convey technical details. Leave the job of a dictionary to a dictionary; if there are thoughts/details which are unclear or vague given their wording, simply fix the wording (or provide multiple phrasing, e.g. what I did with the Attribute Table description in nestech.txt). TL;DR: I think what's going on here is ridiculously excessive OCD and catering to it does not help make documentation any clearer. - Koitsu (talk) 18:34, 26 May 2015 (MDT)

Rainwarrior wrote in this edit summary: (and then saying it's a "specification"?) But what is this wiki if not the specification of the Nintendo Entertainment System virtual machine as understood by homebrew developers and emulator developers? --Tepples (talk) 18:35, 26 May 2015 (MDT)

Please stop treating everything I say as some black and white absolute. I think the choice of words was poor on those two edits. It's not wrong to say it's a specification, but I think it was terrible form to say it that way. - Rainwarrior (talk) 18:38, 26 May 2015 (MDT)

There is three reasons to ever use words in all caps:

1) If lowercase is not available. This is clearly not the case in this wiki 2) For acronyms. 3) To indicate that you are shouting loud.

Here the capitalization of MUST looks like an accronym but in context its clear its not, instead it is shouting. I believe that shouting like that and saying THIS MUST NOT BE DONE! NEVER! FORBIDDEN! do not suit a technical documentation style and should be forbidden (no joke) on this wiki. Do not assume the reader is a 3 years old kid who can't think for himself, you don't have to say "Do NOT cross the road!" like you'd shout a small kid (for his own safety), instead, say "if you're going to cross the road, be aware that there is also vehicles on it, and many drivers tends not to respect speed limitations.". Any adult person knowns exactly what this means.

In short, I agree with Rainwarrior. I do not even know what RFC2119 is and I do not care. This is not related to NES development in any way. Bregalad (talk) 03:28, 27 May 2015 (MDT)

I do not agree. RFC 2119 is good in many cases. (However, that doesn't mean it should be used everywhere.) --Zzo38 (talk) 14:55, 28 May 2015 (MDT)

Are you disagreeing with the idea that we shouldn't stick this template all over the articles and capitalize MUST and SHOULD, or are you just stating your approval of RFC-2119's definitions of must and should? (I have no problem with it as a suggested guideline for editors on how to use the words; it's the template and capitalization that I object to.) - Rainwarrior (talk) 15:43, 28 May 2015 (MDT)

You certainly shouldn't use it in all articles, although in cases where you should use RFC2119 then it probably makes sense to capitalize it which would probably make it clear to people who know RFC2119 even if you don't have the template (although not using the template may make it less clear to those who don't already know RFC2119). I do not mean any as shouting anyways. This is about protocol compatibility (which is why RFC2119 helps, and in turn why using all capitals helps here); it isn't meant to be the law or whatever. Tepples wrote "The capitalization is intended to distinguish the RFC 2119 readings from the far less precise dictionary readings." and this is really how I agree with. --Zzo38 (talk) 01:34, 29 May 2015 (MDT)

What is RFC2119?! I have absolutely no idea. Please explain me. Also the verbs "to must" and "to shall", along with other verbs such as "to can", "to have to", etc... have very precise meanings in English language. We learned them very early when learning the language, too, because when going to a foreign country it is usually important to know what is forbidden or obligatory, and what is just tips or advice. In call cases, I see no reason to capitalize those particular words, this makes absolutely no sense to shout like that at the poor little reader.Bregalad (talk) 01:45, 29 May 2015 (MDT)

There is a really easy way to make "must" precise. All you have to do is add a clause explaining what must is predicated on. "You must buy a ticket if you want to get on the train." The RFC 2119 approach seems to be "You MUST buy a ticket." This implies to me that the reader is beneath you and undeserving of explanation. Actually, reading RFC 2119 again, it continually and clearly explains that it is primarily for work specifications; that is: ordering someone to make something for you. When you say MUST in a specification, the point of RFC 2119 is just to pedantically clarify that it's not an option for the implementer, because a lot of people like to take shortcuts and adjust the specification to fit what is convenient for them. (I'm sure everyone who has been involved in this kind of work has experienced this problem, which is why RFC 2119 is a popular clarification for it.) This kind of relationship is not what the Wiki is. We are not ordering someone to make us an Emulator. We are not hiring someone to build us a cartridge. We are not managing the development of open source software (you may be, personally, but the Wiki isn't). People come to the wiki to learn how to make things for themselves, not for you, and in this kind of situation there is no RFC 2119 "MUST", they don't actually have to do anything you say. Taking this kind of "fall in line and do as I say" approach to the wiki is abrasive, insulting, and completely unnecessary. - Rainwarrior (talk) 10:44, 29 May 2015 (MDT)

I can only speak for myself in this regard, but RFC 2119 reads in the exact same tone as the Tiger Oil Memos to me. It is the tone of a superior addressing a subordinate, as such. - Rainwarrior (talk) 10:54, 29 May 2015 (MDT)

The purpose of a manual (or this wiki) is to instruct people what they MUST do for their program to interact with the NES in well-defined ways. The purpose of the RFC 2119 infobox is to clarify that capital letters is to denote not a shouting tone, but a particular meaning for the modal verbs: that is, to indicate that a MUST is a "you must do this, in order to comply with the specification and produce well-defined, as-documented behavior", but because this meaning is so-often used, being able to drop the "in order to..." modifier-clause and only define it once is useful (Don't Repeat Yourself). The infobox is hardly intrusive. Now, if it floated over everything and followed my scroll, that would be intrusive, and that behavior should be changed, not the inclusion of the infobox. Incidentally, RFC 2199 itself...is indeed a memo for the IETF instructing people how to write their specification requirement levels consistently. Myask (talk) 14:56, 29 May 2015 (MDT)

I agree with tepples. While I agree that nobody forces you to follow the specification, but if you don't, then it is not going to be correct and it is not guaranteed to work! (Maybe in some cases it might work, but you should follow an agreed-on protocol/API/format/whatever if you want to properly claim support for such things.) (For example: The program MUST wait for the PPU to be ready before expecting it to work; however you can still write some registers before then but they aren't guaranteed to do anything (but still might); some of my own programs do try to disable NMI immediately upon reset; if the register write fails, then it is guaranteed that NMI is already disabled anyways so it doesn't matter. An implementation of the PPU MAY require the game program to wait in this way.) --Zzo38 (talk) 12:53, 29 May 2015 (MDT)

NINA-001

NINA-001 is a particular third-party cartridge board used by American Video Entertainment. The iNES format assigns mapper 34 to this board (as well as BxROM).

Contents

1 Overview
2 Banks
3 Registers

3.1 PRG bank select ($7FFD)
3.2 CHR bank select 0 ($7FFE)
3.3 CHR bank select 1 ($7FFF)

4 Hardware
5 Variants

Overview

PRG ROM size: 64 KB
PRG ROM bank size: 32 KB
PRG RAM: 8 KB, not battery backed [1]
CHR ROM capacity: 64 KB ROM
CHR bank size: 4 KB
Nametable mirroring: hardwired to horizontal mirroring
Subject to bus conflicts: No

Banks

CPU $8000-$FFFF: 32 KB switchable PRG ROM bank
PPU $0000-$0FFF: 4 KB switchable CHR ROM bank
PPU $1000-$1FFF: 4 KB switchable CHR ROM bank

Registers

PRG bank select ($7FFD)

7  bit  0
---- ----
xxxx xxxP
        |
        +- Select 32 KB PRG ROM bank for CPU $8000-$FFFF

CHR bank select 0 ($7FFE)

7  bit  0
---- ----
xxxx CCCC
     ||||
     ++++- Select 4 KB CHR ROM bank for PPU $0000-$0FFF

CHR bank select 1 ($7FFF)

7  bit  0
---- ----
xxxx CCCC
     ||||
     ++++- Select 4 KB CHR ROM bank for PPU $1000-$1FFF

Hardware

The NINA-001 board contains a 74LS133 (13-input NAND gate), 74LS74 (dual D flip-flop), 74HCT139 (dual 1-4 decoder), 74LS00 (quad 2-input NAND gate), two 74HCT173s (4-bit tristate D flip-flop), as well as a microcontroller labelled NINA to act as a CIC defeat mechanism. These 4 registers reside "on top" of PRG RAM: each write to the register goes both to the register and to the RAM location at the same address. Thus, reading the register's address returns the last value written to the RAM, which is also the last value written to the register.

One 2-NAND and one half of the 74'139 together generate /RAMSEL. Another 2-NAND inverts that to form +RAMSEL. A third 2-NAND inverts R/W to produce +WR. The 13-NAND combines +RAMSEL, +WR, and A12…A2 to generate /REGSEL. The other half of the 74'139 uses /REGSEL, A1, and A0 to generate the latching signals for the three flip-flops.

The final 2-NAND inverts PPU A12. PPU A12 and PPU /A12 are fed to the two 74'173s /OE inputs, implementing a simple quad 1-of-2 multiplexer.

This hardware has a trivial oversize definition that supports 8 MiB PRG and 1 MiB CHR, made by replacing the three flip-flops with 74'374s.

Variants

The iNES mapper used to implement this mapper also includes a writable register at $8000-$FFFF for emulation of the BxROM boardset which has caused many headaches for NES emulator authors. Emulator developers should consider switching between NINA-001 emulation and BxROM emulation based on the amount of CHR (≥ 16KiB implies NINA-001; ≤ 8KiB implies BNROM).

Categories: Discrete logic mappers

Nintendo header

About 33% of licensed Nintendo NES games have an header present at their last bank, at addresses $ffe0-$fff9, right before the interrupt vectors.

The info in them is frequently incomplete and/or inaccurate. When info on a particular filed is not present, a byte $00 or $ff is used for padding

$ffe0-$ffef : Name of the game, in ASCII, zero terminated (sometimes the name is abbreviated or replaced by Nintendo's code). ASCII codes 20h-5Ah allowed. Supposed to be right-justified.
$fff0-$fff1 : PRG checksum (either the last 16k bank, or the whole PRG-ROM). Clamped sum of all bytes, excluding the two checksum bytes.
$fff2-$fff3 : CHR checksum. 0x00 if RAM
$fff4 : Data sizes. Values: 0 = 8 KiB or 64 KiB based on board type, 1 = 16 KiB, 2 = 32 KiB, 3 = 128 KiB, 4 = 256 KiB, 5 = 512 KiB

D7-D4: PRG size
D3: 0 = CHR ROM, 1 = CHR RAM
D2-D0: CHR size

$fff5 : Board Type.

D7: 0 = Horizontal nametable arrangement, 1 = Vertical arrangement (inverse of iNES mirroring bit)
D6-D0: 0 = NROM, 1 = CNROM, 2 = UNROM/AOROM, 3 = GNROM, 4 = MMC (any).

$fff6 : Title encoding : 0 = No title entered, 1 = ASCII, 2 = Another encoding
$fff7 : Valid Title Length - 1. 0 if no title entered.
$fff8 : Maker's code, the same used for the FDS, GB, GBC and SNES headers : 1 = Nintendo, 2-254 = everyone else. 255 must be reserved.
$fff9 : Header Validation Byte. 8-bit checksum of FFF2-FFF9h should = 0

NROM-368

NROM-368 is a name for an extension to all mappers incapable of banking PRG, such as NROM, CNROM, CPROM, Sunsoft 1, and CHR-less, allowing 46 KiB of linearly addressed ROM instead of 32 KiB. The name comes from the naming scheme for Nintendo's NROM boards, as 368 kilobits of PRG ROM are addressable. Its original intent was to provide more space for a game written in C, as cc65 tends not to be good at optimizing for space.

Format

The PRG ROM is 47104 bytes in size. Due to constraints of the iNES format, it is padded at the beginning with 2048 bytes of ignored data so that it is an even multiple of 16384 bytes; the rest is loaded in order into $4800-$7FFF, $8000-$BFFF, and $C000-$FFFF.

So an iNES or NES 2.0 image would look like this:

16 bytes: Header. PRG ROM size must be 3. Trainer and battery are forbidden; NES 2.0 PRG RAM size must be 0.
2048 bytes: Ignored.
47104 bytes: PRG ROM mapped to $4800-$FFFF.
8192×n bytes: CHR ROM mapped to PPU $0000-$1FFF.

The UNIF encapsulation should ignore all padding and just have PRG0 be exactly 47104 bytes.

Hardware

Just as the addition of PRG RAM and bus conflict avoidance to these mappers takes one chip to decode, the addition of $4800-$7FFF also takes one chip that uses PRG /CE, M2, and A14-A11 to construct an enable signal for the PRG ROM. This is a 74HC85 comparator.

TO DO: Once the circuit is tested on a real PCB, details of how to wire up the '85 will be given here.

A14 through A0 go to the PRG ROM as is, and PRG /CE goes to A15. When burning the EPROM, you have to rearrange the 16 KiB segments of the PRG ROM into the order 1, 2, 0, 0, as PRG /CE is inverted compared to A15.

References

BBS topic, including wiring instructions

Categories: Mappers using $4020-$5FFF

NSF

The NES Sound Format (.nsf) is used for storing and playing music from the NES and related systems. It is similar to the PSID file format for C64 music/sound, where one rips the music/sound code from an NES game and prepends a small header to the data. An NSF player puts the music code into memory at the proper place, based on the header, prepares sound hardware, then runs it to make music. An NSF can be played on NES/Famicom hardware or in an emulator (NSF player or NES emulator).

There are two extensions of the NSF format:

NSFe - Allows a playlist with track titles and times, as well as other metadata.
NSF2 - A proposed extension to the NSF format. Not yet finalized.

Contents

1 Header Overview
2 Loading a tune into RAM

2.1 Bank Switching

2.1.1 FDS Bankswitching
2.1.2 Example

3 Initializing a tune
4 Playing a tune
5 Sound Chip Support

5.1 APU
5.2 VRCVI
5.3 VRCVII
5.4 FDS Sound
5.5 MMC5 Sound
5.6 Namco 163 Sound
5.7 Sunsoft 5B Sound
5.8 Multi-chip tunes

6 Caveats
7 Summary of Addresses
8 Pseudo-IRQ Technique
9 See also
10 References

Header Overview

offset  # of bytes   Function
----------------------------
$000    5   STRING  'N','E','S','M',$1A (denotes an NES sound format file)
$005    1   BYTE    Version number (currently $01)
$006    1   BYTE    Total songs   (1=1 song, 2=2 songs, etc)
$007    1   BYTE    Starting song (1=1st song, 2=2nd song, etc)
$008    2   WORD    (lo, hi) load address of data ($8000-FFFF)
$00A    2   WORD    (lo, hi) init address of data ($8000-FFFF)
$00C    2   WORD    (lo, hi) play address of data ($8000-FFFF)
$00E    32  STRING  The name of the song, null terminated
$02E    32  STRING  The artist, if known, null terminated
$04E    32  STRING  The copyright holder, null terminated
$06E    2   WORD    (lo, hi) Play speed, in 1/1000000th sec ticks, NTSC (see text)
$070    8   BYTE    Bankswitch init values (see text, and FDS section)
$078    2   WORD    (lo, hi) Play speed, in 1/1000000th sec ticks, PAL (see text)
$07A    1   BYTE    PAL/NTSC bits
                bit 0: if clear, this is an NTSC tune
                bit 0: if set, this is a PAL tune
                bit 1: if set, this is a dual PAL/NTSC tune
                bits 2-7: not used. they *must* be 0
$07B    1   BYTE    Extra Sound Chip Support
                bit 0: if set, this song uses VRC6 audio
                bit 1: if set, this song uses VRC7 audio
                bit 2: if set, this song uses FDS audio
                bit 3: if set, this song uses MMC5 audio
                bit 4: if set, this song uses Namco 163 audio
                bit 5: if set, this song uses Sunsoft 5B audio
                bits 6,7: future expansion: they *must* be 0
$07C    4   ----    4 extra bytes for expansion (must be $00)
$080    nnn ----    The music program/data follows until end of file

Loading a tune into RAM

If file offsets $070 to $077 have $00 in them, then bank switching is not used. Data should be read from the file beginning at $080 and loaded contiguously into the 6502 address space beginning at the load address until the end of file is reached.

Some FDS NSFs use a load address below $8000 to fill in the $6000-7FFF range. It is recommended to use bankswitching to accomplish this instead, because it is not universally supported.

Bank Switching

If any of the bytes from $070 to $077 in the file header are nonzero then bank switching is used. In this case, take the logical AND of the load address with $0FFF, and the result specifies the number of bytes of padding at the start of the ROM image. The ROM image should consist of a contiguous set of 4k banks, read directly from the NSF file beginning at $080 after inserting the requested number of pad bytes. If the file does not have enough data to fill the last bank completely, it may be padded out.

The 6502's address space is divided into 8 4k bank switchable blocks. For each block the current bank is controlled by writing the bank number to at corresponding register at $5FF8 through $5FFF. The initial bank assignment is determined by bytes $070 through $077 in the file.

NSF    Address      Register
====   ==========   ========
$070   $8000-8FFF   $5FF8
$071   $9000-9FFF   $5FF9
$072   $A000-AFFF   $5FFA
$073   $B000-BFFF   $5FFB
$074   $C000-CFFF   $5FFC
$075   $D000-DFFF   $5FFD
$076   $E000-EFFF   $5FFE
$077   $F000-FFFF   $5FFF

The initial bank assignment should be done before any call to the INIT routine. Once the ROM image has been built from the NSF file, this can be set up simply by writing the 8 values from the file header $070-077 to the corresponding registers $5FF8-$5FFF.

If the INIT routine needs to change the bank assignments based on the selected song, it may do so by writing the bank control registers.

FDS Bankswitching

If the FDS expansion is enabled, bank switching operates slightly differently. Two additional registers at $5FF6 and $5FF7 control the banks $6000-6FFF and $7000-7FFF respectively, and the initial load values at $076 and $077 now specify the banks used for $6000-7FFF as well as $E000-FFFF (these regions will both be set up to use the same banks before INIT is called).

Because the FDS has a RAM area at $8000-DFFF for the disk image to be loaded to, that means this area is writable when the FDS expansion is enabled. Some NSF player implementations will treat this like bankswitched RAM, and some players will treat an FDS bank switch operation as a copy into RAM. Hardware players are more likely to use bankswitched RAM.

This has a number of caveats:

Writes may be mirrored if the same bank is used in multiple places. Care should be taken to avoid accidental overwrites when the same bank appears more than once in the bankswitch table. In particular, unique banks should be used for memory regions that must be written to.

Since the FDS itself was incapable of mirrored writes like this and many players will not have them, mirrored writes should not intentionally be used to store the same data in two memory locations. It is a side effect, not a supported feature.

Writes to the area may or may not persist in the bank written to if it is switched out and then switched back in. This is another side effect that should be accounted for, but not relied upon.

Writes may or may not persist between songs, depending on whether the NSF player reloads the NSF image when the song is changed. Hardware players are not likely to reload, but software players may.

See also the notes on multi-chip tunes below.

Example

METROID.NSF will be used for the following explanation.

The file is set up like so:  (starting at $070 in the file)

$070: 05 05 05 05 05 05 05 05
$078: 00 00 00 00 00 00 00 00
$080: ... music data goes here...

Since $070-$077 are something other than $00, this NSF is using bank switching. The load address given is $8000. The load address AND $0FFF specifies 0 bytes of padding, so we set up our ROM image with contiguous data starting from $080 in the file.

This NSF has 6 4k banks in it, numbered 0 through 5. It specifies that each of the 8 memory regions should be switched to bank 5, which begins at $05 * $1000 bytes in the ROM image.

Initializing a tune

The desired song number is loaded into the accumulator register A, and the X register is set to specify specify PAL (X=1) or NTSC (X=0).

Valid song numbers are 0 to one less than the number of songs (specified at $006 in the header). The first selected song is in the header at $007. The NSF player should display to the user song numbers from 1 up to and including the number of songs, and these should correspond to the same number - 1 loaded into register A. Note that when choosing the first song from the value in $007, subtract 1 from it before loading that value into register A.

Write $00 to all RAM at $0000-$07FF and $6000-$7FFF.
Initialize the sound registers by writing $00 to $4000-$4013, $0F to $4015.
Initialize the frame counter to 4-step mode ($40 to $4017).
If the tune is bank switched, load the bank values from $070-$077 into $5FF8-$5FFF.
Set the A register for the desired song.
Set the X register for PAL or NTSC.
Call the music INIT routine.

The INIT routine MUST finish with an RTS instruction before music playback will begin. At this point, the NSF player will begin executing the PLAY routine at the specified interval.

If this is a single standard tune (PAL or NTSC but not both) the INIT routine MAY ignore the X register. Otherwise, it SHOULD use this value to determine how to set pitches and tempo for the appropriate platform.

The use of the $4017 register is not well supported by existing NSF players. The NSF should not normally clear bit 6 (the IRQ disable bit), though there are exceptions to this rule.

Playing a tune

Once the tune has been initialized, it can now be played. To do this, simply call the routine at the PLAY address at the rate determined by the file header at $06E-06F (NTSC) or $078-079 (PAL).

The playback rate is determined by this formula:

        1000000                  1000000
rate = ---------       period = ---------
        period                    speed

Where period is the value you place at $06E-$06F in the file, and rate is how often the PLAY routine should be called in Hz.

The following playback rates are common:

60.002 Hz (recommended by the original NSF specification, close to APU timer IRQ rate): 16666 ($411A)
60.099 Hz (actual NTSC NES frame rate): 16639 ($40FF)
50.007 Hz (suggested PAL NES frame rate): 19997 ($4E1D)

Nonstandard rates may be difficult for hardware players. If the rate is much faster the PLAY routine may not be short enough to execute in the specified amount of time. Additionally, an NES player will usually require mapper hardware to create an IRQ to execute the PLAY routine at the required rate.

The PLAY routine will be called at the specified interval. If the X register passed to INIT was 1 (PAL), it will be called at the rate specified by $078-079, and if 0 (NTSC), it will use the rate at $06E-06F.

A PLAY routine should normally finish with an RTS instruction, but is not required to do so. A non-returning PLAY will cause problems for NSF players that use the same CPU to control the user interface and to run the NSF, such as NSF players that run on an NES. It is strongly recommended to return every few frames if at all possible, such as when no PCM is playing. If PLAY takes longer to finish than the specified interval, that interval may be skipped and PLAY may not be called again until the next one.

Some popular modern NSF engines use a non-returning PLAY to implement an output stream of PCM sound (e.g. SuperNSF, MUSE, Deflemask), and this can also be combined with a Pseudo-IRQ technique.

Sound Chip Support

Byte $07B of the file stores the sound chip flags. If a particular flag is set, those sound registers should be enabled. If the flag is clear, then those registers should be disabled. All I/O registers within $8000-FFFF are write only and must not disrupt music code that happens to be stored there. Some audio register addresses have mirrors in their original hardware mappers, but NSF code should use only the lowest address for each register, listed here.

APU

Uses registers $4000-4013, and $4015. See APU for more information.
$4015 is set to 0F on reset by most players. It is better if the NSF does not assume this and initializes this register itself, but there are several existing NSF files that require it (Battletoads, Castlevania and Gremlins 2 are examples).
The APU interrupts that can be generated via $4015 and $4017 are not supported by the NSF format, which reserves IRQ for the player's internal use.
$4017 is not consistently supported across NSF players.

VRCVI

Uses registers $9000-9003, $A000-A002, and $B000-B002, write only. See VRC6 Audio for more information.
The A0 and A1 lines are flipped on a few games. If you rip the music and it sounds all funny, flip around the xxx1 and xxx2 register pairs. (i.e. 9001 and 9002) Esper2 and Madara will need this change, while Castlevania 3j will not.

VRCVII

Uses registers $9010 and $9030, write only. See VRC7 Audio for more information.

FDS Sound

Uses registers from $4040 through $4092. See FDS Audio for more information.

Notes:

$6000-DFFF is assumed to be RAM, since $6000-DFFF is RAM on the FDS. $E000-FFFF is usually not included in FDS games because it is the BIOS ROM. However, it can be used on FDS rips to help the ripper (for modified PLAY/INIT addresses).
Bank switching is different if FDS is enabled. $5FF6 and $5FF7 control banks at $6000-6FFF and $7000-7FFF, and the NSF header $076-$077 initialized both $6000-7FFF and $E000-FFFF. See above.

MMC5 Sound

Uses registers $5000-5015, write only as well as $5205 and $5206, and $5C00-5FF5. see MMC5 Audio for more information.

Notes:

$5205 and $5206 are a hardware 8 * 8 multiplier. The idea being you write your two bytes to be multiplied into 5205 and 5206 and after doing so, you read the result back out.
$5C00-5FF5 should be RAM to emulate EXRAM while in MMC5 mode.

Namco 163 Sound

Uses registers $4800 and $F800. See Namco 163 audio for more information.

Sunsoft 5B Sound

Audio in the Sunsoft 5B mapper, a variant of the FME-7, uses registers $C000 and $E000. See Sunsoft audio.
Many players do not implement the noise or envelope capabilities of the 5B, as they were not used in the only 5B game, Gimmick.

Multi-chip tunes

Multiple expansion chips can be used at the same time, but because this was not something that was ever supported by an original Famicom games, actual practice with multi-expansion NSF varies.

Some mappers mirror their audio registers at addresses that would conflict. Many NSF players only support the lowest address, which avoids these conflicts, but the following conflicts may need resolution in an attempted hardware multi-chip implementation:

N163's address port $F800 overlaps a mirror of Sunsoft 5B's data port $E000. This can be avoided by setting Sunsoft 5B's address port $C000 to $0E or $0F (unused internal registers) before writing to the N163.
VRC6 and VRC7 have a conflict at ports $9010 and $9030, where the VRC6's pulse 1 control port is mirrored.

Additionally, NSFs using FDS sound make the normally read-only area from $8000-$DFFF writable. This may cause corruption of these areas when writing to VRC6, VRC7, or 5B audio registers. The safest way to avoid this is to make sure your code and data do not fall within these addresses, so that you may safely write to them. NSF player implementations may wish to disable memory writes at these addresses to avoid the conflict.

Caveats

The starting song number and maximum song numbers start counting at 1, while the INIT address of the tune starts counting at 0. Remember to pass the desired song number minus 1 to the INIT routine.
The NTSC speed word is used only for NTSC tunes and dual PAL/NTSC tunes. The PAL speed word is used only for PAL tunes and dual PAL/NTSC tunes.
If bit 1 of the PAL/NTSC is set, indicating a dual PAL/NTSC NSF, bit 0 may be interpreted as a preference for PAL or NTSC. Most players do not support this, however, and some older players may have problems if bit 0 is set.
The length of the text in the name, artist, and copyright fields must be 31 characters or less. There has to be at least a single NULL byte ($00) after the text, between fields.
If a field is not known (name, artist, copyright) then the field must contain the string "<?>" (without quotes).
There should be 8K of RAM present at $6000-7FFF. MMC5 tunes need RAM at $5C00-5FF7 to emulate its $EXRAM. $8000-FFFF should be read-only (not writable) after a tune has loaded. The only time this area should be writable is if an FDS tune is being played.
Do not assume the state of anything on entry to the INIT routine except A and X. Y can be anything, as can the flags.
Do not assume the state of anything on entry to the PLAY routine. Flags, X, A, and Y could be at any state.
The stack sits at $01FF and grows down. The precise position of the stack on INIT or PLAY is not guaranteed, as the NSF player may need to use the top area of the stack for its own internal purpose. Make sure the tune does not attempt to modify $01F0-01FF directly. (Armed Dragon Villigust did, and was relocated to 2xx for its NSF.)
The NSF should not initialize the stack pointer in INIT or PLAY. These subroutines are called from the player; some software emulators may not have a problem with this, but it will almost certainly cause an error on a hardware player. It is the player's job to initialize the stack pointer, and some hardware players (e.g. PowerPak) will place their own variables on the stack.
RAM should be addressed from $0000-07FF, and should not expect mirror addresses to work. If the tune writes outside this range, e.g. $1400 it should be relocated. (Terminator 3 did this and was relocated to 04xx for NSF.)
The vector table at $FFFA-FFFF should not be filled with code or data by the NSF. These can be overridden by hardware NSF players.
Instructions which modify the stack, PLP, PHP, and TXS must be used with great care, as a player may need to rely on being able to store data at the end of the stack. An NSF should use the stack pointer given; the stack past this pointer should remain intact, as it may be needed by the player.
Instructions CLI, SEI, and BRK are problematic, and should usually be avoided. The NSF itself should generally not attempt to interfere with IRQs, as the player implementation may use them to control its playback rate. One notable exception is using SEI in a non-returning PLAY routine for a pseudo-IRQ technique. BRK should generally not be used, as it reads the IRQ routine address from the vector table which is reserved for the player's use.

Summary of Addresses

These lists all the addresses which should be readable by the code in the NSF; no other addresses should ever be accessed for reading:

$0000-$01EF
$01F0-$01FF (may be used internally by NSF player)
$0200-$07FF
$4015
$4040-$407F (if FDS is enabled)
$4090 (if FDS is enabled)
$4092 (if FDS is enabled)
$4800 (if Namco 163 is enabled)
$5205-$5206 (if MMC5 is enabled)
$5C00-$5FF5 (if MMC5 is enabled)
$6000-$FFF9

These lists all the addresses which should be writable by the code in the NSF; no other addresses should ever be accessed for writing:

$0000-$01EF
$01F0-$01FF (may be used internally by NSF player; do not use for non-stack variables)
$0200-$07FF
$4000-$4013 (always clear bit7 of $4010)
$4015
$4040-$4080 (if FDS is enabled)
$4082-$408A (if FDS is enabled)
$4800 (if Namco 163 is enabled)
$5205-$5206 (if MMC5 is enabled)
$5C00-$5FF5 (if MMC5 is enabled)
$5FF6-$5FF7 (if bankswitching and FDS is enabled)
$5FF8-$5FFF (if bankswitching is enabled)
$6000-$7FFF
$8000-$DFFF (if FDS is enabled)
$9000-$9003 (if VRC6 is enabled)
$9010 (if VRC7 is enabled)
$9030 (if VRC7 is enabled)
$A000-$A002 (if VRC6 is enabled)
$B000-$B002 (if VRC6 is enabled)
$F800 (if Namco 163 is enabled)

Reading/writing anything other than specified here results in undefined behaviour.

Pseudo-IRQ Technique

Some modern NSFs use a trick[1] first made popular by Deflemask, primarily intended to support PCM sample playback. This technique is not universally supported, because it may rely on a lack of conflict with the player's implementation. Some hardware implementations do support it correctly (e.g. PowerPak), and it also works with several software NSF players.

The technique uses a non-returning PLAY in the following way:

Use SEI to mask interrupts.
Enable the APU interrupt by writing to $4017.
Enter a sample playback loop, polling $4015 to see if an APU IRQ is pending.
When the poll registers the APU IRQ flag (occurring at 60 hz on NTSC), temporarily exit the sample playback loop to do other tasks.
Return to step 3, never returning from PLAY.

See also

List of NES music composers
Emulation Libraries: NSF Players
iNES Mapper 031: Cart mapper with NSF-inspired bankswitching

References

↑ NSF PCM technique (via Deflemask) forum post

Categories: File formats, Audio

Overscan

The NES PPU always generates a 256x240 pixel picture. But there is a recurring misconception that the picture is 256x224 pixels on NTSC. This article explains how both are true.

Consumer TV monitors draw the picture slightly larger than the screen, with some of the picture hidden by the border. This is called "overscan".[1][2] The BBC recommends keeping a 5 percent margin inside the screen and putting all important information, such as text, within the center 90 percent of the width and height of the screen.[3] Most TVs show slightly more than 90 percent, so make sure to keep any glitch pixels well outside this margin.

Contents

1 NTSC

1.1 For game developers
1.2 For emulator developers
1.3 Statistics

2 PAL
3 References

NTSC

BT.601 (formerly CCIR 601) is a standard for digital processing of component video signals. It describes a way to sample NTSC video at exactly 13.5 MHz to produce 704x480 non-square pixels or 135/11 MHz to produce 640x480 square pixels in the "clean aperture".[1] (The commonly quoted 720x480 is slightly wider to capture signals slightly before and after the clean aperture in case of a sync shift, allowing the signal to be recentered before broadcast. There are still only 704 pixels on a scanline.) This means the signal associated with one scanline is 640/(135,000,000/11) s = 704/13.5 s = 52.148 microseconds long.

The NTSC color subcarrier is at 39,375,000/11 Hz = 3.5795 MHz. The NES master clock is always 6 times the color subcarrier frequency because there are 12 hues on the NES PPU, and the color generator uses a double-pumped counter to generate the hue signal. So the PPU's pixel rate is 1/4 of the master clock, or 6/4 of the color subcarrier, or 39,375,000*6/4/11 = 5.3693 million pixels per second. (This pixel rate appears to have originated in the TMS9918 VDP used in the ColecoVision. The NTSC Sega Master System VDP and Super NES PPU use this same rate, as does the Sega Genesis VDP in the 256-pixel mode that several multiplatform titles used.)

Multiplying the pixel rate by the scanline length gives 39,375,000*6/4/11*640/(135,000,000/11) = 280 pixels per scanline. The PPU puts signal in 256 of these and a border at the left and right sides. The color of this border is the same as the backdrop color (usually the value in $3F00). This makes the pixel aspect ratio on a 4:3 TV to be 240/280*4/3 = exactly 8:7, or about 1.143:1.

In NTSC video sampled at 13.5 MHz, there are 481.5 non-square pixels from the start of the horizontal sync pulse to the center of the picture. This equals 191.5 NES pixels. But there are 65 pixels from the start of hsync to the left side of the active picture, or 193 to the center. So the NES picture is in theory a pixel and a half to the right of center.

For game developers

For a 280x240 pixel picture, the 90 percent safe area is 252x216 pixels. Because of the off-center horizontal timing, these 252 pixels are actually the leftmost ones. Some CRT TVs have rounded corners; it's a good idea to keep text away from the corners if possible.

This, however, doesn't give developers a free pass to ignore glitches caused by background mirroring. Actual TVs show about 224 lines of the signal, hence the commonly reported 256x224 resolution. But the vertical position may be slightly off center. Emulators and LCD HDTVs tend to use lines 8 to 231, but some TVs have been seen to show lines 12 to 235. In fact, even some CRT SDTVs made in the 2000s show more of the bottom than the top; this may be so that tickers on cable news channels aren't cut off.

As seen in an interview with the Zelda team, Nintendo's official background planning sheets had a conservative 224x192 pixel title safe area. It reserved 24 lines at the top and bottom and 16 pixels at the left and right as potential overscan. Later in the NES's commercial life, as TVs became manufactured to tighter tolerances, some developers pushed this out farther. The scaled mode of PocketNES, an NES emulator for Game Boy Advance, has 8 pixels of overscan on the left and right, 16 on the top, and 11 on the bottom. If all your graphics are visible in PocketNES, they should be visible on a TV.

Since 2007, most new TVs have been 16:9. To prepare your game for zoomed-in mode, assume a 160-line safe area surrounded by an overscan of 40 lines on the top and bottom.

For emulator developers

There are two ways to emulate the pixel aspect ratio of the NES: scale before padding and pad before scaling. The NES PPU hardware performs the padding first, adding 24 pixels of border to form a 280x240 pixel picture that can be resized to 320x240, 640x480, or 960x720 square pixels, or to 352x240 or 704x480 if your SDTV output circuit produces non-square pixels at 13.5 MHz (Rec. 601/DVD dot clock, 132/35*colorburst) or 13.423 MHz (PlayStation dot clock, 15/4*colorburst). But as a slight optimization, you can scale first (256 * 8/7 = 292) and then pad: stretch the 256x240 pixels to 292x240, 584x480, 876x720, or 1168x960 square pixels or 320x240 or 640x480 non-square pixels. Then you can emulate the overscan by drawing a TV bezel on top of the edges of the emulated picture.

Statistics

Here are some numbers of overscan lines from actual TVs, determined using a homebrew paint program on an NTSC NES + PowerPak. Ranges denote fewer hidden lines at top and bottom center (x = 120-135) than at the corners (x = 16-31 and 223-239) due to CRT curvature.

TV | Description | Mode | Top lines | Bottom lines
Vizio VX32L | LCD HDTV | Normal | 8 | 6
Vizio VX32L | LCD HDTV | Zoom | 36 | 35
Magnavox MS2530 C225 | CRT SDTV | | 12-14 | 8-10
Sylvania 6420FF | CRT SDTV | | 13-15 | 8-11

PAL

When sampled at 14.75 MHz (768x576) or 7.375 MHz (384x288), PAL video has square pixels. The width of a scanline is 768 pixels, or 768/14750000 seconds, or 52.068 microseconds.[1]

The PAL color subcarrier is defined as 4,433,618.75 Hz. The PAL NES master clock is six times that, and the PPU generates one pixel for every 5 master clock cycles, or 5320342.5 Hz. This makes the width of a scanline 5320342.5*768/14750000 = 277 pixels, and the pixel aspect ratio 7375000/5320342.5 = (59*125000)/(165*64489/2) ≈ 1.3862:1.

The width of the picture is nearly the same as on NTSC, so we need not reconsider horizontal placement. The border is always black, and it extends into the leftmost and rightmost 2 pixels[2] and the top scanline, the one that never shows sprites.[3] However, the total picture is 288 lines tall, making the safe area roughly 260 lines tall. This means every TV shows blank bars at the top and bottom of the 240-line active area that the NES generates. So for a PAL-only title, the developer need not concern himself with TVs cutting off the status bar, but minimizing artifacts caused by nametable mirroring and sprite pop-on at the top becomes paramount. Both the PAL NES and PAL famiclones (such as Dendy) behave this way.[4]

Emulator developers can simulate this system's pixel aspect ratio by stretching the picture to a multiple of 355×240, such as 1065×720 or 1420×960.

References

↑ [1.0] [1.1] Chris Pirazzi. "Programmer's Guide to Video Systems". Lurkertech. Accessed 2015-11-17.
↑ BBS topic: Looking for PAL display that displays ALL pixels
↑ BBS topic: 240p test suite
↑ BBS topic: 240p test suite

Pointer table

Contents

1 Preface
2 The problem
3 Organization of the data file
4 Using the pointer table
5 Code pointer tables

Preface

A pointer table is any area of memory that is filled with the addresses of other specific areas of memory. When we store the address of an area of memory this is referred to as a "pointer", because it "points to" that area of memory. This article demonstrates how a pointer table can be used to access variable-length data.

The problem

When we have multiple pieces of variable-length data, such as complex sprite meta-tile definitions, we need to be able to access those pieces of data using some index number. This allows us to uniquely identify each meta-tile compactly. This also allows us to go to the previous or next meta-tile without having to know anything about the underlying data.

Organization of the data file

Typically the pointer table and the data it points to is defined together within an assembly file. This allows us to easily change the data and re-arrange the pointer table as needed.

Tip: If you prefer to keep this data in a external file format such as XML and process it with a custom tool, have the tool generate the assembly file described below rather than a binary format. This is often much easier to debug and address.

In our sprite meta-tile example we might have several sprite frame definitions at the bottom of the file. These definitions will use the assembler's BYTE directive (typically .db or .byte) to declare the data. Each frame's data will be preceded by a unique label that we will reference from within the pointer table.

The pointer table usually comes at the top of the file. The pointer table will use the assembler's BYTE directive again to store the high and low bytes of our frame labels in two different tables.

Finally the length of the data must be stored so we know how much data to copy. We use the assembler's ability to perform math on labels for this. Not all assemblers support this however.

; Pointer table for our frames
frame_pointers_lo:
    .byte <_frame01, <_frame02, <_frame03, <_frame04
frame_pointers_hi:
    .byte >_frame01, >_frame02, >_frame03, >_frame04

; Data lengths
frame_data_lengths:
    .byte _frame02 - _frame01, _frame03 - _frame02
    .byte _frame04 - _frame03, _frame_end - _frame04

; Frame Data
_frame01:
    .byte "Some random data"
_frame02:
    .byte "related to the frames"
_frame03:
    .byte "that is of variable"
_frame04:
    .byte "length", $00
_frame_end:

Using the pointer table

To use the pointer table to access our data we will need to use the frame index as an offset into the pointer table. We then load this pointer into a zero-page variable so we can use it to load data.

Example:

; Routine to load the sprite frame definition for a given frame.
; Y = The frame to load data for
.proc load_frame_data
    ; Local variables
    .segment "zp"
        frame_pointer: .word 0 ; Our zero-page pointer for the frame data.
    .segment "ram"
        frame_length: .byte 0 ; The number of bytes in our frame data

    ; Routine Start
    .segment "prg"

    ; Frame pointer low byte
    lda frame_pointers_lo,y
    sta frame_pointer

    ; Frame pointer high byte
    lda frame_pointers_hi,y
    sta frame_pointer

    ; Iterate over each byte
    lda frame_data_lengths,y
    sta frame_length
    ldy #0
data_loop:
    lda (frame_pointer),y
    ; Do something with the frame byte in A, like transform it into OAM data
    iny
    cpy frame_length
    bne data_loop

    rts
.endproc

Code pointer tables

Code is another form of data, and subroutines can be accessed through pointer tables as well. See Jump table.

PPU OAM

The OAM (Object Attribute Memory) is internal memory inside the PPU that contains a display list of up to 64 sprites, where each sprite's information occupies 4 bytes.

Contents

1 Byte 0
2 Byte 1
3 Byte 2
4 Byte 3
5 DMA
6 Sprite zero hits
7 Sprite overlapping
8 Internal operation
9 See also

Byte 0

Y position of top of sprite

Sprite data is delayed by one scanline; you must subtract 1 from the sprite's Y coordinate before writing it here. Hide a sprite by writing any values in $EF-$FF here. Sprites are never displayed on the first line of the picture, and it is impossible to place a sprite partially off the top of the screen.

Byte 1

Tile index number

For 8x8 sprites, this is the tile number of this sprite within the pattern table selected in bit 3 of PPUCTRL ($2000).

For 8x16 sprites, the PPU ignores the pattern table selection and selects a pattern table from bit 0 of this number.

76543210
||||||||
|||||||+- Bank ($0000 or $1000) of tiles
+++++++-- Tile number of top of sprite (0 to 254; bottom half gets the next tile)

Thus, the pattern table memory map for 8x16 sprites looks like this:

$00: $0000-$001F
$01: $1000-$101F
$02: $0020-$003F
$03: $1020-$103F
$04: $0040-$005F
[...]
$FE: $0FE0-$0FFF
$FF: $1FE0-$1FFF

Byte 2

Attributes

76543210
||||||||
||||||++- Palette (4 to 7) of sprite
|||+++--- Unimplemented
||+------ Priority (0: in front of background; 1: behind background)
|+------- Flip sprite horizontally
+-------- Flip sprite vertically

Flipping does not change the position of the sprite's bounding box, just the position of pixels within the sprite. If, for example, a sprite covers (120, 130) through (127, 137), it'll still cover the same area when flipped. In 8x16 mode, vertical flip flips each of the subtiles and also exchanges their position; the odd-numbered tile of a vertically flipped sprite is drawn on top. This behavior differs from the behavior of the unofficial 16x32 and 32x64 pixel sprite sizes on the Super NES, which will only vertically flip each square sub-region.

The three unimplemented bits of each sprite's byte 2 do not exist in the PPU and always read back as 0 on PPU revisions that allow reading PPU OAM through OAMDATA ($2004). This can be emulated by ANDing byte 2 with $E3 either when writing to or when reading from OAM. It has not been determined whether the PPU actually drives these bits low or whether this is the effect of data bus capacitance from reading the last byte of the instruction (LDA $2004, which assembles to AD 04 20).

Byte 3

X position of left side of sprite.

X-scroll values of $F9-FF results in parts of the sprite to be past the right edge of the screen, thus invisible. It is not possible to have a sprite partially visible on the left edge. Instead, left-clipping through PPUMASK ($2001) can be used to simulate this effect.

DMA

Most programs write to a copy of OAM somewhere in CPU addressable RAM (often $0200-$02FF) and then copy it to OAM each frame using the OAMDMA ($4014) register. Writing N to this register causes the DMA circuitry inside the 2A03/07 to fully initialize the OAM by writing OAMDATA 256 times using successive bytes from starting at address $100*N). The CPU is suspended while the transfer is taking place.

The address range to copy from could lie outside RAM, though this is only useful for static screens with no animation.

Not counting the OAMDMA write tick, the above procedure takes 513 CPU cycles (+1 on odd CPU cycles): first one (or two) idle cycles, and then 256 pairs of alternating read/write cycles. (For comparison, an unrolled LDA/STA loop would usually take four times as long.)

Sprite zero hits

Sprites are conventionally numbered 0 to 63. Sprite 0 is the sprite controlled by OAM addresses $00-$03, sprite 1 is controlled by $04-$07, ..., and sprite 63 is controlled by $FC-$FF.

While the PPU is drawing the picture, when an opaque pixel of sprite 0 overlaps an opaque pixel of the background, this is a sprite zero hit. The PPU detects this condition and sets bit 6 of PPUSTATUS ($2002) to 1 starting at this pixel, letting the CPU know how far along the PPU is in drawing the picture.

Sprite 0 hit does not happen:

If background or sprite rendering is disabled in PPUMASK ($2001)
At x=0 to x=7 if the left-side clipping window is enabled (if bit 2 or bit 1 of PPUMASK is 0).
At x=255, for an obscure reason related to the pixel pipeline.
At any pixel where the background or sprite pixel is transparent (2-bit color index from the CHR pattern is %00).
If sprite 0 hit has already occurred this frame. Bit 6 of PPUSTATUS ($2002) is cleared to 0 at dot 1 of the pre-render line. This means only the first sprite 0 hit in a frame can be detected.

Sprite 0 hit happens regardless of the following:

Sprite priority. Sprite 0 can still hit the background from behind.
The pixel colors. Only the CHR pattern bits are relevant, not the actual rendered colors, and any CHR color index except %00 is considered opaque.
The palette. The contents of the palette are irrelevant to sprite 0 hits. For example: a black ($0F) sprite pixel can hit a black ($0F) background as long as neither is the transparent color index %00.
The PAL PPU blanking on the left and right edges at x=0, x=1, and x=254 (see Overscan).

Sprite overlapping

Priority between sprites is determined by their address inside OAM. So to have a sprite displayed in front of another sprite in a scanline, the sprite data that occurs first will overlap any other sprites after it. For example, when sprites at OAM $0C and $28 overlap, the sprite at $0C will appear in front.

Internal operation

In addition to the primary OAM memory, the PPU contains 32 bytes (enough for 8 sprites) of secondary OAM memory that is not directly accessible by the program. During each visible scanline this secondary OAM is first cleared, and then a linear search of the entire primary OAM is carried out to find sprites that are within y range for the next scanline (the sprite evaluation phase). The OAM data for each sprite found to be within range is copied into the secondary OAM, which is then used to initialize eight internal sprite output units.

See PPU rendering for information on precise timing.

The reason sprites at lower addresses in OAM overlap sprites at higher addresses is that sprites at lower addresses also get assigned a lower address in the secondary OAM, and hence get assigned a lower-numbered sprite output unit during the loading phase. Output from lower-numbered sprite output units is wired inside the PPU to take priority over output from higher-numbered sprite output units.

Sprite zero hit detection relies on the fact that sprite zero, when it is within y range for the next scanline, always gets assigned the first sprite output unit. The hit condition is basically sprite zero is in range AND the first sprite output unit is outputting a non-zero pixel AND the background drawing unit is outputting a non-zero pixel. (Internally the PPU actually uses two flags: one to keep track of whether sprite zero occurs on the next scanline, and another one—initialized from the first—to keep track of whether sprite zero occurs on the current scanline. This is to avoid sprite evaluation, which takes place concurrently with potential sprite zero hits, trampling on the second flag.)

See also

PPU sprite evaluation
Sprite overflow games

PPU pin out and signal description

Pin out

          .--\/--.
   R/W -> |01  40| -- +5
CPU D0 <> |02  39| -> ALE
CPU D1 <> |03  38| <> PPU AD0
CPU D2 <> |04  37| <> PPU AD1
CPU D3 <> |05  36| <> PPU AD2
CPU D4 <> |06  35| <> PPU AD3
CPU D5 <> |07  34| <> PPU AD4
CPU D6 <> |08  33| <> PPU AD5
CPU D7 <> |09  32| <> PPU AD6
CPU A2 -> |10  31| <> PPU AD7
CPU A1 -> |11  30| -> PPU A8
CPU A0 -> |12  29| -> PPU A9
   /CS -> |13  28| -> PPU A10
  EXT0 <> |14  27| -> PPU A11
  EXT1 <> |15  26| -> PPU A12
  EXT2 <> |16  25| -> PPU A13
  EXT3 <> |17  24| -> /RD
   CLK -> |18  23| -> /WR
  /INT <- |19  22| <- /RST
   GND -- |20  21| -> VOUT
          `------'

Signal description

R/W, CPU D0-D7, and CPU A0-A2, are signals from the CPU. CPU A2-A0 are tied to the corresponding CPU address pins and select the PPU register (0-7).
/CS is generated by the 74139 (address decoder) on the mainboard to map the PPU regs in the CPU memory range from $2000 to $3FFF.
EXTx allows the combination of two PPUs - setting the "slave" bit in the PPUCTRL ($2000) register causes the PPU to output palette indices to these pins, and clearing said bit causes it to instead read indices from these pins (and use them to select the background color). For the Vs. System and Playchoice PPUs, EXT0…2 are replaced with R, G, and B respectively. EXT3 is tied to ground; its functionality is unknown.
CLK is the 21.47727 MHz (NTSC) or 26.6017 MHz (PAL) clock input. It is doubled for the color generator (and then divided by 12 to get the colorburst frequency) and also divided by 4 (NTSC) or 5 (PAL) for the pixel and memory clocks.
/INT is connected to the CPU's /NMI pin.
ALE (Address Latch Enable) goes high at the beginning of a PPU VRAM access and is used to latch the lower 8 bits of the PPU's address bus; see the PPU address bus section of PPU rendering. It stays high for one PPU cycle.
PPU ADx (Address + Data) is the PPU's data bus, multiplexed with the lower 8 bits of the PPU's address bus.
PPU A8-A13 are the top 6 bits of the PPU's address bus.
/RD and /WR specify that the PPU is reading from or writing to VRAM. As an exception, writing to the internal palette range (3F00-3FFF) will not assert /WR.
/RST resets certain parts of the chip to their initial power-on state: the clock divider, video phase generator, scanline/pixel counters, and the even/odd frame toggle. It also keeps several registers zeroed out for a full frame: PPUCTRL, PPUMASK ($2001), PPUSCROLL ($2005; the VRAM address latch "T", fine X scroll, and the H/V toggle), and the VRAM read buffer. It is used in the NES to clear the screen when the console is reset either by the button or the CIC, and in a dual-PPU system it can be used to genlock the two PPUs together.
VOUT is the shifted analog video output. For the Vs. System and Playchoice PPUs, this is only the composite sync signal.

See also

Wiring diagram of RF Famicom
電子機器(Electronics) Junker's redrawn schematic of the HVC-001
Electronix Corp's redrawn schematic of the NES-001

Note: Minor error on page "NES 3" for the power led / reset switch board: pin 5 connects to LED, pin 4 connects to switch, pin 3 is +5V.

Categories: Pinouts

PPU power up state

In March 2008, Blargg reverse-engineered the power-up/reset state and behavior of the NES PPU, NTSC version.

Initial Register Values

Register | At Power | After Reset
PPUCTRL ($2000) | 0000 0000 | 0000 0000
PPUMASK ($2001) | 0000 0000 | 0000 0000
PPUSTATUS ($2002) | +0+x xxxx | U??x xxxx
OAMADDR ($2003) | $00 | unchanged^1
$2005 / $2006 latch | cleared | cleared
PPUSCROLL ($2005) | $0000 | $0000
PPUADDR ($2006) | $0000 | unchanged
PPUDATA ($2007) read buffer | $00 | $00
odd frame | no | no
OAM | pattern | pattern
NT RAM (external, in Control Deck) | mostly $FF | unchanged
CHR RAM (external, in Game Pak) | unspecified pattern | unchanged

? = unknown, x = irrelevant, + = often set, U = unchanged

The PPU comes out of power and reset at the top of the picture. See: PPU rendering.
Writes to the following registers are ignored if earlier than ~29658 CPU clocks after reset: PPUCTRL, PPUMASK, PPUSCROLL, PPUADDR. This also means that the PPUSCROLL/PPUADDR latch will not toggle. The other registers work immediately: PPUSTATUS, OAMADDR, OAMDATA ($2004), PPUDATA, and OAMDMA ($4014).

There is an internal reset signal that clears PPUCTRL, PPUMASK, PPUSCROLL, PPUADDR, the PPUSCROLL/PPUADDR latch, and the PPUDATA read buffer. (Clearing PPUSCROLL and PPUADDR corresponds to clearing the VRAM address latch (T) and the fine X scroll. Note that the VRAM address itself (V) is not cleared.) This reset signal is set on reset and cleared at the end of VBlank, by the same signal that clears the VBlank, sprite 0, and overflow flags. Attempting to write to a register while it is being cleared has no effect, which explains why writes are "ignored" after reset.

If the NES is powered on after having been off for less than 20 seconds, register writes are ignored as if it were a reset, and register starting values differ: PPUSTATUS = $80 (VBlank flag set), OAMADDR = $2F or $01, and PPUADDR = $0001.
The VBL flag (PPUSTATUS bit 7) is random at power, and unchanged by reset. It is next set around 27384, then around 57165.
Preliminary testing on a PAL NES shows that writes are ignored until ~33132 CPU clocks after power and reset, 9 clocks less than 311 scanlines. It is conjectured that the first VBL flag setting will be close to 241 * 341/3.2 cycles (241 PAL scanlines); further testing by nocash has confirmed this.
It is known that after power and reset, it is as if the APU's $4017 were written 10 clocks before the first code starts executing. This delay is probably the same source of the 9 clock difference in the times for PPU writes being ignored. The cause is likely the reset sequence of the 2A03, when it reads the reset vector.
^1: Although OAMADDR is unchanged by reset, it is changed during rendering and cleared at the end of normal rendering, so you should assume its contents will be random.
During the warmup state, the PPU outputs a solid color screen, usually grey, but it depends on the hardware.
The Reset button on the Control Deck resets the PPU only on the front-loading NES (NES-001). On top-loaders (Famicom, NES-101), the Reset button resets only the CPU.
Nametable memory in the Control Deck and CHR RAM in the Game Pak are unchanged by Reset, as are the CHR bank settings of most mappers. Their contents are unspecified at power on.

Best practice

The easiest way to make sure that 29658 cycles have passed, and the way used by commercial NES games, involves a pair of loops like this in your init code:

  bit PPUSTATUS  ; clear the VBL flag if it was set at reset time
vwait1:
  bit PPUSTATUS
  bpl vwait1     ; at this point, about 27384 cycles have passed
vwait2:
  bit PPUSTATUS
  bpl vwait2     ; at this point, about 57165 cycles have passed

Due to the $2002 race condition, alignment between the CPU and PPU clocks at reset may cause the NES to miss an occasional VBL flag setting, but the only consequence of this is that your program will take one frame longer to start up. You might want to do various other initialization, such as getting the mapper and RAM into a known state, between the two loops.

See also

CPU power up state

References

Confirmation by nocash
Notes on reset color
PPU warmup testing by Blargg

PPU registers

The PPU exposes eight memory-mapped registers to the CPU. These nominally sit at $2000 through $2007 in the CPU's address space, but because they're incompletely decoded, they're mirrored in every 8 bytes from $2008 through $3FFF, so a write to $3456 is the same as a write to $2006.

Immediately after powerup, the PPU isn't necessarily in a usable state. The program needs to do a few things to get it going; see PPU power up state and Init code.

Contents

1 Summary
2 Ports

2.1 Controller ($2000) > write

2.1.1 Master/slave mode and the EXT pins
2.1.2 Bit 0 bus conflict

2.2 Mask ($2001) > write

2.2.1 Render Control
2.2.2 Color Control

2.3 Status ($2002) < read

2.3.1 Notes

2.4 OAM address ($2003) > write

2.4.1 Values during rendering
2.4.2 OAMADDR precautions

2.5 OAM data ($2004) <> read/write
2.6 Scroll ($2005) >> write x2
2.7 Address ($2006) >> write x2

2.7.1 note

2.8 Data ($2007) <> read/write

2.8.1 The PPUDATA read buffer (post-fetch)

2.9 OAM DMA ($4014) > write

3 References

Summary

Common Name | Address | Bits | Notes
PPUCTRL | $2000 | VPHB SINN | NMI enable (V), PPU master/slave (P), sprite height (H), background tile select (B), sprite tile select (S), increment mode (I), nametable select (NN)
PPUMASK | $2001 | BGRs bMmG | color emphasis (BGR), sprite enable (s), background enable (b), sprite left column enable (M), background left column enable (m), greyscale (G)
PPUSTATUS | $2002 | VSO- ---- | vblank (V), sprite 0 hit (S), sprite overflow (O), read resets write pair for $2005/2006
OAMADDR | $2003 | aaaa aaaa | OAM read/write address
OAMDATA | $2004 | dddd dddd | OAM data read/write
PPUSCROLL | $2005 | xxxx xxxx | fine scroll position (two writes: X, Y)
PPUADDR | $2006 | aaaa aaaa | PPU read/write address (two writes: MSB, LSB)
PPUDATA | $2007 | dddd dddd | PPU data read/write
OAMDMA | $4014 | aaaa aaaa | OAM DMA high address

Ports

The PPU has an internal data bus that it uses for communication with the CPU. This bus, called _io_db in Visual 2C02 and PPUGenLatch in FCEUX,[1] behaves as an 8-bit dynamic latch due to capacitance of very long traces that run to various parts of the PPU. Writing any value to any PPU port, even to the nominally read-only PPUSTATUS, will fill this latch. Reading any readable port (PPUSTATUS, OAMDATA, or PPUDATA) also fills the latch with the bits read. Reading a nominally "write-only" register returns the latch's current value, as do the unused bits of PPUSTATUS. This value begins to decay after a frame or so, faster once the PPU has warmed up, and it is likely that values with alternating bit patterns (such as $55 or $AA) will decay faster.[2]

Controller ($2000) > write

Common name: PPUCTRL
Description: PPU control register
Access: write

Various flags controlling PPU operation

7  bit  0
---- ----
VPHB SINN
|||| ||||
|||| ||++- Base nametable address
|||| ||    (0 = $2000; 1 = $2400; 2 = $2800; 3 = $2C00)
|||| |+--- VRAM address increment per CPU read/write of PPUDATA
|||| |     (0: add 1, going across; 1: add 32, going down)
|||| +---- Sprite pattern table address for 8x8 sprites
||||       (0: $0000; 1: $1000; ignored in 8x16 mode)
|||+------ Background pattern table address (0: $0000; 1: $1000)
||+------- Sprite size (0: 8x8; 1: 8x16)
|+-------- PPU master/slave select
|          (0: read backdrop from EXT pins; 1: output color on EXT pins)
+--------- Generate an NMI at the start of the
           vertical blanking interval (0: off; 1: on)

Equivalently, bits 0 and 1 are the most significant bit of the scrolling coordinates (see Nametables and PPUSCROLL):

7  bit  0
---- ----
.... ..YX
       ||
       |+- 1: Add 256 to the X scroll position
       +-- 1: Add 240 to the Y scroll position

Another way of seeing the explanation above is that when you reach the end of a nametable, you must switch to the next one, hence, changing the nametable address.

After power/reset, writes to this register are ignored for about 30000 cycles.

When turning on the NMI flag in bit 7, if the PPU is currently in vertical blank and the PPUSTATUS ($2002) vblank flag is set, an NMI will be generated immediately. This can result in graphical errors (most likely a misplaced scroll) if the NMI routine is executed too late in the blanking period to finish on time. To avoid this problem it is prudent to read $2002 immediately before writing $2000 to clear the vblank flag.

Master/slave mode and the EXT pins

When bit 6 of PPUCTRL is clear (the usual case), the PPU gets the palette index for the background color from the EXT pins. The stock NES grounds these pins, making palette index 0 the background color as expected. A secondary picture generator connected to the EXT pins would be able to replace the background with a different image using colors from the background palette, which could be used e.g. to implement parallax scrolling.

Setting bit 6 causes the PPU to output the lower four bits of the palette memory index on the EXT pins for each pixel (in addition to normal image drawing) - since only four bits are output, background and sprite pixels can't normally be distinguished this way. As the EXT pins are grounded on an unmodified NES, setting bit 6 is discouraged as it could potentially damage the chip whenever it outputs a non-zero pixel value (due to it effectively shorting Vcc and GND together). Looking at the relevant circuitry in Visual 2C02, it appears that the background palette hack would not be functional for output from the EXT pins; they would always output index 0 for the background color.

Bit 0 bus conflict

Be very careful when writing to this register outside vertical blanking if you are using vertical mirroring (horizontal arrangement) or 4-screen VRAM. For specific CPU-PPU alignments, a write near the end of a visible scanline may cause only the next scanline to be erroneously drawn from the left nametable. This can cause a visible glitch. Worse, it can theoretically cause a sprite 0 hit to fail, which may crash a game using a sprite 0 spin loop that's not resilient.

Only writes at the exact moment between active picture and horizontal blanking cause this glitch; well-timed mid-scanline writes do not, nor do writes that land well within horizontal blanking. The glitch has no effect in horizontal or one-screen mirroring. It also does not appear if bit 0 of the written value is 0; this always correctly sets the left nametable.

This produces an occasionally visible glitch in Super Mario Bros. when the program writes to PPUCTRL at the end of game logic. It appears to be turning NMI off during game logic and then turning NMI back on once the game logic has finished in order to prevent the NMI handler from being called again before the game logic finishes. To work around this in new productions, have your game logic set a flag that your NMI handler checks.

Mask ($2001) > write

Common name: PPUMASK
Description: PPU mask register
Access: write

This register controls the rendering of sprites and backgrounds, as well as colour effects.

7  bit  0
---- ----
BGRs bMmG
|||| ||||
|||| |||+- Greyscale (0: normal color, 1: produce a greyscale display)
|||| ||+-- 1: Show background in leftmost 8 pixels of screen, 0: Hide
|||| |+--- 1: Show sprites in leftmost 8 pixels of screen, 0: Hide
|||| +---- 1: Show background
|||+------ 1: Show sprites
||+------- Emphasize red*
|+-------- Emphasize green*
+--------- Emphasize blue*

* NTSC colors. PAL and Dendy swaps green and red[3][4].

Render Control

Bits 3 and 4 enable the rendering of background and sprites, respectively.

Bits 1 and 2 enable rendering of the background and sprites in the leftmost 8 pixel columns. Setting these bits to 0 will mask these columns, which is often useful in horizontal scrolling situations where you want partial sprites or tiles to scroll in from the left.

A value of $1E enables all rendering, with no color effects. A value of $00 disables all rendering. It is usually best practice to write this register only during vblank, to prevent partial-frame visual artifacts.

If either of bits 3 or 4 is enabled, at any time outside of the vblank interval the PPU will be making continual use to the PPU address and data bus to fetch tiles to render, as well as internally fetching sprite data from the OAM. If you wish to make changes to PPU memory outside of vblank (via $2007), you must set both of these bits to 0 to disable rendering and prevent conflicts.

Disabling rendering (clear both bits 3 and 4) during a visible part of the frame can be problematic. It can cause a corruption of the sprite state, which will display incorrect sprite data on the next frame. (See: Errata) It is, however, perfectly fine to mask sprites but leave the background on (set bit 3, clear bit 4) at any time in the frame.

Sprite 0 hit does not trigger in any area where the background or sprites are hidden.

Color Control

Bit 0 controls a greyscale mode, which causes the palette to use only the colors from the grey column: $00, $10, $20, $30. This is implemented as a bitwise AND with $30 on any value read from PPU $3F00-$3FFF, both on the display and through PPUDATA. Writes to the palette through PPUDATA are not affected. Also note that black colours like $0F will be replaced by a non-black grey $00.

Bits 5,6,7 control a color "emphasis" or "tint" effect. Each bit emphasizes 1 color while darkening the other two. Setting all three emphasis bits will darken all colors.

Bit 5 emphasizes red on the NTSC PPU, and green on the PAL & Dendy PPUs.
Bit 6 emphasizes green on the NTSC PPU, and red on the PAL & Dendy PPUs.
Bit 7 emphasizes blue on the NTSC, PAL, & Dendy PPUs.
See NTSC video for a description of how bits 5-7 work on NTSC and PAL PPUs.
The RGB PPU used by PlayChoice and some other systems treat the emphasis bits differently. Instead of darkening other RGB components, it forces one component to maximum brightness. A few games, which set all three tint bits to darken all colors, are unplayable on these PPUs.

The emphasis bits are applied independently of greyscale, so they will still tint the color of the grey image.

Status ($2002) < read

Common name: PPUSTATUS
Description: PPU status register
Access: read

This register reflects the state of various functions inside the PPU. It is often used for determining timing. To determine when the PPU has reached a given pixel of the screen, put an opaque pixel of sprite 0 there.

7  bit  0
---- ----
VSO. ....
|||| ||||
|||+-++++- Least significant bits previously written into a PPU register
|||        (due to register not being updated for this address)
||+------- Sprite overflow. The intent was for this flag to be set
||         whenever more than eight sprites appear on a scanline, but a
||         hardware bug causes the actual behavior to be more complicated
||         and generate false positives as well as false negatives; see
||         PPU sprite evaluation. This flag is set during sprite
||         evaluation and cleared at dot 1 (the second dot) of the
||         pre-render line.
|+-------- Sprite 0 Hit.  Set when a nonzero pixel of sprite 0 overlaps
|          a nonzero background pixel; cleared at dot 1 of the pre-render
|          line.  Used for raster timing.
+--------- Vertical blank has started (0: not in vblank; 1: in vblank).
           Set at dot 1 of line 241 (the line *after* the post-render
           line); cleared after reading $2002 and at dot 1 of the
           pre-render line.

Notes

Reading the status register will clear D7 mentioned above and also the address latch used by PPUSCROLL and PPUADDR. It does not clear the sprite 0 hit or overflow bit.
Once the sprite 0 hit flag is set, it will not be cleared until the end of the next vertical blank. If attempting to use this flag for raster timing, it is important to ensure that the sprite 0 hit check happens outside of vertical blank, otherwise the CPU will "leak" through and the check will fail. The easiest way to do this is to place an earlier check for D6 = 0, which will wait for the pre-render scanline to begin.
If using sprite 0 hit to make a bottom scroll bar below a vertically scrolling or freely scrolling playfield, be careful to ensure that the tile in the playfield behind sprite 0 is opaque.
Sprite 0 hit is not detected at x=255, nor is it detected at x=0 through 7 if the background or sprites are hidden in this area.
See: PPU rendering for more information on the timing of setting and clearing the flags.
Some Vs. System PPUs return a constant value in D4-D0 that the game checks.
Caution: Reading PPUSTATUS at the exact start of vertical blank will return 0 in bit 7 but clear the latch anyway, causing the program to miss frames. See NMI for details.

OAM address ($2003) > write

Common name: OAMADDR
Description: OAM address port
Access: write

Write the address of OAM you want to access here. Most games just write $00 here and then use OAMDMA. (DMA is implemented in the 2A03/7 chip and works by repeatedly writing to OAMDATA)

Values during rendering

OAMADDR is set to 0 during each of ticks 257-320 (the sprite tile loading interval) of the pre-render and visible scanlines.

The value of OAMADDR when sprite evaluation starts at tick 65 of the visible scanlines will determine where in OAM sprite evaluation starts, and hence which sprite gets treated as sprite 0. The first OAM entry to be checked during sprite evaluation is the one starting at OAM[OAMADDR]. If OAMADDR is unaligned and does not point to the y position (first byte) of an OAM entry, then whatever it points to (tile index, attribute, or x coordinate) will be reinterpreted as a y position, and the following bytes will be similarly reinterpreted. No more sprites will be found once the end of OAM is reached, effectively hiding any sprites before OAM[OAMADDR].

OAMADDR precautions

On the 2C02, writes to OAMADDR reliably corrupt OAM.[5] This can then be worked around by writing all 256 bytes of OAM.

It is also the case that if OAMADDR is not less than eight when rendering starts, the eight bytes starting at OAMADDR & 0xF8 are copied to the first eight bytes of OAM; it seems likely that this is related. The former bug is known to have been fixed in the 2C07; the latter is suspected to be. On the Dendy, the latter bug is required for 2C02 compatibility.

OAM data ($2004) <> read/write

Common name: OAMDATA
Description: OAM data port
Access: read, write

Write OAM data here. Writes will increment OAMADDR after the write; reads during vertical or forced blanking return the value from OAM at that address but do not increment.

Because changes to OAM should normally be made only during vblank, writing through OAMDATA is only effective for partial updates (it is too slow). Most games will use the DMA feature through OAMDMA instead.

Reading OAMDATA while the PPU is rendering will expose internal OAM accesses during sprite evaluation and loading; Micro Machines does this.

Writes to OAMDATA during rendering (on the pre-render line and the visible lines 0-239, provided either sprite or background rendering is enabled) do not modify values in OAM, but do perform a glitchy increment of OAMADDR, bumping only the high 6 bits (i.e., it bumps the [n] value in PPU sprite evaluation - it's plausible that it could bump the low bits instead depending on the current status of sprite evaluation). This extends to DMA transfers via OAMDMA, since that uses writes to $2004. For emulation purposes, it is probably best to completely ignore writes during rendering.

It used to be thought that reading from this register wasn't reliable[6], however more recent evidence seems to suggest that this is solely due to corruption by OAMADDR writes.

In the oldest instantiations of the PPU, as found on earlier Famicoms and NESes, this register is not readable[7]. The readability was added on the RP2C02G, found on most NESes and later Famicoms.[8]

In the 2C07, sprite evaluation can never be fully disabled, and will always start 20 scanlines after the start of vblank[9] (same as when the prerender scanline would have been on the 2C02). As such, you must upload anything to OAM that you intend to within the first 20 scanlines after the 2C07 signals vertical blanking.

Scroll ($2005) >> write x2

Common name: PPUSCROLL
Description: PPU scrolling position register
Access: write twice

This register is used to change the scroll position, that is, to tell the PPU which pixel of the nametable selected through PPUCTRL should be at the top left corner of the rendered screen. Typically, this register is written to during vertical blanking, so that the next frame starts rendering from the desired location, but it can also be modified during rendering in order to split the screen. Changes made to the vertical scroll during rendering will only take effect on the next frame.

After reading PPUSTATUS to reset the address latch, write the horizontal and vertical scroll offsets here just before turning on the screen:

 bit PPUSTATUS
 ; possibly other code goes here
 lda cam_position_x
 sta PPUSCROLL
 lda cam_position_y
 sta PPUSCROLL

Horizontal offsets range from 0 to 255. "Normal" vertical offsets range from 0 to 239, while values of 240 to 255 are treated as -16 through -1 in a way, but tile data is incorrectly fetched from the attribute table.

By changing the values here across several frames and writing tiles to newly revealed areas of the nametables, one can achieve the effect of a camera panning over a large background.

Address ($2006) >> write x2

Common name: PPUADDR
Description: PPU address register
Access: write twice

Because the CPU and the PPU are on separate buses, neither has direct access to the other's memory. The CPU writes to VRAM through a pair of registers on the PPU. First it loads an address into PPUADDR, and then it writes repeatedly to PPUDATA to fill VRAM.

After reading PPUSTATUS to reset the address latch, write the 16-bit address of VRAM you want to access here, upper byte first. For example, to set the VRAM address to $2108:

  lda #$21
  sta PPUADDR
  lda #$08
  sta PPUADDR

Valid addresses are $0000-$3FFF; higher addresses will be mirrored down.

note

Access to PPUSCROLL and PPUADDR during screen refresh produces interesting raster effects; the starting position of each scanline can be set to any pixel position in nametable memory. For more information, see PPU scrolling and tokumaru's sample code on the BBS.[10]

Editor's note: Last comment about external page should be re-directed to the getting started section instead.

Data ($2007) <> read/write

Common name: PPUDATA
Description: PPU data port
Access: read, write

VRAM read/write data register. After access, the video memory address will increment by an amount determined by $2000:2.

When the screen is turned off by disabling the background/sprite rendering flag with the PPUMASK or during vertical blank, you can read or write data from VRAM through this port. Since accessing this register increments the VRAM address, it should not be accessed outside vertical or forced blanking because it will cause graphical glitches, and if writing, write to an unpredictable address in VRAM. However, two games are known to read from PPUDATA during rendering: see Tricky-to-emulate games.

VRAM reading and writing shares the same internal address register that rendering uses. So after loading data into video memory, the program should reload the scroll position afterwards with PPUSCROLL writes in order to avoid wrong scrolling.

The PPUDATA read buffer (post-fetch)

When reading while the VRAM address is in the range 0-$3EFF (i.e., before the palettes), the read will return the contents of an internal read buffer. This internal buffer is updated only when reading PPUDATA, and so is preserved across frames. After the CPU reads and gets the contents of the internal buffer, the PPU will immediately update the internal buffer with the byte at the current VRAM address. Thus, after setting the VRAM address, one should first read this register and discard the result.

Reading palette data from $3F00-$3FFF works differently. The palette data is placed immediately on the data bus, and hence no dummy read is required. Reading the palettes still updates the internal buffer though, but the data placed in it is the mirrored nametable data that would appear "underneath" the palette. (Checking the PPU memory map should make this clearer.)

OAM DMA ($4014) > write

Common name: OAMDMA
Description: OAM DMA register (high byte)
Access: write

This port is located on the CPU. Writing $XX will upload 256 bytes of data from CPU page $XX00-$XXFF to the internal PPU OAM. This page is typically located in internal RAM, commonly $0200-$02FF, but cartridge RAM or ROM can be used as well.

The CPU is suspended during the transfer, which will take 513 or 514 cycles after the $4014 write tick. (1 dummy read cycle while waiting for writes to complete, +1 if on an odd CPU cycle, then 256 alternating read/write cycles.)

The OAM DMA is the only effective method for initializing all 256 bytes of OAM. Because of the decay of OAM's dynamic RAM when rendering is disabled, the initialization should take place within vblank. Writes through OAMDATA are generally too slow for this task.

The DMA transfer will begin at the current OAM write address. It is common practice to initialize it to 0 with a write to OAMADDR before the DMA transfer. Different starting addresses can be used for a simple OAM cycling technique, to alleviate sprite priority conflicts by flickering. If using this technique, after the DMA OAMADDR should be set to 0 before the end of vblank to prevent potential OAM corruption (See: Errata). However, due to OAMADDR writes also having a "corruption" effect[5] this technique is not recommended.

References

↑ ppu.cpp by Bero and Xodnizel
↑ Reply to "Riding the open bus" by lidnariq
↑ PAL PPU swaps green and red emphasis bits: http://forums.nesdev.com/viewtopic.php?p=131889#p13188
↑ Dendy PPU swaps green and red emphasis bits: http://forums.nesdev.com/viewtopic.php?p=155513#p155513
↑ [5.0] [5.1] Manual OAM write glitchyness: http://forums.nesdev.com/viewtopic.php?f=2&t=10189
↑ $2004 reading reliable? http://forums.nesdev.com/viewtopic.php?f=2&t=6424
↑ $2003 not readable on early revisions: http://forums.nesdev.com/viewtopic.php?p=62137#p62137
↑ hardware revisions and $2003 reads: http://forums.nesdev.com/viewtopic.php?f=2&t=12958&start=45#p150926
↑ 2C07 PPU sprite evaluation notes: http://forums.nesdev.com/viewtopic.php?f=9&t=11041
↑ PPU synchronization from NMI: http://forums.nesdev.com/viewtopic.php?p=64111#p64111

Program compatibility

This page describes defects in homebrew games. For defects in games prior to 1996, see Game bugs.

Homebrew development is as subject to bugs as old software was, but many suffer from additional compatibility problems with the NES hardware due to being tested on emulators exclusively. This page is an incomplete list of homebrew releases that have known bugs, or especially hardware compatibility problems.

For a partial list of homebrew projects, see: Projects

Title | Year | Problem Description
Dikki Painguin in: TKO for the Third Reich (ROM) | 2004 | Incorrectly implemented parallax scrolling effect causes a severe graphical problem.
Final Fantasy II (English translation, Neo Demiforce) (Patch) | 1998 | Version 1.02 and 1.03 — graphic glitches during intro, no text during prologue (blue screen without text).

Caused by incorrect setting of nametables in PPUCTRL, misuse of PPUSCROLL, and reading of PPUSTATUS to detect VBlank.[1]

LAN Master (ROM) | 2012 | The original release had occasional nametable corruptions when resuming from pause. If the pause dialog was opened during a drum hit, the APU DMC could cause byte deletions when reading back nametables from $2007. If this happened, it would fail to restore the background tiles correctly when unpausing. The ROM was updated with a fix on 10/27/2015.
Mouser (ROM) | 1998 | Severe graphical problems prevent any useful gameplay.

Its author later created a sequel that addressed the compatibility problems.[2]

RTC Demo (ROM) | 2000 | Graphical glitches at the raster-bars portion because it incorrectly expects a sprite-0 hit on X=255.[3]

The sound-mode portion erratically advances tracks due to DPCM conflict with the controller read.

Ironically, this demo has a screen that attempts to detect the user of an emulator and warns the user that they are not playing it on hardware (this screen still triggers if played on a PowerPak).

Sack of Flour, Heart of Gold (ROM) | 2002 | Severe graphical problems on some screens due to $2007 access outside of vblank.[4]

Common compatibility problems

This is a list of issues that commonly appear due to lack of popular support in emulators, or sometimes even hardware limitations of flash-carts like the PowerPak. Many emulators are merely trying to be compatible with existing games, rather than accurately reflecting the hardware, making them inadequate for verifying the correctness of new software.

Use of DPCM samples causes a conflict with controller and PPU reads during sample playback.
Writes to PPU registers outside of vblank with rendering enabled conflicts with internal use of the PPU address, causing graphical corruption.
Failure to initialize registers not guaranteed by the CPU power up state or the PPU power up state.
Failure to initialize RAM, nametables, or mapper registers. (Few mappers have guaranteed power up states.)
Failure to delay use of the PPU after power/reset to avoid conflicts with its warm up state.

References

↑ http://forums.nesdev.com/viewtopic.php?p=53111#p53111
↑ http://forums.nesdev.com/viewtopic.php?f=22&t=10594
↑ http://forums.nesdev.com/viewtopic.php?p=4965#p4965
↑ http://forums.nesdev.com/viewtopic.php?f=2&t=3522

Programming UNROM

UNROM is the common name for a discrete mapper found on the UNROM board as well as the less common UOROM board. UNROM has 64 KB or 128 KB PRG-ROM (divided into 8 16k banks) and CHR-RAM. The UOROM board works the same way and can take PRG-ROM up to 256 KB (16 banks). It is very easy to use once you know how to load CHR RAM.

iNES header

Here is an NES 2.0 header for mapper 2 on the UNROM and UOROM boards. It should be backward-compatible with emulators supporting only the older iNES header format, but they may emulate extra RAM at $6000-$7FFF, where official boards have open bus.

.segment "HEADER"
  .byte "NES", $1A
  .byte 8         ;UNROM has 8 16k banks; change this to 4 or 16 as needed
  .byte 0         ;No CHR ROM
  .byte $20, $08  ;Mapper 2, horizontal mirroring, NES 2.0
  .byte $00       ;No submapper
  .byte $00       ;PRG ROM not 4 MiB or larger
  .byte $00       ;No PRG RAM
  .byte $07       ;8192 (64 * 2^7) bytes CHR RAM, no battery
  .byte $00       ;NTSC; use $01 for PAL
  .byte $00       ;No special PPU

To use vertical mirroring instead of horizontal mirroring, change the .byte $20, $08 to .byte $21, $08

Bankswitching

UNROM has four or eight banks 16 KB in size; UOROM has 16 banks. The last of these banks is fixed at $C000-$FFFF. The rest (numbered 0-2, 0-6, or 0-14) are switchable at $8000-$BFFF.

Switching banks requires a write to $8000-$FFFF. In UNROM, bits 0-2 of the byte written to $8000-$FFFF will select the bank; UOROM uses bits 0-3. When writing to $8000-$FFFF, the value you are writing must match the value located at the destination address in ROM (see Bus conflict). One way to ensure this is to have a bankswitch lookup table. You can read from this table and then immediately write that value back to the table.

.segment "RODATA"
banktable:              ; Write to this table to switch banks.
  .byte $00, $01, $02, $03, $04, $05, $06
  .byte $07, $08, $09, $0A, $0B, $0C, $0D, $0E
  ; UNROM needs only the first line of this table (0-6)
  ; but UOROM needs both lines (0-14).

.segment "ZEROPAGE":    ; The mapper is read-only; need to track its state separately
current_bank: .res 1

.segment "CODE"
bankswitch_y:
  sty current_bank      ; save the current bank in RAM so the NMI handler can restore it
bankswitch_nosave:
  lda banktable, y      ; read a byte from the banktable
  sta banktable, y      ; and write it back, switching banks
  rts

The lookup table and the bankswitching subroutine are normally located in the fixed bank ($C000-$FFFF).

To save 12 cycles per bankswitch at a cost of 5 bytes of ROM, the bankswitch_y subroutine can be made into a macro.

With the lookup table and bankswitching subroutine in place, switching banks is as easy as this:

  ldy #$02
  jsr bankswitch_y     ;switch to bank 2

If you switch banks in the NMI handler, such as to run a sound engine, do not write to current_bank. Instead, do this at the end of the NMI handler just before pulling registers:

  ldy current_bank
  jsr bankswitch_nosave

See also

UxROM technical reference
How to load CHR RAM

Random number generator/Linear feedback shift register (advanced)

Further commentary on the linear feedback shift register example at random number generator.

Contents

1 Basic version
2 Sacrifice entropy for speed
3 24 and 32 bit LFSR
4 Additional Resource

Basic version

prng:
	ldx #8     ; iteration count
	lda seed+0
:
	asl        ; shift the register
	rol seed+1
	bcc :+
	eor #$2D   ; apply XOR feedback whenever a 1 bit is shifted out
:
	dex
	bne :--
	sta seed+0
	cmp #0     ; reload flags
	rts

Sacrifice entropy for speed

The iteration count stored in X can be reduced to speed up the generator, at the expense of quality of randomness. Each iteration effectively generators one more bit of entropy, so 8 iterations are needed for an 8-bit random number. If you intend to use fewer bits of the result (e.g. use AND to mask the result), or if you are satisfied with less randomness, you can reduce X, or even parameterize it:

; X as a parameter specifies number of random bits to generate (1 to 8)
prng:
	lda seed+0
@bitloop:
	asl
	rol seed+1
	bcc :+
	eor #$2D
:
	dex
	bne @bitloop
	sta seed+0
	cmp #0
	rts

Alternatively this loop could be unrolled with 8 entry points, saving the need to use X or load it as a parameter.

Because the 16-bit LFSR has a repeating cycle of 65535 values, groups of 6, 5, or 3 bits will reduce the length of its output sequence. This should be avoided, if possible.

24 and 32 bit LFSR

By adding an extra byte or two to the seed variable, and choosing an appropriate polynomial to XOR with, we can extend the sequence length significantly with only one additonal ROL per byte (+40 cycles).

This 24-bit version has a sequence length of 16777215:

.zeropage
seed: .res 3 ; 24-bit

.code
prng:
	ldx #8
	lda seed+0
:
	asl
	rol seed+1
	rol seed+2
	bcc :+
	eor #$1B
:
	dex
	bne :--
	sta seed+0
	cmp #0
	rts

This 32-bit version has a sequence length of 4294967295:

.zeropage
seed: .res 4 ; 32-bit

.code
prng:
	ldx #8
	lda seed+0
:
	asl
	rol seed+1
	rol seed+2
	rol seed+3
	bcc :+
	eor #$C5
:
	dex
	bne :--
	sta seed+0
	cmp #0
	rts

Even longer sequences are possible, but it's not likely to be practical, as it would already take approximately 7 days for an NTSC NES to complete this 32 bit LFSR cycle.

A note about the chosen polynomials, $2D, and $1B are the lowest 1-byte polynomials that give a maximal sequence for 16 and 24-bit generators. $AF is the lowest for a 32-bit generator, but $C5 was preferred because it has less crowded taps (i.e. "better" behaviour if you're lowering the iteration count). There are other maximal sequence polynomials that can be used for all of these, the choice is somewhat arbitrary.

Additional Resource

http://users.ece.cmu.edu/~koopman/lfsr/index.html - a source for maximal polynomials for LFSRs of many lengths.

RTS Trick

The RTS Trick is one implementation of jump tables, which are a neat way to avoid long, complicated branching code to subroutine calls. It is easier to implement than a pile of branches, reads well, and saves bytes. In fact, the syscall dispatcher for the Apple IIGS toolbox (JSL $E10000) uses this same approach.

Contents

1 When to use the RTS Trick
2 About JSR and RTS
3 Using RTS as a jump table

3.1 Step 1: Return Address Table
3.2 Step 2: Table-friendly Data Format
3.3 Step 3: RTS Trick Launcher subroutine.
3.4 Potential Pitfall

4 Unofficial-MagicKit Macro
5 Games that use the RTS Trick
6 See also

When to use the RTS Trick

The RTS Trick is especially useful for anything that can be clearly expressed as a finite-state machine.

Sometimes a module or data format will have a large set of subroutines that will be invoked based on the value of a variable or a data read. One example would be a textbox module for an RPG game. In addition to the mundane displaying of letters you will likely need subroutines to perform various textbox-related tasks. Some examples might be:

clear the textbox
freeze the textbox (to wait for a button press, for example)
insert a pause
pluralize words (that is, add or omit an "s" based on a number in a case like: 1 *piece of gold/43 pieces of gold)
play a sound
close the textbox (end the dialogue)
update a variable (set flags, add items to inventory, etc)
pop up a yes-no box and prompt the player for a response
etc..

Another example would be a music engine. Your song data will have values that represent note values and note lengths, but your data format will also have opcodes that invoke subroutines to perform different tasks. For example:

set a segno, or loop point (possibly more than one, so you can nest loops)
dal segno, or loop
alter the pitch of a playing note
change tempo
silence a channel or otherwise set volume
set volume envelope
set sweep envelope
set square duty
apply vibrato
etc.

The more opcode-invoked subroutines you have at your disposal, the more unwieldy branching code will become:

    lda (data_pointer), y   ;read a byte from the text data stream
    bmi textbox_opcodes  ;let's say a value >= #$80 indicates an opcode
                         ;in our imaginary text data format
    ;...do ordinary text stuff
    
textbox_opcodes:
    cmp #$FF
    bne not_end
    jsr tb_end_dialogue
    jmp end_of_opcodes
not_end:
    cmp #$FE
    bne not_clear
    jsr tb_clear_dialogue
    jmp end_of_opcodes
not_clear:
    cmp #$FD
    bne not_pluralize
    jsr tb_pluralize_word
    jmp end_of_opcodes
not_pluralize:
    cmp #$FC
    bne not_add_inventory
    jsr tb_add_inventory
    jmp end_of_opcodes
not_add_inventory:
     
    ...
     
    etc...

In the above code example, we read a byte from our data stream and then determine whether that byte represents a character of text or a control character. If it's an opcode, we have to check which opcode. If it FF? no. well is it FE? no. well is it FD? crap. how about FC? The more opcodes you have, the more checks you have to do, and the more painful it will be to rearrange if you decide later to swap the values around. This is where jump tables can help, and the RTS Trick is one efficient way to make a jump table on 6502.

About JSR and RTS

Before talking about the RTS Trick, we need to make clear how JSR and RTS work. When you call a subroutine using JSR, two things happen:

the address of the last byte of the JSR (that is, the next instruction minus 1) is pushed onto the stack
the program counter jumps to the subroutine indicated.

When the program encounters an RTS instruction, this happens:

an address is popped off the stack.
the program counter jumps to this address + 1

$C0E0: 20 00 80     JSR $8000
$C0E3: A2 00        LDX #$00
$C0E5: A0 00        LDY #$00

$8000: A9 0F        LDA #$0F
$8002: 8D 15 40     STA $4015
$8005: 60           RTS

Let's run through this code.

The Program Counter is at $C0E0.
We encounter a JSR instruction. The address of the next instruction - 1 is pushed onto the stack. The next instruction is $C0E3. $C0E3 - 1 is $C0E2. $C0, then $E2 are pushed onto the stack (note the order). Then we jump to $8000.
We load #$0F into the accumulator.
We store the accumulator in $4015.
We encounter an RTS instruction. Two bytes are popped off the stack. In this case, those two values will be E2 and C0. The program counter jumps to this address + 1. $C0E2 + 1 is $C0E3. The Program Counter jumps to $C0E3, which is the instruction after our original JSR.
We continue on with our program as normal from $C0E3.

The part we need to take note of for the RTS Trick is the fact that RTS expects the stack to have a destination address MINUS 1. For the rest of this article, let's call this a return address. The two byte return address should be positioned on the stack so that the low byte is popped first, then the high byte. That's all we need to know: Destination address minus 1. Low byte popped first.

Using RTS as a jump table

We said above that we want to avoid having a long chain of comparisons and branches, and that the RTS Trick will help us do that. So what is the RTS Trick?

The RTS Trick consists of a lookup table of return addresses. You read a return address from this table, push it onto the stack, and then RTS. It's really, really simple to understand with an example. Let's use our textbox example above. What do we need?

We need a table of return addresses
We need a data format that will allow us to index into this table easily.
We need a RTS Trick launcher subroutine (I'll tell you why below. Don't worry, it's super-simple)

Step 1: Return Address Table

This is really easy to make. Assuming we already have a bunch of subroutines:

tb_end_dialogue:
    ;do stuff
    rts
   
tb_clear_textbox:
    ;do stuff
    rts
   
tb_pluralize_word:
    ;check a number and add an "s" if it's > 1
    rts
   
tb_add_inventory:
    ;do stuff
    rts
   
tb_set_flag:
    ;do stuff
    rts
  
tb_insert_dramatic_pause:
    ;do stuff
    rts
   
tb_play_dramatic_sound:
    ;do stuff
    rts
   
tb_set_text_color:
    ;do stuff
    rts

    ... etc

This is how our return address table will look:

tb_opcode_rts_table:
     .word tb_end_dialogue-1
     .word tb_clear_textbox-1
     .word tb_pluralize_word-1
     .word tb_add_inventory-1
     .word tb_set_flag-1
     .word tb_insert_dramatic_pause-1
     .word tb_play_dramatic_sound-1
     .word tb_set_text_color-1
     .word ...etc

Finished. That's it. Recall that RTS will expect the address on the stack to be its destination - 1. So we tack a minus one to all of our addresses in the table.

Step 2: Table-friendly Data Format

Our text engine reads a byte from our data stream. It checks to see whether that value represents a letter or an opcode. If it is an opcode, we want to turn that value into an index into our return address table. Indexes start at 0 and go up. The data format we have now, counting down from $FF probably won't be quite as convenient as one that counts up. It doesn't really matter from where. It could start at $80, or $C0, or $E0, or it could start from $00 and reach $1F (such as $0A for a new line). For this example, let's keep it simple and choose $80. Here is our new data format:

 $00-$7F: letters (a, b, c, d..etc)
 $80-$FF(potentially): opcodes

 Opcode list:
 
 $80 = end dialogue
 $81 = clear the textbox
 $82 = pluralize a word
 $83 = add an item to the character's inventory
 $84 = set a flag
 $85 = insert a pause
 $86 = play a sound
 $87 = set text color
 $88 = add to gold total
 $89 = subtract from gold total
 $8A ... etc

This Data Format for the opcodes is very table-friendly. It starts at $80 and goes up. When we read a byte from our data stream and determine it to be an opcode, all we have to do is chop off bit7 to turn our value into a table index:

 $80 = %10000000
 $81 = %10000001
 $82 = %10000010
 $83 = %10000011
        |
        +----------- if we chop off this bit7, we will get $00, $01, $02, $03, etc.
                     That's easy.  Just AND with $7F (%01111111) 

Finished. Step 2 Complete.

Step 3: RTS Trick Launcher subroutine.

This is easy. We need a subroutine that will turn our data value into an index, read a return address from the table, push the values and RTS.

tb_opcode_launcher:
    asl             ;we have a table of addresses, which are two bytes each. double that index.
                    ;incidentally, this chops off bit 7 and stashes it in the carry.
    tax
    lda tb_opcode_rts_table+1, x    ;RTS will expect the low byte to be popped first,
                                    ;so we need to push the high byte first
    pha
    lda tb_opcode_rts_table, x      ;push the low byte
    pha
    rts             ;this rts will launch our opcode subroutine.

That's it!

Potential Pitfall

One point I would like to stress: your launcher must be a subroutine. The opcode subroutines that you are RTS-launching all end in an RTS of their own. Do you know where they will return? Consider the following two examples:

The Right Way

tb_read_data:
    lda (data_pointer), y
    bmi opcode_stuff    ;if negative (bit7 set), we have an opcode
    ;do normal text stuff here

opcode_stuff:
    jsr tb_opcode_launcher    ;key point!  This JSR will put a return address on the stack!
                              ;When our opcode finishes execution, it will return to the right place!
    iny
    ;continue

The Wrong Way

tb_read_data:
    lda (data_pointer), y
    bmi opcode_stuff
    ;do normal text stuff

opcode_stuff:
    and #$7F
    asl
    tax
    lda tb_opcode_rts_table+1, x
    pha
    lda tb_opcode_rts_table, x
    pha
    rts ;the opcode return address is on the stack, but our starting point isn't.
        ;When the opcode returns, our game will leave this subroutine entirely
    iny ;and will never get here.

Let's assume that in both cases, the last INY instruction happens to be located at address space $D333.

In the first example, we JSR to our launcher. The JSR will put $D332 on the stack and jump to our launcher. Our launcher will read an opcode return address from our table and push it onto the stack. Then our launcher will RTS, which will pull the opcode return address off the stack, add one, and jump there. Our opcode will execute and return. Our opcode's RTS will pull our D332 address off the stack, add one and jump there. Good! We made it back to our INY instruction.

In the second example, there is no JSR to our launcher. No values are pushed on the stack to mark our place. We read from the table and push an opcode return address onto the stack and RTS to it. Our opcode executes and returns. Our opcode's RTS will pull two bytes off the stack, but we have no idea what those two bytes are. Usually, this will be the return address of whatever called our launcher, but if you have pushed something else onto the stack, it could return anywhere. We are in big trouble.

So make sure your launcher is wrapped up in a subroutine and called via JSR, or that it is otherwise the last thing in a subroutine, and you will be safe.

Unofficial-MagicKit Macro

In the Unofficial-MagicKit assembler, you may use a macro like the following:

	macro def_inst
	macset 2,4,*
	macset 3,4,?B
	bank bank(instadl)
	org instadl+(\1)
	db low(\2-1)
	org instadh+(\1)
	db high(\2-1)
	bank \3
	org \2
	endm

Note: This creates tables in a different format than mentioned above. It uses a separate table for the low-byte and high-byte, rather than putting them together. This avoids needing a shift operation (although you may also avoid a shift just by not defining any odd-numbered opcodes).

Now you may have a table like (they must be in the same 8K bank, and they should be aligned to a 256-byte page):

instadl	ds 256
instadh	ds 256

And then before the subroutines that would be called in this way you can do, for example:

	def_inst 42

Games that use the RTS Trick

The Guardian Legend uses the RTS trick in its sound engine for opcodes.
Concentration Room uses the RTS trick for three jump tables: one for the menu, one for the state of the board, and one for the state of the AI.
Famicom Z-machine has two: one for Z-character decoding (which uses a state machine) and one for instruction decoding.
Attribute Zone uses it for keyboard decoding in the level editor.
Haunted: Halloween '85 uses it to call enemies' move handlers.
240p test suite has a jump table for main menu activities.
Games using Pently audio engine version 5 or later use the RTS trick to process pattern opcodes that enable effects.

See also

The Fixed Bit Length Encoding article has an example of the RTS Trick in action.

Scanning large tables

Scanning tables larger than 256 bytes is more involved than scanning small tables, because there are no 16-bit equivalents to X and Y. Consider clearing a large block of RAM quickly. A straight-forward approach is to keep a 16-bit index in X and Y, and increment it until it reaches the desired index:

begin = ... ; address of first byte to clear
count = ... ; number of bytes

.zeropage
addr:    .res 2

.code
        lda #<begin
        sta addr
        lda #>begin
        sta addr+1
        
        lda #0
        
        ; X and Y form 16-bit index, with Y holding low byte
        ldx #0
        ldy #0
        
loop:   ; Clear one byte
        sta (addr),y
        
        ; Go to next byte
        iny
        bne nohigh
        inx
        inc addr+1
nohigh:
        ; See if low and high bytes of index match count
        cpy #<count
        bne loop
        cpx #>count
        bne loop

Using the same approach used in Efficient Forwards Scanning, we can make this more efficient.

First, consider the case of clearing all 64K of RAM. X and Y start out at 0, and they increment up to $FF $FF, then the loop ends.

        lda #0
        sta addr
        lda #0
        sta addr+1
        
        lda #0
        
        ldx #0
        ldy #0
        
loop:   sta (addr),y
        
        iny
        bne nohigh
        inx
        inc addr+1
nohigh:
        cpy #0
        bne loop
        cpx #0
        bne loop

Since we end once X and Y wrap to 0, we can optimize the inner loop to not check X every time:

        lda #0
        sta addr
        lda #0
        sta addr+1
        
        lda #0
        
        ldx #0
        ldy #0
        
loop:   sta (addr),y
        iny
        bne loop

        inc addr+1
        inx
        bne loop

If we wanted to clear just the last $103 bytes of memory, we'd start with the values the above clear loop has when there are only $103 bytes remaining. So we'd start with X=$FE and Y=$FD, and add $FE00 to addr. This would first clear a byte at $FEFD, then $FEFE, $FEFF, and the 256 bytes beginning at $FF00, as desired:

        lda #0
        sta addr
        lda #$FE
        sta addr+1
        
        lda #0
        
        ldx #$FE
        ldy #$FD
        
loop:   sta (addr),y
        iny
        bne loop

        inc addr+1
        inx
        bne loop

Now, if we can have the above loop clear the last $103 bytes of the 64K block "beginning" at address 0, we can have it clear the last $103 bytes of a 64K block that "begins" at any address in memory (it would wrap around to the beginning). For example, a 64K block at $1234 extends through $FFFF, then back to $0000 and through $1233, covering 64K total, and the last $103 bytes of this table would go from $1131-$1233.

Thus, we can use this to clear a block of $103 bytes anywhere in memory; it doesn't matter whether they are the last $103 bytes of a 64K-byte block, since the loop only accesses those $103 bytes. But it does add $FD to the address, since Y starts out with that value, so we must subtract that. The following efficiently clears $103 bytes anywhere in memory:

        lda #<(begin - $FD)
        sta addr
        lda #>(begin - $FD)
        sta addr+1
        
        lda #0
        
        ldx #$FE
        ldy #$FD
        
loop:   sta (addr),y
        iny
        bne loop
        
        inc addr+1
        inx
        bne loop

Addr starts out as begin-$FD. The first time through the loop, Y=$FD, so it accesses a byte at begin-$FD+$FD, that is, at begin, as desired. Then Y=$FE, so it accesses begin+1. Then Y=$FF and it accesses begin+2. Y wraps around to 0 and the inner loop falls through to the outer loop, which increments the high byte of addr and increments X to $FF and loops back. Now, Y=0 and addr=begin-$FD+$100, or more simply, begin+3, which is the desired address to be accessing this time through. Y keeps incrementing to $FF, then the inner and outer loops end, and it's cleared exactly $103 bytes of memory.

The general pattern is to load X with the high byte of $10000-count, Y with the low byte, and also subtract Y's initial value from begin. $10000-count can more simply be calculated as -count, since you get the same result:

        lda #<(begin - <-count)
        sta addr
        lda #>(begin - <-count)
        sta addr+1
        
        lda #0
        
        ldx #>-count
        ldy #<-count
        
loop:   sta (addr),y
        iny
        bne loop

        inc addr+1
        inx
        bne loop

If the address and/or size isn't known until the program is running, the above must be done at run-time with instructions, rather than relying on the assembler:

.zeropage
addr:   .res 2
size:   .res 2

.code
        ; Clears memory from addr through addr+size-1.
        ; Clears all memory if size=0.
        
        ; Adjust addr. Subtracting low byte of negated size is the same
        ; as adding the low byte of size and then a high byte of $FF,
        ; which greatly simplifies this calculation.
        lda addr
        clc
        adc size
        sta addr
        lda addr+1
        adc #$FF
        sta addr+1
        
        ; Subtract size from 0 to negate it, and put that into X and Y
        lda #0
        sec
        sbc size
        tay
        lda #0
        sbc size+1
        tax
        
        lda #0
        
loop:   sta (addr),y
        iny
        bne loop

        inc addr+1
        inx
        bne loop

An alternate approach of similar efficienty is a dual loop, with the first handling full 256-byte pages efficiently and the second handling the final partial page:

        ; Clears memory from addr through addr+size-1.
        ; Clears nothing if size=0.
        
        lda #0
        
        ldy #0
        
        ; Load page count and handle case where it's zero
        ldx size+1
        beq final
        
        ; Do full pages first
pages:  sta (addr),y
        iny
        bne pages
        inc addr+1
        dex
        bne pages
        
final:  ldx size
        beq done
        
        ldy #0
loop:   sta (addr),y
        iny
        dex
        bne loop
        
done:

This dual-loop approach works if the loop operation is short (here just the STA (addr),Y). If lots is done to each table entry, the previous approach is preferable due to reduced code size and not having to duplicate the code that operates on the table.

Scanning tables

There are several ways to scan a table that is 256 bytes or smaller, thanks to the many indexed addressing modes available (for larger tables, see Scanning Large Tables). Scanning could be reading values looking for a particular one, writing multiple values, copying, etc. Some are more efficient than others, or simpler to code.

Common approaches

For example, this code fills a table of size bytes with 0, from beginning to end:

        lda #0
        ldy #0
loop:   sta table,y       ; Y = 0 through size-1
        iny
        cpy #size
        bne loop

It's often more efficient to scan backwards, since DEY and similar instructions implicitly compare the decremented value with zero. Since it doesn't matter which direction we fill a table, backwards is preferable:

        lda #0
        ldy #size
loop:   dey               ; decrement BEFORE sta
        sta table,y       ; Y = size-1 through 0
        bne loop

Note how the DEY is before the STA. If it were after, once Y reached 0, the loop would end, even though the STA would never have been executed with Y=0.

If we're doing something besides simply filling, we might not be able to put the DEY before the table operation. For example, if we're finding the sum of all values in the table using ADC, the ADC will alter flags. We could add a CPY #0 just before the branch, but then we're back with code similar to the original code. If the table is 128 bytes or smaller, we can instead use the BPL instruction:

        lda #0
        ldy #size - 1     ; size must be 128 or less
loop:   clc
        adc table,y       ; Y = size-1 through 0
        dey
        bpl loop

Once DEY decrements Y to 0, BPL still branches, since 0 is considered positive. The loop then executes a final time, with Y=0. Then DEY decrements it to $FF (-1), and BPL falls through.

If the table is more than 128 bytes, we can still use BNE, and adjust the table address to compensate:

        lda #0
        ldy #size
loop:   clc
        adc table-1,y     ; Y = size through 1
        dey
        bne loop

Efficient forwards scanning

Sometimes a table must be scanned forwards, not backwards. For example, we might want to find the first occurrence of a particular byte equal to A:

        ldy #0
loop:   cmp table,y       ; Y = 0 through size-1
        beq found
        iny
        cpy #size
        bne loop
        
found:  ...

The original approach works, but there is one as efficient as the backwards approach. First, consider scanning a 256-byte table forwards. We don't need a compare since Y will wrap around to 0 on the 256th iteration. So this is as fast as the backwards version:

        ldy #0
loop:   cmp table,y       ; Y = 0 through $FF
        beq found
        iny
        bne loop

Now, let's say we only want to scan the last 3 bytes of table. We would simply start the loop with Y set to $FD rather than 0. It would scan entries $FD, $FE, and $FF, then end (or find what it was looking for):

        ldy #$FD
loop:   cmp table,y       ; Y = $FD through $FF
        beq found
        iny
        bne loop

Since we can use the above loop to scan the last 3 bytes of table, we can use it to scan any three bytes of memory; it doesn't matter whether they are the last 3 bytes of a 256-byte table, or a table that's only 3 bytes long. But it does add $FD to whatever table address we use, so we'll need to subtract that. The following scans a 3-byte table forwards for a value:

        ldy #$FD
loop:   cmp table - $FD,y          ; Y = $FD through $FF
        beq found
        iny
        bne loop

The general pattern is to load Y with the $100-size, and subtract that same value from table:

        ldy #$100-size
loop:   cmp table - ($100-size),y       ; Y = $100-size through $FF
        beq found
        iny
        bne loop

There is a slight overhead introduced by this approach: since most indexed instructions take an extra cycle if the low byte of the address added to the index exceeds $FF, this is likely to introduce an extra cycle. Using the 3-byte table example, if table's address were $10ED, the compare would assemble to CMP $0FF0,Y. Then, with Y=$FD, there would be a page crossing, adding an extra cycle. Since this approach uses the upper portion of Y's range, rather than the lower portion, it's more likely to cause page crossings. However, one cycle due to a page crossing is less than two cycles due to an immediate compare.

If size is less than 128, Y going negative could stop the loop, allowing the typical offset to the table halved, reducing the chance of a page crossing:

        ldy #$80-size
loop:   cmp table - ($80-size),y       ; Y = $80-size through $7F
        beq found
        iny
        bpl loop

This approach has the efficiency of the decrement approach while avoiding accessing the table in reverse. One downside is that finding the actual index of the current byte requires some calculation. Also, since it's somewhat tricky to code, backwards is still preferred where the access order doesn't matter. Don't overlook the possibility of storing the table itself in reverse order so that the reverse approach can be used.

Serial Cable Routines

This page covers implementation of bit-banged serial read/write routines for use with a serial cable. It's meant if you're implementing your own, or want to understand how the library routines work.

Contents

1 Serial

1.1 Encoding
1.2 Decoding
1.3 Stop bit/idle

2 Implementation

2.1 Timing
2.2 Initialization
2.3 Transmit
2.4 Receive
2.5 Timing accuracy

Serial

Encoding

Serial data bytes are transferred as a series of bits followed by an idle state until the next byte. Each bit lasts the same amount of time. An 8-bit byte is transferred as 10 bits, with the first and last bits serving as markers of the start and end of the byte. The start bit is encoded as a 0, and the stop bit and idle state as a 1. Data bit 0 is first.

-----       ----- ----- ----- ----- ----- ----- ----- ----- ---------
     \     /     X     X     X     X     X     X     X     /            
      ----- ----- ----- ----- ----- ----- ----- ----- -----
      start   0     1     2     3     4     5     6     7   stop

For example, the byte 00110001 ($31) is encoded as

--------       -----                   -----------             ----------
        \     /     \                 /           \           /
         -----       -----------------             -----------
           0     1     0     0     0     1     1     0     0     1

Decoding

To decode a byte, the receiver must read each bit, ideally in its center:

--------       ----- ----- ----- ----- ----- ----- ----- ----- ---------
        \     /     X     X     X     X     X     X     X     /
         ----- ----- ----- ----- ----- ----- ----- ----- -----
                 *     *     *     *     *     *     *     *

The transmitter and receiver each have their own clock to time the bits, and these might differ. So the receiver might slowly shift towards one edge due to timing differences. If it weren't aiming for the center, it would be more likely to hit an edge. At that point, it might read an adjacent bit.

The receiver must re-synchronize on each byte because its clock can't be accurate enough stay in sync with the transmitter's over long periods. The beginning of the start bit provides a known transition it can wait for. Once this occurs, it knows a byte is beginning, and that it should wait 1.5 bits before reading bit 0 (one bit to skip the start bit, and a half bit to get to the middle of bit 0).

--------       ----- ----- ----- ----- ----- ----- ----- ----- ---------
        \     /     X     X     X     X     X     X     X     /
         ----- ----- ----- ----- ----- ----- ----- ----- -----
                 *     *     *     *     *     *     *     *
        ^     ^  ^
      edge    1  .5

Above the receiver waits for the edge, then one bit, then a half bit to read bit 0.

Stop bit/idle

The idle state between bytes is also a 1, so it's as if the stop bit lasts until the next start bit. It can last any amount longer than a normal bit, and doesn't have to be a multiple of a bit long. That is, two bytes may be back-to-back, have a stop bit that's slightly longer than normal, or have one that's much longer than normal:

--- ----- ----- ----- ----- ----- -----       ----- ----- ----- ----- -----
   X     X     X     X     X     /     \     X     X     X     X     X 
--- ----- ----- ----- ----- -----       ----- ----- ----- ----- ----- -----
      3     4     5     6     7   stop  start   0     1    2      3     4

--- ----- ----- ----- ----- ----- -------       ----- ----- ----- ----- ---
   X     X     X     X     X     /       \     X     X     X     X     X 
--- ----- ----- ----- ----- -----         ----- ----- ----- ----- ----- ---
      3     4     5     6     7    stop   start   0     1    2      3    

--- ----- ----- ----- ----- ----- -------------------------------       ---
   X     X     X     X     X     /                               \     X  
--- ----- ----- ----- ----- -----                                 ----- ---
      3     4     5     6     7   stop          idle              start

Implementation

The following implementation is for clarity rather than usability or efficiency.

Timing

A serial rate of 57600 bits per second is the most useful on the NES. This gives the following timings:

| NTSC | PAL
CPU Clock | 1789773Hz | 1662607Hz
Clocks per bit | 31.07 | 28.86
Rounded clocks | 31 | 29
Error | -0.2% | +0.5%

Rounding to 31 (29 PAL) cycles per bit gives less than half a percent timing error, well within RS-232 tolerances. This allows the code to be written as simple loops.

Initialization

Before transmitting or receiving for the first time, write $03 to $4016 and delay:

        ldx #$03
        stx $4016
        ldx #350/5      ; delay 350 cycles, more than 10 bit lengths on NTSC
wait:   dex
        bne wait

This puts an idle state on the output lines so that the first byte sent will not be corrupt. It also prevents Famicom or other controllers also connected from interfering with receiving (as long as the A button isn't being pressed).

Transmit

To transmit a byte, output each of the 10 bits for 31 cycles each (29 for PAL).

| NTSC | PAL
Output start bit (0)
Delay | 31 | 29
Output bit 0
Delay | 31 | 29
...
Output bit 7
Delay | 31 | 29

        clc             ; start bit
        ldx #10
loop:   tay
        lda #$ff        ; replicate carry in low two bits and output
        adc #0
        eor #$ff
        and #%11
        sta $4016
        tya
        sec             ; stop bit
        ror a           ; next bit into carry, stop bit into shift reg
        nop             ; delay 6 cycles
        nop
        nop             ; remove for PAL timing
        dex
        bne loop

Remove the indicated NOP for PAL timing.

This outputs the start bit (0), 8 data bits, and the stop bit (1), each lasting 31 cycles. Note how it only outputs on bits 0 and 1 of $4016, and clears the others. Some serial connections may be using bit 1 in the future, so a routine should write to both bits if possible. Other devices may be using higher bits, so these should always be clear.

Receive

The NES inverts serial input, but not output, so when receiving data, things are inverted: a start bit is 1, a stop bit 0, and data bits are inverted.

To receive a byte, wait for the start bit, delay 1.5 bits = 46.5 cycles (42.5 for PAL), read bit 0, delay 31 cycles (29 for PAL), read bit 1, etc.

| NTSC | PAL
Wait for beginning of start bit
Delay | 46.5 | 42.5
Input bit 0
Delay | 31 | 29
...
Input bit 7

        lda #%10111 ; wait for start bit
start:  bit $4017
        beq start
                    ; LDA $4017 here would be 9.5 cycles after start bit
        nop         ; delay 17 cycles
        nop
        nop
        nop
        nop
        pha
        pla
        ldx #8      ; read 8 data bits
        nop         ; remove for PAL timing
loop:   nop         ; remove for PAL timing
        nop         ; delay 10 cycles
        nop
        nop
        nop
        nop
        tay
        lda #%10111 ; mask input lines and put into carry
        and $4017
        cmp #1
        tya
        ror a       ; shift into output byte
        dex
        bne loop
        eor #$FF    ; invert final byte

Remove both indicated NOPs for PAL timing.

The receive loop masks the bits serial data might come in on, and sets the carry if any of these is not zero. It shifts this bit into the shift register, and un-inverts everything in the end.

The start bit loop waits for the beginning of the start bit. It reads $4017 every 7 cycles:

bit $4017 ; 4 read
beq start ; 3
bit $4017 ; 4 read
beq start ; 2 (not taken)
nop
...

The start bit could occur anywhere between two of these reads, so the next read to notice it will be seeing it from 0 to almost 7 cycles later. It might read just as the start bit begins and see it immediately, or it might read just before it begins and not see it until 7 cycles later when it reads again. On average it thus notices it 3.5 cycles after it began. So we must add 3.5 cycles to our calculations of how long it's been since the start bit began. This means that if we put an LDA $4017 just after the BEQ, it would read on average 9.5 cycles after the start bit began (3.5+4+2):

bit $4017 ; 4 read
beq start ; 3
bit $4017 ; 4 read
beq start ; 2 (not taken)
lda $4017 ; 4 reads 9.5 cycles on average after start bit began

Timing accuracy

The 31/29 and 46.5/42.5 delays give the following timings, in cycles relative to the beginning of the start bit. The actual NTSC/PAL time is listed, then the ideal time, and the error (difference).

Transmit timing is only a quarter of a percent off for NTSC and half a percent for PAL. Listed is the starting time for each bit.

Bit | NTSC | Ideal | Error | PAL | Ideal | Error
Start | 0.0 | 0.0 | 0.0 | 0.0 | 0.0 | 0.0
0 | 31.0 | 31.1 | -0.1 | 29.0 | 28.9 | 0.1
1 | 62.0 | 62.1 | -0.1 | 58.0 | 57.7 | 0.3
2 | 93.0 | 93.2 | -0.2 | 87.0 | 86.6 | 0.4
3 | 124.0 | 124.3 | -0.3 | 116.0 | 115.5 | 0.5
4 | 155.0 | 155.4 | -0.4 | 145.0 | 144.3 | 0.7
5 | 186.0 | 186.4 | -0.4 | 174.0 | 173.2 | 0.8
6 | 217.0 | 217.5 | -0.5 | 203.0 | 202.1 | 0.9
7 | 248.0 | 248.6 | -0.6 | 232.0 | 230.9 | 1.1
Stop | 279.0 | 279.7 | -0.7 | 261.0 | 259.8 | 1.2

Receive timing is good on average, though all the times can be +/- 3.5 cycles shifted due to the start bit loop. Listed is the times the routine reads each bit in the middle, along with the ideal and error.

Bit | NTSC | Ideal | Error | PAL | Ideal | Error
0 | 46.5 | 46.6 | -0.1 | 42.5 | 43.3 | -0.8
1 | 77.5 | 77.7 | -0.2 | 71.5 | 72.2 | -0.7
2 | 108.5 | 108.8 | -0.3 | 100.5 | 101.0 | -0.5
3 | 139.5 | 139.8 | -0.3 | 129.5 | 129.9 | -0.4
4 | 170.5 | 170.9 | -0.4 | 158.5 | 158.8 | -0.3
5 | 201.5 | 202.0 | -0.5 | 187.5 | 187.6 | -0.1
6 | 232.5 | 233.0 | -0.5 | 216.5 | 216.5 | 0.0
7 | 263.5 | 264.1 | -0.6 | 245.5 | 245.3 | 0.2

In the above tables, the best we can do in software is to keep the error within -0.5 to +0.5 cycles, so we can't improve on most of the above timings. To correct the rest, we'd do the following. Transmit, NTSC: extra cycle during bit 6, PAL: one fewer cycle during bit 3. Receive, NTSC: extra cycle after bit 5, PAL: extra cycle before bit 0, one fewer cycle after bit 2. This requires unrolled loops so these special actions can be done on particular iterations.

Software Serial Routine

This page covers implementation of bit-banged serial read/write routines for use with a Serial Cable. It's meant if you're implementing your own, or want to understand how the library routines work.

Contents

1 Encoding
2 Timing
3 Initializing
4 Sending
5 Receiving

Encoding

Serial data is transferred as a series of bits followed by an idle state. Each bit lasts the same amount of time, but the idle state can be any length. An 8-bit byte is transmitted as 10 bits, with the first and last bits serving as markers of the start and end of the byte. The start bit is encoded as a 0, and the stop bit as a 1. Data bit 0 is first.

...--       ----- ----- ----- ----- ----- ----- ----- ----- -------//---
     \     /     X     X     X     X     X     X     X     /            \
      ----------- ----- ----- ----- ----- ----- ----- -----              -----...
           
     start    0     1     2     3     4     5     6     7   stop  idle  start ...

For example, the byte 00110001 is encoded as

...--       -----                   -----------             ------...
     \     /     \                 /           \           /
      -----       -----------------             -----------
           
     start    1     0     0     0     1     1     0     0   stop

The idle state between bytes is also a 1, so it's as if the stop bit lasts until the next start bit. It can be any length. Compressing the time scale, the byte 00110001 sent three times with varying delays between might appear as (S=start s=stop)

...--  --      ----    --  --      ----    -------  --      ----    --...
     --  ------    ----  --  ------    ----       --  ------    ----  
     S 1 0 0 0 1 1 0 0 s S 1 0 0 0 1 1 0 0 s      S 1 0 0 0 1 1 0 0 s 
    |<-- first byte  -->|<-- second byte -->|idle|<-- third byte  -->|
    

Above, the first two bytes are encoded back-to-back with no idle time between. This achieves the highest throughput, since no time is wasted. The last byte is delayed. Note that the idle state can last any amount of time, in particular, it doesn't have to be a multiple of the bit length.

Timing

A serial rate of 57600 bits per second is the most useful on the NES. On NTSC, this comes close to 31 cycles per bit (1789772.7/57600=31.07). On PAL, this comes close to 29 cycles per bit (1662607/57600=28.86).

Sending is simple: just output each of the 10 bits for 31 cycles each (29 for PAL).

Receiving is more involved: wait for the beginning of a start bit, delay 1.5 bit lengths before reading the first bit, then delay one bit length between the remaining bits. This way, the code is reading the bits in the middle so that any slight variations in timing won't cause bits to be read too close to the edges. Below, the * represents the read, and the delays are shown between them.

...--       ----- ----- ----- ----- ----- ----- ----- ----- -----...
     \     /     X     X     X     X     X     X     X     /
      ----------- ----- ----- ----- ----- ----- ----- -----
*******       *     *     *     *     *     *     *     *
         1.5    1.0   1.0   1.0   1.0   1.0   1.0   1.0

Allowing for a +/- 1% variation in NES/serial speeds, a receive routine must meet this timing:

| NTSC | PAL | Notes
Start to bit 0 | 43-50 | 39-46 | Number of cycles from beginning of start bit to read in middle of bit 0. Range because code to wait for start bit takes 7 cycles per iteration, and may read just after start bit has begun, or just before, in which case it will be another 7 cycles until it reads again. This averages to 46.5 cycles (42.5 on PAL), almost exactly 1.5 bit lengths.
Bit n to bit n+1 | 31 | 29 | Cycles between data bits.
Bit 7 to next start bit | 23-47 | 20-43 | Cycles between read in middle of bit 7 and first read in start bit loop for next byte. This causes the start bit loop's first read to fall within the stop bit

The following routines demonstrate proper timing. Note that they are written entirely for clarity, rather than optimized for practical use.

Initializing

Before sending or receiving for the first time, write $03 to $4016 and delay:

        ldx #$03
        stx $4016
        ldx #350/5      ; delay 350 cycles, more than 10 bit lengths on NTSC
wait:   dex
        bne wait

This puts an idle state on the output lines so that the first byte sent will not be corrupt. It also prevents Famicom controllers from interfering with reads (as long as the A button isn't being pressed).

Sending

To send a byte, write each of the 10 bits, with 31 cycles between (29 for PAL).

        clc             ; start bit
        ldx #10
loop:   tay
        lda #$FF        ; replicate carry in low two bits
        adc #0
        eor #$FF
        and #%11
        sta $4016
        tya
        sec             ; stop bit
        ror a           ; next bit into carry
        nop             ; delay 6 cycles
        nop
        nop             ; remove for PAL timing
        dex
        bne loop

Remove the indicated NOP for PAL timing.

This outputs the start bit (0), 8 data bits, and the stop bit (1), each lasting 31 cycles. Note how it only outputs on bits 0 and 1 of $4016, and clears the others. Some serial connections may be using bit 1 in the future, so a routine should write to both bits if possible. Other devices may be using higher bits, so these should always be clear.

Receiving

The NES inverts serial input, but not output, so when receiving data, things are inverted: a start bit is 1, a stop bit 0, and data is inverted.

To receive a byte, wait for the beginning of the start bit, delay 43 cycles (39 for PAL), read bit 0, delay 31 cycles (29 for PAL), read bit 1, etc. through bit 7:

        lda #%10111 ; wait for start bit
start:  bit $4017
        beq start
        pha         ; delay 17 cycles
        pla
        nop
        nop
        nop
        nop
        nop
        ldx #8      ; read 8 data bits
        nop         ; remove for PAL timing
loop:   nop         ; remove for PAL timing
        nop         ; delay 10 cycles
        nop
        nop
        nop
        nop
        tay
        lda #%10111 ; mask input lines and put into carry, inverted
        and $4017
        cmp #1
        tya
        ror a       ; shift into output byte
        dex
        bne loop
        eor #$FF    ; invert final byte

Remove both indicated NOPs for PAL timing.

A 1.5 bit period delay is 46.5 cycles (31*1.5), but in this code there are only 43 cycles between the time that BIT $4017 reads the start bit and AND $4017 reads bit 0. This is because the start bit loop takes 7 cycles, and if the start bit begins just after the BIT $4017, the loop will take another 7 cycles before it's seen. Since it can start at any point in this 7-cycle loop, the final BIT $4017 sees the start bit an average of 3.5 cycles after it began. Thus the 43-cycle delay in the code gives an average of 46.5 cycles between the beginning of the start bit and where it reads bit 0, exactly as desired. The actual bit 0 read time can vary by +/- 3.5 cycles from the center of bit 0 (7 cycles/2). Since each bit lasts 31 cycles, this variation isn't a problem.

Stack

In computer programming, a stack is any of several data structures used to store values and retrieve them in the reverse order. CPUs use stacks to track which subroutines call which other subroutines, and programs use them to pass arguments to subroutines and save values for later use.

All stacks support two operations: push to add a value, and pull (also called pop) to retrieve and remove a value. Stacks may also support peek, or retrieve a value n positions from the top without removing it.

Stacks may be implemented on top of an array or linked list. Some elements are used and others unused; an array index called the "stack pointer" sets the boundary between used and unused elements. The 6502 has hardware support for a stack implemented using a 256-byte array whose location is hardcoded at page $01 ($0100-$01FF), using the S register for a stack pointer.

There are two ways to implement a stack on top of an array. A descending stack (or one that grows downward) starts the stack pointer at the end of the array, decreases it on a push, and increases it on a pull. An ascending stack (or one that grows upward) does the opposite. The 6502, Z80, 65816, MIPS, ARM/Thumb, and PowerPC all use a descending stack.

Each of these allows two ways to interpret the stack pointer. In a full stack, the stack pointer points to the topmost value. It is moved before pushing and after pulling. In an empty stack, the stack pointer points to the element where the next value will be stored. It is moved after pushing and before pulling. ARM traditionally uses a full stack, but 6502 and 65816 use an empty stack. For example, on a 6502, if S = $FD, and the program pushes something, it'll be written to $01FD and then S becomes $FC to show that $01FC is available to store the next value. It is common practice on a 6502 to initialize the stack pointer to $FF at reset time.

Imagine stacking a bunch of dinner plates on top of one another; you can't take a plate out from the middle of the stack, you have to take one off the very top each time.

Contents

1 Pushing values
2 Pulling values
3 Overflow and underflow
4 Multitasking
5 Pop slide
6 External links

Pushing values

Let's look at some example code:

_init:
  ldx #$ff	; Set the stack pointer to $FF
  txs		; (e.g. $01FF)

_pushstack:
  lda #$e0	; Push value $e0 on to the stack.
  pha		; $01FF now contains $e0, and S is now $FE.

  ldy #$bb	; Push value $bb on to the stack.
  tya
  pha		; $01FE now contains $bb, and S is now $FD.

  txa
  pha		; Push value $ff (from the _init routine) on to the stack.
		; $01FD now contains $ff, and S is now $FC.

At this point in our program, we have pushed 3 values on to the stack: $e0, $bb, and $ff. Because the stack grows downward, these will appear as FF BB E0 in a memory viewer. Since $ff was the last thing we pushed onto the stack, it will be the first thing we pull off the stack. We can't pull the $bb value until $ff has been pulled off, and so on -- hence the term "stack".

Pulling values

Begin with the values pushed in the previous section, with S = $FC and $01FD-$01FF = FF BB E0.

_pullstack:
  pla		; Pull the value $ff off the stack, and put it into the accumulator.
  tax		; S now becomes $FD.

  pla		; Pull the next value ($bb) off the stack, and put it into the X register.
  tay		; S now becomes $FE.

  pla		; Pull $e0 off the stack, and put it into the Y register.
		; S now becomes $FF -- which is where we started!

Pulling may be called "popping" by people who come from an 8080, Z80, or x86 background, where the instruction is called pop.

Overflow and underflow

A stack overflow occurs when a program attempts to push data to a full stack, or push more data than the stack can hold. A stack underflow occurs when a program attempts to pull data off an empty stack. Usually this implies a PHA vs. PLA mismatch of some sort. Another cause is misuse of a JMP to exit a subroutine without returning (and without jumping to another subroutine that will return). Here, "full" and "empty" are defined in terms of whatever area a program uses for the stack.

On the 6502, if a program is using the entire page ($0100-$01FF) for the stack, pulling when S = $FF causes an underflow, while an overflow occurs when a 257th byte is pushed to the stack (when S is also $FF, having wrapped around after reaching $00). This overflow is difficult to diagnose, as a problem won't appear until later after many pull operations and the original values at the bottom of the stack are needed again. In a debugger you may wish to breakpoint S = $00 to warn both that the stack is almost full, or that an underflow has just occurred.
Many NES programs use a stack far smaller than 256 bytes, leaving some of that page available for other uses. For example, a program might build a buffer of things to be copied to VRAM in $0100-$019F, leaving $01A0-$01FF for the stack. In this case, the stack pointer is initialized to $FF and overflows when more than 96 bytes are pushed. Here S <= $9E would indicate overflow, though the problem isn't triggered until access to the buffer overwrites $019F, corrupting the out-of-range stack.
Some programs just leave S uninitialized, which puts the base of the stack wherever it is when the NES is reset, and let it wrap within the stack page. This overflows when more than 256 bytes have been pushed, or underflows when more data is pulled than pushed. Not initializing the stack pointer is poor practice, however, as it creates an inconsistent program state on reset, and makes it difficult to use a debugger to inspect the stack.

Multitasking

Most operating systems for 32-bit and larger machines support multitasking, where each process or thread gets its own stack. When switching from one thread to another, the kernel saves the thread's registers (including its stack pointer) and loads that of the other thread. Implementing this on a 6502 is difficult because all tasks have to share the $0100-$01FF page. It becomes somewhat easier on a 65816, whose 16-bit stack pointer allows putting the stack anywhere in $000000-$00FFFF, though some systems reserve much of bank $00 for I/O and ROM for compatibility with 6502 software.

Pop slide

Most NES programs do not use the entire $0100-$01FF page as a stack for subroutine return addresses. Many use only a small portion, freeing up the rest for storing other data.

Many NES programs write data to a buffer to be copied into video memory during vertical blanking. In an unrolled loop that accesses data linearly, the PLA instruction has two advantages. First, it's two bytes shorter than an absolute load, allowing the loop to be unrolled more in the same ROM space. Second, its pre-increment behavior frees the program from having to adjust the X register after a set of copies. So a program such as Battletoads may write large amounts of data to the stack and use a "pop slide" to copy the data into video memory. It starts with code like this, with the data starting one byte after the top of stack:

  pla
  sta $2007
  pla
  sta $2007
  pla
  sta $2007
  ; omitted
  pla
  sta $2007
  jmp finish

The program calculates where to jump based on the length of the data to be copied, much as in Duff's device.

When using a pop slide or anything else that uses multiple stacks, it's safest to leave a few bytes before the buffer unused in case something interrupts your process. This way, the return address and saved flags won't overwrite something important.

The name "pop slide" was chosen, despite the 6502 "pull" naming convention, as a rhyme for "NOP slide".

External links

Wikipedia:Stack (abstract data type)

Standard controller

All NES units come with at least one standard controller - without it, you wouldn't be able to play any games!

Standard controllers can be used in both controller ports, or in a Four score accessory.

For code examples, see: Controller Reading

Contents

1 Input ($4016 write)
2 Output ($4016/$4017 read)
3 Hardware
4 APU DMC conflict glitch

4.1 Multiple Read Solution
4.2 Synchronized OAM Solution

5 Turbo
6 See also
7 References

Input ($4016 write)

7  bit  0
---- ----
xxxx xxxS
        |
        +- Controller shift register strobe

While S (strobe) is high, the shift registers in the controllers are continuously reloaded from the button states, and reading $4016/$4017 will keep returning the current state of the first button (A). Once S goes low, this reloading will stop. Hence a 1/0 write sequence is required to get the button states, after which the buttons can be read back one at a time.

(Note that bits 2-0 of $4016/write are stored in internal latches in the 2A03/07.)

Output ($4016/$4017 read)

Front-loading NES $4016 and $4017, and Top-loading NES $4017
7  bit  0
---- ----
OOOx xxxD
|||| ||||
|||| |||+- Serial controller data
|||+-+++-- Always 0
+++------- Open bus

Famicom $4016 and Top-loading NES $4016:
7  bit  0
---- ----
OOOx xMFD
|||| ||||
|||| |||+- Player 1 serial controller data
|||| ||+-- If connected to expansion port (and available), player 3 serial controller data (0 otherwise)
|||| |+--- Microphone in controller 2 on traditional Famicom, open bus on AV Famicom and top-loader
|||+-+---- Open bus on traditional Famicom, all 0s on AV Famicom and top-loader
+++------- Open bus

Famicom $4017:
7  bit  0
---- ----
OOOx xxFD
|||| ||||
|||| |||+- Player 2 serial controller data
|||| ||+-- If connected to expansion port, player 4 serial controller data (0 otherwise)
|||+-+++-- Returns 0 unless something is plugged into the Famicom expansion port
+++------- Open bus

The first 8 reads will indicate which buttons are pressed (1 if pressed, 0 if not pressed); all subsequent reads will return D=1 on an authentic controller but may return D=0 on third party controllers.

Button status for each controller is returned as an 8-bit report in the following order: A, B, Select, Start, Up, Down, Left, Right. On plug-in controllers (the NES and AV Famicom) and the first controller of the original Famicom, all buttons are present. But on the original Famicom's second controller, the Select and Start buttons are completely missing, and the encoder chip returns 0 instead: A, B, 0, 0, Up, Down, Left, Right. Because these buttons are missing, games for the Famicom should not require the second player to press Select or Start.

In the NES and Famicom, the top three (or five) bits are not driven, and so retain the bits of the previous byte on the bus. Usually this is the most significant byte of the address of the controller port—0x40. Paperboy relies on this behavior and requires that reads from the controller ports return exactly $40 or $41 as appropriate.

Due to the presence of internal pull-up resistors, and the internal inverter, any pin without power connected will return zero, as shown above in the diagrams.

Because the Famicom controllers are permanently attached, some games, such as Simon's Quest, allow the use of the player 3 and 4 data for players 1 and 2.

A Super NES controller can be wired to the NES controller port, and it returns a 16-bit report in a similar order: B, Y, Select, Start, Up, Down, Left, Right, A, X, L, R, then four 0 bits.

Hardware

The 4021 (or 74LS165) IC is an 8-bit parallel-to-serial shift register. It has a pin "serial input", ordinarily used to chain the output of one shift register into the next one as seen in the Four Score or the Super NES controller. The serial input on the tail end of such a chain (or the only one in the case of an NES) can be tied to ground or Vcc, which determines the state of the output after all bits have been shifted out. If this is grounded, the shift register produces a 0 after all bits have been shifted out; if it's tied to Vcc, it produces a 1.

In the NES controller, this input is grounded. But because the signals from the controllers pass through an inverter before reaching the CPU, the register produces a 1 for all reads after the first eight.

APU DMC conflict glitch

The CLK line for controller port is R/W nand (ADDRESS == $4016/$4017) (i.e., CLK is low only when reading $4016/$4017, since R/W high means read). When this transitions from high to low, the buffer inside the NES latches the output of the controller data lines, and when it transitions from low to high, the shift register in the controller shifts one bit.[1]

This can cause glitches if the DMC DMA is running, and happens to start a read in the same cycle that the CPU is trying to read from $4016 or $4017. Since the address bus will change for one cycle, the shift register will see an extra rising clock edge (a "double clock"), and the shift register will drop a bit out. The program will see this as a bit deletion from the serial data. Not correcting for this results in spurious presses, especially of Right.

This glitch is fixed in the 2A07 CPU used in the PAL NES.

This detail is poorly represented in emulators. Because it is not normally a compatibility issue, many emulators do not simulate this glitch at all.

Multiple Read Solution

The standard solution used in most games using DMC will read the controller multiple times and compare the results to avoid this problem.

See Controller Reading for examples.

Synchronized OAM Solution

Because OAM DMA synchronizes the CPU and APU such that reads on an "even" CPU cycle never overlap a glitch, a program on an NTSC NES can miss all the glitches by triggering an OAM DMA as the last thing in vblank just before reading the controller, so long as all the reads are spaced an even number of cycles apart.[2]

Because this is a relatively new discovery, many current emulated implementations of the DMC glitch may be inadequate for testing this technique[3]. Hardware testing is recommended.

Turbo

A turbo controller such as the NES Max or NES Advantage is read just like a standard controller, but the user can switch some of its buttons to be toggled by an oscillator. Such an oscillator turns the button on and off at 15 to 30 Hz, producing rapid fire in games.

A controller should not toggle the button states on each strobe pulse. Doing so will cause problems for games that poll the controller in a loop until they get two identical consecutive reads (see DMC conflict above). The game may halt while the turbo button is held, or crash, or cause other unknown behaviour.

See also

Controller Reading
Controller detection
Controller port pinout

References

↑ Forum post: DPCM generates extra $4016 read pulse
↑ Forum post: Rahsennor's OAM-synchronized controller read
↑ Forum post: as of May 2016, Nintendulator and Nestopia do not accurately emulate OAM-synchronized controller reading.

Categories: Controllers

Status flags

The 6502 has 6 status flags: carry, decimal mode, interrupt disable, negative, overflow, and zero. Each of these can either be set or clear. The processor stores the current state of each at all times. There are 2^6 = 64 total states these flags can be in.

During certain events, a copy of the flags is written to a byte in memory. There are 8 bits in a byte, and when writing to memory, all 8 bits must be written. Since there are only 6 status flags, the unused 2 bits must be given values.

There are four events that cause the flags to be written to memory: NMI and IRQ vectoring, and the BRK and PHP instructions. Rather than set the unused bits in the copy in memory to the same values in all cases, the 6502 sets one of them based on whether the event was interrupt vectoring or an executed instruction.

The flags are copied to memory in this arrangement:

Bit 7: Negative
Bit 6: Overflow
Bit 5: Always set
Bit 4: Clear if interrupt vectoring, set if BRK or PHP
Bit 3: Decimal mode (exists for compatibility, does not function on the Famicom/NES's 2A03/2A07)
Bit 2: Interrupt disable
Bit 1: Zero
Bit 0: Carry

Note bits 4 and 5. This means that the following will put $30 into A, not 0:

LDA #$00
PHA      ; pushes $00 on stack
PLP      ; clears all 6 status flags
PHP      ; pushes $30 on stack
PLA      ; pops the $30 off the stack

Since bit 4 is set if the cause was a BRK instruction, and clear if it was an IRQ, this allows code to determine the cause of its IRQ handler being invoked, since BRK and IRQ both use the vector at $FFFE:

irq:
        STA temp
        PLA        ; get saved flags off stack
        PHA        ; save again
        AND #$10   ; check bit 4
        BNE caused_by_brk
caused_by_irq:
        ...
caused_by_brk:
        ....

The above is the only way to determine the cause of the irq handler invocation. One might think that the following would work, if one thought that there was a status flag that told when it was a BRK instruction that invoked the IRQ handler:

; wrong way to determine cause of IRQ handler invocation
irq:
        STA temp
        PHP        ; save current flags
        PLA        ; get saved flags off stack
        AND #$10   ; check bit 4
        BNE caused_by_brk
caused_by_irq:
        ...
caused_by_brk:
        ....

This fails because there are only 6 status flags, none of which tell the reason the IRQ handler was invoked. This misunderstanding exists because many descriptions of the 6502 incorrectly state that the processor has 7 status flags, the 7th one being the break flag.

There is no break flag; there are only 6 status flags. As covered above, there are 8 bits in a byte, so when saving a copy of the status flags in memory, these unused two bits must be set to something. On the 6502, bit 5 of the copy is always set, and bit 4 is set BRK or PHP, clear if an interrupt. When restoring the flags from memory, bits 4 and 5 are ignored, since again, there are only 6 status flags, and thus the extra 2 bits of the byte must be ignored.

See also

CPU status flag behavior

Sunsoft 5B audio

The Sunsoft 5B is a superset of the Sunsoft FME-7. It is identical to the FME-7 except it contains extra audio hardware. This audio hardware was only used in one game, Gimmick! Because this game did not use many features of the chip (e.g. noise, envelope), its features are often only partially implemented by emulators.

Contents

1 Registers

1.1 Audio Register Select ($C000-$DFFF)
1.2 Audio Register Write ($E000-$FFFF)
1.3 Internal audio registers

2 Sound

2.1 Tone
2.2 Noise
2.3 Envelope

2.3.1 Period
2.3.2 Shape

2.4 Output

3 References

Registers

The audio hardware is a type of Yamaha YM2149F, which is itself a variant of the General Instrument AY-3-8910 PSG.

Audio Register Select ($C000-$DFFF)

7......0
----RRRR
    ++++- The 4-bit internal register to select for use with $E000

Audio Register Write ($E000-$FFFF)

7......0
VVVVVVVV
++++++++- The 8-bit value to write to the internal register selected with $C000

Internal audio registers

The YM2149F has 16 internal audio registers, selected with $C000 and written to with $E000.

Register | Bitfield | Description
$00 | LLLL LLLL | Channel A low period
$01 | ---- HHHH | Channel A high period
$02 | LLLL LLLL | Channel B low period
$03 | ---- HHHH | Channel B high period
$04 | LLLL LLLL | Channel C low period
$05 | ---- HHHH | Channel C high period
$06 | ---P PPPP | Noise period
$07 | --CB Acba | Noise disable on channels C/B/A, Tone disable on channels c/b/a
$08 | ---E VVVV | Channel A envelope enable (E), volume (V)
$09 | ---E VVVV | Channel B envelope enable (E), volume (V)
$0A | ---E VVVV | Channel C envelope enable (E), volume (V)
$0B | LLLL LLLL | Envelope low period
$0C | HHHH HHHH | Envelope high period
$0D | ---- CAaH | Envelope reset and shape: continue (C), attack (A), alternate (a), hold (H)
$0E | ---- ---- | I/O port A (unused)
$0F | ---- ---- | I/O port B (unused)

Sound

There are three channels that output a square wave tone. In addition there is one noise generator, and one envelope generator, both of which may be shared by any of the three channels.

The 5B's audio is driven by the CPU clock (1.789773 MHz), but like the NES's APU, the YM2149F has an optional clock divider which halves the internal clock speed. By comparison of the produced pitches in Gimmick! with the register values used, it appears that the 5B is a YM2149F operating in this mode. To use an AY-3-8910 as a substitute, you would need an external divider to reduce the clock speed by half.

The frequency formulas given below assume the standard 1.789773 MHz as the Clock value; note that each formula includes an additional divide by 2 to compensate for the YM2149F's internal divider.

Tone

The tone generators produce a square wave with a period controlled by the CPU clock and the 12-bit period value in registers $00-05.

Frequency = Clock / (2 * 16 * Period)
Period = Clock / (2 * 16 * Frequency)

Register $07 controls the mixing of tone and noise components of each channel. A bit of 0 enables the noise/tone on the specified channel, and a bit of 1 disables it. If both bits are 1, the channel outputs a constant signal at the specified volume. If both bits are 0, the result is the logical and of noise and tone.

If bit 4 of registers $08-$0A is set, the volume of the channel is controlled by the envelope generator. Otherwise, it is controlled by the 4-bit value in bits 3-0 of the same register.

Noise

The noise generator produces a 1-bit random wave with a period controlled by the CPU clock and the 5-bit period value in register $06.

Frequency = Clock / (2 * 16 * Period)
Period = Clock / (2 * 16 * Frequency)

It is likely implemented as a 17-bit linear feedback shift register with taps at bits 16 and 13.

Envelope

The envelope produces a ramp that can be directed up or down, or to oscillate by various shape parameters.

Period

The ramp has a frequency controlled by the CPU clock and the 16-bit period value in registers $0B-0C. Note this formula is the frequency of a single ramp, and not individual steps in it.

Frequency = Clock / (2 * 256 * Period)
Period = Clock / (2 * 256 * Frequency)

The YM2149F subdivides divides each ramp into 32 steps. Note that where alternating envelope shapes are used (triangle wave), the resulting pitch of the envelope is one octave down, since one wave cycle requires two ramps (up and down). Because the envelope is primarily intended for low (sub-audio) frequencies, its pitch control is not as accurate in audio frequency ranges as the tone channels.

The AY-3-8910 instead subdivides the ramp frequency by 16, and as a result has half the resolution for its envelopes. Because they both subdivide the same ramp frequency, the ramp's pitch will be the same as long as the clock speeds are equivalent.

Shape

Writing register $0D resets the envelope and chooses its shape. The shape has four parameters: continue, attack, alternate, and hold.

Continue specifies whether the envelope continues to oscillate after the attack. If it is 0, the alternate and hold parameters have no effect.

Attack specifies whether the attack goes from high to low (0) or low to high (1).

Alternate specifies whether the signal continues to alternate up and down after the attack. If combined with hold it provides an immediate flip after the attack followed by the hold.

Hold specifies that the value shall be held after the attack. If combined with alternate, the value at the end of the attack will be immediately flipped before holding.

Value | Continue | Attack | Alternate | Hold | Shape
$00 - $03 | 0 | 0 | x | x | \_______
$04 - $07 | 0 | 1 | x | x | /_______
$08 | 1 | 0 | 0 | 0 | \\\\\\\\
$09 | 1 | 0 | 0 | 1 | \_______
$0A | 1 | 0 | 1 | 0 | \/\/\/\/
$0B | 1 | 0 | 1 | 1 | \¯¯¯¯¯¯¯
$0C | 1 | 1 | 0 | 0 | ////////
$0D | 1 | 1 | 0 | 1 | /¯¯¯¯¯¯¯
$0E | 1 | 1 | 1 | 0 | /\/\/\/\
$0F | 1 | 1 | 1 | 1 | /_______

Output

The tone channels each produce a 5-bit signal which is then converted to analog with a logarithmic DAC. Note that the least significant bit cannot be controlled by the volume register, it is only used by the YM2149F's double-resolution envelope generator. The logarithmic curve increases by 1.5 decibels for each step in the 5-bit signal. This can easily be implemented as a lookup table.

Some emulator implementations that are based on the AY-3-8190 instead treat it as a 4-bit signal with a 3dB per step curve. Since the only extant 5B game does not use the envelope, the difference is unimportant unless accuracy is desired for homebrew 5B work.

The three output channels are mixed together linearly. The output is mixed with the 2A03 and amplified. It is very loud compared to other audio expansion carts.

References

YM2149 datasheet: http://pdf1.alldatasheet.com/datasheet-pdf/view/103366/ETC/YM2149.html
GI AY-3-8910 datasheet: http://www.speccy.org/hardware/datasheet/ay38910.pdf

Categories: Expansion audio

Sunsoft FME-7

FME-7
Sunsoft 5A/5B

Company | Sunsoft
Games | 9 in NesCartDB
Complexity | ASIC
Boards | JLROM, JSROM,
NES-BTR, others
PRG ROM capacity | 512K (FME-7)
256K (5A/5B)
PRG ROM window | 8K×4 + 8K fixed
PRG RAM capacity | 512K (FME-7)
PRG RAM window | 8K
CHR capacity | 256K
CHR window | 1Kx8
Nametable mirroring | H, V, or 1, switchable
Bus conflicts | No
IRQ | CPU cycle counter
Audio | 5B only
iNES mappers | 069

The Sunsoft FME-7 is a mapper IC used by Sunsoft in several of its games. It is nearly identical to the Sunsoft 5A and Sunsoft 5B mapper chips used only in Famicom games, with the 5B notably having expansion audio (see Sunsoft 5B audio).

The FME-7, 5A and 5B are grouped together as iNES Mapper 69.

Both the Sunsoft 5B and FME-7 exist as a 44 pin TQFP chip: diagram

In Europe, boards using the FME-7 were labeled as JSROM and JLROM. The FME-7 mapper was used in only one game released in the US, Batman: Return of the Joker. Many Japanese releases by Sunsoft used the FME-7: Gimmick!, Hebereke, Gremlins 2 (but not in the US version), Barcode World, and others.

Contents

1 Banks
2 Registers

2.1 Command Register ($8000-$9FFF)
2.2 Parameter Register ($A000-$BFFF)

3 Commands

3.1 CHR Bank 0-7 ($0-7)
3.2 PRG Bank 0 ($8)
3.3 PRG Bank 1-3 ($9-B)
3.4 Name Table Mirroring ($C)
3.5 IRQ Control ($D)
3.6 IRQ Counter Low Byte ($E)
3.7 IRQ Counter High Byte ($F)

4 IRQ Operation

4.1 How to Use the IRQ Generator

5 References
6 See also

Banks

CPU $6000-$7FFF: 8 KB Bankable PRG ROM or PRG RAM
CPU $8000-$9FFF: 8 KB Bankable PRG ROM
CPU $A000-$BFFF: 8 KB Bankable PRG ROM
CPU $C000-$DFFF: 8 KB Bankable PRG ROM
CPU $E000-$FFFF: 8 KB PRG ROM, fixed to the last bank of ROM
PPU $0000-$03FF: 1 KB Bankable CHR ROM
PPU $0400-$07FF: 1 KB Bankable CHR ROM
PPU $0800-$0BFF: 1 KB Bankable CHR ROM
PPU $0C00-$0FFF: 1 KB Bankable CHR ROM
PPU $1000-$13FF: 1 KB Bankable CHR ROM
PPU $1400-$17FF: 1 KB Bankable CHR ROM
PPU $1800-$1BFF: 1 KB Bankable CHR ROM
PPU $1C00-$1FFF: 1 KB Bankable CHR ROM

Registers

Configuration of the FME-7 is accomplished by first writing the command number to the Command Register at $8000-9FFF, then writing the command's parameter byte to the Parameter Register at $A000-BFFF.

There are 16 commands:

$0-7 control CHR banking
$8-B control PRG banking
$C controls nametable mirroring
$D-F controls IRQ

On the 5B variant, there are two additional registers at $C000-DFFF and $E000-FFFF that control the audio expansion. See: Sunsoft 5B audio

Command Register ($8000-$9FFF)

7  bit  0
---- ----
.... CCCC
     ||||
     ++++- The command number to invoke when writing to the Parameter Register

Parameter Register ($A000-$BFFF)

7  bit  0
---- ----
PPPP PPPP
|||| ||||
++++-++++- The parameter to use for this command. Writing to this register invokes the command in the Command Register.

Commands

CHR Bank 0-7 ($0-7)

7  bit  0
---- ----
BBBB BBBB
|||| ||||
++++-++++- The bank number to select for the specified bank.

Bank $0 - PPU $0000-$03FF
Bank $1 - PPU $0400-$07FF
Bank $2 - PPU $0800-$0BFF
Bank $3 - PPU $0C00-$0FFF
Bank $4 - PPU $1000-$13FF
Bank $5 - PPU $1400-$17FF
Bank $6 - PPU $1800-$1BFF
Bank $7 - PPU $1C00-$1FFF

PRG Bank 0 ($8)

7  bit  0
---- ----
ERbB BBBB
|||| ||||
||++-++++- The bank number to select at CPU $6000 - $7FFF
|+------- RAM / ROM Select Bit
|         0 = PRG ROM
|         1 = PRG RAM
+-------- RAM Enable Bit (6264 +CE line)
          0 = PRG RAM Disabled
          1 = PRG RAM Enabled

The FME-7 has up to 6 bits for PRG banking (512 KiB), though this was never used in a game. The 5A and 5B, however, support only 5 (256 KiB). The extra address line is instead an audio expansion line, or unused.

It is confirmed that the FME-7 outputs the bank number during accesses to $6000-$7FFF even if RAM is enabled. Though Sunsoft never took advantage of this, it would allow making a cartridge that bank switches up to 256 KiB of PRG RAM. The FME-7 mapper in Loopy's PowerPak mappers, for example, supports 32 KiB.

Open bus occurs if the RAM / ROM Select Bit is 1 (RAM selected), but the RAM Enable Bit is 0 (disabled), i.e. any value in the range $40-$7F. This is a limited form of WRAM write protection on power-up.

NOTE: the enable bit is NOT functional with 2048×8, 32768×8, and 524288×8 RAMs, because those RAMs don't have a +CE input.

There is a tentative report that not all games honor some or any of the bits in this register. Corroboration is needed before any action is taken.

PRG Bank 1-3 ($9-B)

7  bit  0
---- ----
..bB BBBB
  || ||||
  ++-++++- The bank number to select for the specified bank.

Bank $9 - CPU $8000-$9FFF
Bank $A - CPU $A000-$BFFF
Bank $B - CPU $C000-$DFFF

The FME-7 has up to 6 bits for PRG banking, but the 5A and 5B support only 5.

Name Table Mirroring ($C)

These values are the same as MMC1 mirroring modes with the MSB inverted.

7  bit  0
---- ----
.... ..MM
       ||
       ++- Mirroring Mode
            0 = Vertical
            1 = Horizontal
            2 = One Screen Mirroring from $2000 ("1ScA")
            3 = One Screen Mirroring from $2400 ("1ScB")

IRQ Control ($D)

7  bit  0
---- ----
C... ...T
|       |
|       +- IRQ Enable
|           0 = Do not generate IRQs
|           1 = Do generate IRQs
+-------- IRQ Counter Enable
            0 = Disable Counter Decrement
            1 = Enable Counter Decrement

All writes to this register acknowledge an active IRQ.[1] It is not yet known what will happen if this register is written to at the same time as an IRQ would have been generated.

IRQ Counter Low Byte ($E)

7  bit  0
---- ----
LLLL LLLL
|||| ||||
++++-++++- The low eight bits of the IRQ counter

IRQ Counter High Byte ($F)

7  bit  0
---- ----
HHHH HHHH
|||| ||||
++++-++++- The high eight bits of the IRQ counter

Writes to the IRQ counter registers directly set the lower or upper eight bits of the counter. Unlike on MMC3, there is no separate reload latch.

IRQ Operation

The IRQ feature of FME-7 is a CPU cycle counting IRQ generator. When enabled the 16-bit IRQ counter is decremented once per CPU cycle. When the IRQ counter is decremented from $0000 to $FFFF an IRQ is generated. The IRQ line is held low until it is acknowledged.

How to Use the IRQ Generator

Set the counter to the desired number of cycles minus one.
Enable the IRQ generator by turning on both the IRQ Enable and IRQ Counter Enable flags of the IRQ Control command.
Within the IRQ handler, write to the IRQ Control command to acknowledge the IRQ.
Optional: Go back to Step 1 for the next IRQ.

References

↑ Test performed in 2015 by Oliveira using IRQ acknowledge test ROM on NESdev BBS

See also

Sunsoft Mapper by goroh, translated by Sgt. Bowhack.
NES Mapper List by Disch
Comprehensive NES Mapper Document by \Firebug\

Categories: Nintendo licensed mappers, In NesCartDB, ASIC mappers, Mappers with large PRG RAM, Mappers with cycle IRQs

Synthetic instructions

There are several additional instructions that would be nice to have on the NES. Even though not present, they can be synthesized using existing instructions, resulting in synthetic instructions or pseudoinstructions. If turned into assembler macros, they can be used almost as if they were natively supported. Being able to think of them as native instructions lightens the mental load when programming, because instructions are an important tool for abstraction. Even without making the following into macros, after reading them you will be more likely to think of one of these while coding, saying "I need a subtract-from instruction here".

Contents

1 Negate A
2 Reverse subtraction
3 Sign-extend
4 Arithmetic shift right
5 8-bit rotate
6 16-bit increment and decrement
7 X/Y as Operand
8 JMP (addr,X)
9 External links

Negate A

Many processors have a native negate instruction, which subtracts the value from zero. Here we must manually calculate the two's complement of A, which involves a one's complement and increment:

; A = -A
eor #$FF
sec
adc #0

Or if we know carry is clear coming in:

; A = -A
eor #$FF
adc #1

Reverse subtraction

Using SBC, a value can be subtracted from A, but there's no direct way to subtract A from some value. The ARM instruction set includes instructions RSB (reverse subtract) and RSC (reverse subtract with carry) that negate the register and add the value. The 6502 can do this too:

; A = Value - A
eor #$FF
sec
adc Value

As a special case, if we want to subtract A from 255, we can just do

; A = 255 - A
eor #$FF

This also shows another way of understanding the general subtract from; we first subtract A from 255, then add one, so it's as if we subtracted from 256, which is the same as subtracting from zero, since A is only 8 bits.

Sign-extend

When increasing the number of bits in a signed value, the new high bits are filled with copies of the sign bit. This is called sign extension. For example, sign-extending the 8-bit value $80 (-128) to 16 bits sets the new bits, resulting in $FF80; sign-extending $7F (+127) to 16 bits results in $007F. The following sequences calculate the upper byte of the sign-extended value.

        ; calculates upper byte of sign-extension of A
        ora #$7F
        bmi neg
        lda #0
neg:

This constant-time version (7 bytes, 8 cycles) destroys the carry, so don't try using it in the middle of a multi-byte addition:

  asl a     ;  cpx #$80 or cpy #$80 is also possible
  lda #$00
  adc #$FF  ; C is unchanged and A = $00 if C was set or $FF if C was clear
  eor #$FF  ; now all bits of A are set to what bit 7 was

If you're just trying to add an 8-bit delta to a 16-bit value, you could try subtracting 256 from the value by decrementing the high byte if the value is negative and then adding as if it were unsigned.

  lda delta_value
  bpl notneg
  dec value_hi
notneg:
  clc
  adc value_lo
  sta value_lo
  lda #0
  adc value_hi
  sta value_hi

This forum thread describes addition of signed deltas with clamping.

Arithmetic shift right

The ARM instruction set has an arithmetic right shift, which doesn't alter the sign (top) bit. This shift is used to divide a signed value by two. But the 6502 lacks this instruction; LSR doesn't work because it shifts the sign bit to the right, then clears it.

To implement this, we need carry set to the sign bit, then we can use ROR. CMP #$80 performs this task; if the value is less than $80, carry is cleared, otherwise it's set:

; Arithmetic shift right A
cmp #$80
ror a

If the operand is in memory, we just use ASL to move the sign bit into carry:

; Arithmetic shift right Value
lda Value
asl a
ror Value

8-bit rotate

The 65xx series rotate instructions are all 9-bit, not 8-bit as often imagined. If they really were 8-bit, then eight ROR or ROL instructions in a row would leave A with its original value. In actuality, nine are required to do so, since the carry acts as a ninth bit of A.

Similar to arithmetic right shift, we must set carry to the top or bottom bit in advance of the rotate. For 8-bit rotate left, it's simple:

; 8-bit rotate left A
cmp #$80
rol a

; alternate method
asl a
adc #0

For 8-bit rotate right, we must save and restore A:

; 8-bit rotate right A
pha
lsr a
pla
ror a

A could be saved and restored using other methods, like TAX and TXA, etc.

Branching can also be used:

    ; 8-bit rotate right A
    lsr a
    bcc skip
    adc #$80-1 ; carry is set, so will add extra 1
skip:

If the operand is in memory:

; 8-bit rotate left Value
lda Value
asl a
rol Value

; 8-bit rotate right Value
lda Value
lsr a
ror Value

16-bit increment and decrement

Incrementing/decrementing a 16-bit value involves first adjusting the low byte, then adjusting the high byte if necessary. Increment is simpler, since the high byte is adjusted when the low byte wraps around to zero; for decrement, the high byte is adjusted when the low byte wraps around to $FF.

        ; 16-bit increment Word
        inc Word
        bne noinc
        inc Word+1
noinc:

        ; 16-bit decrement Word
        lda Word
        bne nodec
        dec Word+1
nodec:  dec Word

16-bit increment shows even more advantage when used to control a loop, because the 16-bit increment conveniently leaves the zero flag set at the end only if the entire 16-bit value is zero.

X/Y as Operand

Normally X and Y cannot be used as an operand to an instruction operating on A. For example, CMP X isn't possible. Where X or Y needs to be used in such a way, they are usually saved to a temporary variable:

; Compare A with X
stx temp
cmp temp

By putting a 256-byte table in memory with each entry simply having the value of its index, X and Y can be used as operands:

table:  .byte $00,$01,$02,$03,$04,$05,$06,$07,$08,$09,$0A,$0B,$0C,$0D,$0E,$0F
        .byte $10,$11,$12,$13,$14,$15,$16,$17,$18,$19,$1A,$1B,$1C,$1D,$1E,$1F
        ...
        .byte $F0,$F1,$F2,$F3,$F4,$F5,$F6,$F7,$F8,$F9,$FA,$FB,$FC,$FD,$FE,$FF

cmp table,x      ; CMP X

eor table,x      ; EOR X

clc
adc table,y      ; ADC Y

JMP (addr,X)

The JMP (addr,X) instruction is present in later 65xx processors. It behaves like JMP (addr), except it fetches the 16-bit value from addr+X. The least-problematic way to implement this is using RTI:

; Jump to address stored at addr+X
lda addr+1,x
pha
lda addr,x
pha
php
rti

See Jump table for further explanation and alternate approaches.

External links

Pseudoinstructions in MIPS

Talk:Action 53 mapper

Pin count

Do few-enough-pin PALs/CPLDs still exist such that pointing out "there's no reason to connect D6 at all and D7 in mode selection could be changed to D5 and free up another input pin" is even remotely useful?—Lidnariq 19:25, 13 October 2012 (MDT)

It might free up pins in the current design, but I'm thinking ahead to how oversize expansions would work should the time come. And I don't see how you're getting 25 pins; it looks like 28 to me, especially with the equivalent of a 7420 for PRG RAM decoding and bus conflict avoidance included. --Tepples 20:30, 13 October 2012 (MDT)

I don't think I said 25 pins anywhere? Unrelatedly, my having suggested D5 might not be the best because of this future-proofing you said; using D4 or D1 might be cleaner. But regardless, it looks like there aren't any PALs or CPLDs both cheaper and fewer pins than the XC9536XL infiniteneslives had specified in the forum, so I think my initial "hey, maybe..." is irrelevant. —Lidnariq 01:19, 14 October 2012 (MDT)

512-KiB Mode - Is it Possible?

I don't think you can fit a 512-KiB game for use in that mapper right now, I think you can replace a mode, or use a new mode if it fits? I possibly doubt it though due to constraints...

Even then, I like the idea of a multicart like this! --Hamtaro126 01:56, 14 October 2012 (MDT)

An oversize BNROM game will fit, though only one such game at a time unless each game's bank number table is modified to correspond to its position in the cart. This is the same technique that I had planned for BNROM games in Action 53 before I learned that homebrew developers prefer UNROM over BNROM. --Tepples 22:15, 3 November 2012 (MDT)

Writable flash

There are rumors on the BBS that INL will make boards that allow in-circuit programming of the beginning of the PRG flash in 4096 byte sectors as a method for saving the game. An extra 8 KiB of SRAM will be mapped at $6000 for managing a log-structured file system. I think I know how to represent this in NES 2.0: if non-backed and backed PRG RAM are present, the non-backed memory is SRAM at $6000 and the backed memory replaces the first pages of the ROM and is writable through Common Flash Memory Interface sequences. I'm waiting on INL for details before I add it. --Tepples (talk) 20:08, 31 January 2014 (MST)

Talk:APU

This page has ad-hoc protection on it to deter spambots. To reply to a thread or start a new thread:

Unlock this page

Looking at Visual 2A03 and e.g. the sq0_on and sq0_len nodes, it seems that disabling a channel doesn't touch the length counter at all. Rather, there are internal channel enable flags (eg. sq0_on) that get set when the length counter is initialized (presumably only for non-zero values, though I haven't checked) and cleared when either the length counter reaches zero or the channel is disabled. These are the flags you get back from $4015/read as well. Even if this page only describes "abstract APU operation", that's not any more complicated than the current version, so maybe the descriptions should be updated. -Ulfalizer (talk) 23:30, 28 April 2013 (MDT)

Glossary entry for "timer"

The glossary entry for timer says

The triangle channel's timer is clocked on every CPU cycle, but the pulse, noise, and DMC timers are clocked only on every second CPU cycle and thus produce only even periods.

But my understanding is the triangle, noise, and DMC timers are clocked on every CPU cycle, and only the pulse channel timers are clocked on every second CPU cycle. Have I understood correctly? --Bavi H (talk) 21:29, 19 February 2014 (MST)

Then why do noise and DMC timers produce only even periods? --Tepples (talk) 07:22, 20 February 2014 (MST)

The noise and DMC channels use lookup tables to set the period of their timers. It looks like all of the lookup table entries happen to be even.

I've been studying the NES sound capabilities as a hobby, let me know if I've gotten something wrong. Here's what I understand.

From the References section, I read Blargg's NES APU Reference. In that document, the "Timer" section says "All channels use a timer which is a divider driven by the ~1.79 MHz clock." I interpret this to mean all sound channels have a timer clocked by the CPU clock. In the same document, the "Square Channel" section block diagram has a block called "Timer / 2", whereas the block diagrams in all other channels have a block called "Timer".

If I understand correctly, a "Timer / 2" clocked by every CPU clock would be the same as a "Timer" clocked by every other CPU clock. I'm not sure which one it really is implemented as. My main concern was it seems the statement in the glossary may be wrong regarding the noise and DMC timers, if I understand correctly, they are clocked every CPU clock. --Bavi H (talk) 19:02, 20 February 2014 (MST)

The terminology here is problematic. The APU clock, which is used by all audio hardware except the triangle channel, is formed by dividing the CPU clock by two. In practice, the formulæ on this page already include this division, and any differences in implementation will likely only show up on the most pedantic of tests. —Lidnariq (talk) 19:41, 20 February 2014 (MST)

I see. Blargg's document states it's just an functional model that may differ from actual implementation, so I guess it's not usable as proof of how the timers are actually implemented.

To make sure I understand: The lookup tables at APU Noise and APU DMC are in terms of CPU clocks, correct? But you're saying the hardware implementation of the lookup tables are actually in terms of APU clocks (using values that are half those shown in the documents), and the actual noise and DMC timers in hardware are clocked by APU clocks?--Bavi H (talk) 21:11, 20 February 2014 (MST)

You understand correctly. If you go to visual2a03 you can find the signals apu_clk1, apu_/clk2, apu_clk2a, …b, …c, …d, which control this. This is briefly mentioned in Visual circuit tutorial#APU clock signals. —Lidnariq (talk) 23:28, 20 February 2014 (MST)

From a different approach, the DPCM tunings are all evidently a closest match to an A440 tuning scheme (notwithstanding 2 mistakes in the PAL table implementation), but only if we're using half-clocks. If the DPCM tables could have "odd" values in it, the DPCM tuning scheme would have used them to better fit it. More info here: [1] - Rainwarrior (talk) 07:44, 22 February 2014 (MST)

Lengthcounter and Framecounter inconsistency

The page about the APU Framecounter suggests that the Lenghtcounter is clocked twice per sequence (regardless of the Framecounter mode flag). Oddly the documentation for the lengthcunter assumes that it is clocked only once. So what is right? If it is really clocked twice per sequence, the bpm values would be 150 bpm and 180 bpm instead of 75 bpm and 90 bpm. In this case the document would also completely miss that the notes are slower if the framecounter mode flag is set. This would provide two alternative paces of 120 bpm (MSB set) and 144 bpm (MSB clear).

The resource document (Blargg's NES APU Reference) also says that the lengthcounter is clocked twice per sequence.

The length counter is clocked twice per sequence. Where on the Wiki does it say otherwise? (This would need to be corrected.) - Rainwarrior (talk) 14:32, 19 September 2014 (MDT)

Talk:APU basics

I removed some of the comments you added to the initial register values, because the aim of this article is to present a simplified model of the APU, and not require the programmer to bother with anything more. You can add them back if you want, but I'm thinking this should focus on simplicity and getting results, not understanding the APU.

I also removed the use of the round() function, as I didn't feel it would be clear to the intended audience (I put a comment explaining to round the result).

Again, I'm fairly new to Wikis so feel free to explain better ways of handling these than I have. :)

Blargg 15:28, 29 July 2010 (UTC)

Some comments are helpful so that advanced programmers can understand why it's written the way it's written. For instance, the init code that's been on the page the last couple years until now had a nasty side effect where $4014 (OAMDMA) was written during APU init. When I fixed this issue, I made a note explaining why $4014 has to be skipped. While that comment will probably mean nothing to a total newbie, it will prevent other people from trying the same simplification that led to this bug in the first place. - Furrykef (talk) 11:35, 21 August 2016 (MDT)

As I said in the forum, in my personal opinion, this page should be removeed completely from the wiki and any significant about the APU should go to the APU page. I do not see the purpose of this page, and most information is either wrong, incorrect or incomplete. The coding exemples are bad exemples and extremely unrealistic of how a NES game actually uses the APU. I say this as someone who wrote multiple sound engines, and deeply analyzed multiple kinds of sound engines written by other people. Bregalad (talk) 13:34, 22 August 2016 (MDT)

This page doesn't offer any new information about the APU, there's nothing here that would be appropriate to fold back into APU. That's not what this page is for, though, it's a tutorial. Towards the quality of the tutorial, I might make some suggestions:

The init code loop obfuscates what it's doing. I suggested an unrolled version so that details can be explained.
The init code writes $40 to $4017, but then the triangle code writes $C0 to it, which is inconsistent. Should just initialize to $C0?
I would suggest not using $4017 with the triangle code; yes there's a slight delay otherwise, but I think messing with $4017 is an advanced topic. It will still mute during the correct frame without it.
The playing a musical note example should write LO before HI. Not terribly significant to the example, but good practice esp. if you eventually want to use the envelopes, etc.
I think this deserves a note somewhere that is disabling a lot of APU features (envelope, length counter, etc.), doesn't need to describe exactly what, just that the examples are taking a simplified subset approach.
The example code linked at the bottom still has the "unpleasant" $4016 write that started this discussion. A new version should be written and hosted on the wiki.

Aside from these nitpicks, I think it's actually a good tutorial example program. It works, and it seems like a useful simple way to demonstrate how to use the APU channels. What exactly do you find unrealistic about it, bregalad? I mean, obviously most games are going to be loading data from a music/sound engine and not immediate values to feed to the APU registers, but I think all that's separate from just learning to use the APU, i.e. do one first, then the other. - Rainwarrior (talk) 14:18, 22 August 2016 (MDT)

The wiki is not just a reference, but a place for tutorials as well, even if we haven't got all that many at he moment. Hmm…we don't have a Tutorial category yet. Myask (talk) 00:24, 23 August 2016 (MDT)

Then, after renaming the page as "tutorial", and applying all the numerous changes that Rainwarrior suggested in order to make this tutorial stop being so horrible, then yet I do no have anything against keeping the page anymore. But you have to admit, before those changes, this page sucked hard. I still think it's weird to load registers from direct data, but if the intent is just "trying" the APU then this make sense. I'll also suggest adding a link to SNDTEST.NES, which is what I always used to "play with" the APU registers, personally.Bregalad (talk) 12:53, 23 August 2016 (MDT)

So, why is this horrible initialisation loop still there ?Bregalad (talk) 14:02, 25 August 2016 (MDT)

Talk:APU DMC

Similarly to the noise channel, the DPCM channel's frequency counter on the die is a 9-bit linear feedback shift register (with taps at the 5th and 9th bits); when I take the counter values from the on-die ROM and run the LFSR until the result is '100000000', the cycle counts (for NTSC) match once multiplied by 2. --Quietust 05:00, 23 January 2011 (UTC)

I suspect there's no "address increment", but another shift register. Just pay attention to the address wrap - if we had a counter, it would wrap to zero, but instead, it wraps to $8000, like ($10000 >> 1). --Zepper 01:49, 6 June 2011 (UTC)

The generated addresses are linear, and I don't think a shift register can do that. So I'm conjecturing an up-counter here. --Tepples 02:30, 6 June 2011 (UTC)

The DPCM address register is only 15 bits wide (with A15 being connected to the VCC rail @ 2850,5450), and the upper bit (A14) gets initialized to 1 (@ 2565,5365) instead of the last value written to $4012 (and the bottom 6 bits get initialized to 0, but we already know this). --Quietust 03:03, 6 June 2011 (UTC)

DMC find

Looks like the DMC silent flag makes difference for $4011 raw output. If this flag is non-zero, the $4011 value written is ignored by the raw output only. I could test a few NSFs and it works flawlessly. --Zepper 14:53, 14 November 2011 (UTC)

By "the DMC silent flag" do you mean bit 4 of $4015? And what exactly do you mean by "ignored by the raw output only"? Do you mean that values are queued up and take effect after the sample period ends? --Tepples 15:10, 14 November 2011 (UTC)

Well, the silent flag is described in the APU DMC section, "The output unit continuously outputs a 7-bit value to the mixer. It contains an 8-bit right shift register, a bits-remaining counter, a 7-bit delta-counter, and a silence flag". Just read the rest of the APU DMC output unit. About the raw output, I mean the timed writes to $4011 register, as listen in Battletoads (drums) for example. --Zepper 15:31, 14 November 2011 (UTC)

So as I understand it, you're saying that in effect, $4011 writes don't take effect if a sample is not playing. Interesting; is there a test ROM for me to run on my PowerPak? --Tepples 17:20, 14 November 2011 (UTC)

Could you point out the location (within the Visual 2A03) of the hardware responsible for this hypothetical behavior? Because if it's there, I can't see it - the internal signal for "write $4011" comes solely from the address+R/W+CLK lines, and when it's active, it immediately updates the position register (of which only the upper 6 bits are a "delta-counter" - the bottom-most bit is just a simple latch) to match the state of D0-D6. An example, for D6: during a write to $4011, t13375 activates and connects node 13255 to node 10616 (D6), then that updates t13885 and causes node 10957 to be set to the inverse of node 13255, then that updates t13872 and causes node 10881 (PCM_OUT6) to be set to the inverse of node 10957, which works out to be the value of D6. --Quietust 22:55, 14 November 2011 (UTC)

Thanks for verifying it. I suspected it's empirical. It works only when emulating $4011, as such behavior do not exist in the hardware. In short words, it's a trick that can be used for emulation only, avoiding sound pops. Sorry for the inconvenience, if any. --Zepper 00:02, 15 November 2011 (UTC)

I mentioned something similar in the enhancement article. But there's still one problem: What happens when the DMC tries to write back to the position register on the same cycle as a $4011 write? --Tepples 00:23, 15 November 2011 (UTC)

Most of the APU "runs" when M2 is low, while writes to registers happen when M2 is high. The logic that updates the DMC position register appears to be an exception, though - I'm not sure what will happen if a $4011 write happens at the same time as an increment/decrement, but I'm guessing the resulting state would be (position +/- 1) AND (data bits). --Quietust 00:45, 15 November 2011 (UTC)

Well, it's the $4011 position register value (7 bit delta-counter) being treated as wave data (raw) too. Since the silence flag is not zero, the value is ignored as wave data, working as it should be. --Zepper 02:24, 15 November 2011 (UTC)

PAL frequency table

Is this table correct? There are two entries I find really strange, for reasons which I outlined here: http://forums.nesdev.com/viewtopic.php?p=94079#p94079

The two values in question:

$4 : $114 = 276
$C : $062 = 98

I think these should have been:

$4 : $10A = 266
$C : $064 = 100

I don't have a PAL NES to test, but can someone confirm if the table in this article is correct or not? The NTSC table represents a scheme that consistently uses the best match to a tone in an A440 tuning. The PAL table does the same thing except these two pitches which are significantly detuned. Either our table is wrong, or the chip was designed "wrong", and I'm open to either possibility, but as I said I cannot verify for myself. - Rainwarrior 22:50, 18 May 2012 (PDT)

With some help from jrlepage, who has a PAL NES, I have verified that the two frequencies are indeed 276 and 98. I guess they implemented the chip incorrectly. Weird. - Rainwarrior 17:30, 25 July 2012 (PDT)

Just for reference, the table I verified is: 398, 354, 316, 298, 276, 236, 210, 198, 176, 148, 132, 118, 98, 78, 66, 50
- Rainwarrior 17:42, 25 July 2012 (PDT)

Pitch table

I removed the pitch names from the table.

The "pitch table" was really a sample rate table. In the table, the frequencies in Hz are sample points per second, or deltas per second. (When talking about pitch, frequencies in Hz are wave periods per second.) In other words, having pitch names in the table isn't useful. It's as useless as saying CD audio that plays at 44100 samples per second is pitch F11 - 23 cents.

If I've made a mistake, feel free to revert. --Bavi H (talk) 20:53, 28 December 2013 (MST)

The important part of the table is relative pitch. Maybe my table at User:Lidnariq/DPCM_mistuning would be a better presentation of it, I dunno. While it's definitely not useful to say that "4181.71 Hz is C-8 -1.78c", it is useful to point out that "4709.93 Hz is to 4181.71Hz as C-8 -1.78c is to D-8 +4.16c". —Lidnariq (talk) 21:56, 28 December 2013 (MST)

(edit conflict:) I reverted the change. After thinking about it, the table is trying to show the rates were chosen to get particular intervals or a particular scale (not specific pitches). I'm still not comfortable with the absolute pitches in the table (C8 to C11 is at the upper end to above human hearing), but I think I'll leave it there and play around with alternatives before changing it again. --Bavi H (talk) 22:00, 28 December 2013 (MST)

It's not as irrelevant as it may seem. The organization of the DPCM samplerates clearly demonstrates that they were designed to be tuned to a scale. (See this thread.) They happen to be nearly useless for this purpose, especially because of the +1 modifier on the sample length that looks like an accident of the implementation, but the design intent is clear. I agree that it's unfortunately misleading to label them with pitches, but I can't think of a simpler way to express their tuning relationships to each other. You can have a matrix with cents and relative intervals, maybe, but I think using letter pitch names gets the idea across quicker and more easily. - Rainwarrior (talk) 02:05, 29 December 2013 (MST)

As an aside, I've found a use for these pitches in the past when wanting to play a DPCM ramp to adjust triangle volume. By knowing the pitch of the samplerate, I can tune the ramp to a pitch that will be hidden by the existing harmony of the music. - Rainwarrior (talk) 02:06, 29 December 2013 (MST)

Talk:Board table

Old and outdated

Man I can't belive this old and outdated table has been copied to this wiki. Shouldn't a link to the complete and recently updated Bootgod's database be better ?!?Bregalad 18:35, 8 June 2011 (UTC)

This page can be downloaded as HTML and searched offline with Ctrl+F in a web browser. What tool do you recommend for displaying and searching the NesCartDB XML offline? I could make a short Python program that updates this table from the XML; would that be better? --Tepples 19:22, 8 June 2011 (UTC)

You got a point. Although even better, the table could be downloaded in txt. I always throught it could be amazing to have the board list when going to a garage sale and you see games you don't remember which board they use (to use them for donnor cart). Now that I have a powerpak, I don't need devcarts anymore though so this is no problem anymore for me, therefore I didn't think about the offline thing. Your tool in Python sounds good but shouldn't it be a bit hard to do ? Well if you feel like it I'm not preventing anyone from doing it.Bregalad 19:50, 8 June 2011 (UTC)

The Python program wouldn't be too hard. It would go essentially like this: load the XML from NesCartDB, load the existing rarity value for each title (NesCartDB doesn't track these), and then for each title that was released in the NTSC NES region, spit out the mapper number and board name in wiki table format that I can paste here. I might work on it after I finish my current project, which is related to the NESdev compo hosted by NA. --Tepples 01:36, 9 June 2011 (UTC)

Talk:Cartridge connector

Orientation

I'm a little confused about this. Why does the pin orientation for the NES appear to be viewed from underneath the connector? Wouldn't it make more sense if it was a top-down view like on the famicom diagram? - Rainwarrior 20:45, 26 August 2012 (MDT)

Probably to be consistent with standard pinout numbering, which always goes counterclockwise and has pin 1 as top-left. It's also consistent with the edge on the mainboard. Not the best of reasons... —Lidnariq 20:53, 26 August 2012 (MDT)

It make it very counter-intuitive if you're trying to do something related to Famicom<->NES conversion. I could see it being more useful if you're soldering something to the back of a toploader board, but other than that case I find it really confusing. Would you mind if I reversed it to be consistent with the Famicom version? I could reverse the numbers alongside it, if it's important that they stay the same. - Rainwarrior 21:12, 26 August 2012 (MDT)

Ahh, I see that many Nintendo NES carts are numbered in this way, but I still think it'd be better just to have the numbering proceed upside down. As it is right now you would have to be looking at the card-edge upside down to see the same orientation as this diagram (and the numbers on the board would be upside down as well). - Rainwarrior 21:37, 26 August 2012 (MDT)

The hesitations I have to reordering it is 1- that the parallelism between the Famicom and NES header isn't as obvious and 2- the presented pin order isn't consistent with the industry convention. But these aren't good enough reasons for me to stop you. (But they're good enough for me to not do the edit myself)—Lidnariq 23:21, 26 August 2012 (MDT)

Okay, I have reversed the NES diagram. The numbering in both diagrams is consistent with the numbering on Nintendo PCBs, so I made no changes to that. I don't know what industry convention is for numbering pins of a card-edge connector, but I don't think it's relevant here, since Nintendo provided their own numbering on their PCBs (and if one of them meets the industry standard, the other is backwards). I added some notes about the orientation and how the two systems relate to each other. - Rainwarrior 10:47, 27 August 2012 (MDT)

What is the industry convention for card edges? I'm used to pin orders being counter-clockwise around a chip from the top. Is it different for a card edge? The Nintendo boards are numbered left to right on one side, right to left on the other, rather than clockwise or counterclockwise around the board. - Rainwarrior 12:41, 27 August 2012 (MDT)

I meant "same as IC convention", but I think industry convention for card edges is (letter)(pin number) in line, without any rotation. e.g. ISA has A01-A31, B01-B31, C01-C18, D01-D18, arranged as

B01 B02 … B30 B31   D01 … D18
A01 A02 … A30 A31   C01 … C18

—Lidnariq 12:52, 27 August 2012 (MDT)

CIRAM A10

If you connect CIRAM A10 to PA6 (the adjacent pin), will this work for a fixed single page mirroring (it won't actually be contiguous in RAM but as far as I can tell it could work)? If so, do any known cartridges do this? --Zzo38 14:44, 23 September 2012 (MDT)

Audio In vs Out

Just curious about this change: http://wiki.nesdev.com/w/index.php?title=Cartridge_connector&diff=5344&oldid=4339

The descriptions on this page of Audio Out and Audio In are relative to the Famicom, not the cartridge, so "Audio Out" means out from the 2A03, and "Audio In" means audio in from the cart. Is that in line with the change you made, Lidnariq? (And if not, perhaps we should revise the descriptions, and/or use a more descriptive naming than In/Out to avoid future confusion.) - Rainwarrior (talk) 21:46, 19 January 2013 (MST)

Good point. I changed it because I'd noticed I'd RE'd the SS5B schematic incorrectly due to misunderstanding the names, but I agree that "in" and "out" are insufficiently unambiguous. So now this should be plenty clear.—Lidnariq (talk) 23:34, 19 January 2013 (MST)

Talk:Clock rate

Divider

Ok, ok. I went to the visual2A03, saw that Quietust had implemented a "microstep" function which drives the 2A03's clock input (instead of the inside 6502's φ0 input), and so tested this. In the 2A03, the input clock is implemented using a Johnson counter, which intrinsically divides by an even number. They couldn't use the same design to divide by 15, so they instead divided by 16.

Interestingly, there is even two more unused bits on this divider (off the bottom), so maybe by the time they made the 2A03G's die they had unified the 2A07 and 2A03 designs sufficiently to just be a "move this tap from here to here".

Dividing by 15 would have required an entire different design, and I suspect that the smallest ÷15 circuit (4 bit binary counter plus 4-input AND gate) would have taken more silicon die space than the 8-stage Johnson counter they used. —Lidnariq 00:05, 4 September 2012 (MDT)

The CIC uses a polynomial counter for the program counter to save die space. How hard would it have been to use a 4-bit linear feedback shift register to divide by 15? I guess there would have to be some post-decoding of the LFSR's state to produce a binary clock signal, and that might have taken a lot of space too. --Tepples 08:13, 4 September 2012 (MDT)

Right, that would have required at least a 2-input XOR gate. I'm not clear on whether 4 bits of shift register plus the smallest 2-input XOR gate (implementated as an and-or-invert and an inverter, no P-type MOSFETs so no transmission gates yet) is bigger, but regardless none of the internal bits of state are even close to a 50% duty cycle at ≈1.8MHz, and converting that back would definitely have been more silicon space. Meanwhile, a design with a synchronous 4-bit counter that skipped state 0b1111 would have required 4 JK registers, and one each of a 2-, 3-, and 4- input AND gate.—Lidnariq 13:25, 4 September 2012 (MDT)

I don't know if it's a requirement of the output, but a johnson counter very conveniently has each bit output equal time high and low, doesn't it? If you an effective 15x divide with equal time high/low, would you actually need a 30x divider that is clocked twice as fast? - Rainwarrior 12:20, 4 September 2012 (MDT)

While other microcontroller datasheets specify fairly strict requirements on duty cycle, the 6502 datasheet only specifies that φ0 high and low times both need to be at least 240ns (2MHz binned parts). A nonuniform division should have been ok as long as it complied with that part; for the PAL CPU they probably could have divided it into 6.5 (240ns×26.6MHz=6.4) and 8.5 safely but no further. To answer the other half: yes, so you'd need a design that reacted to both rising and falling edges from the master clock. Possible, but bigger, and probably easier to use a binary counter. —Lidnariq 13:25, 4 September 2012 (MDT)

I slightly misspoke: In the 2A0x, two Johnson counters are used, each clocked on opposite edges, and a NOR gate (output is node 11200) combines the two phases. —Lidnariq 16:47, 17 January 2013 (MST)

Kev tells me the "In the 2A03" link is broken. Did you mean this? Perhaps die shots from a Dendy CPU might help. --Tepples 15:50, 17 January 2013 (MST)

Looks like Q replaced the traditional view with the expert one. Fixed my link. Dollars to doughnuts that the Dendy implements its ÷15 with an arithmetic up-counter and a 4-input AND gate. —Lidnariq 16:47, 17 January 2013 (MST)

NTSC frequency

Where did 1.78977267 MHz come from? Why is it not 1.78977273? It's only 30ppb error, insignificant by NTSC's 3ppm requirement, but it's odd. —Lidnariq (talk) 16:56, 14 November 2014 (MST)

Probably the master clock (21.477272 MHz), rounded to the nearest Hz, then divided by 12. --Tepples (talk) 17:16, 14 November 2014 (MST)

Talk:CNROM

Bankswitching and $2007 reads

I wonder if this info is any useful, especially the second sentence :

Many CNROM games such as Milon's Secret Castle store data tables in otherwise unused portions of CHR ROM and access them through $2007 reads. If an emulator can show the title screen of the NROM game Super Mario Bros., but CNROM games don't work, the emulator's $2007 readback is likely failing to consider CHR ROM bankswitching.

The technique to read non-graphics data from CHR ROM is of course worth mentioning, there's no doubt about that, but I don't feel like this is the right page to mention it, as it has nothing to do with CNROM / mapper 3 itself, in fact games using all kind of mappers does that (Super Mario Bros (NROM), Tiny Toons Adventure 2 (MMC3), Batman - Return of the Joker (FME-7), etc....) This should be mentioned on a page which deals directly with CHR-ROM or something.

As for emulators where the title screen of SMB works, and that Milon's Secret Castle doesn't work, well how many of them there are ? I really see zero pertinence in this sentence. Bregalad (talk) 01:40, 5 May 2014 (MDT)

People tend to implement the simpler mappers first, so they're more likely to collide with this failure mode while implementing NROM and CNROM long before they could notice it with MMC3 or FME7. I can see an argument that the information belongs only in Tricky-to-emulate games, but it fits very nicely in the lede here, and Tricky-to-emulate games is a poorly-organized info dump... —Lidnariq (talk) 03:20, 5 May 2014 (MDT)

I understand, but what is emu-dev stuff doing just below the headline of a mapper/hardware page ? I'm not saying the info is useless, just that it is out of place. The fact another page is a poorly-organized info dump is not an excuse to leave info that doesn't belong to here here.Bregalad (talk) 04:03, 5 May 2014 (MDT)

1- A mention of this problem in some form belongs on this page anyway, because emulator authors will implement CNROM before the more complicated games that combine backswitching with 2007 reads.
2- Removing this germane, clear, and unambiguous piece of information is of negative utility without a better place to put it. —Lidnariq (talk) 12:55, 5 May 2014 (MDT)

Security Diodes

About the security diodes, I noticed that a Japanese Gradius board has slots for 4 diodes instead of 2 (but only 2 are used). Surprisingly, many non-Nintendo made boards cloning the CNROM mapper (Konami, Taito, Bandai) also have those same diodes. Considering how few sense those makes, it's very surprising they would all use them, isn't it ? Bregalad (talk) 01:40, 5 May 2014 (MDT)

I've moved the NROM diode discussion to Talk:NROM; it doesn't belong here. —Lidnariq (talk) 12:55, 5 May 2014 (MDT)

Talk:Comparison of Nintendo mappers

Mapper Wizard

I don't really like the mapper wizard (for one thing it doesn't seem to mention how much PRG RAM you need, and doesn't have a lot of choices), which is one of the reasons why I made User:Zzo38/mapperlist. However, that list is incomplete; can you help with it? Perhaps more information would be useful in there too, such as the number of 74xx series ICs, etc, and then we can improve it and use that list of mappers to make up a lot of things, such as SQL queries to select one, or a wiki article listing them in various tables, etc. --Zzo38 (talk) 17:25, 23 June 2013 (MDT)

Have you seen User:Lidnariq/MMC3_Variants ? In any case, if you want more than 8KiB PRG-RAM, your only choices are MMC1 and MMC5. Period. Also, I'm really not clear what's up with the template stuff you've put on your userpage there; it makes it completely illegible. —Lidnariq (talk) 17:57, 23 June 2013 (MDT)

OK, I have seen it now, and that helps a bit too. Note that I mean in general; I don't only mean the program with 64K PRG RAM (which I was going to write a Z-machine interpreter for versions 1 to 3; however, MMC5 works too and makes some things easier to program in, although it is a more complicated mapper so it might discourage someone who want to make a cartridge of it; MMC5 is probably also needed if I extend it to version 4 and 5 of Z-machine). The reason the template stuff is used, is that you can easily add new fields when needed and then you can call it as a template from another template with a callback, to make tables and so on in the wiki, and it could be converted into other formats such as SQL and so on using external programs too. --Zzo38 (talk) 23:17, 23 June 2013 (MDT)

What exactly are you making that needs more than 8 KiB? Is it working memory or save memory? --Tepples (talk) 19:45, 23 June 2013 (MDT)

Working memory; it is a Z-machine interpreter (see above). However, note that when I mention the mapper list, I don't mean only for this program; I mean in general it can be useful for various purposes. However, if I make a different text adventure system for the Famicom (where the same authoring system can compile into Z-machine format), then a simple variant of UNROM (with 8K PRG RAM added and changed from CHR RAM to CHR ROM) should be sufficient (although some emulators might fail to support it anyways; looking at the FCEUX source codes it seems to fail to support such a variant of UNROM and I cannot find another discrete mapper doing such a thing). --Zzo38 (talk) 23:17, 23 June 2013 (MDT)

Actually, instead of UNROM, I could use MMC4 to emulate it but write the program in such a way that it works even if discrete logic is used to implement only the PRG RAM and the PRG ROM 16K bank switching and even if it has bus conflicts, but also works with MMC4. However, I don't know if there is a similar thing to be done with a game written to use MMC5 and converted to discrete logic. --Zzo38 (talk) 01:58, 24 June 2013 (MDT)

MMC5 has no registers outside of $5xxx. You could implement it such that writes to $5115 are mirrored to $C000 or whatever. You may also want to put the "how to make a reproduction using hardware that's not MMC5" guide inside the ROM so that it can't be separated. —Lidnariq (talk) 12:15, 24 June 2013 (MDT)

Thank you; I think this can help. (I am not sure that the instructions should be inside of the ROM; I could put them in another file too which is in the same ZIP archive.) --Zzo38 (talk) 16:16, 24 June 2013 (MDT)

Talk:CPU pin out and signal description

Pin 30

The signal from pin 30 goes through the exact same "processing" as the chip's /RESET signal (which includes a Schmitt trigger), at which point it goes to the output logic for the M2 pin (don't know exactly what it does) and then through an inverter which goes to the enables for $4018-$401A and to some other spots (seemingly related to the data buffer used for Sprite DMA). Bit 7 of the writable register at $401A seems to propagate to numerous locations within the sound channels and thus might be responsible for the observation of all writable registers disappearing. --Quietust 16:49, 29 April 2011 (UTC)

When pin 30's input is "processed" it gets inverted, just like with the /RESET pin (since transistors themselves are active-high) - that signal then gets inverted again (so it's now equal to pin 30's input, normalized) and NORed together with the inverted +RESET signal (so it's also the actual state of the input signal), and that result goes to the M2 pin's output logic; thus, if pin 30 is pulled high, then M2 will not be tri-stated during RESET. --Quietust 20:33, 7 May 2011 (UTC)

The area where pin 30 goes which I thought was part of the Sprite DMA buffer is actually the logic that controls the R/W pin and the direction of the data pins (it puts the data pins in output mode to handle reading from internal registers), and pulling pin 30 high forces all of $4000-$401F to become internal registers (instead of just $4015). This means that pulling pin 30 high will effectively disable the joypad read ports (but not the write port) - the read enables will still go low, but the CPU won't get any of the data. I'm guessing the designers figured it'd be simpler to do it that way than to combine the 3 read enable signals for $4018-$401A. --Quietust 15:21, 9 May 2011 (UTC)

Given Lidnariq's edits to the main article, has this actually been tested and verified against actual hardware? --Quietust 19:58, 14 September 2011 (UTC)

I've just performed a test with my CopyNES (removed the CPU, carefully bent pin 30 up, then plugged it in and clipped a wire between it and VCC) and I can confirm that registers $4018-$401A do behave as described here - reading $4018-$401A returns the output values of each channel, writing $401A bits 0-4 sets the triangle channel position, and setting $401A bit 7 freezes all of the channels. I can also confirm that the joypad ports no longer work, though they still seem to return open bus - presumably, it's actually coming from inside the chip. Additional confirmation would be highly desirable. --Quietust 18:28, 16 September 2011 (UTC)

Will it work OK if pin 30 and pin 7 are wired together? Is someone able to try this to see what happens? --Zzo38 (talk) 16:24, 1 January 2014 (MST)

If by "work OK" you mean "permit access to $4018-$401A without breaking $4016-$4017 by making debug mode only activate when accessing $4008-$400F/$4018-$401F/etc.", then the answer is probably "yes", but I don't have the means to test that right now. --Quietust (talk) 09:50, 2 January 2014 (MST)

M2

M2 goes high 1.5 clock cycles (i.e. three clock edges from the 21.477272MHz master clock) before Φ2, but it goes low at the same time as Φ2.

Would it be okay to still mention the 6502 input clock (Φ0) in conjunction with M2? It helped me a lot when I realized they're "basically" the same (i.e. when reading [1]), and it's pretty easy to miss still scanning through the description. -Ulfalizer (talk) 19:05, 9 April 2013 (MDT)

I feel like that point belongs with CLK instead of M2; does my last edit satisfy?—Lidnariq (talk) 20:18, 9 April 2013 (MDT)

Stating that M2 is (roughly) the CPU clock cuts down the chain of inference a bit, and it's handy knowledge even for code monkeys like me when trying to figure out timing diagrams and the like. I'll see if I can come up with some reasonable middle ground. :) -Ulfalizer (talk) 20:24, 9 April 2013 (MDT)

I guess the "(φ0 is in turn inverted to form φ1, which is then inverted to form φ2.)" part could be removed if you feel it's getting too verbose/redundant. -Ulfalizer (talk) 20:51, 9 April 2013 (MDT)

LGTM. —Lidnariq (talk) 20:58, 9 April 2013 (MDT)

Talk:CPU power up state

Parts of the APU which appear to be affected by reset (determined by tracing the reset signal throughout the chip):

Square channel volume/envelope timer (not the reload value at $4000/$4004 bits 0-3) and counter (the actual volume output)
Noise channel volume/envelope timer (not the reload value at $4008 bits 0-3) and counter (the actual volume output)
Square channel frequency counter, including the 3 duty cycle bits
Triangle channel frequency counter
Noise channel frequency counter, sort of - it forces the LFSR input to 0, so a very short reset pulse might only partially clear it
DPCM channel frequency counter, sort of - it forces the LFSR input to 0, so a very short reset pulse might only partially clear it
Noise channel frequency ($400E bits 0-3)
Square channel sweep counter
All 4 length counters
All 5 channel enables ($4015)
Triangle channel linear counter (not the reload value at $4008)
Triangle channel Position
DPCM channel Sample Length counter (not the reload value)
DPCM channel Position ($4011)
DPCM channel Sample Buffer and Bit Counter
DPCM channel Sample Address counter (not the reload value)
DPCM channel state machine
Sprite DMA address counter and state machine
Part of the Frame Counter (notably, not the two writable bits of $4017)
Debug register $401A bit 7

--Quietust 16:40, 8 June 2011 (UTC)

Detecting User Reset

Is there way using common mappers to check if power on or reset button pushed? --Zzo38 18:35, 10 September 2012 (MDT)

Common practice seems to be "put a canary in memory, if it's still there assume warm (re)boot instead of cold boot. e.g., Galaxian puts the programmer's name in $0100-$010F, and if it's there on boot, it doesn't clear high scores or the easter egg counter.—Lidnariq 19:47, 10 September 2012 (MDT)

Consistent RAM power-up state?

I tested my NES and Famicom today with a simple ROM that just displays the contents of RAM. I get widely varying results at power-on. I tried leaving the system off for varying amounts of time between powerings, but I don't see much consistency at all. Here's some examples of what I've seen:

Mostly $FF.
Mostly some specific byte, e.g. $E7.
Repeating patterns like $00 $FF $00 FF, often in consistent lines of 16 or 32 bytes.
Often I get groups with a specific byte value, especially in columns (using rows of 16).

All of these patterns are heavily subject to noise. Sometimes a lot of noise, sometimes only a little. Really I don't see much consistent behaviour at all on my NES.

My Famicom usually powers up with mostly a repeating 16 byte pattern of 00FF00FF00FF00FFFF00FF00FF00FF00, often with one or many columns of bytes (using rows of 16) that look completely random in contrast to that pattern. Occasionally the Famicom powers up with different patterns than this too.

I finally got an opportunity to test this myself. My Front loading NES powers on with a 32 byte base pattern that's briefly described as "data = ((addr>>0 ^ addr>>2 ^ addr>>4 ^ addr>>5) & 1) * 0xff" with some pattern of toggled bits I have not discerned yet. Ns43110 (talk) 11:58, 21 January 2016 (MST)

The recommendation for specific values at $0008/9/A/F seems bizarre to me. Why is this in the article at all? These bytes are not particularly consistent on either of my machines, and certainly don't match these magic values. A few quick power cycles sometimes seems to leave some bytes alone, but I don't see anything special about 8/9/A/F?

Nowhere does it say that it's a recommendation. Those are simply results from a test (I believe from blargg). --Thefox (talk) 16:24, 5 October 2015 (MDT)

Two emulator authors seemed to have taken it as some kind of recommendation (NEStopia and puNES), so I think at the very least I think we need a better description of what should be expected. I don't see any value at all in describing these 4 magic values here, personally. - Rainwarrior (talk) 18:25, 5 October 2015 (MDT)

I'm not certain the idea that it should be "mostly FF" is particularly good either. On my Famicom, it looks like 50/50 for a randomly selected bit (though with a high probability of fitting the pattern listed for any specific bit). On my NES, I'd guess there's might be a slight bias toward 1 bits, but I really don't think that's a very useful piece of information given how random it is, and how often there are repetitive (and different) patterns in the bits.

I'm curious what other people might see on their machines.

- Rainwarrior (talk) 16:07, 5 October 2015 (MDT)

My NES (RAM is a LH5116) is mostly $FF, although random bits are randomly clear. It's often patterned with a stride of 32 bytes. —Lidnariq (talk) 18:39, 5 October 2015 (MDT)

Talk:Errata

To-do list

Some things to add by people who know what these refer to:

PPU: must wait a couple of vblanks before chip is fully active

PPU: can't reliably write to ports more often than several CPU cycles apart

Page-crossing pointer quirks:

JMP ($nnnn)

($nn),Y

($nn,X) -- Blargg (talk) 18:03, 21 October 2013 (MST)

That's something personal, but I don't think zero-page overflowing is a caveat at all... after all it's called zero-page adressing, so it's suppose to address bytes in zero page. If it would overflow into page 1 THEN it'd be a caveat, but apparently it's not the case.Bregalad (talk) 15:09, 23 May 2014 (MDT)

A terminology issue... I think it's a caveat, but not an errata. It's by design, not a flaw in the implementation (errata), but it is something the programmer needs to be aware of (caveat). - Rainwarrior (talk) 15:54, 23 May 2014 (MDT)

I don't understand this caveat

 In horizontal or 4-screen mirroring, writing $2000 at the exact start of horizontal blanking may cause the PPU to start reading from the first pattern table instead of the second.
 (Workaround: Don't disable NMI during active picture. Instead, use a variable to lock out reentrant NMI.)

Can someone rewrite it with a better wording so that non-native english speakers understand it ? Bregalad (talk) 05:12, 4 November 2013 (MST)

Errata in the errata? Chalk it up to Muphry's law. --Tepples (talk) 15:54, 4 November 2013 (MST)

This was the SMB bug where on 1/3 power-ons, the PPU alignment allows the mid-screen write to $2000 to interfere with the nametable selection on the next line if perfectly (unfortunately) timed. It results in one line of the screen being rendered with the wrong nametable. What do you think would help the wording, Bregalad? Rainwarrior (talk) 09:52, 5 November 2013 (MST)

Sorry to confuse... I already edit-ninja'd the thing he was confused by. Look at my change —Lidnariq (talk) 11:40, 5 November 2013 (MST)

OK now I think I understand the problem, but I don't see how the "workarround" proposed is related to the problem in any way - which leads me to think I might have misunderstanded the problem in the 1st place.

So my understanding is that, writing to $2000, in any scanline, at a particular PPU clock cycle, will force the nametable bit to '0', even if D0 of the data written to $2000 is 1. Is my understanding correct ? In this case the workarround would be sure to make write to $2000 early enough so they happen before HBlank, right ? I don't see why this is related to NMIs in any way.Bregalad (talk) 01:05, 23 May 2014 (MDT)

It's related because disabling/enabling NMIs is in the same register as the upper nametable selection bits. Also, "just have to write to $2000 before hblank" isn't useful advice without some way to know when in the frame you are (whether timed code, irq, polling: all of which are more complicated than "use a semaphore to prevent reentry") —Lidnariq (talk) 03:12, 23 May 2014 (MDT)

Ok so did I understand the caveat correctly ? I still see no point between it and NMIs, in fact with your post I noted that yes, the NMI enable bit is in the same register as upper scrolling bits, but if the user is writing to $2000 outside of VBlank for adjusting scrolling horizontally, and has control of the timing, so it's always possible to adjust the timing to prevent scrolling glitches caused by it.

The problem observed was using $2000 to disable NMI on entry to your NMI routine to prevent re-entry, and then using $2000 when the routine is finished to re-enable the NMI (timing for this is not consistent). If you don't know about this conflict, it seems like a valid solution to prevent re-entrant NMI. Since it was used in Super Mario Bros. it would be easy to assume this is a problem free technique, but it is not, as we have determined. The other place this conflict will come up would be for some sort of scanline split of a rendering state, which, yes, you should be able to easily time to avoid writing $2000 on the wrong cycle. - Rainwarrior (talk) 11:11, 23 May 2014 (MDT)

Oh, OK, I got it now. Not that it was clearly worded in the 1st place...Bregalad (talk) 14:41, 23 May 2014 (MDT)

Unofficial instructions

I just want to point out that more games rely on not simply connecting CIRAM/CE to PPU/A13 than using unofficial instructions, and there are plenty of clones that disable that control. Furthermore, if they use a non-NMOS implementation of the CPU, many of the unofficial opcodes would require extra effort to implement.

On the other hand, the A53 cart contains two games that use the MUSE replay engine, which uses AXS and LAX (zz),y and I don't think we've had anyone unable to run it as a result. — Lidnariq (talk) 17:18, 12 December 2013 (MST)

Talk:Family Computer Disk System

Contents

1 Typo?
2 $eb13
3 VRAM Buffer
4 Pinout
5 QDI format

Typo?

I think there was a mistake in the document, it said that GetDiskInfo was at E23A, and that makes no sense since it overlaps with another function. Another document said it was E32A (not E23A), so I changed it. --Dwedit 21:37, 11 October 2010 (UTC)

Yes, it was a typo. Thank you for correcting it Bregalad 11:14, 12 October 2010 (UTC)

$eb13

Given a few minutes of analysis, the routine at $eb13 appears to read the Family basic keyboard state into $00-$08. --Quietust 13:31, 13 October 2010 (UTC)

Great finding Q ! What about completing the article about it ? Now only $e8b3 and $e94f are still somewhat obscure. Bregalad 21:03, 13 October 2010 (UTC)

VRAM Buffer

I'm trying to learn how the FDS works (hence my efforts to tidy up descriptions and such), and I'm a little confused. There's a buffer at $3xx which is what the various PrepareVRAMString routines and such copy to/from, but it doesn't support fills and doesn't support 32-byte increment? WriteVRAMBuffer is what you use to actually copy the $3xx buffer into VRAM, correct?

That seems a little less useful than just simply using VRAMStructWrite, pointing to $0302, and gaining access to the extra features like fill and 32-byte increment. --Drag 17:27, 26 February 2012 (PST)

You are correct. The missing future are fill, 32-byte increment, but also sub-structures. The advantage, however, is that the second routine (WriteVRAMBuffer) is way faster than the first (VRAMStructWrite), as it doesn't have to check for those flags (which aren't available any longer), and uses direct addressing $302,X instead of indirect addressing to access the buffer. So the second routine is more suited to do VRAM updates during VBlank, while the first routine is more suited to do bulk updates during forced blanking, although technically both can do both. BTW thanks for fixing/correcting my work.Bregalad 12:33, 27 February 2012 (PST)

VRAM updates during VBlank like writing a column of a horizontally scrolling background? --Tepples 12:38, 27 February 2012 (PST)

Well....... Then you either upload it a tile at a time or call the slow routine (both will be slow) or write your own (fast).Bregalad 13:18, 27 February 2012 (PST)

Thanks! I wanted to see if it would be better to use the one in the BIOS first, before I went straight to just using my own. Thank you for clearing that up for me. :D --Drag 18:01, 27 February 2012 (PST)

Pinout

Do you have information of Famicom Disk System pinout? --Zzo38 11:43, 28 September 2012 (MDT)

QDI format

I want to mention this here in case someone finds it useful. A .QDI file is a raw disk image for a single side of a single disk (including gaps, checksums, full size, etc). In order for an emulator to support it, I recommend the following:

If loading a .NES ROM image with mapper 20, it should treat it as a BIOS ROM and start the FDS with no disk inserted. If a hard or soft reset is requested, and any .QDI is inserted, it should boot that disk side; if none is inserted, it should boot from no disk.
If loading a .FDS disk image, it should enable the "insert disk 1 side A" and so on, and treat it as it already does. (Some emulators may make a private copy in the user's home directory for saving (maybe even converting to .QDI upon first loading!); others may overwrite the existing .FDS instead.)
If loading a .QDI disk image, it should boot from that one, and have a "insert .QDI" option.
If possible, the emulator should use the underlying filesystem's read-only flag (or otherwise determine if it is read-only) to determine how to set the write-protect flag in the FDS registers.

--Zzo38 (talk) 10:31, 4 November 2013 (MST)

Talk:Fixed cycle delay

Contents

1 No requirements missing from most examples?
2 Page size problematic? Maybe the wiki sin't the best place for exhaustive permutations...
3 Formalizing random writes
4 What is the point of this ridiculously huge page?
5 Tool suggestions

No requirements missing from most examples?

Shouldn't there be a "no requirements" entry for every example? Isn't that the natural maximum byte size / endpoint for each of these? - Rainwarrior (talk) 20:14, 16 March 2016 (MDT)

It is not possible to do 3-cycle delay without any requirements. The best you can get is JMP *+3 which requires relocations, but does not have any execution-time side-effects. Additionally, "no requirements" would always involve a long sequence of "NOP"s followed by a "JMP" if the cycle count is odd. To reduce the size of the page, I omitted these for larger delays, and additionally started considering "writes to stack" harmless from 64 cycles onwards, because in most applications it is. --Bisqwit (talk) 15:02, 17 March 2016 (MDT)

Page size problematic? Maybe the wiki sin't the best place for exhaustive permutations...

I'm noticing the wiki has some serious problems trying to diff some of the history on this page. I noticed this edit with the comment "Further tweak code to prefer repeated sequences, because reducing the page size helps fend off MediaWiki crashing". Given the explosive nature of permutations here, maybe it would be better to just implement this as a javascript tool on a webpage, and link it from here? (Would also be nice because you could just dial in constraints, etc.) - Rainwarrior (talk) 21:02, 16 March 2016 (MDT)

I'd recommend splitting them by 2-19, 20-100, 100-200, etc. --Tepples (talk) 09:40, 17 March 2016 (MDT)

I agree with principle on a Javascript tool, but there is the problem that finding these delay options is rather CPU-time intensive. The running time for my generator program is O(n^2) for the number of cycles to delay. This bodes badly with a tool that would run in the browser. --Bisqwit (talk) 15:18, 17 March 2016 (MDT)

All O(n^2) tells me is that if n gets large enough, execution times would eventually be unbearable, but n isn't unbounded here. Does generating a single case really take a significant amount of time for, say, n=200? How long does the whole table take? - Rainwarrior (talk) 16:53, 17 March 2016 (MDT)

Just to be clear, I'm not really trying to pressure you into rewriting it as javascript; I don't have any need for such a tool, I'm just asking from a standpoint of outside curiosity. - Rainwarrior (talk) 16:56, 17 March 2016 (MDT)

A program in JavaScript need not necessarily run in browser, but could also be able to run on command-line by Node.js. (It would be possible also to write a JavaScript program that can detect it so that it work on a webpage but also it will work on a if you download it and run it on Node.js too; for example if(this && this.document) is one way to detect) --Zzo38 (talk) 10:47, 22 April 2016 (MDT)

Formalizing random writes

"it is difficult to formalize the rules under which one could write to such random addresses."

A write to a random address in a 256-byte page is fine if all addresses in the page are decoded to nothing, to a read-only memory, to a read-only port without side effects, or to memory that will be overwritten later. Most NES mappers decode $4100-$41FF to nothing. In addition, many games use $0200-$02FF, $0300-$03FF, or $0700-$07FF to hold a display list rebuilt from scratch every frame; if the delay occurs before the next rebuild of the display list, there is no conflict. --Tepples (talk) 09:43, 17 March 2016 (MDT)

I tried to think of a way to use "INC abs,X" in a partial-instruction context, but without any additional game-specific knowledge, there are only a few addresses where one can write safely. Here's a sample:

A9 FE    LDX #$FE ; hides 'INC $FDD0,X'
D0 FD    BNE *-1

This would read from $FDCE, read from FECE, and then write to FECE. Writing to $8000-$FFFF is unsafe in several mappers, so I tried a bit different approaches.

A9 FE    LDX #$3E ; hides 'ROL $3FE0,X'
E0 3F    CPX #$3F
D0 FB    BNE *-3

This would read from $3F1E (maps to $2006; write-only register, so reading is safe), and then read and write $401E (unmapped, so access is safe). This would be completely safe. Similar combinations were found for each RMW operation (limited by the value of X which doubles as the RMW opcode number). However, there is no guarantee that the code will not loop infinitely, because the branch instruction is not masked on the second iteration, unlike in the previous sample. If the second opcode was 1-byte long, then the first byte of the branch instruction would be masked, but the second byte would still be executed. The only byte that would work for the second byte of the branch instruction would be F8, which means the code would have to be at least 9 bytes long, which further complicates matters.

If branches and partial-instruction execution are not involved, then it bears down to how to set up X in such manner that a wrap is guaranteed, and whether the setup code + the RMW instruction are short enough for the number of cycles they consume.

I am yet to think of a way where RMW abs,X can be used. I was able to incorporate INC zp,X in a few situations where X is known to be zero, though. Of course if you can know a certain page is free for tampering, something could be devised. There might also be benefit if it is known some zp address contains a pointer to another address that can be read/written safely. The addresses I considered unsafe for reading were 4015-4017, 4020-5FFF, and (&7 in (2,7)) in 2000-3FFF. The addresses I considered unsafe for writing were everything except 4018-401F, and (&7==2) in 2000-3FFF. --Bisqwit (talk) 15:18, 17 March 2016 (MDT)

Why include all 6 variations on INC $0200,X? Isn't this trivial? - Rainwarrior (talk) 16:28, 30 March 2016 (MDT)

In this article it is admittedly trivial, but the code comes from a generator that also considers INC $02xx,X instructions in contexts where half of the instruction is hidden in another instruction, which puts more constraints onto which memory addresses can be used. It just happens to be that within the first 160 samples these cases do not manifest. --Bisqwit (talk) 20:32, 30 March 2016 (MDT)

What is the point of this ridiculously huge page?

This page is certainly competely useless, as anyone who has a notion of how many cycles an instruction takes can write fixed delay code. This page should be IMO removed. There is certainly NO need to provide 10 examples of fixed delay cycles for every single number between 3 and 100. I am too lazy to log in, but it's me Bregalad. 193.134.219.72 06:02, 1 April 2016 (MDT)

The point is both ROM hacking and trivial interest. You need to create as small code as possible, and there are constraints of what you can clobber. It is not a trivial challenge. But if you so choose as to delete the page, be my guest. I just hoped someone would share my interest. --Bisqwit (talk) 07:56, 1 April 2016 (MDT)

It's not up to me to decide whether to delete or not, but my opinion is that this information is not meaningful for NES development. A routine which can do a delay in a certain range with a variable is, however, meaningful for NES development. The fact that "pha" is considered as a delay routine of 3 cycles is by itself a huge aberration to me, if the whole list goes on like that I cannot imagine how much of a mess this is. Maybe if it would be stripped of so many versions and have only a single version for each # of cycles that could at least make a little sense. (Bregalad)193.134.219.72 07:07, 4 April 2016 (MDT)

Sorry to Bisqwit, but I also agree that this page is of no practical use. I was following it from curiosity because I think the permutations are bizarre/interesting. I think as instruction it's bad for beginners (i.e. too much information, requires advanced knowledge to really sort out what you want-- and if you have advanced knowledge you don't need this table, really). Like I suggested above, I still think an online generator program would be tons better than a huge dump on a wiki page like this. The wiki is just a poor medium to approach this. Also there's the issue that trying to look at diffs of this page crashes the wiki, which I think might indicate that the wiki itself isn't happy about it? ;) Even just a forum thread with a link to a pastebin of the dump might be a better place to share this information; you could have a dialog with people about the generator, etc. which as a discussion would be more interesting/useful/fruitful than trying to create this pointless reference table on the wiki in relative isolation. - Rainwarrior (talk) 15:59, 4 April 2016 (MDT)

On a slightly less unilateral note ... in what not-awkwardly-construed situation is it ever useful to have a delay function that trashes S? —Lidnariq (talk) 14:36, 4 April 2016 (MDT)

Well I have no personal experience of it, but when making demos you need to squeeze every cycle and every byte, and it may sometimes involve using registers in non-conventional manner. An example that comes to my mind is Blargg's NES tests, where in some of them, interrupt/NMI handlers never return, and/or they clobber registers. The "stomper" NES demo does almost all its processing without stack manipulations. Similarly for the "full palette" demo. While it is indeed farfetched, it is not unconceivable that a demo might not care about clobbering S if it saves space. --Bisqwit (talk) 18:19, 5 April 2016 (MDT)

Tool suggestions

I like the new webpage tool, but I have some suggestions.

Decimal clobber should not be on by default. Inconsequential on a real NES, but lots of subtle consequences on emulators/clones, so I think this should be the same category as unofficial opcodes.
It should have option to generate a single delay length, or some other kind of grouping options.

If you're trying to use this for practical code generation, you really only need 1 specific delay length (or maybe a couple, but never hundreds of variations). The sheer size and complexity of the generated include file makes it a little daunting for use. Would you want to add 100,000 lines of code to your program just to delay 15 cycles optimally?
If you're trying to use this to investigate how to write delay code, sticking hundreds of code snippets together in an include file like this obfuscates this study, I think. Maybe seeing a range of delays (e.g. 10 to 20) would be interesting to study, seeing how the code changes between them. Similarly, seeing the same delay length with various constrains would be interesting to look at side by side.
Could "preview" a single delay case in a text field on the page. That would let you quickly generate and look at a couple of related cases, would be good for the person trying to learn, but also the person who just wants to copy and paste a small code snippet to do the job they need.

Relative branching using *- is also obfuscating for study. Unless jumping to the middle of an instruction, an anonymous label would be better for study. (Even "label+1" would more clearly express a split instruction than something like "*-5".)

- Rainwarrior (talk) 18:34, 20 April 2016 (MDT)

I will remove the default-selection from the decimal mode flag. I kind of wish to see references on the "lots of subtle consequences on emulators/clones" claim though.
I disagree on the 1 specific delay length. I explained the rationale on romhacking.net: “Advantages over handwritten code include that the number of cycles to delay can be any compile-time numeric expression, as is needed in my project, where the number of splits & delays per screen can be large, especially with the map screen that is split into four slices, and the number of cycles to delay depends on various factors: The NTSC/PAL selection, and the mapper, as page-switches in each mapper consume a different number of cycles. Using generated code thus helps keep small not only the binary size, but the source code size as well.” In other words, using a macro is necessary when the number of cycles to delay depends on compile-time options, and can not be known in advance when the source code is written. And even when that is not a factor, it is still much more convenient and better for documentation purposes to say delay_n 5000 than to copypaste 12 lines of code. :)
Relative branching is done that way because it works well for the generator, but more importantly it helps bring down the source code length, which is a factor with macros this long. It also helps avoid scope problems that easily arise with ca65.

Previewing would be entirely possible and not too inefficient to implement, I think. Still requires going through a 4-gigabyte unindexed data file on the server side though. I will think of it. Thank you for the feedback! --Bisqwit (talk) 19:39, 20 April 2016 (MDT)

Does that mean this "generator" is really just a selector for which .inc file to download, all pre-generated? - Rainwarrior (talk) 01:04, 21 April 2016 (MDT)

There are three layers of "generators". On the bottom layer, there is the generator that makes the database, and takes about a week or two to run. Done once (or more, if updated). It is a database of all different options for 20000 cycles, with bitmasks for which constraints are required for each option. I found this to be the most efficient solution considering the vast number of combinations from all different constraints (about 30 bits, i.e. thousand million combinations). Now it only needs about 100 choices for each bitmask by average. During generation the constraints may vary. For example, wrapping code in "PHA-PLA" allows to use code that clobbers A without actually clobbering A. It allows the generator to reuse work. On the middle there is a second generator that reads the database and produces a single .inc file, and it is continuously run to produce more of them. It takes about a minute or two to run for a single combination of constraints. For each clock cycle, it selects the nicest line from the database matching the given constraints, and then searches and combines identical or similar subsequences and parametrizes them to reduce the macro file size. On the top is the website which simply selects an .inc file, does sanity checks and either redirects or informs the user. For the user, the whole process is represented as a single "generator". --Bisqwit (talk) 05:14, 21 April 2016 (MDT)

Talk:Four Score

Is it possible to use the NES Four Score connected to each NES controller port and to the Famicom four-player adapter to make eight players? --Zzo38 (talk) 13:39, 20 March 2013 (MDT)

That depends on photos of the controller sockets on the Famicom four-player adapter. If they're identical to NES controller sockets, or an extension cable would make them that way, I don't see how it wouldn't work. Just make sure at least one of them is actually a (wired) Four Score; two (infrared) NES Satellite accessories would probably just interfere with each other. --Tepples (talk) 14:45, 20 March 2013 (MDT)

The wired controllers (commons:File:Wikipedia_nes_fourscore.jpg) plug into both ports on the from on the NES or AV Famicom. Player 1 and 2 are permanently attached to the plain famicom. You could cut apart a NES four score and solder on a DA15 connector to get 6 players on a conventional famicom.
The Famicom expansion port doesn't connect to $4016.0, so there's a bunch of discussion/confusion on the internet about how Hori's four player adapter could possibly work. Nonetheless, games do expect the four player adapter to work as outlined on Standard controller —Lidnariq (talk) 13:55, 21 March 2013 (MDT)

Talk:Game bugs

Actually, there should probably be an option in the emulator to enable "impossible" input if it is wanted (such as to figure out what strange things are happening, or if you want to pretend to be different kind of input devices where it is possible, etc). --Zzo38 (talk) 18:58, 25 March 2013 (MDT)

Yeah, impossible controller input can be pretty fun, plus TASers love it. I've rephrased it a bit :). -Ulfalizer (talk) 22:41, 25 March 2013 (MDT)

Lots of emulators have an option to allow L+R/U+D but it really needs to be prevented by default. Considering that preventing it from happening requires more code than not preventing it (i.e. doing nothing), I think it the phrasing should be more like: "Emulators should prevent this kind of input by default, but may offer an option to turn off this protection for users that want to experiment." - Rainwarrior (talk) 09:02, 27 March 2013 (MDT)

Done! Are you unable to edit the wiki yourself by the way? I don't guard the stuff I write religiously, and this is pretty sensible stuff with low risk of being controversial. :) --Ulfalizer (talk) 09:08, 27 March 2013 (MDT)

I can edit it, I just didn't feel like it for some reason I don't recall. - Rainwarrior (talk) 00:36, 28 March 2013 (MDT)

If I'm not wrong, the game Predator has a secret based on impossible inputs. Just press UP + DOWN + JUMP or FIRE to skip the current level. --Zepper (talk) 18:25, 27 March 2013 (MDT)

That could just as easily be a bug. - Rainwarrior (talk) 00:36, 28 March 2013 (MDT)

Recent changes by PGCX864

I don't understand the bugs description added recently by PGCX864. They are badly phrased and are not understandable. A more precise description of what looks wrong (and possibly where in the game) is just what is needed.Bregalad (talk) 02:06, 29 April 2015 (MDT)

And then he does that again. Most of his stuff is incorrect English and is total nonsense.Bregalad (talk) 01:48, 12 May 2015 (MDT)

Assume good faith, and ayez de la patience, s'il vous plait. English does not seem to be his first language. (It has an East Asian ring to it.) Of the ones I can puzzle out and check/knew about before, all of them exist. The Megaman ladder trick he refers to is | this, I believe. Zelda 2 having the simultaneous left+right input granting enormous speed is used well in one of the TASes, and likewise in Tiny Toon Adventures. The screen does indeed shake one pixel when a door closes in Castlevania III/Akumajou Densetsu, but I believe this to be an intentional effect from the door slamming shut. I'll continue to correct what I can. Myask (talk) 03:47, 12 May 2015 (MDT)

Thanks. As for the Akumajo Densetsu door, I belive it's not intentional, because

1. It also shift one pixel when you first touch the door, before it is slamming 2. Castlevania III does not have this bug. If it wasn't a bug it wouldn't have been fixed. Bregalad (talk) 04:42, 12 May 2015 (MDT)

It is as you say. I suppose if they'd wanted a serious shake effect, it might be for more than once (compare: shaking after each move of the tower in block 9-03, but obviously the tower moving makes for more shaking than a door would.) Or perhaps they just decided it wasn't nice to look at and cut it out. Though, they were changing mappers, and there were a fair number of other, less-desirable changes made. (Also, as an aside, I checked Panic Restaurant's bug myself.) Myask (talk) 04:56, 12 May 2015 (MDT)

smooth sprite flickering in smb3 world 1-4

World 1-4 in Super Mario Bros 3, the moving wooden lifts flicker smoothy --46.130.11.158 03:32, 5 October 2015 (MDT)

Sprite flickering occurs in most NES games. What is notable about this example in SMB3 that would make someone think it's a bug? - Rainwarrior (talk) 11:13, 5 October 2015 (MDT)

Talk:INES Mapper 001

Would it be okay to add a note to Disch's note explaining the "too close together" behavior? Kev says it's due to edge-triggering.

The note would clearly indicate that it's an edit and not part of the original notes. -Ulfalizer (talk) 00:14, 19 March 2013 (MDT)

I'm torn about what to do with Disch's notes, especially when they're wrong. Sometimes I've just completely replaced them (iNES Mapper 234). Sometimes I've completely rewritten them (iNES Mapper 072). Sometimes I just put a big warning label at the top of the article (iNES Mapper 019). We don't have a standing policy of not editing Disch's notes, although I've accidentally caused confusion by not marking it when I've done so... oops.
Anyway, I'm not clear how edge triggered behavior causes what's happening here, unless the MMC1 ignores M2 altogether. —Lidnariq (talk) 01:33, 19 March 2013 (MDT)

It's likely that the writing mechanism might be ignoring M2. The only thing M2 is really needed for is enabling the PRG RAM chip. --Tepples (talk) 06:51, 19 March 2013 (MDT)
Maybe someone should ask Disch, if he's easy to reach. I personally wouldn't mind people correcting mistakes in documents that are still credited to me. ;) --Ulfalizer (talk) 13:22, 19 March 2013 (MDT)

I wouldn't add this information on a "Kev says" basis, please test it first, or add a "big warning label" that it's just speculation. The reason I'm skeptical about it is the fact that MMC1 (seemingly) only ignores consecutive writes if the high bit of the first write is set. If it was edge-triggered, it would seem logical that the ignoring would also happen for non-reset writes. Then again, that, too, is just speculation (although parts of it have been tested on hardware). :) --Thefox (talk) 00:03, 14 July 2013 (MDT)

hey everyone

hello

Talk:INES Mapper 028

Miscellany

Does this mapper use RAM at $6000-$7FFF? PRG RAM? Whatever? --Zepper (talk) 06:15, 18 September 2013 (MDT)

It supports the same PRG RAM at $6000-$7FFF that the iNES format implies for most discrete mappers. There's no disable register, if that's what you meant. --Tepples (talk) 12:47, 18 September 2013 (MDT)

Are both the inner and outer PRG regs always used in PRG swaps? --Zepper (talk) 18:44, 21 September 2013 (MDT)

Both registers are used to form the final 16K bank number unless you're in P=G=0 mode, in which case only the outer bank is used. But if you're just switching banks within one game, you're probably writing only to the inner PRG register. Let me make an analogy to a possibly more familiar mapper, MMC1: Consider the inner PRG register like $E000 and the outer like bit 4 of $A000 on SUROM/SXROM. --Tepples (talk) 12:57, 22 September 2013 (MDT)

Yes, but there's something weird for me. While the PRG diagram shows $8000-$BFFF to use R:01, _and_ $C000-$FFFF to use R:81, I think such PRG bank selection would be _separated_. Later, there's an info regarding ORing both PRG registers $01 and $81 (and making shift and ANDs) _to compose_ the desired PRG page. Could someone clarify it? --Zepper (talk) 18:56, 24 September 2013 (MDT)

DRY failure

Apropos of the edit log for the page itself, I'm pretty certain this page's existence is a DRY failure. Why do we have documentation for the same thing in two places? —Lidnariq (talk) 20:50, 2 April 2015 (MDT)

Talk:INES Mapper 030

Board allocation

Study Hall definitely needs its own mapper, but why does BK:MoT need to be here? It's handled by the standard m2 emulator oversize logic... —Lidnariq (talk) 11:54, 8 April 2014 (MDT)

While it is true that BK:MoT can function with just the Mapper 2 oversize, the game was made on the board that Mapper 30 is defined for. Given that it exists on the UNROM 512 board, I do have some plans to make a convenience hack, where the games continue points write something to the flash, so that the game can be saved, resumed later, without needing to write down passwords. Modding that to real cart will just be a matter of desoldering the 4 flash locked jumnpers, soldering the flash enabled jumper, mounting the 74*139, and flashing the modified rom to the cart. Such a hack would definitely need the mapper 30 definition. Caitsith2 (talk) 12:15, 8 April 2014 (MDT)

So... you want to allocate mapper 30 for a BK2 hack you plan to make in the future? I don't think it's good practice to allocate mappers before there is something to be emulated that needs one. - Rainwarrior (talk)

Oh wait, I missed the comment about Study Hall. What are Study Hall's special requirements? Bankable CHR-RAM? - Rainwarrior (talk) 15:09, 8 April 2014 (MDT)
Ah, OK, I see from the UNROM 512 Talk Page this mapper would support several RetroUSB games? I misunderstood the discussion. Are there other such games that don't already fall into existing mappers, or is it just Study Hall? - Rainwarrior (talk)

Study Hall explicitly requires self-flashing support. —Lidnariq (talk) 15:41, 8 April 2014 (MDT)

Talk:INES Mapper 034

Emulating both

Isn't it possible to emulate this mapper as a single "mapper" (that is without distinguishing between BNROM and NINA) with the following setup :

1 PRG bankswitching register at $7ffd and $8000-$ffff
2 CHR bankswitching registers at $7ffe and $7fff, initialized to 0 and 1 respectively on powerup.

That way, the BNROM game starts up with the right CHR banks switched in, bus conflicts aren't emulated, but aren't required for emulation anyways. The NINA game should work well as long as it doesn't write to $8000-$ffff (I fail to see why it would do this).

The only problem is that this doesn't support BNROM + SRAM extension, but no game was ever made using this anyways. Bregalad (talk) 14:20, 17 March 2014 (MDT)

I'm not familiar with the two games to know for sure they don't write to conflicting places, but as the mappers are described, yes I believe that is fine as a mapper that supports both. If you'd like to check them both with a debugger to verify that this is the case, it might help resolve this question. If it's safe, we should probably add to that second paragraph in the lead section to mention this. - Rainwarrior (talk) 19:20, 17 March 2014 (MDT)
The PowerPak emulates both at once, as do many emulators that don't implement NES 2.0. But the Holy Diver Batman multi-mapper test ROM is designed to test BxROM + PRG RAM circuit, and the overlaid NINA logic causes it to fail on PowerPak. --Tepples (talk) 22:32, 17 March 2014 (MDT)

Talk:INES Mapper 087

Mapper 87 vs 101

Just for the sake of argument, I'd like to outline my reasoning. Only one of the following three things can be true:

Mapper 87 describes only the 16 KiB CHR games, with the 2s bit controlling bank, and mapper 101 describes the 32 KiB CHR games, with the bits in order.
Mapper 87 describes both, where the 32 KiB configuration has the bits out of order, and mapper 101 was erroneously assigned.
There are two different 100% correct dumps of the exact same cartridge.

I object to #3. GoodNES and other sources have decided on #2. —Lidnariq (talk) 01:35, 25 April 2014 (MDT)

Any CNROM image will run when changed to GNROM, and any NROM image will work when changed to CNROM or GNROM. Heck, the only existing commercial BNROM game will work on Color Dreams. Whether to go with #1 or #2 depends on whether the community wants to deprecate 87/101 for new development in favor of CNROM (#2) or not (#1). --Tepples (talk) 08:58, 25 April 2014 (MDT)

But conceptually, a copy of (e.g.) SMB marked as GNROM isn't correct. Perhaps I should have said "canonical" instead of "100% correct". Anyway, as for the last point, there's no reason to pick either m87 or m101 anymore: they're inferior to CNROM because a bus-conflict prevention table is cheaper; or as INL pointed out, just connecting R/W to /WE (while tying /OE low) on most Flash will prevent bus conflicts; or even if it doesn't, a transistor or 74'1g04 is cheaper than a 74'20 or 74'138. —Lidnariq (talk) 13:59, 25 April 2014 (MDT)

I also don't get the difference between 87 and 101, because who cares if the bits are in order or not - that's equivalent to exchange banks 1 and 2 in the CHR-dump (or exchange A13 and A14 when dumping the CHR-ROM). But how relevant is it that the banks in the iNES (or whathever other format) dump is in the same order as in the CHR-ROM itself physically ? If this is relevant then the 87 and 101 difference makes sense, but I don't think it's relevant, and therefore I don't think the difference makes sense.Bregalad (talk) 02:43, 15 May 2014 (MDT)

Talk:INES Mapper 088

In the edit log for iNES Mapper 154, Tepples said: Isn't 206, the ordinary MIMIC-1/108/118 board, theoretically just an undersize 88 anyway?

I'm betting that m88 was allocated before m206, and m88's difference from MMC3 does need its own mapper. It does seem to imply that allocating m206 was superfluous, since games with less than 64kB of CHR ROM don't have an CHR A16 line to connect to the PPU's A12.
However, m88 could be also interpreted as "the MSB line of the address going into the CHR ROM is connected to PPU A12", meaning a 64kB CHR game would have the left and right pattern tables restricted to the first and last 32kB of CHR ROM. Since no m88 game exists with anything other than 128kB of CHR ROM, it's not really clear what the least surprising choice would be. — Lidnariq 00:54, 16 July 2012 (PDT)

I see three different approaches, depending on how you want to handle "oversize" 206 games:

Your suggestion for 88 = always run PA12 out to the highest existing CHR ROM address line as determined by the CHR ROM size in the header. When combined with an "oversize" variant of the Namco 108 family IC, this would allow up to 512K CHR.
Treat these mappers as synonymous and have the CHR ROM size determine whether to emulate with A16. This is how the various Bandai FCG boards are handled in NES 2.0: 128 bytes mean 159 (24C01), 256 bytes mean 16 (24C02), and more means 153 (6264).
Treat 88 as the actual board's behavior, with CHR ROM A16 == PA12 installed on those games that use 128K CHR, and have 206 refer to an oversize variant with CHR bank registers as wide as those of MMC3.

Which is most logical? You might have to consult with the ROM dumping communities to distinguish these. --Tepples 05:43, 16 July 2012 (PDT)

Talk:INES Mapper 099

Minimal discrete logic clone

A 74138, selecting on M2, A14, A4, and A1 high; R/W and A0 low, and a 7474 (or any larger latch). Maps the write-only register at every address [4-7C-F].[13579BDF][26AE]. Incorrectly decodes writes to $4012 and DualSystem RAM. Using a 74161 or any other latch with an additional active-low enable would remove the collision with the DualSystem RAM; however, there's no obvious place to get an extra active-high enable to prevent the collision with $4012. —Lidnariq (talk) 16:15, 31 October 2013 (MDT)

Half of the 7474 can be configured to act as an inverter. In this case, instead of requiring A0 low, we could instead require A2 high, mapping the register at [4-7C-F].[13579BDF][67EF]. Now it incorrectly decodes writes to $4017, but few games will write to that register more than once. (It still collides with writes to the RAM at $6xxx.)
For games that require the extra RAM, using a 74138 or 74139 has the advantage that it already produces a /($4000-$5fff) signal. This could then be combined with another '138 or '139 to require A4, A2, and A1 high; and R/W (and A0) low.

Regardless, open bus behavior will cause the game to perceive one of the coin acceptors as always true. The last configuration above can produce /RD4016or4017, which can be combined with a tristateable buffer (and a button? or infrared receiver? or oscillator?) to pull D6 and D5 high or low as appropriate to fake the coin acceptors. —Lidnariq (talk) 12:37, 4 May 2014 (MDT)

Talk:INES Mapper 163

VRAM Scanline switching

Despite its annoying pirate features, this mapper is on the whole rather simple. A complex scanline counter seems unlikely. The games I've seen all use this feature only for a static title screen, which got me to thinking: What if it isn't scanline based at all? I implemented the following setup in Bizhawk and it appeared to work for all of the games that I could try with no graphical glitching:

Whenever PPU A13 transitions from 0 to 1, latch the current value of PPU A9. When the 'c' bit is on, use that latched value instead of PPU A12 as the input to CHR RAM A12.

(Note that Bizhawk implements an accurate PPU fetch pattern, including all dummy fetches). This method is reminiscent of Mapper 096 and can be implemented with discrete hardware or with a very small number of gates in a ASIC or CPLD. Natt (talk) 10:10, 27 January 2014 (MST)

Looks plausible... If there are any differences, they'll pop up if any games ever set the Y scroll to something non-zero. —Lidnariq (talk) 11:34, 27 January 2014 (MST)
That said, a PPUA12-clocked 13-bit counter isn't that complicated either. —Lidnariq (talk) 15:06, 27 January 2014 (MST)

If anyone has such cartridge, then see if you are able to put a program to set Y scroll to nonzero to see if there is a difference which you describe. --Zzo38 (talk) 13:47, 27 January 2014 (MST)

Talk:INES Mapper 210

Does this mapper actually exist? The boards Disch mentions as #210 are #19 in Bootgod's DB and don't seem to have hardwired mirroring when I trace the board. Lidnariq 23:11, 15 June 2012 (PDT)

I checked out a bunch of roms. They all came to me as mapper 19. I removed the 210 special logic from this mapper, and they all seemed to work, as long as the default nametable registers were $FE, $FF, $FE, $FF (vertical mirroring). Wagyan 2 depended on this. Wagyan 2 is NAMCOT-175. Splatterhouse 2 is NAMCOT-175 as well, and it needs vertical mirroring as well, but it sets its registers. So Wagyan 2 must be on a board that uses the nametable regs and is truly depending on the default values. Therefore, I agree that there is no difference between 019 and 210.

Even if there is no functional difference between 019 and 210, if there are roms in the wild that are 210, we should keep the mapper reserved for it, at the very least with notes similar to this. Itd be a good candidate for recovery, but there are better. Ill have to scour my roms and see if there are any 210 left.
Zeromus 08:49, 16 June 2012 (PDT)

I wonder if m210 is 'supposed' to represent the Namco175/340, with its simpler mirroring control (as described by naruko). It's just close enough, and few enough games were released, that I could see how "fixed mirroring" or "correct default" might be good enough to make the games work. —Lidnariq 12:04, 18 June 2012 (PDT)

Ok, so having looked over Naruko's notes and added them to the Namco 163 description, my take is:

Mapper 19 is Namcot 129/163, or an unseen variant of it without sound.
Mapper 210 was originally for Namcot 175, which has hardwired mirroring, but has only one functionality conflict (register at $c000 becomes WRAM protect, but Naruko only mentions one game that has it), and so almost any game that used the Namcot 175 can probably actually be emulated safely using Mapper 19.
No mapper was allocated for the Namcot 340, which uses the top bits of $e000 to select 1ScA/H/V/1ScB mirroring.

I think I can interpret Naruko's documentation to recommend that m210 be reallocated to the n340, and that the one n175-with-wram game be emulated as n340. —Lidnariq 12:53, 24 June 2012 (PDT)

Talk:INES Mapper 218

Alternate PPU memory maps

I can make a suggestion of the variant of mapper 218 using NES 2.0 header. If the header specifies neither CHR ROM nor CHR RAM, then it acts as described in this document. If it does specify either CHR ROM or CHR RAM (only one or the other is allowed, not both; RAM can optionally be battery-backed (but you can't combine battery with non-battery)), then it is mirrored across 16K, and the mirroring flags control how many positions to shift the high bit of the address (if vertical mirroring is specified, this is the ordinary memory mirroring; this also means specifying 2K non-battery RAM is the same as using CIRAM, regardless of mirroring setting, and that specifying 1K non-battery RAM and vertical mirroring acts like using CIRAM but connecting CIRAM A10 to ground). This is no longer a single chip cartridge, but it does seem to be what would be a variant of this iNES mapper nevertheless. --Zzo38 (talk) 12:55, 30 December 2013 (MST)

I cannot fathom the use of variants that map any size of ROM over the entire PPU address space. The background would never be anything more than a static 512x480 (or smaller) picture.
Otherwise, I think you're describing the following six new modes:

4KiB RAM, RAM A10,11 = PPU A10,A11 : Nametables and both pattern tables all from the same RAM. Technically allows four screen layout, but not in a particularly useful way
4KiB RAM, RAM A10,11 = PPU A11,A12 : Each pattern table gets 2KiB, but the left pattern table is shared with the nametables (which are equivalently in horizontal mirroring)
4KiB RAM, RAM A10,11 = PPU A12,A13 : 1-screen mirroring, 1KiB for each pattern table
8KiB RAM, RAM A10,11,12 = PPU A10,11,12 : Four-screen layout, but left pattern table is more or less unusable
8KiB RAM, RAM A10,11,12 = PPU A11,12,13 : Each pattern table gets 2KiB and the nametables are in horizontal mirroring
16KiB RAM, all connected : traditional 8KiB CHRRAM + 4 screen layout.

The reason, as I understand it, that m218 is interesting is that it lets you save on populating one IC, so that you only need PRG ROM and maybe the CIC. One you have to add an extra IC, you may as well add it in a useful layout; therefore an 8KiB RAM for patterns with the NES's CIRAM for nametables is strictly more useful than variants 2, 3, and 5. Variants 1 and 4 could have some merit, but only because there's no established variant that uses 10KiB of RAM for anything other than (8KiB pattern + 2KiB NT) or mapper 77. Variant 6 is already the default behavior for all mappers than have CHRRAM and 4-screen layout specified. —Lidnariq (talk) 13:55, 30 December 2013 (MST)

You are correct I agree that mapper 218 is interesting since PRG ROM is the only IC needed (other than CIC, if necessary); however, there is a potential interest for the variant I mentioned, which seems like it would be a reasonable thing for mapper 218 to do if the NES 2.0 header specifies the existence of CHR-ROM or CHR-RAM (regardless of how useful it might be). However, full area CHR-ROM might not be entirely useless; maybe it can be useful for some kind of very simple game that uses only a scrolling static background and sprites (one example of such a game might be Pong). The 16KiB RAM can of course also be useful (if you don't want mirroring); doing this also gives you some extra RAM (usable only when not rendering), and if it is battery-backed you might use it for save game data. Of course what is useful depends much on the program. --Zzo38 (talk) 19:29, 31 December 2013 (MST)

Talk:Init code

Prophylactic read of $2002

Is this bit of code necessary? I'm having trouble finding any original NES game that does it. Are there any known examples of a startup problem caused by this?

; Clear the vblank flag, so we know that we are waiting for the
; start of a vertical blank and not powering on with the
; vblank flag spuriously set
bit $2002

If it isn't a problem, does anyone have an explanation as to why it isn't? If it is, can anyone point to an example of the problem? (Maybe I'll write a test if I have time later...) - Rainwarrior (talk) 12:09, 28 May 2015 (MDT)

Yes, it's necessary, and a problem, see PPU power up state. There's a thread on the forum of at least one homebrew that failed to boot sometimes because it would immediately fall through the first wait and not wait long enough after the second wait before it started trying to write to PPU registers. —Lidnariq (talk) 12:49, 28 May 2015 (MDT)

The power up state article doesn't have enough information to answer my question. There is "The PPU comes out of reset at the top of the picture" but it's unclear whether this applies to power on. It says $2002 often powers on set, but is unclear whether this is because the PPU starts in vblank. "The VBL flag (PPUSTATUS bit 7) is usually clear at power, and unchanged by reset. It is next set around 27384, then around 57165." Is that consistent? Why "around"? Is "ignored if earlier than ~29658 CPU" an upper bound, or an average?

I'm trying to understand why it doesn't seem to be a problem for commercial games. So far I haven't found any that don't just do 2x $2002 poll loops, but also all of them seem to do a bit of extra initialization work before they start hitting the PPU. If it's the case that the $2002 vblank flag powers on randomized, and the next set is always at 27384 consistently, then the margin of error for failure is <3000 cycles?

Trying to think of a good way to test this and demonstrate the failure. Can you remember anything else about the homebrew in question that might help me search for it? - Rainwarrior (talk) 13:04, 28 May 2015 (MDT)

The only thing I remember is someone saying something like ~and now I will always wait for $2002.7 three times in my init code~.

Anyway, order of events:

PPU always comes out of reset at Y=0
PPUSTATUS.7 may or may not be set when it comes out of reset
CPU can only detect when Y=240, because that's when the PPU sets PPUSTATUS.7
PPU is not available for pertinent writes until Y=262=0
Waiting for PPUSTATUS.7 twice without clearing the register on startup could therefore sometimes have the CPU think the PPU is ready when Y=240, instead of Y=262+240 —Lidnariq (talk) 13:18, 28 May 2015 (MDT)

Found this post by Blargg claiming to have tested it and basically verifying what I just asked. http://forums.nesdev.com/viewtopic.php?f=2&t=3958 i.e. the idea that there is a 3000 cycle margin of failure if you don't pre-clear. - Rainwarrior (talk) 13:19, 28 May 2015 (MDT)

Talk:IRQ

Is it really impossible to acknownledge a DMC IRQ by reading $4015 ? It's weird this register has a DMC IRQ flag, but that reading it would not ack the interrupt. Also it sounds fishy you'd have to stop the sample and restart another one to acknownledge.Bregalad 14:00, 24 April 2012 (PDT)

Whatever my DPCM Split and DPCM Letterbox demos are doing works on an NES. --Tepples 16:15, 24 April 2012 (PDT)

Table

Just how comprehensive do we want this list to be? Obviously including every single mapper with IRQs is overkill (q.v. my list, sort it by IRQ presence), but does it make sense to include non-US mappers here? If so, why these ones? (e.g. there were more games released on the Namco 163 (20) than the VRC4+6+7 combined (16)) —Lidnariq (talk) 18:28, 17 May 2015 (MDT)

Yeah, actually the whole table is probably useless. Knowing some value to enable/disable/ack an IRQ is too little information to do anything useful with it (except the disable, I guess). Really that information is best left at the article page. What we really need is Category:Mappers with IRQs, and your list is a great TODO list for building that category. I guess this article needs a rewrite with a better focus, probably. - Rainwarrior (talk) 18:50, 17 May 2015 (MDT)

Before I go and start adding that Category to everything ... do we want to distinguish at the category level between "quantized to scanlines" and "cycle-based" ? I'd vaguely be inclined to, although there's some fuzziness for the ones that can be switched between cycle-based and scanline-quantized. (Obviously both of those categories would be subcategories of "Mappers with IRQ")... —Lidnariq (talk) 19:56, 17 May 2015 (MDT)

Sure, I don't see why not. You could just put something in both categories if it can do both. - Rainwarrior (talk) 20:13, 17 May 2015 (MDT)
Sure. Whether it uses the PPU or CPU as a time base is especially important for whether a program would need to be adapted for the longer vblank and slower clock divider of the PAL NES. --Tepples (talk) 21:01, 17 May 2015 (MDT)

Hm. Where should we file VRC IRQs then? I was originally going to say with the scanline IRQs, but if the argument here is 2C02-and-Dendy-vs-2C07, it might then instead belong in cycle-based...—Lidnariq (talk) 21:37, 17 May 2015 (MDT)

VRC is cycle based. It's just cycle based with an interface that's convenient for working with scanlines. Any cycle based counter can do what VRC does, but no cycle based counter can do what a true scanline counter does. - Rainwarrior (talk) 22:23, 17 May 2015 (MDT)

Talk:List of games by mirroring technique

This page was created with a good intention of cleaning up the mirroring page, and I thank Rainwarrior for that. However, this raises a new (unrelated) question. Is it in scope of the wiki to do List of games by xxx ?

Then we could do list of games by mapper, list of games by genres, list of games by publisher/developer list of games by sprite size (8x8 or 8x16), and so on and so forth. I do believe this kind of lists can be useful and interesting, for instance, Bootgod's databse is extremely useful in listing games by mapper or board or other hardware related factors.

However, we have to know that there is more than 1500 FC/NES games officially, and much more if we include pirated games sold in 3rd world countries (and I know someone will include them eventually). Do we really want to maintain lists of such games?Bregalad (talk) 02:58, 18 May 2015 (MDT)

I don't want to maintain it, myself, but that's not why I created the article. Bootgod only contains mirroring information from iNES headers, it'll never have information on rendering techniques, so I do think this article could be potentially useful. I wanted to create a space where PGCX864 can contribute the wealth of minutiae he seems to be interested in, organized in a place where it can be useful on its own, rather than becoming a detriment-by-verbosity in an importan reference article like Mirroring. It's not a great article at the moment, but I think it has potential, and isn't harming the wiki. - Rainwarrior (talk) 12:00, 18 May 2015 (MDT)

Talk:List of games with expansion audio

Romanization

I understand that someone who speaks French or Greek as a first language might see ou and think [u], but in Japanese transliteration it's [o:]. The Japanese sound オウ can be transliterated ou, ô (with circumflex), or ō (with macron), depending on a particular publication's house style. I imagine that this list may have been pulled from NesCartDB, which uses the ou convention. Sometimes this is dictated by character set: ou for ASCII or ô for Latin-1. Or occasionally, a particular transliteration becomes customary for a particular name. For example, a publisher or the fan community may have consistently used one transliteration in Western media. For example, the Japanese version of Animal Crossing series (どうぶつの森) is most often spelled Doubutsu no Mori. In a few cases, homophones end up developing distinct customary transliterations, such as Toho (東宝, the Godzilla company) vs. Touhou (東方, the shmup series). Do we need to hammer out a manual of style page for transliterating titles of Famicom games? --Tepples (talk) 07:26, 26 January 2014 (MST)

I don't see the point of the change. There is nothing invalid in the use of "ou", as it is a very standard romanization and was consistent across the entire list. I made this list based on the filenames used in my NSF collection, and every NSF archive I can find online appears to use the "ou" convention (e.g. the collections of Gil Galad, joshw, Zophar's Domain, akuma, and kingshriek). Changing them all to "ō" makes them inconsistent with these collections, which I think is a disadvantage here. Naively searching these games with "ō" is less likely to yield the desired result. Someone familiar with Japanese might think to try again with "ou", so it would be merely an inconvenience for such a person, but someone unfamiliar with it might have a harder time finding what they're looking for. There's nothing to gain by this convention change, in my opinion. - Rainwarrior (talk) 21:23, 26 January 2014 (MST)

To put another way, the reason to use the "ou" convention is it creates a more direct mapping from the Roman characters to Japanese, and also avoids the use of extended characters. The reason to use the "ō" convention is to help understand the pronunciation, as "ou" will be pronounced wrong by a naive English speaking reader. I don't think there is any good reason to favour pronunciation for the purposes of the NesDev wiki, and there is indeed an advantage to having a more direct transliteration of the titles given by the "ou" convention. - Rainwarrior (talk) 21:28, 26 January 2014 (MST)

Well is the capital of Japan known as Tōkyō or Toukyou ? That's the question. If you guys don't like the ō because of unicode characters I understand very much, then a plain 'o' (as in Tokyo) is probably the closest you can go. "ou" is just a mapping from kana to romanji, which leads to wrong pronunciation (and probably not only for French or Greek speakers). Now as long as the game did have their titles in kanjis, it's technically wrong to have them a name with roman letters. Now I think everyone will agree that it's much more convenient to use roman letters in an international context, so the quesiton is, do you want to have correct pronunciation, or a mapping to kana ? Since nobody cares about kana, I'd think that rationally, the correct pronunciation is the way to go. Although I perfectly understand the point about matching it to the NSF collection names or Bootgod's database, both of which used "ou" for no particular reason. So in short, if you want to refert, fine go ahead I won't mind. But I still think that "Akumajou" sounds extremely weird.Bregalad (talk) 09:50, 28 January 2014 (MST)

That city has a common English name, "Tokyo", so it is not appropriate to romanize it. Similarly we should not normally write "Firenze" or "Wien" in an English context. I think the highest priority for NESDev purposes is being able to use these names to search and find ROMs or other relevant information, and using the same convention as every ROM/NSF database is key toward fulfilling this goal. Avoiding extended characters for ease of typing is a secondary benefit toward this goal. (The character ō is not easily available on any common keyboard. Even less so if your keyboard is missing a numpad.) I would agree that attempting to reconstruct kana from the romanization is not important, though I would point out that the Microsoft IME for Japanese text displays potential kanji as you type the ou style romanization. I also thing pronunciation is unimportant for NESDev. If you are a person who does not know any Japanese and doesn't even know what Akumajou means, it doesn't matter that you might pronounce it wrong from this reading. If you already are familiar with Japanese neither romanization presents a challenge to correct pronunciation. Let pronunciation be taught elsewhere, we have other goals here. - Rainwarrior (talk) 11:09, 28 January 2014 (MST)

Talk:Mapper

Contents

1 Allocations
2 unicode joke terms
3 n\T icon
4 Why some mappers are assigned to "Rare, Ltd."'s logo
5 32x32 upscaling
6 A newbie-friendly page introduction

6.1 Mapper

Allocations

By FCEUX 2.2.1, they allocated mapper 160 to describe an undersize NINA-003-006 board (32k PRG, 16k CHR). This seems superfluous. They also allocated mapper 181 to describe another board like iNES Mapper 185 that didn't fit with the existing heuristic. It would be nice to take the opportunity to promote NES 2.0 submappers#iNES Mapper 185. —Lidnariq (talk) 21:41, 23 June 2013 (MDT)

Also, wasn't 256-511 supposed to be for developers or debugging use? I need to request a reserved number for future hardware designs. I'll probably go find the IRC channel for that.  ;) BTW: The documentation for NES 2.0 header format has different allocation planes. It's best to fix this BEFORE someone goes and tries to update/make any mapper code libraries. Again, going to bring this to attention of mods in chat. alphamule (talk) 13:51, 29 August 2014 (MDT)

Rule of thumb: once you have final hardware, then you can get a mapper #. Before then, pick something arbitrary and otherwise unusable such as m100, or use UNIF. There's more theoretical possible mappers than there will ever be space for. —Lidnariq (talk) 14:40, 29 August 2014 (MDT)
In the plan as described by KH in the original NES 2.0 doc, 256-511 were to be filled after 0-255 had been filled. Because of the continuing pace of new Chinese discoveries since then, a revised, Unicode-inspired plan splits this into 256-511 for western games and 512-767 for eastern games. Presently, 3840-4095 are reserved for private use, as well as 100 and 248. --Tepples (talk) 15:34, 29 August 2014 (MDT)

Cool, thanks for the info! This should be helpful to future readers, as well. I found out that blargg is working on a similar project so I'm waiting for a PM response. I also need to get a working NES to test the hardware out on. alphamule (talk) 07:42, 30 August 2014 (MDT)

unicode joke terms

Might we rename "Supplementary Multilingual Plane" and "Supplementary Ideographic Plane"? Jokes about the unicode standard are rather obscure, and don't help anyone understand what these categories are for. - Rainwarrior (talk) 16:33, 16 April 2015 (MDT)

Jokes about unicode ?! I would never have guessed that was some. Anyways, jokes do not belong to here.Bregalad (talk) 04:12, 17 April 2015 (MDT)
I found them funny, but it was a laugh and an eye-roll. Myask (talk) 23:55, 20 April 2015 (MDT)

So, the second question to ask is what to name them. From what I can tell, the two planes are meant to distinguish mappers for new games (plane 1) from mappers that are used for illegal compilations/reproductions/modifications (plane 2). Presumably the idea is that emulator authors may wish to de-prioritize pirate mappers that don't contribute new games to the library. There's a bit about "east asia" in the current description which seems unnecessary to me; shouldn't pirate carts from any region be included here? (Russian? Brazilian?) China probably has the most prolific market for it, sure, but I don't think that needs to be part of the plane's definition. My suggestion:

Plane 0: iNES 1

Still has a few slots open for new homebrew?
Put new pirate mappers in plane 2, not here.

Plane 1: Homebrew

New games developed for newly created mappers
Undiscovered commercial-era mappers (if any exist)

Plane 2: Pirate

Multicarts used to illegally compile existing games
Modifications and hacks of existing games

- Rainwarrior (talk) 10:06, 17 April 2015 (MDT)

True, title hacks, graphics hacks, pure mapper hacks, and multicarts "that don't contribute new games to the library." But not all games made for the East Asian market fall into these categories. Some are ports from a more powerful system, such as Final Fantasy VII, Pokemon, and Somari. Some are original games (ab)using others' characters, such as Kart Fighter and various Pokemon and Harry Potter-themed games. But what makes East Asian games stand out from games for other markets is provision in the mapper for writing systems with more than a hundred characters, which needs either CHR RAM, ExGrafix, or precomposed phrases. (See CHR ROM vs. CHR RAM.) Games for Russian and Brazilian markets can get away with assuming a 1:1 relationship among tiles, glyphs, and characters. Besides, with the deprecation of UNIF, we need to allocate mappers for a bunch of CaH4e3 dumps, and separating out the Chinese stuff will help keep that effort from colliding with homebrew too much. So I've renamed the planes to "Plane 1" and "Plane 2" but left the East Asian wording. --Tepples (talk) 17:45, 19 April 2015 (MDT)

Okay, so you're not trying to separate pirate/multicart from homebrew/legitimate? Your goal is just to separate them by language/region? The language in place right now doesn't seem to mention an appropriate place for new pirate stuff, unless it already falls in the East-Asian category. You should probably write a description that designates that material to one plane or another, so that it's clear where to allocate. Of course, nobody has wanted to allocate anything yet, except zzo38 who appears to have pre-allocated 380, despite not having released any ROMs for it? I'm never going to be the maintainer of pirate mapper allocation, so I don't feel very strongly about how they are specifically organized. I just found the names borrowed from unicode the opposite of helpful when trying to figure out what the planes were being designated for. - Rainwarrior (talk) 21:09, 20 April 2015 (MDT)

n\T icon

The n\T icon (File:Mfr icon Namco Tengen.png) is a bit harder to read than the ir\AVE icon because both have the same (transparent) background and similar (reddish) colors, so the strokes of the twosort of blend into each other. NesCartDB lists 20 games developed or published by Namco and only three (Fantasy Zone, Gauntlet, and Indy 2) that Namco did not develop or publish. --Tepples (talk) 08:00, 11 June 2015 (MDT)

Not sure how you're getting only three non-Namco for mapper 206; plus Tengen Gauntlet is a pretty high-profile game. I see some Data East games in there, too! (Perhaps you missed the pagination?) Myask (talk) 19:32, 11 June 2015 (MDT)

Most of the rest were renamed and/or ported by Tengen for the US Market, but are originally made by Namco. (AFAICT, the entire reason that Tengen used the MIMIC-1 is because they were importing Namco games to the US market to get around Nintendo's limitation on a maximum of 6 (or was it lower?) games per publisher per year. —Lidnariq (talk) 19:57, 11 June 2015 (MDT)

Okay, that knocks out RBI and Ring King. And Pac-Mania is so obviously a Namco-developed game it hurts, but doesn't seem to have had a Famicom release? Super Sprint and Toobin', though... Still, the icons are for manufacturers (that is, publishers), and the Tengen boards are different, so does it really matter for our "whose-mapper-is-this" if someone was pulling an ljn trick? Myask (talk) 21:14, 11 June 2015 (MDT)

Why some mappers are assigned to "Rare, Ltd."'s logo

TQROM board's mapper was only used by Rare, Ltd. but uses a chip from Nintendo, the MMC3. It could be labelled Nintendo.

Mapper #7 was used most often by Rare, Ltd., but not exclusively. Solstice was not developed by Rare, Ltd. but uses mapper #7. Also, the PCB and carts were made by Nintendo, and contains no chip developed by Rare, Ltd, not even the PCB. Other discrete logic mappers which were used by various 3rd party developers but licenced by Nintendo are tagged Nintendo, there is no real reason mapper #7 would escape that rule.

It's true there is no mapper #7 games that was developed by Nintendo, however, this is true for many other mappers as well, such as the MMC5.Bregalad (talk) 03:38, 12 June 2015 (MDT)

I don't think it's reasonable to expect perfect accuracy when you reduce a mapper to a single 16x16 image. There's no good scheme for choosing that will be entirely consistent. It's always going to be subjective. The point of the images is just to make it easy to spot which mapper is which, so we're not just looking at some monolithic block of buttons. For that reason, I'd rather see a "mostly Rare" mapper with a Rare icon than have yet another Nintendo icon in there, but that's just my subjective opinion. - Rainwarrior (talk) 14:08, 12 June 2015 (MDT)

For the same reasons, I think Image:Mfr icon Namco Tengen.png is pushing the limits of utility for these icons, and I'd really hate to see someone try to stuff 3 companies into an icon. Don't try to cram too much information into these things. It's supposed to be easy to read at a glance, not tell you 20 years of game development history. - Rainwarrior (talk) 14:15, 12 June 2015 (MDT)

Also, the saturated green of the current icon really stands out from the others in an ugly way (it's very harsh against the white background). Personally I'd go with the 16/32-bit era logo with the gold rimmed blue badge, but again this is a rather subjective suggestion. (I don't think they had a consistent logo before then?) - Rainwarrior (talk) 15:30, 12 June 2015 (MDT)

Agreed. I intended the Nintendo icon to be used where no third party developer or publisher has a majority. Of the 34 unique games on mapper 7, 26 were either developed or ported by Rare, and an additional four were developed or ported by Zippo Games, which appears to also be Rare in the sense that Ultra is Konami. Hence Ꝛ on 7. Namco likewise has a stake in a supermajority of 206, which is why I think 206 deserves the Namco n. --Tepples (talk) 19:04, 12 June 2015 (MDT)

It's no problem as long as the way icons are chooses was never meant to be consistent. I was just pointing to an inconsistency.Bregalad (talk) 12:51, 14 June 2015 (MDT)

32x32 upscaling

I'd like to offer a guideline for upscaling mapper images 32x32. The vast majority display resolution is 16x16, and for that reason all of these images should be optimized for 16x16 first. What this means is that pixel art should be 16x16 and nearest-neighbour rescaled, creating the optimal image at 16x16 and defeating unpleasant linear resampling at 32x32. Do not upscale pixel art by adding smoother edges, etc, as this reduces legibility when downscaled to 16x16. For things that are vector art, text that is already anti-aliased, etc. feel free to take advantage of the full detail level at 32x32. Just remember the most important thing is legibility at 16x16. After doing a quick pass over it, I think everything we've got now is OK. - Rainwarrior (talk) 22:17, 12 June 2015 (MDT)

A newbie-friendly page introduction

As a beginner I found this page to be confusing and unhelpful. The opening paragraphs are overly technical and contain too many details and acronyms for a beginner to grok. The information contained may be factually true and helpful to some, but I'd really like to see a plain-English introduction added in addition to what's already on the page. Something like:

Mapper

NES games come in cartridges, and inside of those cartridges are various circuits and hardware. Different games use different circuits and hardware, and the configuration and capabilities of such cartridges is called their mapper. Mappers were used to extend the system and bypass its limitations, such as by adding RAM to the cartridge or even extra sound channels. More commonly though, mappers were used to allow games larger than 32K to be made.

Example games and their mappers:

Contra uses a mapper called UNROM, providing it with 128K of PRG ROM space.
Castlevania 3 uses a mapper called MMC5 offering additional sound channels (on Famicom systems only).
Bible Adventures uses the "Color Dreams" mapper which contains CIC-defeating circuitry.
Super Mario Bros. uses the simplest mapper: NROM, which contains 32K of PRG ROM and 8K of CHR ROM. Many early NES games and modern homebrew games use the NROM mapper.

Pubby (talk) 11:21, 11 May 2016 (MDT)

Talk:Mask ROM pinout

SLxROM, TLxROM

Does anyone have the pinout for SLxROM and TLxROM boards ? Such boards were apparently rarely/never used in PAL games so I can't do much about it, unless I pay more than $30 to import USA games. —User:Bregalad (talk) 04:34, 08 February 2014 (MST)

The pictures on NesCartDB show the SL3ROM, SL1ROM, and TL1ROM boards are using ordinary 28-pin 128KiB mask ROMs for CHR, combining PPU A13 and PPU /RD with a 74'32 (*-TL1ROM, NES-SL1ROM, NES-SL3ROM) or a one-transistor A≤B gate (HVC-SL1ROM).
The pictures on NesCartDB of SLRROM and SL2ROM similarly only indicate parts with typical pinouts: they have a standard 32-pin 128KiB mask ROM for CHR.
Only one copy of game, without photos, claims to have a TL2ROM board, which I'm going to declare a typo until further evidence arrives. —Lidnariq (talk) 12:57, 8 February 2014 (MST)

When you say "standard", does it mean JEDEC, or standards in regard to Nintendo's habits ?Bregalad (talk) 15:07, 8 February 2014 (MST)

The 28-pin ROM is the standard 28-pin 128KiB mask ROM pinout (JEDEC 21-C, p3.2.1-6 which specifies mask ROM pinout of 28-pin ROMs from 8KiB to 128KiB). The 32-pin CHRROMs look to be Nintendo's standard 32-pin layout, since at least one IC, µPD23C1013, is used as CHR on both SLRROM and TLROM. —Lidnariq (talk) 18:17, 8 February 2014 (MST)

Nintendo SROM CHR ROM pinout - 8 KBytes (24pin)

The pinout of this 64Kb (8KB) ROM is the same as the Motorola MCM68764/MCM68766 EPROM. Enjoy! - RJ @ arcadecomponents.com

Higher CHR lines

Apparently, the unused high address lines of PRG and CHR mask ROMs must be connected to VCC, but this was vital only on PRG ROMs as the CHR-ROM are not required to be enabled for booting, before the first mapper write. So, does games which don't use all their available CHR-space uses '1' for the unused bits ? For instance, a 32kb CHR-ROM MMC1 game should use either CHR bank range 8-15 or 24-31 instead of using 0-7 which would happen naturally, in order to set A15 to '1'. Does commercial games do this ?—User:Bregalad (talk) 04:34, 08 February 2014 (MST)

No, most commercial games more often use the lowest mirror (although sometimes a random mirror) of undersized ROMs. I'm not clear where the "must be" comment came from. —Lidnariq (talk) 12:57, 8 February 2014 (MST)

I think it came from me. It's a known fact Nintendo used different boards for different PRG sizes of compatible pinout (16k, 32k, 64k - respectively 128, 256 and 512 kbits). The only difference between these boards is that higher address lines that goes unused on smaller sizes are hard-wired to VCC, instead of being connected to the mapper. If the pins were unused on the mask ROMs, then it wouldn't matter to connect them on the mapper, so they could just use the biggest sized board for everything (i.e. NROM-256 instead of NROM-128, SBROM instead of SEROM, SAROM instead of SIROM, etc, etc...). CNROM boards also have a solder pad to choose between connecting A14 and forcing it to VCC (resulting in a 16k PRG-ROM).

It's clear that designing and producing more different boards with no reason makes few sense, so they probably had a reason for forcing unused higher address lines to VCC. My theory is that it could in some cases be either an enable signal, or a higher address lines, as they could use larger mask ROM, and program only the upper half/quarter and tie the line to VCC in order to mirror it to the whole range (effectively making it almost the same as an enable signal, bus conflicts aside). Bregalad (talk) 15:08, 8 February 2014 (MST)

Talk:MMC1

SOROM, SUROM, and SXROM

I'm a little fuzzy about why these are considered different NES 2.0 submappers. The functionality of all three of these looks the same to me if the extra banking bits become useless/mirror when the ROM/RAM addressed is a smaller size (just like in any other mapper supporting various sizes).

43210
+---+
PSSxC

4:P - A18 of 512k PRG ROM, disconnected if smaller
3:S - A13 of 16k PRG RAM, disconnected if smaller
2:S - A14 of 32k PRG RAM, disconnected if smaller
1:x - unused
0:C - 4k CHR banking control

What am I missing? I can't spot the incompatibility that necessitated three submappers. Isn't this just one mapper together? - Rainwarrior (talk) 00:58, 8 August 2015 (MDT)

Just my $2, but I fully agree with Rainwarrior.Bregalad (talk) 02:28, 9 August 2015 (MDT)

Yeah, tepples confirmed it in a discussion elsewhere (and lidnariq seemed to confirm it in an oblique way?). I've already put this information to use in the description at NES 2.0 submappers#001: MMC1 anyway. - Rainwarrior (talk) 11:58, 9 August 2015 (MDT)

The only issue I see is that people seem to like thinking of the two PRG-RAM banking bits in order, which would pose a problem if exchanging SXROM save RAM images is desired. On the other hand, this is a much more elegant way to handle it, so it sgtm. —Lidnariq (talk) 00:09, 10 August 2015 (MDT)

Actually, thinking about this for a moment, this is a far better explanation of why I think we don't need a submapper for SUROM/SXROM/SOROM, by parsing the bits as follows:

43210
+---+
EDCBA

4:E - CHR A16, if extant; PRG ROM A18, if extant
3:D - CHR A15, if extant; PRG RAM A13, if extant
2:C - CHR A14, if extant; PRG RAM A14, if extant
1:B - CHR A13, if extant
0:A - CHR A12

—Lidnariq (talk) 12:39, 11 August 2015 (MDT)

Talk:MMC2

Sprite Splits

I read carefully the operation of the PPU rendering and sprite evaluation, and it seems to me that you could use the sprites to adjust the CHR latch per scanlines (for example, make a sprite $FE and one line down $FD (if after the first one in the OAM) might make a single scanline to use the other bank). Is this correct? --Zzo38 (talk) 11:07, 16 June 2013 (MDT)

Yes, this could work. As you suggest, if you're willing to use sprites from the same pattern table as the background tiles you can do no-CPU-time raster effects. But that's also a big downside. I'm a little skeptical that the inclusion of two switchable banks is particularly useful, given how few pixels all the sprites can cover (using 8x16 sprites, only 14% of the screen). Maybe if you want to clip more than two sprites vertically on the same line, since currently the only solution is overlaying a sprite with another transparent sprite. —Lidnariq (talk) 11:37, 16 June 2013 (MDT)

Circuit to convert MMC2->MMC4 and vice-versa

I just realize the circuits I drew here several years ago are completely useless, apparently Nintendo didn't use such circuit in their cartridges, and nobody else is likely ever going to use them. They serve no "encyclopedic" purpose, it's merely a theoretical possibility that was never put in practice. Is it okay if I remove them ? 128.178.180.88 02:05, 15 April 2014 (MDT) I forgot to log in but it's me, who wrote the paragraph above.Bregalad (talk) 08:14, 15 April 2014 (MDT)

They illustrate the difference in a manner I find useful. I object to removing the MMC2→MMC4 one, at least; the MMC4→MMC2 one is enough more complex that I am open to argument. —Lidnariq (talk) 13:21, 15 April 2014 (MDT)

Then is it okay if I just remove the part on the MMC4 article (which is more complicated) and leave the one that is on this (MMC2) article which is more simple, "prooving" that it's possible to make a MMC4 from a MMC2 and a single 74xx series chip ? (although the proof is only theoretical, nobody ever prooved it for real as far I know) ? I'd say that if there is no objection I'll remove the MMC4 schematic in a few days. Bregalad (talk) 00:26, 29 April 2014 (MDT)

Talk:MMC3

The hardware section of this page needs to be tidied up a bit, because right now, it's just a giant infodump with little organization. :P --Drag 13:09, 4 June 2012 (PDT)

There's some documentation about the differences between MMC3 revisions here: [1] I'll add them in at some point, if nobody else does. --Drag 18:00, 19 April 2011 (UTC)

Contents

1 PRG RAM bank behavior
2 MMC3 scanline counter
3 Oversize "non-compliance"?
4 PRG RAM protection

PRG RAM bank behavior

When PRG RAM is accessed via $6000-$7FFF, what does the MMC3 put on the upper PRG ROM address lines? --Tepples 23:24, 20 April 2011 (UTC)

Ideally, the MMC3 wouldn't put anything on the ROM address lines. :P Either way, if the CPU is accessing $6000-7FFF, I'd imagine whatever chip is selected would see %011xxxxx xxxxxxxx on its address lines. RAM would just see the x part, and whatever mapper-supplemented upper address lines if the RAM is bankswitched. --Drag 04:05, 21 April 2011 (UTC)

When I hear "wouldn't put anything", I think "high impedance". It appears you claim that if $6000-$7FFF is accessed, the PRG A13 through PRG A18 outputs from the mapper are high-Z, not the value in either PRG bank register. Do I misunderstand? --Tepples 22:42, 21 April 2011 (UTC)

The simplest thing electrically is to never disable the address drivers. Given how MMC3 works I'd guess it drives the upper address lines high. Lidnariq 18:08, 22 April 2011 (UTC)

Actually, I'm not entirely sure I understand what you're saying. When you say PRG ROM address lines, I thought you meant the address lines on the actual ROM. Yes, even if the CPU is accessing $6000-7FFF, the ROM would still see the address bus, but it won't do anything with it, because the mapper won't select the chip. That's what I meant by "wouldn't put anything on the ROM address lines". Even though it's physically putting something there, the ROM is disabled so it never does anything with it.

If you're talking about what happens with WRAM, I imagine the chip wouldn't have the upper three address lines, unless the RAM is bankswitched. --Drag 07:33, 25 April 2011 (UTC)

I was asking whether or not it's feasible to build PRG RAM bankswitching by running the same upper address lines out of the mapper to both PRG ROM and PRG RAM. When PRG RAM is being accessed, what is the voltage on each of the upper address lines PRG A18-A13 (pins 23, 25, 21, 18, 22, 19) coming out of the MMC3? Does it depend on either of the PRG ROM bank values, or is it a constant value? --Tepples 13:25, 25 April 2011 (UTC)

Ahh, ok, that makes more sense. The MMC3 outputs different things to the most significant rom bits depending on what address is being accessed, so it's entirely possible that the circuitry involved selects between a couple different latches, depending on bits 14 and 13 of the PRG address. If it uses an ordinary decoder, then it's possible that bit 15 goes to the /OE of whatever multiplexer it uses.
TL;DR: The "banks" for $0000-$7FFF may mirror the bank configuration of $8000-$FFFF, or it may not. Either way, accessing $6000-7FFF is like accessing $E000-FFFF (which is fixed to the last bank), so whether it looks at A15 or not, you'll probably end up with all 1's across A13+. This is just my speculation though. --Drag 19:56, 25 April 2011 (UTC)

I can't say for sure, because very complex equipment would be needed to verify this, but it's extremely likely that the MMC3's PRG-banking ciruitery completely ignores the state of A15. That is, acessing any adress with A15 low will have the higher adress lines pointed to the same latch as if the corresponding adress with A15 high was used. In particular, when acessing $6000-$7fff, the MMC3 will act like when acessing $e000-$ffff (which means all adress lines will go high, pointing to the "last-hardwired" bank).

This hypothesis is especially robust when you consider there is no A15 on the cart edge, so you have to invert PRG /CE to get the state of A15. Also, when the PPU fetches nametable area ($2000-$2fff), the MMC3 does bank the CHR-ROM exactly like when acessing the corresponding area with A13 low, that is $0000-$1fff, and the TLSROM and TKSROM boards makes a good use of this.

This is valid not only for the MMC3 but for 99% of mappers in fact : Anyone would be crazy to add extra circuitry in their chips so that it acts differently when the CPU is adressing space where the ROM will never respond anyways. (Probably only mappers such as the MMC5 or FME7, which can map ROM and RAM anywhere regardless of the state of A15, will not follow this rule). So, no, sorry but no PRG-RAM switching would be possible on MMC3. But any mapper that was not designed to switch PRG-RAM, but that was designed to switch PRG-ROM at $e000-$ffff could be abused to also switch RAM. Bregalad 11:39, 1 May 2011 (UTC)

MMC3 scanline counter

What happens when both background and sprites are fetched from $1xxx? --Zepper 02:28, 8 November 2011 (UTC)

I think that should disable IRQs, because A12 will never be 0 for longer than 4 pixels —Lidnariq (talk) 14:12, 25 January 2015 (MST)

Even during the dummy fetches at the end of a line (337-340)? --Tepples (talk) 16:03, 25 January 2015 (MST)

Depends on what the idle cycle's address is. If A12 is 0 during it, then A12 could be low for 9 pixels. And then that gets into the question below… —Lidnariq (talk) 17:40, 25 January 2015 (MST)

The MMC3 scanline counter is based entirely on PPU A12, triggered on rising edges (after the line remains low for a sufficiently long period of time) Which period of time exactly? —anonymous contributer from 94.254.14.226

Without clocking it manually, it's hard to say, but certainly not more than 64 pixels (because it still works if the pattern tables are swapped). See also https://github.com/christopherpow/nes-test-roms/tree/master/mmc3_irq_tests ; test 3.4 there also requires that it be no longer than ≈22cy, but that's about the same as 64 pixels. —Lidnariq (talk) 14:01, 25 January 2015 (MST)

I performed some tests using my own dumper and real cartridge. Seems like IRQ counter working when there are 2 rising edges of M2 between falling and rising of A12. It's the only one necessary condition. —83.149.9.144 07:25, 31 January 2015 (MST)

Oversize "non-compliance"?

I could use a clarification about this edit by Lidnariq. If the ROM size is <= 512K the top two data bits have to be ignored when writing the bank register. What possible incompatibility could result from implementing an 8-bit register? Why would an emulator choose to present an error to the user instead of simply supporting the oversize ROM? - Rainwarrior (talk) 13:59, 30 May 2015 (MDT)

For the same reason that NES emulators shouldn't implement a plugin that takes in arbitrary video and quantizes it to the NES output: the hardware that does that doesn't exist. Same problem with ROM hacks that only work in Nesticle. Emulators must implement the restrictions of the hardware, because otherwise you end up with crap like the aforementioned ROM hack where because they don't understand why they're not allowed to do that, they include patches to hack FCEUXDSP and Nintendulator to support their BS oversize ROM, and no-one can ever make a reproduction that uses an MMC3. —Lidnariq (talk) 14:55, 30 May 2015 (MDT)

Ahh, the extension seems extremely logical and straightforward to me, but after checking FCEUX, Nestopia, and Nintendulator, I can see that all of them prevent oversized MMC3. I don't really understand the motivation for this (does it create other software incompatibility?), but the lack of emulator support is good reason to remove oversize support from the infobox. Hadn't read the description of that romhack either (was just part of a merge), but it's kind of interesting that not much supports it. I'll revise. - Rainwarrior (talk) 15:15, 30 May 2015 (MDT)

PRG RAM protection

I just noticed that Zoda's Revenge uses some strange writes to $A001 (RAM protection).

   LDA #$30
   STA $A001

or

   LDA #$B0
   STA $A001

So RAM should be protected. But it writes to RAM after this.

FCE ultra actually ignores state of $A001 for mapper #4 and game is working fine but it crashes on my cartridge (no sound after start, crashes later). Is it game using some other revision of MMC3? Or MMC3 actually using other bits in $A001 too? Or maybe this game using some weird wiring of MMC3? 94.253.14.226 01:20, 22 September 2015 (MDT)

Startropics and Startropics 2 use the MMC6, not the MMC3, which is the same except for this write protect behaviour. Unfortunately both are assigned to iNES mapper 4, so emulators that chose to implement the write protection have a compatibility conflict. - Rainwarrior (talk) 01:39, 22 September 2015 (MDT)

Thank you very much! 94.253.14.226 01:47, 22 September 2015 (MDT)

Talk:MMC5

Don't Repeat Yourself failure

Ok, it's crazy to have two completely different pages explaining the MMC5 mapper, one on iNES mapper 5 and the other on MMC5. I think the info should be present on a single page (like it is for all other mappers).

Well in fact it seems it's Zeromus who added Dish's notes on all iNES mapper pages. This would be nice if the info wasn't already present on the wiki - having twice the same info isn't very logical is it ? I don't know what to do but something should probably be changed...Bregalad 00:36, 23 March 2012 (PDT)

Disch' format is much better for reading. Funny, I was really thinking to discuss about such thing. :) --Zepper 14:44, 23 March 2012 (PDT)

Problem solved. @Zepper : If there is a particular point that should be improved about how the mappers are presented on the wiki, then please change it (or at least say more precisely what is much better).Bregalad (talk) 06:02, 20 April 2015 (MDT)

Rather than just deleting them, I've been trying to review the disch notes and compare them to the existing article, integrating anything that it was adding before removing it. It's more time consuming than just deleting them, but the whole point of zeromus pasting them here was that they might improve the articles. Sometimes they add nothing, for sure, but it's worth reviewing before deleting, I think. In the process you might find other things here and there to improve in the mapper articles too. This review process is healthy for the wiki content. We don't need to be in a hurry to scour the disch notes from the wiki. - Rainwarrior (talk) 20:38, 20 April 2015 (MDT)

They have been here for more than three years, so how much time should have been waited for their removal in your opinion? 10 years? As I said they are still available, so you can just download them, and do the review work using your local copy of Dish notes. No point to have them pasted here, period. I absolutely agree that such a review work is benefical, and if there is a particular part you'd want me to review, just ask.Bregalad (talk) 03:13, 21 April 2015 (MDT)

If you'd bothered to pay attention to what Rainwarrior's been doing, he's been carefully looking over each page and incorporating Disch's documentation as he goes, not just blindly removing everything.—Lidnariq (talk) 04:53, 21 April 2015 (MDT)

I did not just remove it but link to the original place. That's a different thing. Please explain me why Rainwarrior cannot download dish's document on his hard drive and work with that copy. (answer : he can, and that makes a lot more sense). Anyways I'm sick of editing this wiki for a while. Bregalad (talk) 06:04, 21 April 2015 (MDT)

There are several reasons why I would not do it that way:
- If I download the document and begin integrating it into the Wiki, it can no longer be a collaborative process. If I do that, I have to do every single one myself (nobody can help, sensibly, without being redundant), and there is really no good way to know which have been done already.
- Several of the Disch notes sections have had edits in the time since being pasted here, and all of these deserve an overview before being removed.
- I believe zeromus' addition of the Disch notes to the Wiki was overall a good thing, filling in content where it was missing at the temporary expense of redundancy.
- Simply reverting someone's changes without reviewing them treats them in bad faith.
"if there is a particular part you'd want me to review, just ask." Please review every deletion you make. That's what I am asking, and that was the project I had begun, myself. If you don't want to do this, please just leave it there. I will get to it eventually! I had started working on this carefully (but slowly). It will probably take me a few months if I do it alone, but I really don't appreciate someone coming in with sweeping deletions and making it difficult for me to try and attempt to finally make good on zeromus' good-faith effort to have the wiki improved by Disch's notes. - Rainwarrior (talk) 10:48, 21 April 2015 (MDT)

Oh because those HAVE HAD EDITS ?! :O

Now everything makes even less sense. I give up! This wiki is a huge mess anyway and will always be. Collaborative work just doesn't work. My only regrets is to have worked so hard for the hardware page and the FDS page, when they are doomed to be in the little of this huge disorganized mess with no head and no tail. Any change I make is systematically criticized, even if I asked in the forums if it was ok to do it, and nobody reacts which I belive is "I'm ok with that", but after the change everytime screams like "Begalad you're doing it all wrong, revert those changes!" It's the fourth time there is an issue like that where changes I made in a lame attempt to make this wiki a slightly better place are refuted only AFTER I made them.

By the way a great thing would be to report those edits to RHDN, so that at least a clean and up to date version of Dish' doccument lies somewhere (and that is on RHDN, not here).185.26.182.29 12:47, 21 April 2015 (MDT)

If consensus for large scale editing has been established in a topic on the forum, it would be a good idea to include the URL of this topic in the edit summary of each edit so that we know what you're doing. --Tepples (talk) 12:56, 21 April 2015 (MDT)

I can't complain about your changes before you make them, unless you tell us what your intentions are first. If you want to make large scale changes unannounced, yes, people will complain after the fact. When else would they complain? I think we want the same thing in the end (no more redundant Disch notes), but I am unhappy with the way you are doing it. I began several days ago a long term effort to do it carefully to make sure we aren't losing information as the Disch notes are removed, but suddenly you have come in to just bulldoze it to the ground, and this does bother me. This isn't collaboration, this is in effect just you having an edit war with zeromus with a 2 year delay. I don't know what argument you had about the FDS article, or what, but it's not at all relevant to the current discussion. - Rainwarrior (talk) 13:13, 21 April 2015 (MDT)

Yeah, it really suck because we're making efforts and we get in the way of eachother. That's just how this wiki works and is doomed to work. As for the thread it's here, but it was in an abandoned state after one day. If I say "should we do that" and nobody react I assume nobody cares if I to do it. Well wrong assumption I guess. I was absolutely sure the Dish docs were untouched that is why I acted this way. However the edits from the are not lost because they're in the history logs. I'll track for them, and update new Dish docs to RHDN to apologize for this behaviour (so I don't have to deal with the wiki anymore but still repair what I have broken). I hope this is okay for everyone. It will take a few days, though.Bregalad (talk) 13:28, 21 April 2015 (MDT)

I reacted, and I started working on the problem. I didn't want to just revert your deletions because it would basically be an edit war if we don't talk about it first. Undoing a single revision I can explain in the comment summary, but doing many is kind of hostile. I know you spent a good amount of time (in good faith) making the edits, though zeromus also spent a good amount of time putting that stuff up in the first place. Both of you wanted to improve the wiki, and I'm trying to mediate this by keeping anything of value that was there. You don't need to revert anything yourself, at this point; I have been reviewing the changes, and keeping a list of deletions at User:Rainwarrior, and I'll eventually get through them one by one as part of the ongoing project I started. I want to keep all the document links you added, for eaxmple, because those are good. As for updating RHDN, you can do that if you like, but I'm only concerned about the wiki. - Rainwarrior (talk) 13:42, 21 April 2015 (MDT)

MMC5-internal RAM

What is the logic in the ASIC that causes it to write zero if the PPU is not rendering? --Zzo38 01:51, 22 September 2012 (MDT)

Another question about the ExRAM is, what happens when you try to read/write ExRAM nametables through the PPU registers, and if extended attribute mode is selected, what happens when reading/writing attribute tables using the PPU registers (when it isn't rendering the picture, and in any potentially random order)? --Zzo38 (talk) 22:23, 24 February 2014 (MST)

Yet another question : Is the ExRAM battery backed ? It would seem no, but technically the Battery is connected to the MMC5 so who knowns ? Bregalad (talk) 04:38, 5 May 2014 (MDT)

Even more extended PRG RAM

Parsimony of silicon strongly implies that the higher address lines (corresponding to the 0x78 bits of the register) are still driven for the registers from $5114 to $5116 even when RAM is selected, meaning >64KiB PRG-RAM would be usable when mapped to $8000-$DFFF. It's conceivable that these same bits of the register at $5113 (controlling PRG-RAM bank) are implemented, since they have to feed a multiplexer anyway. Something to test, maybe. —Lidnariq (talk) 23:34, 20 January 2014 (MST)

Talk:MMC5 pinout

Will the colors still scroll in CL mode even if the pattern isn't? --Zzo38 (talk) 12:52, 28 April 2013 (MDT)

CL mode => PPU controls CHR A0, CHR A1, CHR A2. SL mode => MMC5 controls those lines instead (passing the signal through when vertical split is not used, with a delay).

In both cases (scrolling or not), the vertical split section have the MMC5 trick the PPU by feeding name and attributes fetches with tiles from EXRAM instead of VRAM (while disabling the real VRAM). When scrolling is used as well, it just fetch from a different address for the coarse scrolling (adding a row to the fetched tile every 8 pixels), and shift the address of the CHR-ROM for fine scrolling.

So, in CL mode, the MMC5 decides which tile to display while the PPU choose which line of the tile is displaying, while in SL mode the MMC5 decides everything. If ones tries to use a different fine scroll for the main area and the vertical split (EXRAM) area, then the tile themselves will scroll smoothly, but their content won't, and will stick to the main background. This will lead to a quite interesting effect !

As for attributes, the MMC5 has to "guess" which attribute byte is fetched basing on the fine scrolling. If it scrolls fine in SL mode (let's assume it does) then it means the colour data is fetched form the correct place within EXRAM, so it will scroll the same way in CL mode, because the CHR-ROM is not involved in any way. Bregalad (talk) 15:35, 8 February 2014 (MST)

Yes, this is exactly what I expected it would do. Is the delay ever significant? What exactly do pins 97 and 98 do, then? Are they used for saving power or something like that? --Zzo38 (talk) 01:07, 9 February 2014 (MST)

CHR enable lines...where?

It seems like pins 29-30 would be the logical place to put them, but is that right? Where are those? Surely they're signals that the MMC5 generates? Is a /WE implemented so as to make CHR-RAM easy?Myask (talk) 18:52, 12 July 2016 (MDT)

I think Rockman 4 Minus Infinity, which uses MMC5 with CHR RAM, just runs /WE from the cart edge directly to the CHR RAM chip. --Tepples (talk) 20:42, 12 July 2016 (MDT)

Because the MMC5 can't do anything peculiar with its pattern table (e.g. no ROM nametables), the carts just normally connect PPU A13 to ROM /CE and PPU /RD to ROM /OE. I wouldn't be surprised if one of pin 29 or pin 30 were (PPU A13 OR PPU /RD), though, to accommodate a never-released board with a 28-pin 128 KiB mask ROM. —Lidnariq (talk) 22:58, 12 July 2016 (MDT)

Talk:Music tools

The drum to sample converter links to a thread which links to a dead link. Has anyone made a backup of the tool ? So we can link to it on nesdev main page or something like that instead ? Bregalad 20:32, 30 October 2010 (UTC)

Sorry about that. My server's hard drive crashed and I moved to a new provider. I've restored the archive from backup. Lidnariq 01:38, 31 October 2010 (UTC)

Great, then maybe we could have a working link ?Bregalad 11:23, 31 October 2010 (UTC)

Augh, the web server was down. I turned it back on... Lidnariq 02:30, 1 November 2010 (UTC)

Good, but I don't see any .exe file or anything in the like in the archive Bregalad 14:03, 5 November 2010 (UTC)

I never claimed there was, it always was a perl script with some dependencies. Lidnariq 15:11, 5 November 2010 (UTC)

OK and how am I supposed to compile/run this on my computer ?? Bregalad 17:25, 5 November 2010 (UTC)

Under linux, install perl, PDL, and PDL::Audio. Under windows... I dunno, the thread had someone there try to get it working but didn't succeed. I really haven't thought about this for two years. The 'right' solution is to figure out how on earth libfftw works and rewrite it in C, but I haven't bothered. Lidnariq 22:05, 5 November 2010 (UTC)

OK Ubuntu currently crashes before booting on my PC (stupid non-working automatic updates) but I'll try re-installing it when I'll have the time for that and hopefully get it working.Bregalad 18:14, 6 November 2010 (UTC)

Talk:Myths

Contents

1 Picture
2 All three color emphasis bits with color 0D
3 Source the myths
4 Some Facts that not many people knew (or mention at least)

Picture

- An offhand comment. Wouldn't be better to change "NTSC NES picture" term into "NTSC NES PPU output"? Perhaps the second one sounds more technical than the original though. A NES picture could be anything like the straight thing: a picture of a NES unit, for example. When you say "PPU output", we have something more concrete. Yup, it's a picture, or "frame", but not "a picture of the NES", anyways... :) --Zepper 23:11, 2 February 2011 (UTC)

I was under the impression that "picture" is the word used in video standards for any time that isn't a blanking period. --Tepples (talk) 19:31, 8 September 2015 (MDT)

All three color emphasis bits with color 0D

According to my interpretation of various posts in this forum thread: sony trinitron + color emphasis bits = scrambled image?, if you use all three color emphasis bits and use color 0D, that color's signal may dip too low and confuse some TVs:

In the first post, GradualGames says he used all three color emphasis bits to dim the screen and got "an extremely ugly bunch of scanline artifacts" on his Sony Trinitron. In a later post, Sdwave says he also saw "some bending" using one of the palette demos on a Trinitron and suggested using 3F [= 1D*] for black instead of 0D. Later, GradualGames confirms using 0E [= 1D*] instead of 0D got rid of the artifacts.

*According NTSC video, the xE and xF colors send the same signal level as 1D.

Lidnariq points out that mathematically, even color 1D with all three color emphasis bits dips lower than the normal black:

If all preemphasis bits are set, then color 1D ("black") becomes blacker-than-black and 01-0C no longer decode to a valid RGB color from the received YIQ values (Their brightness is approximately equal to unattenuated color 1D). So if it looks like scanlines restarting all over the place, maybe that's why?

But based on Sdwave's and GradualGames's comments, 1D with all three color emphasis bits was fine on their Trinitrons.

--Bavi H (talk) 21:10, 23 June 2013 (MDT)

Color emphasis does not get applied for phases $xE or $xF, and it similarly does not get applied during horizontal (x=270-327) or vertical (y=241-261) blanking. --Quietust (talk) 17:23, 24 June 2013 (MDT)

Then someone's going to have to make a test ROM to run on an RGB system that displays emphasized $1D on a field of $0F to see how readable it is. --Tepples (talk) 17:41, 24 June 2013 (MDT)

I think I remember someone mentioning having a complete set of Kevtris's 2C03/4/5 dumps except for the "grey"scale dump for one of them; I'm pretty certain on those PPUs it indicated colors xE and xF being collapsed to x0 when the bit was set. ("snarky quotes" because scrambled palettes cause it to not necessarily be grey) I don't know if the greyscale bit is masked with the same flag as the emphasis bits, though. —Lidnariq (talk) 19:51, 24 June 2013 (MDT)

It doesn't tell you what it does with emphasis bits though. I too agree someone should test the function of emphasis bits of $xE and $xF on RGB systems (such as a Famicom Titler or Famicom TV). It would be useful to know, if making a emulator, hardware clone, or a game that uses the emphasis bits. --Zzo38 (talk) 01:47, 25 June 2013 (MDT)

Quietust, thanks for pointing out that using the emphasis bits doesn't attenuate the xE and xF colors, I didn't notice or remember that part of the NTSC video page. Everyone else, I was talking about an NTSC PPU sending a signal to an NTSC TV, not an RGB PPU sending a signal to an RGB monitor. My original point was that the Myths page says

Myth: Enabling more than one color emphasis bit at once will damage the PPU, or at least cause the TV to lose sync.

I agree it's unlikely that enabling multiple emphasis bits will damage the PPU, but according to the forum posts I mentioned, it does seem possible to confuse a TV's line sync if you use all three color emphasis bits and color 0D. And as Lidnariq posted, mathematically (edit:) the attenuated 1D level is lower that the black level, so perhaps using it with all three emphasis bits might confuse some TVs too?

(Above, I misbelieved the xE and xF colors would also be attenuated and so they'd have the same level as an attenuated 1D, so I misinterpreted Sdwave's and GradualGames's comments as equivalent to saying 1D was a safe color to use with all three color emphasis bits. Now I understand the xE and xF colors aren't affected by the color emphasis attenuation, so it's clear they have the same signal level as an unattenuated 1D and they're safe to use with all three emphasis bits. It's not clear how the attenuated 1D level behaves with actual TVs (I didn't see 1D mentioned when the posters described problems), but mathematically I can see it might be wise to avoid it.)

If others agree the forum posts are describing line sync problems (or can recreate the results), maybe the Myths page can be revised to clarify it's possible to confuse (some?) TV's line sync when using all three emphasis bits with color 0D (and maybe color 1D too?).

--Bavi H (talk) 20:38, 25 June 2013 (MDT)

added links to specific posts, struck out misunderstandings in my original post above --Bavi H (talk) 22:13, 25 June 2013 (MDT)

Source the myths

I would be a great idea to know where the myths comes from, adding sources and link to wrong information whenever possible. This would also avoid people "making up their own myths", just for the fun of it.Bregalad (talk) 05:21, 26 May 2015 (MDT)

This any better? --Tepples (talk) 17:58, 26 May 2015 (MDT)

Why does the text appear so tiny on screen?

Bavi H mistyped a closing tag on small text above. - Rainwarrior (talk) 09:49, 26 May 2015 (MDT)

Some Facts that not many people knew (or mention at least)

Using an interrupt (the one used by the sample player, you could generate an interrupt on any screen line (200). In each H-blank you could write 3 colours (and since the 4th is transparent... so for something like a Horizontal shooter, levels with different coloured background images top & bottom. I even wrote a converter that took a picture drawn in OCP Art Studio+ (I just copied how OPC worked on the ST and adapted for images up to 256 colours) fixed to the 53 colours (0-C,10-1C,20-2c,30-3C & OD) available. On each line, I allowed the artist to change 3 colours and after it was drawn, the OCP scanned and came up with an image highlighting errors. These were solved by placing sprites over the error. Sprites could actually be multiplexed so on any lines with no change, I could reuse a sprite OR swap a palette. What can I say... it was as good as you can expect and taught me a useful lesson which made it into Tomb Raider Gameboy colour where I got 2304 colours on screen and pretty damned good images of the whole team. Access is A+B+R+U... or +D (I forget the last one BUT if you hit all 4 in the same frame, about 20 hidden pictures were added - we had to use the biggest cart but were left with 200 odd K.... so as well as the title screen, there were more & better images—(unsigned post by 213.106.56.145 at 11:52, 7 September 2015)

There is not enough time to change even one palette entry during hblank, let alone three. Rendering must be disabled after pixel 256 (in order to be invisible) and enabled before pixel 320 (in order to be invisible). This is only 64 pixels, or 21⅓ CPU cycles. It takes 27 cycles to update a single palette entry:

first half of PPUADDR (free, can happen before rendering is disabled)
disable rendering (1 cycle: the first 3 cycles are free)
second half of PPUADDR (4 cycles)
palette update (4 cycles)
load three new values for next three writes (6 cycles, can be skipped if some of the values are duplicates)
first half of PPUADDR to reset screen to correct location on screen after render stop (4 cycles)
second half of PPUADDR to &c (4 cycles)
enable rendering (4 cycles)

In the specific (and unlikely) case where you can fit all the values that you'll write into just the 6502's three registers, you still have the completely unavoidable 2 pixels of jitter, one more than you can spare.

Possible workarounds:

Blank scanlines
Disable rendering early, as is done by the Indiana Jones and the Last Crusade title screen losing any detail (it's now all the backdrop color) from 18 pixels in exchange for 6 CPU cycles. —Lidnariq (talk) 01:50, 8 September 2015 (MDT)

The practical rate of color replacement with zero artifacts is about one 3-color subpalette per blank line, or the entire background palette in 4 blank lines, or background and sprite palettes in 8 blank lines. So you can have separate palettes for a playfield and status bar, or for both players' playfields in a split-screen 2-player game. --Tepples (talk) 19:29, 8 September 2015 (MDT)

Ok, here's a goofy idea: generate address bus conflicts and the use the bonus cycle from page crossing; write the first value to PPUADDR, and then have four LDA $22F7,x. Externally drive R/W and some of A0..A2 low; also drive the data bus. This allows eight writes in 20 CPU cycles, which, if the timing is permissible to the PPU, should be enough to update 3 palette entries, or update 1 palette entry and do a full 2006-2005-2005-2006 scroll reset. —Lidnariq (talk) 02:01, 9 September 2015 (MDT)

Talk:Namco 163

Wither 106?

I see that Namco 106 has been eradicated from the text of the wiki. I don't know where the number 106 came from originally, so I'm not defending its existence at all, however, it deserves some mention, at least on this page, because it is a commonly used name, even if incorrect. Having no mention of it at all will make it confusing for those who are trying to look it up. Some older programs, like VirtuaNSF or PPMCK/MML use the name 106, for instance.

I'll add a note to this page's lead, but I'd appreciate if someone who knows more about the issue would revise it. - Rainwarrior (talk) 10:04, 11 February 2013 (MST)

Extra 128 bytes of PRG RAM

What is this? Could you please explain it in the article somewhere? (I can't find the information.) Adding it to just the infobox is hella confusing. - Rainwarrior (talk) 11:01, 23 April 2015 (MDT)

Is this referring to the internal audio RAM? I don't think that should be considered as PRG-RAM, since it's not on the PRG address bus, but written through a port. (It's no more PRG-RAM than CHR-RAM is.) If you want to explain that it can be used as RAM if needed, this needs a proper description in the article. (Presumably you have to disable audio via $E000 to do this? I know the audio hardware normally writes to its own channel registers while operating.) - Rainwarrior (talk) 11:24, 23 April 2015 (MDT)

Yes, the internal audio RAM. I don't know that the internal postincrement is fast enough to keep up with execution or DMA, but several games use it for saving, so even given its indirect addressing, it seems important to mention. —Lidnariq (talk) 12:50, 23 April 2015 (MDT)

Talk:Namco 163 audio

Contents

1 Point of terminology: Namco 106 vs. Namco 163
2 Mechanism
3 Mixing noise approximation
4 Found resistor
5 N163 incorrect terminology?

Point of terminology: Namco 106 vs. Namco 163

A regular on another wiki, who might not qualify for trusted on wiki.nesdev.com because he isn't active on the BBS, sent me a message on my talk page at that wiki that Namco 106 audio might need a rename. --Tepples 14:52, 15 December 2010 (UTC)

Mechanism

Is the cycle-by-cycle behavior known? I can guess it's something like "ld_7f ld_8 add_9 st_9 ld_a add_b st_b ld+mask_c add_d bound_c st_d add_e ld_indirect mult_f st_dac"—Lidnariq (talk) 13:41, 11 February 2013 (MST)

I think that would require a decap; it would be hard to determine this externally. The pseudocode I put as an example seems to give very accurate results though. - Rainwarrior (talk) 14:16, 11 February 2013 (MST)

Should be able to figure out which cycle 9, b, and d are updated. But otherwise, yeah.—Lidnariq (talk) 14:45, 11 February 2013 (MST)

How do you intend to do that? They're write-only registers. You can sort of read them by setting the waveform position to sit on the registers and recording the audio out (this is how the contents were determined), but the output only changes every 15 cycles, so there's no way I can think of to see anything getting updated at a finer granularity than that. - Rainwarrior (talk) 02:05, 12 February 2013 (MST)

The same way blargg's tests test the timing of write-only PPU registers: very precisely timed writes. --Tepples (talk) 09:50, 12 February 2013 (MST)

Hmm, so you're saying to devise a test for each of the control bytes, to be executed at each of the 15 cycle alignments, and then deduce from the signal collected what happened in each of these tests? I suppose you could mark your starting alignment with a $4011 write as well. Anyhow... I can see how it would be possible in theory. The real question I suppose is whether anyone will do it? - Rainwarrior (talk) 11:31, 12 February 2013 (MST)

I'm not convinced they're write-only. Certainly the interface as a whole isn't (e.g. games use it as save memory). In order for the control registers to be write-only, they'd have to be shadowed from the 128b actually presented...—Lidnariq (talk) 13:21, 12 February 2013 (MST)

Ah, yeah I hadn't thought about how they are down in the $4000 range. Reading might be possible then. Well, if you test it out, let me know what you find. - Rainwarrior (talk) 18:31, 12 February 2013 (MST)

Mixing noise approximation

A reasonable approximation of the switching noise, and cheaper than full resampling, is to sum the channels as though there were no switching noise, resample to the soundcard's native rate, and then multiply the output by (1+sin(k·n)), where k is chosen to produce a sine wave at the switching rate. (In the case of rendering audio at a rate higher than 48kHz, you may also add sine waves at every multiple of the switching rate that's below the nyquist rate. But none of those should be audible)

Justification: if the sound through each channel is uncorrelated, then it can be treated as though each channel is sounding while all others are silent. In which case, this is standard DSP upsampling, which produces modulated copies of the baseband signal at every multiple of the switching rate. —Lidnariq (talk) 15:30, 17 July 2013 (MDT)

Honestly, I don't think most people will want to listen to the switching noise, so a performance-saving approximation of it probably isn't that desirable. People who want the switching noise are probably interested in accuracy at the expense of performance. Though, in my NSFPlay implementation, it seems that it's not really a performance problem either way, emulating and mixing the N163 is faster/simpler than most of the other chips. - Rainwarrior (talk) 12:11, 18 July 2013 (MDT)

Found resistor

In their current state, these seem a bit misleading. The values for Rolling Thunder and King of Kings seem especially dubious if there is a direct relationship between the resistance values found and the output level. Is there only one resistor involved? (What is the mixing circuit like? Shouldn't the N163 output have its own resistor?) I notice the King of Kings board on Bootgod has 3 surface mount resistors on it... are we sure we have the right one here?

If all the values are correct, then we need to consider whether other factors affect the mix and include them (otherwise the resistance alone is useless). Either this or the carts observed are very inconsistent (I don't want to presume this unless we can be sure). If they are incorrect, we need to fix them before they can be of use.

I like the idea that they can add useful information, but I kinda think we should remove it for now until it can be verified better.

4-Channel Game | Volume | Samples | Resistor on cart
Final Lap | 3.6x | 1 | 4.7k or 15k
Mappy Kids |  ? | 0 | 10k
Megami Tensei II | 4.0x | 1 | 4.7k
Namco Classic 2 |  ? | 0 |  ?
Rolling Thunder | 6.5x | 2 | 22k
Sangokushi |  ? | 0 | 4.7k
Sangokushi 2 |  ? | 0 |  ?
8-Channel Game | Volume | Samples |
Erika to Satoru no Yumebouken | 8.5x | 1 | 10k
King of Kings | 7.3x | 1 | 4.7k

-- Rainwarrior (talk) 14:34, 18 July 2013 (MDT)

Wow, Famicom carts are not easy to open. My Rolling Thunder has a 22k resistor connected to pin 45. My Erika to Satoru has a 10k resistor connected to pin 45. In my tests of these carts, Erika is definitely ~25% louder than Rolling Thunder (N163 relative to 2A03), so I don't think resistance alone is going to be a good enough indicator. I'll take some board pictures if you want to study them. - Rainwarrior (talk) 14:55, 18 July 2013 (MDT)

Boards of Erika and Rolling Thunder:

https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/883356/n163_erika.jpg
https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/883356/n163_rolling_thunder.jpg

-Rainwarrior (talk) 15:18, 18 July 2013 (MDT)

I found the information on a 2chan thread and copied it to iNES Mapper 210 (with citation). The mixing circuit on N163 carts seems to always be:

 AudioFrom2A03 --- Resistor ---+--- AudioToRFModulator
                               |
                          AudioFrom163

So there's got to be some intrinsic resistance on the 163's output to mix properly. I'm not clear how to resolve the resistors with the volumes you found either; it should be a reciprocal function of the resistance. There's also the photos on NesCartDB of the boards, so that you don't need to open them (Or, since all the games seem to use the above circuit, you should be able to just measure the resistance using an ohmmeter without opening the cartridge)

But in NesCartDB, his picture of Rolling Thunder shows a 15kΩ resistor instead. And there's other evidence that different production runs of the same game may well have different resistors, and so different volumes.

It really seems like your musing on a heuristic is a better approach. I'm mostly trying to point out that the mixes are not even fixed per game —Lidnariq (talk) 16:32, 18 July 2013 (MDT)

If Rolling Thunder uses 22k and Erika to Satoru no Yumebouken uses 10k, it's clear that there's another factor here. Presumably different revisions of the N163 have different internal resistance? If we can't measure that, or identify N163 revisions (good luck with these globs), I don't imagine we can really glean anything useful from just the 2A03 mix resistor. As far as games being inconsistent, I do expect changes with different runs, but I wouldn't assume any wide variation in the volume unless we can actually measure it. It seems plausible that we could find 2 runs of Rolling Thunder that have different N163 revisions, and different resistors that compensate for that, keeping the volume consistent? It's equally plausible that lack of care with this could lead to wide variation, but I don't want to assume that until it's actually found in the field. The Rolling Thunder on BootGod looks like mine except it's missing the cap (to ground?) on the audio-- are you sure it says 15k? there don't seem to be enough pixels to read it. I measured a recording of a second Rolling Thunder cart taken by jrlepage (this is what is meant by the Samples column), and it was really close (~6.4x vs ~6.6x). Maybe I can put a call out for recordings on the forums. - Rainwarrior (talk) 18:16, 18 July 2013 (MDT)

If you're logged into NEScartDB, you can click on the image to get an original-resolution copy. (Things I didn't know until he told me). ... of course, now I notice that that's actually the back for Final Lap...
Anyway, as far as we know there's only one revision of the 163; certainly all the QFP versions are labelled the same. I guess who knows what's going on under the epoxy? —Lidnariq (talk) 23:14, 18 July 2013 (MDT)

Yes, I know about the original resolution images, just the one for Rolling Thunder is unreadable even at the original resolution (unless there's more than one board image available?). Anyhow, I put up a survey request on the forum. Hopefully I can compile some useful information from it. Also, I did test pins 45-46 with an ohmmeter to verify that works, and I got 22.2k and 9.9k for my two carts, so that's good to know of an easier way to verify than opening it up and reading the resistors. I damaged my Erika cart's casing trying to open it, there was a centre pin that had a death grip on the front of the cart. I'm currently gluing it back together! - Rainwarrior (talk) 23:39, 18 July 2013 (MDT)
http://forums.nesdev.com/viewtopic.php?f=3&t=10294

This is entirely academic, but to make sure we're looking at the same thing: http://bootgod.dyndns.org:7777/profile.php?id=3339 then image.php?ImageID=4097 then getoriginalimg.php?ImageID=4097 ... I see two resistors, labelled 473 and 153 (or 47k and 15k) —Lidnariq (talk) 02:16, 19 July 2013 (MDT)

Okay, that's weird. I would go to the profile, and then click the image (going to image.php), which is what I had presumed was the original size of the image, and that's what I was looking at (looks like this, below is my own picture scaled to similar size). How do you get to the "getoriginalimg.php" from there? I tried typing it in the link and I had to log in, but even after logging in I can't find anything to click on to get from image.php to getoriginalimg.php. Typing it in manually downloads a file that is named Final Lap, though, so... that's strange, but at least I can see that it's 15k now! - Rainwarrior (talk) 11:26, 19 July 2013 (MDT)

Once you're looking at the 600px image, if you're logged in, you click on that image again to get to getoriginalimg.php —Lidnariq (talk) 12:47, 19 July 2013 (MDT)

Hmm, I dunno why that doesn't work for me, but at least I can type in the URL now that I know about it! - Rainwarrior (talk) 17:55, 19 July 2013 (MDT)

N163 incorrect terminology?

Wondering what the rationale is for calling N163 incorrect terminology. I mean, the chip appears to just have the number 163 on it, but N163 is just a straightforward abbreviation of Namco 163 (or Namcot 163). It's a popular expansion chip and lots of Famitracker users I talk to us the term N163. It's perfectly clear to me why the number 106 was wrong, but I don't understand the new prescription to eliminate N163. - Rainwarrior (talk) 17:31, 8 April 2014 (MDT)

That'd be news to the MAME developers who have been calling the combination of a 6502 without decimal mode and the NES APU the "N2A03". --Tepples (talk) 19:55, 8 April 2014 (MDT)

Talk:NES 2.0

Contents

1 Nintendulator
2 Zero CHR ROM
3 RAM size
4 Vs PPUs and $2002
5 Use of unused features
6 Call it NES 2 file format?
7 Additional problem case: Waveform playback IC
8 Vs. system byte needs link
9 Mirroring bits and one-screen mirroring

Nintendulator

"Kevin Horton reports that Nintendulator supports NES 2.0."

No it doesn't - it detects them (and the mapper interface has room for them), but it doesn't actually read any of the fields. --Quietust 01:58, 5 January 2010 (UTC)

...though now it at least handles larger ROM images (including "Super 8-in-1 99 King Fighter (Unl).nes", which should actually be Mapper 45 with 1MB PRG and 2MB CHR, but with the 256KB CHR blocks 0/1/2/3/4/5/6/7 rearranged to be 0/2/3/1/4/5/6/7). --Quietust 03:30, 5 January 2010 (UTC)

An observation: it would've made more sense for the TV system byte to use bit 0 to mean "Supports NTSC" and bit 1 to mean "Supports PAL", since it would've made it trivial to support Dendy timing by just adding another bit. --Quietust 04:52, 14 January 2011 (UTC)

Zero CHR ROM

Observation: if a ROM is marked as NES 2.0 and has zero banks of CHR ROM, it must set the CHR RAM size field to a nonzero value (ideally 0x07, for 8KB non-batteried), otherwise it technically doesn't have anything at all connected to the PPU bus. --Quietust 02:20, 26 August 2011 (UTC)

Good point. I'll mention 0x07 as the most common CHR RAM size in the article. But I do know of two ways to make a cart with no CHR ROM or CHR RAM. The Game Genie uses one way: wire CHR address lines to data lines through a mux to make 4x4 pixel squares. The other way, which I've talked about before on the forum but have never seen used in a game, involves always enabling CIRAM and wiring PA13 to CIRAM A10, which gives 1-screen mirroring (all banks at $400-$7FF) plus 64 tiles of CHR RAM (at $000-$1FF). --Tepples 10:57, 26 August 2011 (UTC)

Just to close the loop- nocash built a game that used VRAM as CHRRAM: (http://forums.nesdev.com/viewtopic.php?t=9342) and allocated it to iNES Mapper 218.—Lidnariq (talk) 14:46, 13 March 2013 (MDT)

I think it would makes sense that if there is neither CHR ROM nor CHR RAM and the mapper is one that normally has at least one of these, then it should just use CIRAM for pattern tables, as if CIRAM A10 is wired according to the mirroring header (and/or software-controlled), and CIRAM is always enabled. Should you specify this? --Zzo38 (talk) 22:29, 21 March 2013 (MDT)

RAM size

I'm torn about how to deal with RAM-inside-mappers. As far as I know, there are five ICs that have some: MMC5, MMC6, X1-005, X1-017, and Namco 163.

Some of these are easy: for the MMC6, X1-005, and X1-017, their internal RAM is at the exclusion of external RAM. The RAM size byte can just hold $40, $01, $10, or (per rounding up) $70 as appropriate.

For the MMC5, that RAM can be thought of as either of CPU or PPU memory, it's not clear whether it should be marked (and where it should be marked). Apparently no game ever battery-backed only the 1k internal RAM, so perhaps leaving the RAM size byte at 0 for MMC5s without external RAM is best, even if it's contradictory to the advice for the previous three. Only 2k, 8k, and 32k RAMs were available during the MMC5's commercial life, and they were only ever combined as (none, 8+0, 8+8, 32+0); clearly adding 1024 and rounding up would cause nonintuitive values here. (As an aside, there's also no way to express the 2+8 or 8+32 configurations in NES2.0; fortunately neither were used commercially)

The N163 came in 3 of the 4 possible variants: neither battery nor external RAM; battery but no external RAM; battery and external RAM. The first two would easily be $01 and $10, but the last worries me—adding internal+external and storing the rounded-up value in the "RAM size" means we'd have $80=16384 for 8192+128 battery-backed, or $60=4096 for 2048+128 battery-backed. This feels unintuitive to me. Simply always excluding internal RAM here (in addition to being contradictory to the advice given for the MMC6) means we'll have the nonsensical value 0 with the battery bit set in the rest of the header. Maybe the right answer is to only count the internal RAM when there's no external RAM? —Lidnariq (talk) 13:43, 10 February 2013 (MST)

We can add the Datach system to the list. It provides a 256 byte EEPROM that is not strictly speaking part of the game, but rather the cartridge converter, and thus is shared between games. Perhaps here the byte should indicate whether the game uses the EEPROM, rather than whether it's available. —Lidnariq (talk) 03:04, 14 August 2013 (MDT)

Vs PPUs and $2002

"RC2C05-02 (with ID ([2002h] AND 3Fh)=3Dh)" - How can that be? Does the RC2C05-02 not implement the sprite overflow flag? --Quietust (talk) 21:30, 21 March 2013 (MDT)

"Mighty Bomb Jack" checks it right on power-up— $8011: lda $2002; and #$3F; cmp #$3D; bne Reset. But after startup (where it spins on $2002.7) and checking these bits here, it seems to never read from $2002 for anything other than the side effect of resetting the $2006 lo/hi toggle. —Lidnariq (talk) 17:41, 22 March 2013 (MDT)

Use of unused features

I like the feature that for mappers that don't otherwise use the PRG RAM size header, it should specify 8K if it is mapped to $6000-$7FFF or zero if it is open bus or registers or whatever. However, I have some other suggestion: For CHR RAM, if it is a mapper with no CHR bankswitching and no other special use of the PPU address space, then if 16K CHR RAM (battery or non-battery) is specified, zero CHR ROM is specified, and four-screen mirroring is specified, to just map all the CHR RAM to the PPU address space. If a mapper that normally uses non-battery CHR RAM is specified, and the non-battery CHR RAM amount is set to zero but the battery CHR RAM amount is nonzero, then it should emulate it the same as that mapper normally does, but save the contents of the CHR RAM to a file. One other possible concern is, what will the trainer ROM do in mappers that already have something mapped to $7000-$71FF area? I suppose it could simply override it. Also, you say don't assign mapper numbers greater than 255 yet. However, if you have to define a mapper which depends on NES 2.0 features and that the older iNES format is insufficient, then you should assign numbers greater than 255. For example, I have worked on my own mappers and wish to assign them; the other mappers discussed in discrete logic mapper toolbox should also be assigned, and then it could be used to make up games using them on an emulator. (I could write the articles in my user space and they are moved once numbers are assigned.) --Zzo38 (talk) 00:59, 29 June 2013 (MDT)

NES 2.0 allows the description a lot of things that don't have preexisting meanings. For example, only MMC1 and MMC5 have well defined meanings for having both the "nonvolatile" and "static" PRG-RAM nybbles set, but they can be set in the header regardless. Simply deciding that if both nybbles are set to signify 4KiB that e.g. the battery-backed one comes first doesn't make this definition useful or worth the complexity, nevermind that it precludes correct behavior if a later discovery reveals the opposite behavior. To rapidly run through your suggestions: Providing general purpose memory from PPU $3000-$3EFF isn't useful, and 16KiB SRAMs have always been rare. I do agree that "just specifying battery-backed CHR-RAM should DTRT", but once again, it's waiting on an implementation. The "trainer" question is ancient, but has been mostly rendered moot by getting rid of all dumps that request trainers (In general: trainers override any other device mapped in that range, because they are assumed necessary for operation). Mapper numbers will be allocated when a hardware implementation exists. A general purpose mapper description language (as your m768 proposal) is not an obvious fit for the iNES file format. —Lidnariq (talk) 02:09, 29 June 2013 (MDT)

Call it NES 2 file format?

To my eyes NES 2.0 sounds like a program along with its version number. Usually file formats don't undergo constant revision and thus don't have x.y version numbers. Maybe the name NES 2.0 has already stuck, but even NES 2 file format doesn't look much like a program and version number. I'm thinking of phrases like "YANES supports NES 2.0" where it might sound like it is compatible in some way with the 2.0 version of a program called NES. OTOH, NES 2 sounds like a second version of the NES hardware. Maybe there are plans for NES 2.1 etc. Anyway, just noting how the name sounds. Blargg (talk) 01:09, 19 January 2014 (MST)

If I remember correctly, some publications referred to NES-101 (the 72-pin toploader) as "NES 2". As for the naming rationale, you could always get on IRC, bug kevtris, and report your results here. --Tepples (talk) 08:07, 19 January 2014 (MST)

USB & SCSI come to mind... 50.170.133.216 03:56, 29 August 2014 (MDT) Resigned with account... alphamule (talk) 13:53, 29 August 2014 (MDT)

Additional problem case: Waveform playback IC

For iNES Mapper 086: "An additional set of sample files is needed to emulate the sound chip." When the .nes blob is meant to represent all the static data, having no provision for including some seems like an error. Likewise iNES Mapper 018. Myask (talk) 19:11, 21 April 2015 (MDT)

I kind of agree, some sort of "extra data" blob might be nice. Perhaps all we'd need is a 32-bit size, and that number of bytes appended to the file. Though, in this specific case, even if we had the field, we don't have any dumped data to stick in there. The only working sound emulation attempt for that mapper involves having a pile of WAV files in a specific directory, which is obviously less than ideal. We don't have a dump of the sample ROM, let alone a working emulation of the sample playback algorithm used. There just isn't much interest in getting it done. Can you think of any other games that might need extra data? Requiring a companion-file or special solution for one special ROM isn't really that onerous, IMO, just not ideal. - Rainwarrior (talk) 19:56, 21 April 2015 (MDT)

Also iNES Mapper 072, iNES Mapper 092, iNES Mapper 003…so, several rather than few. Myask (talk) 18:53, 2 July 2016 (MDT)
More accurately, eight. Myask (talk) 19:16, 2 July 2016 (MDT)

Vs. system byte needs link

(See the "Vs. system byte" description below for a detailed analysis)

This should probably link to Byte 13 (Vs. hardware)

PatHawks (talk) 20:08, 3 August 2016 (MDT)

Mirroring bits and one-screen mirroring

Since (4-screen & Vertical) is currently held to be indistinct from (4screen & ~Vertical), wouldn't it be more useful to have it mean 1-screen? (Leaving aside Magic Floor's strange use; it's already got to be special-cased for how it uses CIRAM). Myask (talk) 00:29, 23 August 2016 (MDT)

Link to recent forum post outlining my proposal for that: post 177995. Most mappers that do single screen only do that, I think BNROM vs AxROM is the big exception, but it just ended up becoming separate iNES 1 mappers anyway. In this case, it's being proposed because it's come up with a new homebrew board that has 4 different permuations of solder pad settings (4-screen, 1-screen, H/V). So... it would solve the problem for this particular board, maybe for other future homebrew frankenboards too. I don't think there's much danger that some fifth mirroring mode will ever be significantly relevant, so I think it's fine as an iNES 2 extension to say that ....1..1 specifies some kind of "1-screen" configuration. - Rainwarrior (talk) 11:50, 23 August 2016 (MDT)

Talk:NES 2.0 submappers

Contents

1 Zzo38 likes this
2 iNES Mapper 078
3 MMC5
4 MMC3
5 "Don't care" bits
6 iNES Mapper 185
7 Does expansion volume warrant a separate field in the header?
8 Major revision proposal

Zzo38 likes this

I like this. I have written some ideas relating to this (as a user subpage) but your article is much better, but incomplete so we can improve it. --Zzo38 14:39, 23 September 2012 (MDT)

iNES Mapper 078

My point, although poorly represented, is that no existing game needs mapper 78 to support hard-wired mirroring. It is not necessary for original games, and it is not necessary for homebrew: User:Lidnariq/Discrete Logic Table shows that mappers 70 and 72 are equally capable. Thus there is no reason to allocate a submapper. —Lidnariq (talk) 12:14, 6 April 2013 (MDT)

MMC5

Should there perhaps be MMC5 submapper for CL and SL mode? (See also my comment on the MMC5 pinout) If there are significant differences between MMC5 and MMC5B (it says they are unknown; I am guessing there aren't any significant differences), should there also be submapper codes for this? --Zzo38 (talk) 14:11, 28 April 2013 (MDT)

No games were known released in CL mode. For the most part, I'm trying to not allocate a submapper until I can both describe the differences and describe a need for it. ... which makes me have second thoughts about the CNROM allocation; if the game cares about those diodes it'd be m185. —Lidnariq (talk) 14:27, 28 April 2013 (MDT)

Well, the mapper does support CL, even if no existing games use it; it means that a homebrew game can use CL if it ever seems useful for whatever arcane reason (even CL games would probably work fine with SL though, but maybe CL would have other effects; I don't know if it would scroll only the colors or what). --Zzo38 (talk) 18:34, 28 April 2013 (MDT)

I would like to repeat my objection: You have now allocated 3 of the 4 bits in the submapper field, without ANYTHING ACTUALLY EVER USING ANY OF THEM. Please stop.—Lidnariq (talk) 20:52, 21 January 2014 (MST)

OK, but it says "Proposal"; they aren't actually allocated (although maybe proposals shouldn't belong there anyways). Anyways, the ExROM configuration does use them. Also, Disch's notes do mention that Uncharted Waters does use non-contiguous PRG RAM (although it will work fine with 64K contiguous RAM). --Zzo38 (talk) 21:18, 21 January 2014 (MST)

Ok, meaning of the bits here: I'm of the opinion that to the extent possible, all 0s should describe hardware as it existed. No MMC5 game ever provided PRG RAM without battery-backing precisely one RAM, and never battery-backed two RAMs. So the only instance in which the 2s bit of this submapper field would be set are if someone took an ETROM board and modified the jumpers.

Also, encoding exceptions is a PitA; why should the bit have opposite meaning when the field specifies 16KiB PRGRAM than when it specifies any other number? —Lidnariq (talk) 14:54, 12 April 2014 (MDT)

I agree it is very klugy, but the reason I suggested it is so that if someone implements it, that it won't cause it to run incorrectly a file which doesn't use it. However, that was because I didn't know, no MMC5 game ever provided PRG RAM without battery-backing precisely one RAM. Since that is the case, I was clearly wrong, so that kluge can be removed. (I assume you mean, 16K is in two 8K RAMs, one of which is battery and one isn't. Therefore, I made a mistake!) --Zzo38 (talk) 18:52, 12 April 2014 (MDT)

MMC3

Ok, NesCartDB knows of no games that use MMC3 and hardwired 2 screen mirroring, despite its jumper-ability on TEROM and TFROM. Was this supposed need an artifact of splitting off iNES Mapper 206? Also, am I correct in thinking that we believe that all games work correctly with MMC3C style interrupts?

Given this ... what behavior does mapper 4 need submappers for? Should I roll my proposal over kevtris's, replace it with a subset that only handles MMC3A vs MMC3C, or just replace the entire section with an explanation about how why no submappers are necessary? —Lidnariq (talk) 22:13, 30 April 2013 (MDT)

Add the things that the jumpers on the mapper support, even if you know of no games that use it. Anyways, even if all of the games you know about work with MMC3C interrupts, some might not, and there should be a way to indicate this difference since it still can affect things. --Zzo38 (talk) 22:29, 30 April 2013 (MDT)

Thefox, why is mapping "1KB of RAM → MMC6" not adequate, rather than needing a submapper? —Lidnariq (talk) 12:48, 11 August 2014 (MDT)

"Don't care" bits

I see that some submapper numbers say to use 0 for don't care. I might suggest that the Mapper/Number and Mapper/NumberEx fields of .nes.ini to be used to indicate this more explicitly; using the Number you can specify multiple submapper numbers, with vertical bars, so if all combinations are specified then it means "don't care". --Zzo38 (talk) 22:43, 30 April 2013 (MDT)

iNES Mapper 185

Nestopia's internal database instead implements mapper 185 as two trinary numbers: D0 and D1 must be low/high/don't care.

I wonder if that's better?

For that matter, I've never heard of any 16kiB CHR m185 games, nor any games that have only one don't care line. Maybe simply allocating four submappers corresponding to the LSBs is better.—Lidnariq (talk) 20:09, 16 January 2014 (MST)

Does expansion volume warrant a separate field in the header?

You say: "Furthermore, different 163-using PCBs also used a different resistor to change the relative volume of the expansion audio relative to the internal 2A03 audio. It is unclear if this variation warrants a submapper." I may suggest that you could make another header field (perhaps high six bits of byte 12?) for expansion volume. --Zzo38 (talk) 15:04, 18 January 2014 (MST)

Further modifying NES2.0 is uncalled for. The question is whether the information belongs at all, not whether it belongs in the submapper field. (If it does belong, this is exactly what the submapper field is for) —Lidnariq (talk) 15:11, 18 January 2014 (MST)

If it doesn't belong in the NES 2.0 header at all, it can go in the .NES.INI instead, I suppose. However, depending on exactly what groups of cartridges use these different resistors, it might or might not be useful as a submapper number. Didn't I read somewhere that the actual use of different resistors in different cartridges is more confusing than specified here, or something like that? --Zzo38 (talk) 15:36, 18 January 2014 (MST)

The header needs to describe the behavior of the cartridge PCB. Something that is inside the cartridge and cross-cuts across multiple mappers belongs in a dedicated field. Examples of cross-cutting concerns include memory sizes (bytes 4-5, 8-11), mirroring (byte 6 bits 0 and 3), NTSC/PAL/Vs./PC10 (byte 7 bits 0-1 and bytes 12-13), etc. The next step is to determine whether mix volume is a cross-cutting concern or whether it's exclusive to the N163. Do all MMC5 games using expansion audio have the same volume relative to the 2A03 channels? Do all Sunsoft 5B games? Do all VRC6 games? (Among synths listed in the NSF spec, FDS and VRC7 have one cartridge each, so we need not concern ourselves with those.) --Tepples (talk) 18:23, 18 January 2014 (MST)

Correct; this is my reason to think if a expansion audio needs a separate field or not. If there is a separate header field, then it should be defined for VRC7 too (for consistency, and that someone might want to write a new program using different mixer volume) (and that emulators expecting a NES 2.0 header on the BIOS, will allow it to work with FDS too). --Zzo38 (talk) 19:08, 18 January 2014 (MST)

All three VRC6 games use the same module with the 6-bit R-2R DAC and mixing resistor. The Sunsoft 5B is a singleton (Gimmick!). This leaves only MMC5 and the 163, but no-one's ever put an oscilloscope on the four MMC5 audio lines to find out exactly what the four pins do, or exactly what variation in resistors effect.
So, first off: what ExROM says about the resistors is wrong; R1,R2,R4, and C4 are clearly all part of the audio path on the HVC-EWROM, HVC-ETROM, and HVC-EKROM boards. HVC-ELROM has a substantially different layout, but since it has the same values of resistors and capacitors, it seems likely that it also supports expansion audio.

The vast majority of games use the resistor and capacitor values that are silkscreened on the PCB: 15kΩ/15kΩ/10kΩ/0.1µF. This includes Sangokushi 2, Suikoden: Tenmei no Chikai, Nobunaga no Yabou: Sengoku Gunyuuden, L'Empereur, Ishin no Arashi, Daikoukai Jidai, Uchuu Keibitai SDF, and Gunsight.
A few games replace R2R1 with a 6.8kΩ resistor instead of 15kΩ, including Nobunaga no Yabou: Bushou Fuuunroku, Shin 4 Nin Uchi Mahjong: Yakuman Tengoku, Royal Blood, and Just Breed.
In a current NSF archive, only three games seem to use MMC5's audio: Just Breed, Metal Slader Glory, and Shin 4 Nin Uchi Mahjong. The two of those three that are in NESCartDB both use a 6.8k resistor.
We don't know what difference in volume is caused by changing R2R1.

So, my conclusion: there could be two different mixing volumes for MMC5, but most likely only one was ever used. —Lidnariq (talk) 22:39, 18 January 2014 (MST)

Perhaps someone should figure out what exactly R2R1 affects (for this purpose, there is probably no need to figure out the other resistors). Even if only one is used, the other way exists and should be specified, in my opinion which is to include all possibilities even if some aren't used. If R2R1 is figured out and does affect mixing volumes in the way which will become known, then this should be specified. If you are using submapper numbers to indicate the difference, you can assign bit2 of the MMC5 submapper number; set for 15k and clear for 6.8k. (This isn't necessary if nothing applicable to the audio is affected by R2, though.) --Zzo38 (talk) 01:18, 19 January 2014 (MST)

And if it does turn out that two mixing volumes were used on MMC5, we have a cross-cutting concern. I was thinking of repurposing some bits of byte 12 as a signed difference in decibels from each mapper's "normal" output level. Because it's signed, it still follows the overall principle of zero doing something expected. But I'd recommend testing how that replacing that resistor with a pot affects MMC5 channel balance and asking kevtris what he thinks before making a final decision, just as I asked him for clarifications on smaller-than-NROM-128 ROM sizes such as those used by Galaxian and Slappin'. --Tepples (talk) 08:16, 19 January 2014 (MST)

Yes, same as my thoughts; using the high bits of byte 12. I didn't think of making it signed, but you are correct that is a good idea. I don't know if "negative infinity" and "positive infinity" are useful at all; at least the former seems to be wanted by some people (to save CPU time when not emulating expansion audio) and is used on some cartridges having the same mapper number as ones with expansion audio, but the latter isn't used or supported in any cartridge board as far as I know, and probably is useless at the present time at least (although there are two uses I can think of: to silence the DPCM channel (if it is only being used for timing or for side-effects of reads, and to use the 2A03 audio to control a device connected to the Famicom expansion port (for example if only one player is allowed to hear it)). --Zzo38 (talk) 10:49, 19 January 2014 (MST)

Well, we've characterized what the variation in MMC5 could be. I still object to marking such in the header until such time as we find a commercial game that uses this variation. It is incorrect to store every possible variation in the header because there are an exponential number of ways to configure an IC and in the case of analog components, an infinite number of ways. —Lidnariq (talk) 13:49, 21 January 2014 (MST)

According to the forum there are no square waves on R2, or anything at all in the Just Breed game at least. This discussion says it is R2 which is changed. ExROM says it is R1 which is changed, and increases the volume of the pulse waves by 6.9dB. (Which is it; R1 or R2?) If this is the case, then that is what bit2 of the submapper number for MMC5 should be assigned to: cleared if 6.8k, and set if 15k. --Zzo38 (talk) 16:10, 21 January 2014 (MST)

Bleh, I brainoed during this entire discussion. Fixed.—Lidnariq (talk) 19:25, 21 January 2014 (MST)

Major revision proposal

This page is a complete mess, and I think this is largely responsible for why NES 2.0 is poorly and inconsistently adopted across emulators. I started by posting in the submappers thread on the forum but I might as well outline a proposal here.

First and foremost, we need a clear criterion for how to allocate a submapper. I propose this:

Demonstrate the problem by showing us an existing game that is incompatible with the default mapper implementation.
Propose a submapper solution that will solve this problem.
Subject that solution to peer verification of critera 1 and 2. (i.e. Does the problem exist? Is this a solution?)
If it passes review at step 3, add the new submapper to the end of the existing list. Do not delete or deprecate or re-order existing submappers.
When listing a submapper, cite the games the require it.

This is very similar to how I think we should allocate new iNES mappers. Make the software/game/rip/etc. first that requires it. Demonstrate an existing need before allocating. Don't make wishlist requests. (If you don't the ability to add your custom changes to one of the many available open source emulators to work on your project with, I highly doubt that you have the ability to make worthwhile software that needs it.) It doesn't matter if there are hardware variations; if they are compatible with all existing games then we don't need a submapper yet. Pre-emptively allocating submappers puts a burden on anyone trying to implement the NES 2.0 spec, which contributes to poor adoption of it.

Second, I think we should wipe this page out and begin again from Kevtris' submapper document. If there are errors in it, please point them out. I believe all of his suggested submappers are motivated by roughly the same criteria that I just laid out, so I think it's a very good starting point. Add to it, don't take away (unless there is a mistake that causes a real problem), and don't re-implement it because you would have done it differently. There are additions on this page that are probably good candidates (e.g. the MMC3 IRQ variations), and should be allocated.

Thirdly, I would like to advise against the idea of using PRG-RAM, size fields, or any other header information except mapper and submapper to select a mapper implementation to use. Yes, it's true that we could identify MMC1 variants by size fields, or MMC6 by PRG-RAM, but every time you do this you are creating special cases for mapper selection, each of them requiring their own extra selection logic. This makes the specification less clear and harder to adopt. Submappers are not scarce compared to the number of problem cases, and if we ever do run out (I doubt it) I would suggest allocating a second iNES mapper (using the same low-8 bits but on a different plane) for the excess. By making this arbitrary change, and re-allocating and deprecating Kevtris' allocations for mappers 1 and 4 we have created a schism, making it look like both specifications are worthless, quite frankly. We can't establish an authoritative version of this specification unless there is continuity.

Finally, when you add a submapper to the list, cite the games that require it. This is essential for ongoing verification and evaluation. It's the only way someone can look at the list and go "oh, well do I need to implement this submapper? what is it for?" The answer is always that it's for a specific game. It's important to specify what game it is!

- Rainwarrior (talk) 22:00, 6 August 2015 (MDT)

Also, proposals for new additions should go on a talk page, or the forum. Don't add them directly to the article. It should be a living specification that maintains continuity, not have proposals revolving in and out of it muddying the waters. - Rainwarrior (talk) 22:03, 6 August 2015 (MDT)

I've restored Kev's choices for mapper 4 to the proposals page now that I understand the rationale. But what is "worthwhile software"? What's the correlation between experience with 6502 assembly language and experience with C or C++, which are the implementation languages of most NES emulators? Is there a tutorial anywhere for adding a mapper to any of the free emulators, or is it a "throw them in and see if they can swim" situation? --Tepples (talk) 09:23, 7 August 2015 (MDT)

I was just being glib to make an argument that we shouldn't specify fantasy/future implementations as a general rule. I'm not going to argue about whether someone could in theory make a cool NES app with a new mapper without being able to modify an emulator. If someone wants to try it but can't do it, they should enlist someone else's help to modify an emulator, not add it to an important specification like this and hope people implement it for them before any software exists for it. - Rainwarrior (talk) 09:48, 7 August 2015 (MDT)

I've gone over the article, moving anything that was not an implementable specification to NES 2.0 submappers/Proposals. Everything in the article should be ready-to-implement. Anything new that gets added should be discussed and agreed upon before adding to the article, and remember to document new additions with the relevant games. - Rainwarrior (talk) 11:51, 7 August 2015 (MDT)

Talk:NES 2.0 submappers/Proposals

Bus conflict submapper 0

This revision makes the following suggestion:

0: Normal (The game is believed to never elicit a bus conflict. In the event of a bus conflict, the emulator should warn, abort, or produce random values; the exact behavior is not known)

I think the goal for submapper 0 should usually be the greatest compatibility, and backwards compatibility with iNES. Setting the NES 2.0 identifier shouldn't change the behaviour of submapper 0 (if all other fields are otherwise "equivalent"). Validation tools to "warn" or "abort" could work nicely with submapper 2 (i.e. emulate bus conflicts), but I don't think they would do anything except reduce compatibility if used for submapper 0. A validation tool really shouldn't be part of the submapper definition (that's its own tool with its own goal, e.g. like nintendulator DX's thing to warn on use of uninitialized memory).

Cases 1 and 2 are good, it separates two things with specific conflicting needs. I think case 0 should just delegate a recommendation for 1 or 2.

002:0 = 002:1 ? UxROM says that mapper 002 shares UxROM with compatible boards that require no bus conflicts. (Also, that DK pie factory hack?)
003:0 = 003:2 ? INES Mapper 003 lists 1 game (Cybernoid) that requires bus conflicts, and 1 (Colorful Dragon, UNL) that requires none. Does Cybernoid get priority?
007:0 = 007:1 ? a lack of bus conflicts is required for some existing games, but it seems that none require bus conflicts.

Alternatively I would just propose that submapper 0 be used for no bus conflicts, and submapper 1 be used for AND bus conflicts, since a lack of bus conflicts might just generally produce greater compatibility? If your goal is to give homebrewers a nice testing environment that will emulate bus conflicts for them, submapper 2 does that job great, it doesn't need to be the default. The only case I've seen listed so far is Cybernoid?

I was wondering about other mappers besides 002/003/007 but I am guessing that the other bus-conflicting mappers don't have the ambiguity problems and can safely always have bus conflicts on?

- Rainwarrior (talk) 13:53, 31 August 2015 (MDT)

The default for any mapper that physically has bus conflicts (even if never elicited) must not be "no bus conflicts" for reasons we have already discussed and you find uncompelling.
FCEUX has already decided that the iNES1 handler is "produce bogus values (always 0) for CNROM and UNROM" (although it used to be AND) and "no bus conflicts for other data-bus latch mappers". Nestopia has codified bus conflicts as AND, for the "standard" version of specific discrete-logic mappers (UNROM, UOROM, CNROM, BNROM) and none otherwise.
—Lidnariq (talk) 18:31, 31 August 2015 (MDT)

I'm confused by this response? We're not discussing any mappers that always had bus conflicts here. We're discussing iNES mappers 2, 3, and 7, none of which unambiguously represents a physical mapper that had bus conflicts. Mapper 2 seems to include many obscure boards, some of which reputedly require a lack of bus conflicts? (I have no source for this other than statements found on the wiki; what are the actual compatibility cases?) Mapper 3 appears to be have the only compatibility conflict among these 3 mappers, and from the two cases listed a bus-conflicts submapper 0 seems valid to me. Mapper 7 submapper 0 requires no bus conflicts for compatibility. - Rainwarrior (talk) 19:31, 31 August 2015 (MDT)

Your central thesis appears to be that compatibility is the foremost goal, and my argument (from experience) is that prioritizing compatibility produces homebrew that can't run on hardware, so the default must be the strictest narrowest definition instead (and that people must explicitly opt into more lenient behavior). We've already had this argument. What's the point in having it again? —Lidnariq (talk) 20:41, 31 August 2015 (MDT)

I'm not very much interested in restating opinions about ideological concerns for the format either, but I am interested in the specific definition of mappers 2, 3, and 7 here, in response to the submapper 0 text you just proposed. I strongly feel that mapper 7's submapper 0 should not break the existing ANROM games. Are you really arguing that it should? I don't remember you ever responding about mapper 7. We don't actually seem to have a dispute about mapper 3 (i.e. submapper 0 with bus conflicts), but I am unsure about it because I can't find much information about the non-CNROM games that use this mapper? Mapper 2 there is even less knowledge about, but the Disch notes for mapper 2 state "UxROM has bus conflicts, however mapper 002 is meant to be UxROM and compatible. So some mappers which were similar in function, but did not have bus conflicts are included", but again I can't find any existing research about the games/boards involved. Is the best we can do for this an emulator survey? - Rainwarrior (talk) 12:40, 1 September 2015 (MDT)

Hi guys, just thought I'd mention some ideas here even though I don't have a lot of time for this kind of stuff and probably won't be back to debate it. IMO, ines 1 mapper numbers arent strict definitions but rather a vague guide for organizing a family of functionality. Moving forward, I would like to see 'submapper 0' for mapper N to be 'do what you can to get the game to boot' without increasing the strictness of the legacy mapper's definition. Then, exceptions can be written by forwarding to a submapper. For instance, we might see: "Mapper N Submapper 0 = Mapper N Legacy Mode: A game with this submapper can't be safely run without a game-specific logic. It might have bus conflicts (handle as Submapper 1) or no bus conflicts (handle as Submapper 2)." Essentially leave submapper 0 as flexible legacy hack zone ghetto. This allows us the latitude to actually prescribe as part of the specification how legacy garbage is to be interpreted as well as set a simple rule for how to define submapper 0. If there's a channel besides #nesdev I wouldnt mind lurking and giving further feedback, but I don't have time to take a strong stance Zeromus (talk) 21:25, 1 September 2015 (MDT)

Ok, here's a pragmatic argument: What's the practical difference between:

300 games as submapper 0 (the ones where the hardware has bus conflicts, but the games have a bus conflict prevention table)
2 games as submapper 1
2 games as submapper 2

And

302 games as submapper 0
2 games as submapper 1

Especially when the size of the two minority groups is comparable? —Lidnariq (talk) 12:27, 2 September 2015 (MDT)

Scenario the First has four games which can be emulated unambiguously without hacks keyed to hashes. Scenario the Second has two games which can be emulated unamiguously without hacks keyed to hashes--so two of the games won't work on every emulator listing itself as in complete Mapper N compliance without the emulator having special cases for them. . . . . . . . . . . . Now that I've thought about it one more day, I have another proposition. Using submapper 0 as a catch-all for legacy behaviour is a bad idea. We should use iNES1 headers as an indicator that legacy behaviour is required. A rom should not be graduated to iNES2 until it can be assigned to a submapper that precisely defines it. In that scenario, we have 2 games as submapper 0, 2 games as submapper 1, and 300 games in iNES1 that cannot be legally turned into iNES2 without simultaneously encoding their bus conflict needs. Now, from an organizational perspective, this would require namespacing and maybe even documenting iNES1 and iNES2 mappers separately. You could resolve this by declaring that iNES2 is a strict superset defined as enclosing iNES1 within submapper 0 (which was my original proposition). Another way of writing the rule might be: "For mappers with >1 submapper, submapper 0 means, select another submapper using a database" Zeromus (talk) 21:14, 2 September 2015 (MDT)

Yes, with submapper 1 and 2 as an explicit bus conflict indication, really the only thing left for submapper 0 is "unknown" or "doesn't matter", which wouldn't normally need an iNES 2 header anyway, but I think this might be used if, say, it's a rip from an unknown board but you need to specify WRAM or some other unusual iNES 2 only thing besides bus conflicts? What I'd like to know more about, though, is how many ROMs exist for mapper 2 and 3 that rely on a lack of bus conflicts. A reliance on bus conflicts (in mappers 2/3/7) is usually unintentional, isn't it? Cybernoid is a very strange case. Games that rely on a lack of bus conflicts, however, do so because of a deliberate expectation, and I'd expect there to be more of these than ones that rely on bus conflicts. Obviously, every real UxROM and CNROM game are excluded from this case, but both mappers 2 and 3 supposedly contain other boards that aren't. Anyhow, despite my suspicions, in light of how inconsistent emulator implementation appears to be, I think the previous text of the proposal was much more practical: Normal (No advisory statement is made as to whether this game has bus conflicts). People that want an explicit behaviour should really have to choose submapper 1 or 2, since the expected default behaviour is unreliable. - Rainwarrior (talk) 23:25, 2 September 2015 (MDT)

There's two arguments here. One is whether submapper represents ABI (expects bus conflicts, works around; relies on no bus conflicts; relies on AND bus conflicts) or hardware (AND bus conflicts are present; bus conflicts are not present).
The other is "what should submapper 0 be"? There's been two somewhat contradictory rules-of-thumb that have been proposed about submapper 0 "should" mean.
Should it be "the vast majority of games are here"? In which case, for UxROM and CNROM, that means submapper 0 should be "Games with bus conflicts, and (depending on the first question) that work around those bus conflicts".
Or should it be "No advisory statement is made, use existing heuristics"? In that case, we probably want a submapper explicitly for "this game has been checked and yes we know that it expects bus conflicts (and maybe works around those bus conflicts)".

I originally was of the opinion that the submappers should just represent hardware. But as I've thought about FCEUX SVN 2997 (which looks awfully like "intentionally breaking things"), I find myself thinking that a "fail fast" design is better.—Lidnariq (talk) 00:54, 3 September 2015 (MDT)

I am not very good with rules of thumb, apparently. Every mapper seems a bit different case. Perhaps majority compatibility was a suggestion that confused things? Probably the idea that submapper 0 just means "do as iNES does" was the better idea. In this particular case, there just doesn't seem to be an established standard way to implement mapper 2 or 3. When updating the mapper info across the wiki I've tried to describe what someone should expect to see in emulators or hardware, and to be explicit about which is which.

If someone wants to implement an emulator that spits out a warning or refuses to run when it finds something invalid, that's perfectly fine for them to do. Many emulators do this, or have options for this kind of thing. I don't mind suggestions and recommendations to do this, but they shouldn't be the definition of a mapper. They should be explained conditionally. "You can avoid problem X by doing Y." Like the reason I want to know if there are mapper 2/3 games that will break with bus conflicts is so that I can give that information to the implementer to make an informed choice, rather than just blindly following a recommendation.

People put all these hacks and heuristics into their emulators because there was something they wanted to accomplish with it, usually a game they wanted to run. You can tell them "don't do this" all you want, but if you don't tell them why, they already have a "why" they should ignore you (the thing they want to run). - Rainwarrior (talk) 10:18, 3 September 2015 (MDT)

An aside about that FCEUX bus conflict implementation. Cybernoid has a bug that accidentally writes $0F against $50 when you toggle music during gameplay. Since it seems to exclusively use CHR bank 0, a "bus conflicts" implementation that forces 0 by luck doesn't happen to break it. No idea what prompted this as a "solution" for Top Gun, though. I haven't been able to find a bus-conflicting write in it. The bug report said something about mirror_in_use? It mentions a hacked Highway Star, but I don't know why it is being crammed into mapper 2. Very strange. - Rainwarrior (talk) 10:49, 3 September 2015 (MDT)

Looks like cah4e3 had reconsidered the hack and reverted the "highway star" support, just forgot to revert the bus conflict code at the same time. I've gone and restored it. - Rainwarrior (talk) 11:19, 3 September 2015 (MDT)

Well, with that all done, the only question remaining is: do we want the discrete logic submappers to codify ABI, or to codify hardware? Reserving an extra submapper for the former allows an emulator to explicitly mark an error condition, whereas the latter choice instead requires a run-time option. —Lidnariq (talk) 14:05, 3 September 2015 (MDT)

I'd rather have both submappers. I think it's more useful to be able to specify than try to impose a strict behaviour on submapper 0. I have created a set of test ROMs for mapper 3 so far: forum post. The only emulators I could find that currently try to bus-conflict mapper 3 were puNES and FCEUX (though I don't know if I'm running up against heuristics in some cases). - Rainwarrior (talk) 14:20, 3 September 2015 (MDT)

I wasn't even talking about submapper 0 behavior. Instead, whether 1/2 are "bus conflicts Do Not/Do exist" or whether 1/2/3 are "bus conflicts are unexpected/bus conflicts are expected to produce AND/program anticipates bus conflicts and includes a bus conflict prevention table". —Lidnariq (talk) 14:28, 3 September 2015 (MDT)

Since that third option would run correctly on both 1 and 2, I'm not sure what the need is. Like, for UxROM/CNROM boards, really you want those in submapper 2 so that unexpected bugs behave more correctly, right? If it's a game that exists on two different boards, you could make two rips with two headers. If you want a validation mode for an emulator to warn you about unmatched bus conflicts, that's probably a good runtime option (Nestopia's debug build already does this for some things, I think? NST_VERIFY), but I am not sure how a submapper itself would help that. - Rainwarrior (talk) 14:40, 3 September 2015 (MDT)

My idea about what submapper 0 should mean is similar to what is written near the top (I quote: "I think the goal for submapper 0 should usually be the greatest compatibility, and backwards compatibility with iNES. Setting the NES 2.0 identifier shouldn't change the behaviour of submapper 0"), but not quite. In some cases, the old iNES header is ambiguous and the header fields other than submapper number cannot disambiguate; in these cases, where emulators without NES 2.0 would use hash checks, there should be no hash checks when the NES 2.0 header is present; in these cases it may be necessary to set the submapper number when converting the header to NES 2.0 format. --Zzo38 (talk) 13:24, 13 August 2016 (MDT)

MMC5/MMC5B

Difference from MMC5 and MMC5B apparently is currently unknown. The bit3 of the submapper number for mapper 5 may be used to select between MMC5 and MMC5B, where if the bit is clear it is compatible with all known games (even if it does not correctly describe the hardware). The following differences are not considered as significant:

If one variant initializes some mapper registers at power on which the other variant leaves uninitialized
If the rest of the contents of the header (including the rest of the submapper number) can indicate these differences
If one variant has more capacity for external ROM/RAM than the other variant
Electrical tolerances which do not affect software
Internal wiring of the cartridge which software does not detect

These differences will be significant if they exist:

Presence or absence of PCM read mode
IRQ differences which can be detected by software
If spying on mirrors of PPU registers differs between variants
Writing to ExRAM through PPU if possible on one but not on the other

--Zzo38 (talk) 13:14, 13 August 2016 (MDT)

Talk:Nesdev Wiki/current

Layout test pages

If you have any example of layout for the wiki that you would like to share, please make a link to your examples here.

User_talk:Blargg | Blargg_Main | Blargg_PPU

Would be nice if the http://nesdev.com/ main page made it clearer that all the up-to-date stuff is on the wiki. It's just two links and fairly easy to miss. -Ulfalizer (talk) 09:32, 12 April 2013 (MDT)

Anonymous editing

Why are non-registered users allowed to edit talk pages ? Bregalad (talk) 09:23, 27 March 2014 (MDT)

As a means of reporting technical problems with registration to registered users, for one. Almost all automated vandalism gets reverted within twenty-four hours anyway. And because some drive-by edits have in fact been constructive. --Tepples (talk) 18:29, 27 March 2014 (MDT)
It also makes spambots less likely to skip immediately to the sign-up page. Instead, they try to post on whatever pages anonymous visitors can post on, where the ABUSE filter picks up on behavior patterns in the bot software. Looking at all the $#!+ that get through helps me figure out how to stop even those spambots that bother to register. --Tepples (talk) 19:54, 16 July 2014 (MDT)

Talk:NROM

FamicomHDL

I have made some of FamicomHDL already and I think the following code seems to work for implementing NROM-128 with vertical mirroring:

import Language.FamicomHDL;
import Language.FamicomHDL.Cartridge;
import Language.FamicomHDL.Memory;
nrom :: Mapper ();
nrom = do {
  prgrom <- makeROM 0;
  chrrom <- makeROM 16384;
  connects $ zip cpuAddress (take 14 $ addressPins prgrom);
  connects $ zip cpuData (dataPins prgrom);
  connects $ zip ppuAddress (take 13 $ addressPins chrrom);
  connects $ zip ppuData (dataPins chrrom);
  connect romSelect (chipEnablePin prgrom);
  connect ppuA13inv ciramEnable;
  connect ciramA10 (ppuAddress !! 10);
  connect (chipEnablePin chrrom) (ppuAddress !! 13);
};

Perhaps commands should be added for some of these things make shortcut. --Zzo38 22:38, 28 October 2012 (MDT)

CIC Diodes?

Some NES-NROM boards have slots for diodes too. —Bregalad (talk) 01:40, 5 May 2014 (MDT)

I can't think of a context in which diodes could be useful on an NROM board... do you have a photo somewhere (e.g. NesCartDB) ? —Lidnariq (talk) 03:20, 5 May 2014 (MDT)

I also can't think of where they could be useful (not that they are useful on CNROM either...) but NES-NROM-xxx-02 and NES-NROM-xxx-03 boards have slots for 2 diodes next to the CIC. I don't have any game using one of those boards so I can't check where they connect, but you can see the slot clearly on the NesCartDB.—Bregalad (talk) 04:03, 5 May 2014 (MDT)

Those diodes were intended to go from the CIC /RST and CIC CLK lines to vcc, providing overvoltage protection for the key CIC. But I have no idea under which situation that would have been useful.—Lidnariq (talk) 12:35, 5 May 2014 (MDT)

Oh thank you ! I don't know why but I thought about the CNROM diodes when I saw them (since they're close to the CHR ROM as well). My bad, thank you very much for clarifying this.128.178.195.59 13:25, 5 May 2014 (MDT)

Suggested reforms for this page

There is some thing I would belive would change positively. The page is about simultaneously mapper #0 and NROM, the former being wider than the later. Since I don't know if anyone else agree I won't change anything myself (since I bet 99% that any changes will be reverted immediately and everyone disagreeing), so this is just suggestions:

- Mapper #0 is defined as any board that lacks a mapper and bankswitching capability

- It is written explicitly that NROM is just one board that implements "no mapper", but other boards (RROM, Family basic, 3rd party boards, etc, etc....) also implement the same functionality

- It is written explicitly in the intro that there is no registers, and the "registers" paragraph is deleted. There is no need for that explanation of "poor man's CNROM", because it is non-technical, and anyone reading info about the very basic of PPU's way of working and $2000 register already knowns that. Do not assume the reader is a baby.

- PRG RAM capability should be left open for anything 8k or less. There is nothing preventing you to implement NROM with 8k PRG RAM while still following iNES mapper #0 specifications. More than 8k is possible but it would not follow iNES mapper #0 anymore and would be a sparate "mapper" (despite being no mapper, oh the irony). I don't know how to word that correctly. In all cases, I believe that NROM + 8k PRG RAM is a valid configuration, as well as less PRG RAM and not relying on mirroring. Bregalad (talk) 07:59, 27 May 2015 (MDT)

Talk:NSF

Contents

1 Emulator playability
2 $4010 value
3 $4017 register
4 Multi expansion
5 Consistency
6 More clarification

Emulator playability

A NSF tune is perfectly playable in an emulator; in short words, a "normal" NES emulator, not something clipped for exclusive NSF playing and behaviour.

Regarding 4015h, well... it's empirical. My experience says that setting 4015h to 0Fh is required in order to get *a lot of* tunes starting playing. I don't remember of *any* broken tune by setting such value. So, it's recommended *to follow* such thing. --Zepper 14:25, 29 March 2012 (PDT)

Adding NSF support involves a mapper, an executable format, and a piece of shell code to draw the title, artist, and publisher, run the player in a loop, and switch tracks. But you're right that an emulator incapable of playing NSF is incapable of emulating something that runs on an NES, as the PowerPak has an NSF player. --Tepples 20:29, 29 March 2012 (PDT)

Yup, I assigned mapper 256, since iNES cannot assign it. And yes, it's required a player (I wrote my own in asm) and commands to switch tracks, but that's all. Perhaps I wasn't crystal clear... :( --Zepper 14:31, 30 March 2012 (PDT)

NES 2.0 can assign mappers up to $FFF.F. Yes, that's a hexadecimal point, used to separate the mapper number from the variant number. No variants are officially assigned though. --Tepples 15:00, 30 March 2012 (PDT)

I admit that my first statement sounds like "any NSF file can be loaded into any NES emulator", which isn't true. Proper support for NSF is required, as tepples noted. So, the emulator must create a mapper (I assigned 256, since iNES 1.0 cannot assign it), a player (I use 6502 code loaded at $4018-$4FFF) and controls for changing tracks, plus the frame rate control. The NSF header is parsed and then the file is loaded as specified by the document. Sorry for the confusion! --Zepper 10:05, 31 March 2012 (PDT)

NES 2.0 can use mapper number 256. I would recommend mapper number -1 since NES 2.0 cannot assign it, and DotFami also specifies that mapper number -1 is used in the ines.map file to indicate it is NSF. (If it has to be unsigned, you could also use a mapper number greater than $FFF.F instead of -1; it won't be compatible with DotFami but you might not consider that important.) --Zzo38 16:48, 1 September 2012 (MDT)

$4010 value

The page appears to recommend writing $10 to $4010 but $00 to most other APU registers. However APU DMC says there's nothing mapped at D4 of $4010. Where did this come from? --Tepples 12:55, 31 March 2012 (PDT)

That's an odd one. It's in Kevin Horton's spec. /shrugs Rainwarrior 17:57, 31 March 2012 (PDT)

$4017 register

What about this register? For NSFs, is correct to write $00 to $4017 (frame IRQ enabled) and re-writing the last value on reset?

I don't think there should be any specification about what to do with this register for a couple of reasons. 1. NSF does not support any kind of IRQ; so enabling it is inappropriate. 2. Most software NSF players do not support resetting the frame sequencer by writing to $4017. 3. If your hardware player is NMI driven, you probably want to avoid writing to it so that it does not reset and get out of phase. 4. Alternatively your hardware player may be driven by the frame sequencer interrupt (esp. if there is no PPU), in which case the needs of the player dictate how the register should be used anyway. - Rainwarrior 22:14, 31 March 2012 (PDT)

If anything I think it might be good to forbid the use of $4017 in the NSF spec, but I'm not sure on this. - Rainwarrior 22:17, 31 March 2012 (PDT)

Forbidding use of the frame IRQ ($4017 D6) is fine, as it confuses IRQ-driven hardware players. To support all rate/period values, a hardware player implementing the NSF mapper will be using its own timer IRQ anyway, insha'411ah. But if you forbid $4017 writes entirely, then you forbid use of the length counter, linear counter, sweep units, and hardware envelopes, as their rate depends on $4017 D7. --Tepples 06:11, 1 April 2012 (PDT)
Allow me to clarify further: If you keep the wording "$4017 should not be written to, as it may be needed by the player implementation", you're implying that NSFs SHOULD NOT use anything clocked by the frame counter, and that music engines using these features (such as that of Klax) SHOULD be converted to apply these effects in software. --Tepples 14:36, 1 April 2012 (PDT)

I wasn't trying to forbid it entirely, but I do think it should be recommended against. Maybe "should not interfere with the $4017 register" could be "should avoid interfering with..." Forbidding $4017 writes doesn't forbid the use of frame sequenced events at all, it merely forbids tampering with their default timing. The interrupt itself IS explicitly forbidden by the standard. From what I've seen, using $4017 to force a frame sequencer event/reset is widely unsupported by NSF players. For instance, I've heard of writing $4017 to force a sweep clock when attempting to use hardware sweeps to set the high bits of a square channel (avoiding the phase reset). What does Klax do, and how are NSF players responding to it? - Rainwarrior 15:01, 1 April 2012 (PDT)

Okay, I have rephrased those sections to instead address the inability of NSF players to support it. Does this seem okay, or does it need further revision? - Rainwarrior 15:11, 1 April 2012 (PDT)

What Klax does is heavily use the sweep for precise detunes and arpeggiated chords and repeating hardware envelopes for fine rhythm. Have you tried going through the NSF library to see which use a 4-step sequence and which use a 5-step? --Tepples 15:30, 1 April 2012 (PDT)

Here's what I found with a quick check of about 80 random NSF files I had on hand: FamiTracker NSFs set $4017 = $C0 followed by $40 on init, and I believe it also does this when it is beginning any hardware slide. ppMCK and SuperNSF do not use $4017. Zelda, Zelda 2 FDS, Nazo no Murasamejou, SMB, SMB FDS, SMB2, and SMB3 set 4017 = $FF every frame. Metroid, Metroid FDS, Tetris, and Uchuu Kebitai SDF set $4017 = $C0 every frame. Shin 4-Nin Uchi Mahjong sets $00 then $40 on init. Skate or Die 2 sets $FF on init. All the rest I tried (including Klax) completely ignored $4017. So, interestingly, except for Skate or Die 2, the games that would be selecting a 5 step sequence are generally resetting it every frame, which I believe effectively makes it the same as the 4 step sequence. Skate or Die 2 is probably being incorrectly played by a lot of players (it does use envelopes). - Rainwarrior 16:20, 1 April 2012 (PDT)

I guess that also means that it might be generally safe to write $4017 as long as the interrupt disable flag is set, since there is some precedent with a few extremely common Nintendo game NSFs. Maybe the only thing that should be forbidden is clearing the IRQ disable bit, and if there are hardware players relying on the frame counter IRQ they can deal (maybe a brief note would be good). Made another revision, let me know if okay. - Rainwarrior 17:00, 1 April 2012 (PDT)
←

This version should be fine, and it's close in meaning to what I had. "Kate Oar Diiie" 2 isn't well supported by NSF players anyway due to other limits of NSF. I don't think a lot of hardware players use the APU frame counter because it isn't flexible enough rate-wise for NSFs whose playback rate differs sharply from $4100/$411A. --Tepples 17:25, 1 April 2012 (PDT)

What kind of problem/annoyance such NSF suffers? Remember that my emu threats a NSF like a normal game (regarding $4017). --Zepper 19:20, 1 April 2012 (PDT)

As I tried to hint with my nickname for the game, NSF inherently can't encode the 4-bit PCM samples in SOD2's theme song. --Tepples 05:43, 2 April 2012 (PDT)

I remember of... Gil Galad (?) had fixed a bunch of NSFs, regarding $4017. I'm seeing an excessive "caution" about the NSF section, so be easy with it. --Zepper 14:43, 2 April 2012 (PDT)

Multi expansion

I like the new section with multi expansion notes. I have a few thoughts about it.

It's probably worth suggesting to not use mirrored register addresses in general. I don't think mirrored addresses are widely supported in existing NSF players, possibly because the NSF spec never mentions them.
Perhaps some recommendations can be made for NSF players as to how to avoid the conflict, i.e. writes to VRC7 registers should not be mirrored to VRC6 as well, etc. This may facilitate the implementaion of multi-expansion players, so that a consistent practice can be maintained.
Does the 5B actually mirror E000 to E000-FFFF? (...and C000 to C000-DFFF?) I can't find any good documentation on it; the emulators I've checked so far only respond to $C000/$E000. Does the FME-7 mapper page need an update?
FDS and writable memory needs a clarification; these areas conflict with VRC6, VRC7, and 5B, I think. It seems writing those addresses would corrupt your memory unless you're careful to make sure your code isn't stored there, or perhaps we should suggest that players disallow FDS-RAM writes at these addresses for enabled expansions.

I think a good practice for resolving write conflicts could be done fairly easily by having a standardized order in which to issue writes to the various expansions, like, off the top of my head, maybe N163 VRC7 5B VRC6 MMC5 APU FDS, where each enabled layer is allowed to take ownership of the write or pass it to the next layer in turn. Alternatively, perhaps it should just be suggested that mirrors not be supported by NSF players (which also conveniently avoids conflicts). - Rainwarrior 02:28, 1 April 2012 (PDT)

Another thought: it's not necessarily correct to insist that VRC6-VRC7 should conflict, for instance, since the NSF spec defines a mapper that does not include the mirrored registers. I don't believe there are existing NSF rips that rely on these mirrors, and they aren't really supported by playeres anyway. If you were to attempt a mult-expansion hardware solution (e.g. the TNS-HFE4), it's really up to you as the hardware designer to decide how to resolve these conflicts (or not resolve them, if the solution is too difficult and warn the user). For the most part, the various combinations of hardware seem to work pretty well in NSF players; it doesn't seem necessary to suggest that there should be a conflict. FDS, may be a problem though; I suspect some players have a potential memory corruption problem when using FDS with VRC6/VRC7/5B. - Rainwarrior 02:54, 1 April 2012 (PDT)

I was going from the perspective of soldering all the synths to a circuit board and putting that board in a Famicom's cart slot. Your "how to avoid the conflict" and "practice for resolving conflicts" would be implemented in a decoder circuit. This way, people building these hardware solutions will know what behavior to implement, and people building NSF players will know what behavior to emulate. If you've been making 5B tests, you might want to convert them to .nes format and post them to the BBS so that people who have made gimmicky devcarts can verify these hypotheses. --Tepples 05:42, 1 April 2012 (PDT)

I do have a small test NSF/NES I could share. Nobody with hardware to test with responded to my thread; interested people I had shared it with directly, but I will post it to the BBS as well. - Rainwarrior 13:15, 1 April 2012 (PDT)

Short suggestion: support for multiple APU instances. :) --Zepper 08:07, 1 April 2012 (PDT)

That'd depend on figuring out how to make a crossover cable between two systems' controller ports. Make a proof of concept (in .nes format) of keeping two consoles synchronized in this manner, and I'll consider documenting. Likewise with using a Game Link cable between an NES and a Game Boy. --Tepples 10:43, 1 April 2012 (PDT)

I'd save a multi APU suggestion for NSF2 (and I think it's about time to get the ball rolling on NSF2). I'm not trying to rewrite the NSF format here, I just want to clarify what is commonly practiced and what isn't. Multi-expansions of all combinations are widely allowed by NSF players, but there may be some variation in the details. In this area I would like to avoid "must" suggestions unless they agree with practice (avoiding mirror registers appears to be a must). If we suddenly start telling people that FDS-RAM in 8000-DFFF must be disabled for multi expansions, there will be corruption in some existing players. I'd rather provide a guide that helps people make their multi-expansion NSFs in a safe/robust way. - Rainwarrior 12:13, 1 April 2012 (PDT)

I've edited the section to keep the conflict notes you added, Tepples, but I've tried to reorganize how the suggestions are made. I haven't seen any software NSF players that have any problem with the mirror conflicts (probably because, as I said, the mirrors aren't generally implemented). So for the most part, this is a problem for someone trying to build a hardware multi-chip solution to solve, and that's how I think the suggestion should be made. (In the notes I found for the TNS-HFE4 it looks like they did not sort out the VRC6/VRC7 conflict.) The FDS memory problem I suspect has been an issue but due to some luck nobody has noticed yet. There's only one suggestion I can think of that would be safe (i.e. avoid placing code/data at these addresses). Since this is inconvenient, and probably won't be followed anyway, it's probably prudent for the player to prevent this. The least-impact way to resolve it I think it just to block memory writes at the specified audio registers (which I will do in my next version of NSFPlay), but a complete disable of the write behaviour in that area might be easier to do for a hardware solution. - Rainwarrior 13:10, 1 April 2012 (PDT)

Consistency

I converted all 0XXXXh hex numbers to $ for consistency. Since all the references to the file header were of the form 0XXh I kept the extra 0 just to make it easier to spot the difference between header addresses and 8 bit hex numbers. I also converted *starred* words to italic, but some of them were then changed to ALLCAPS. I don't care really what style is used, but I'd like it to be consistent. - Rainwarrior 13:20, 1 April 2012 (PDT)

More clarification

Is the bank switching registers supposed to be write-only? Exactly how much stack space, clock cycles, etc are assumed to be reserved for the player? What assumptions can be made about the stack pointer register? --Zzo38 11:05, 1 September 2012 (MDT)

I believe that: 1- NSFs are made assuming that the bankswitching registers are write-only, but whether they are or not is immaterial. 2- The NSF spec doesn't allow sharing any resources, i.e. it doesn't leave any space in the 2KB RAM for other programs, even if most NSFs don't use all of it. 3- most NSFs initialize their own stack pointer 4- NSFs *should* be capable of running on actual NES hardware for the refresh rate specified (i.e. 60Hz → 30KCy/callback max) but several (earlier) software NSF players didn't enforce this constraint. —Lidnariq 14:23, 1 September 2012 (MDT)

My reasons for asking some of these things (such as if bank-switching registers are write-only) are also because I wanted to write a program to combine multiple NSFs into one NSF file, although it is difficult. In some cases it could be simple (such as, no bankswitching, no FDS), although may still need to do some other things, such as selecting empty RAM/ROM/etc. A more complicated way would be to trace the program execution and use that to relocate banks and so on. Is the play address allowed to be RAM (such as outside of the $8000-$FFFF range)? Another thing I was interested in and asking these questions for is a somewhat unrelated thing: I was writing my own design for hardware NSF. Currently it can use any playback rate although it won't work if the NSF program sets its own stack pointer. Other than that it looks (to me) like it is following the .NSF specification. --Zzo38 16:42, 1 September 2012 (MDT)

I don't think there's any restrictions on the PLAY and INIT pointers; LOAD is apparently supposed to point to nothing below $8000 for hysterical raisins (and it obviously needs to point to initialized memory).—Lidnariq 18:00, 1 September 2012 (MDT)

There are a few players (e.g. NotSoFatso) that don't allow LOAD below $8000, but it makes little sense not to support it if you're supporting the FDS (though there is a workaround using bankswitching). Bankswitch registers should probably be read+write but I haven't yet noticed any NSFs trying to read them (what use would this have?). I don't think it's true that most NSFs initialize the stack pointer, but they don't seem to be forbidden to do so either. PowerPak's NSF player actually uses the top 16 bytes of the stack for its own variables, and I would say it plays the majority of NSFs perfectly fine like this. - Rainwarrior 23:13, 1 September 2012 (MDT)

Either way it does not make sense for LOAD or INIT to be below $6000 (even if FDS is used); but PLAY should be allowed to be as low as $0000. However like I have mentioned above I do have a potential reason for a NSF to read the bankswitch registers. --Zzo38 13:09, 2 September 2012 (MDT)

LOAD should be at $6000 for an FDS rip that has music code/data in that location (e.g. Mr. Gold). Below $6000 there's no point, really, but I do think it's sensible to support this for FDS' sake. It could theoretically have been relevant for FME-7 as well, but I don't think any FME-7 games had music data at that location, so it doesn't really matter. - Rainwarrior 16:09, 2 September 2012 (MDT)

Actually, since INIT and PLAY must end with RTS, it's not really acceptable for either to set the stack pointer. I think this directly implies that the stack pointer should not be initialized by the NSF. Probably we should make this clear in the NSF article. - Rainwarrior 23:17, 1 September 2012 (MDT)

I agree; why would anything work if the stack pointer were initialized by the NSF? --Zzo38 13:09, 2 September 2012 (MDT)

One of the items in the "caveat" section suggested an NSF should not try to store variables in $1F0-1FF, which is consistent with how the PowerPak uses its stack. I would like to ask, are you aware of any NSFs that attempt to initialize the stack pointer in INIT? It seems like this wouldn't run at all on a lot of players... - Rainwarrior 23:30, 1 September 2012 (MDT)

My own hardware NSF (not yet implented) uses only three bytes of stack, and only uses a single byte of RAM for its own variables, which is part of the cartridge and is not available while the NSF is playing. It also uses 30 clock cycles to call the PLAY routine; I thought it should be less but I don't know how. I would like to see the clock and memory information for other hardware NSF. --Zzo38 13:09, 2 September 2012 (MDT)

PowerPak's NSF player source is at loopy's site: http://home.comcast.net/~olimar/NES/, though it does not include source for the NSF mapper. - Rainwarrior 16:10, 2 September 2012 (MDT)

Talk:NSFe

chunk suggestions

Suggestion for "auth" chunk: Add extra fields for composer of original and composer of cover. Another suggestion, for "vrc7" chunk: Specify the VRC7 built-in instrument settings which this file is meant to be played (there are a few different patch sets due to inaccuracy, and some might intend certain ones to sound better as they were written). Also suggestion a "JF13" chunk, which if it exists, contains ADPCM encoded audio, which is controlled by a register at $7FFF. --Zzo38 (talk) 03:22, 25 January 2013 (MST)

Many people who make NSF covers already put both in the existing artist field, or use the Copyright field with it, often prefixing the cover artist with "cv:". Since in NSFe there is no length limit on the strings in the "auth" chunk there's plenty of room for multiple names in there already. People have suggested a lot of extra fields to add, but I personally just think this makes UI implementation for it annoying, which is why I just added a "text" field instead where any arbitrary information could be added and displayed at the author likes. Currently only NSFPlay will show it, and only in the infobox window, though I plan to make a breakout window for it so you don't have to scroll through that tiny box to see it. As for the Jaleco-JF-13 sound board, that's been kinda low priority to me for pretty obvious reasons (i.e. only used in one game, not for music, only for baseball gameplay sounds, lack of implementation details, scarcity of ROM, unrippable ROM, etc.). - Rainwarrior (talk) 08:05, 27 January 2013 (MST)

But, what about "vrc7" chunk? Different emulators will play the built-in VRC7 patches differently, and some files which are tested with older emulators may be made to sound best with certain patch sets, which is what it is for, which is why it is lowercase. (If someone wants to use it to make up completely their own instrument sets, you could make up a uppercase "VRC7" chunk for that but then it won't be really VRC7, and it won't really be the expansion audio which is actually used with Famicom.) --Zzo38 (talk) 22:01, 2 February 2013 (MST)

I never did get an explanation as to how providing the ability to customize the built-in VRC7 instruments is a good thing. Would you humor me? —Lidnariq (talk) 17:36, 2 February 2013 (MST)

Furthermore, another suggestion for "mixe" chunk which tells the volume and panning of each channel, specifying the ratio of the master volume with the maximum volume that the channel can have. Another chunk is "MULT" which combines multiple files into one; each record is an address and length of the ROM data (within the "DATA" block) corresponding to each one. The "INFO" and "BANK" data are copied the same number of times each within their chunks, so if the first block specifies 5 songs and the next 2 songs, then songs 0 to 4 are using the first ROM address/data and INFO and BANK headers, while the songs 5 and 6 use the second one and subtracts 5 to write the accumulator initially. --Zzo38 (talk) 16:21, 2 February 2013 (MST)

re: "mixe" I'm a little wary of providing features that can't be implemented in hardware: as long as we assume a 2A03 as the sound generator (and if not, why does this belong in a NSF specification?), grouping mixing by "both square waves", "triangle, noise, and DPCM", and "expansion" would be something I could defend, but more fine-grained panning/volume control seems untrue. (I guess the sole exception would be I also see an argument for "individually pan-able and volume-control-able channels of the 5B", because we know it's identical to a YM2149F.)

While your NSF combiner has evidently been greatly useful, I find myself a little troubled "MULT" turning NSFe into a almost-general archive format… —Lidnariq (talk) 17:36, 2 February 2013 (MST)

I know it cannot be implemented in standard 2A03 hardware which is why it is lowercased (my idea about the $4009 register for stereo (which does the grouping like you said) could be implemented in a hardware modification, though?); it is not required, and is supposed to play in mono as well. NSFplay can do volume/panning of individual channels in the setting menu but cannot load it from the NSFe file. --Zzo38 (talk) 22:01, 2 February 2013 (MST)

I think these have come up before but here's my thoughts on those features:

I don't think custom VRC7 patches is worth doing. It has nothing to do with Famicom hardware, or any existing hardware, and I don't consider the NSF/NSFe format to be a dumping ground for fantasy hardware features.
A panning/mix option is similar; has no relevance to the actual hardware, ripping games, preserving emulation, etc. the only purpose of this is for people to compose music that requires something the hardware does not have, and I don't see the point of this. Just write music for hardware that doesn't have this limitation.
I also don't particularly see the advantage of packing multiple NSFs into one. It isn't relevant to ripping any game, and would make it more complicated to use with something like the PowerPak. I would recommend .zip/.rar/.7z if you need a way to put multiple NSFs in one file.

- Rainwarrior (talk) 23:14, 3 February 2013 (MST)

Talk:NTSC video

The part of the PPU that generates the video signal (immediately to the right of the NMI and CLK pins) appears to consist of a very long resistor between VCC and GND with taps at various points, and one of them (closest to VCC) is a switchable pulldown to GND (no doubt for color emphasis). The logic itself can select 12 different voltage levels (00/10/20/30, 0D/1D/2D/3D, synch, colorburst L/H, and GND), and they appear to correspond to 10 distinct voltage levels - one of the duplicates is at the highest voltage (likely 20/30), and the other one is the 3rd-lowest [non-GND] voltage (not sure which one). --Quietust 17:59, 28 September 2011 (UTC)

With the help of ChipSim, I've traced down exactly what the 12 voltage levels correspond to - Synch (GND), Colorburst L, Color 0D, Color xE/xF and Color 1D, Colorburst H, Color 2D, Color 00, Color 10, color 3D, Color 20 and Color 30 ("and" == two signals which select the same actual voltage). --Quietust 11:17, 29 October 2012 (MDT)

Absolute Video Signal Timing

Some tests with Visual2C02 managed to confirm all of the contents of the Scanline Timing table, plus one more interesting bit of information: the offset. Specifically, the "active" region begins at cycle 4, which is when the PPU is just finishing the attribute byte fetch for the 3rd tile in the scanline (the first 2 are fetched at the end of the previous scanline). --Quietust 08:50, 1 November 2012 (MDT)

But during which cycles is sync output? We need that too to align the NES picture center relative to the NTSC standard picture center (see Overscan). --Tepples 09:41, 1 November 2012 (MDT)

It's probably been mentioned elsewhere, but for completeness: cycles 280 through 304, inclusive, which happens to correspond to when the VRAM address gets reloaded during the prerender scanline. --Quietust (talk) 07:24, 14 February 2013 (MST)

C++ code?

Is this really C++ code? Can we call it what it is, if it's not?

auto InColorPhase = [=](int color) { return (color + phase) % 12 < 6; }; // Inline function

-- Rainwarrior (talk) 07:26, 13 August 2014 (MDT)

It appears to be C++11 code. Not all C++ compilers understand C++11 yet. --Tepples (talk) 19:42, 13 August 2014 (MDT)

Am I just out of touch? Is C++11 the accepted standard now? I didn't know it was safe to call it "C++" now, but maybe it is? :S - Rainwarrior (talk) 21:08, 13 August 2014 (MDT)

Yes, it's the standard. The draft was commonly referred to as "C++0x" because they aimed to get it accepted by the end of 2009. It became C++11 when the changes were officially added to ISO C++ in 2011. --Tepples (talk) 06:56, 14 August 2014 (MDT)

It was an official standard in 2011, but that's different than it being the primary flavour of C++, which is really what I meant. After looking around, I've noted that as usual Microsoft has done a pick-and-choose with which features to implement, but the C++11 features they did implement have been enabled by default since VS2010. GCC on the other hand much more fully supports it, but requires a compiler switch to enable. Clang is in the same situation as GCC. Intel's compiler looks like partial support, off by default. I imagine other compilers are in similar states. As such, I'd say we're in a period of transition, but C++11 will surely become the default before long. - Rainwarrior (talk) 11:56, 14 August 2014 (MDT)

Talk:Overscan

PAL DAR

If I'm doing the math correctly, PAL display aspect ratio is ≈1.48:1, or close enough to 3:2. So do PAL games basically come pre-widescreen? How does the vertical alignment compare?—Lidnariq (talk) 18:53, 9 April 2013 (MDT)

I have no access to a PAL NES, PAL famiclone, or PAL TV, but I'm getting in the neighborhood of 1.39:1. Could you explain the math that leads to 1.48:1? But for this comment, assume that the 240px of the NES picture is in fact vertically centered on the 288px tall PAL picture. A widescreen TV will show 216px minus overscan, and overscan is (I'll guess) 12px per side, so anything designed for a 192px tall safe area will fit properly. And the old Nintendo BG planning sheet did assume a 192px tall safe area. --Tepples (talk) 19:29, 9 April 2013 (MDT)

Just going on what was said in the page: 1.3862 × 256 ÷ 240 = 1.4786. Am I doing that wrong? —Lidnariq (talk) 19:46, 9 April 2013 (MDT)

Oh, my fault, I misread your first comment. 1.48 is the DAR. I've been so focused on getting proper PAR that sometimes I forget about DAR. But you'd need a DAR near 1.78 to be widescreen friendly. --Tepples (talk) 21:38, 9 April 2013 (MDT)

Having a vertical active area of 200px (back of the envelope: 256×9÷16×1.3862) puts "de-letterboxed widescreen PAL 16:9" as convenient as 4:3 SDTV, which is perhaps worth keeping in mind.—Lidnariq (talk) 01:02, 10 April 2013 (MDT)

Talk:Power Pad

Metric

Are we sure those spacings are in mm and not in inches? 252mm is so close to 254mm=10in, and 285mm is only ¾mm away from 11¼in... Lidnariq 18:34, 17 October 2011 (UTC)

I had the metric side of the ruler out when I measured the distances from button 1 to buttons 2 and 5 because when I was measuring it, I was discussing DDR with Jeroen, and he's Dutch. For comparison, the commonly accepted dimensions of each square of a DDR pad are either 11 inches by 11 inches or 280 mm by 280 mm. --Tepples 22:54, 17 October 2011 (UTC)

I just measured my own Power Pad, and I came up with about 9⅜" x 11¼" by measuring between the white spots on the upper-left corners of each button. --Quietust 23:42, 17 October 2011 (UTC)

Rollover

"It is not known whether the Family Trainer mat has included diodes for n-key-rollover, or whether pressing buttons on three corners of a square will cause a ghost press on the last corner." And how about the Power Pad? Does it? —Myask (talk) 22:17, 19 July 2016 (MDT)

The Power Pad detects every button separately, just like the ordinary joypad. The only reason it's in question with the Family Trainer Mat is that the API is very clearly just scanning a matrix of buttons, where button ghosting can easily be a problem (and a diode for each button can be expensive in large matrices). —Lidnariq (talk) 23:35, 19 July 2016 (MDT)

Talk:PPU memory map

- I believe that memory range illustrates better than offset / size. Example: $3F00-$3F0F - background palette; $3F10-$3F1F - sprites palette.

- Additionally, it shouldn't use the term palette, since it's not palette, but indexes to the palette signals, since there's no real RGB palette.--Zepper 00:59, 30 March 2010 (UTC)

Like mentioned at the bottom of the page, this is a place holder for the PPU memory map since there was none in the first place. It's based on a similar structure to the CPU one and from nestech document as a source. It will require improvement. Banshaku 03:09, 30 March 2010 (UTC)

- Unfortunately, I can't go ahead and create a custom PPU memory table of my wishes... ^_^;; Perhaps tepples can?--Zepper 21:23, 30 March 2010 (UTC)

What do you mean? Anybody has the right to update the wiki. Unless you mean you don't know how to use wiki table format? I don't really know either, just used the format for the CPU one. I would still prefer ascii art actually. Banshaku 22:58, 30 March 2010 (UTC)

There is a set of CSS styles to make tables look prettier. But it's not installed by default in installations of MediaWiki, and only a user in the 'sysop' group can edit the site CSS to install it. I was a sysop on Atarimike's nesdevwiki.org, but the group was never reassigned upon the server move to Parodius. What is the procedure to request rights on this wiki? --Tepples 13:58, 31 March 2010 (UTC)

As far as I can gather from what I've been told on the forum, User:Ndwiki is a role account, and I'm supposed to e-mail Parodius staff to get the password. --Tepples 01:52, 1 April 2010 (UTC)

Well, I did the changes. :) Anyway, here's something to discuss: it says "Either CHR ROM or CHR RAM depending on the board". For my best, the PPU memory 0000-1FFF is CHR RAM: the hardware chip is RAM, not ROM. The CHR ROM data is always in the cartridge. In that case, CHR ROM appears there. Could someone clarify if it's copied, mirrored or whatever..? --Zepper 13:46, 3 April 2010 (UTC)

Are the nametable mirrors at $3xxx ever accessed by the internal logic of the PPU during rendering? --Zzo38 (talk) 23:11, 8 June 2013 (MDT)

Talk:PPU OAM

An observation from a PPU die image - the 2 large blocks at the upper-right (the horizontal strip between them is the address decoder) are the PPU OAM. It is arranged in 8 groups, one hooked up to each CPU data bit (i.e. the ones used for $2000-$2007 - the actual pins are along the upper-right corner of the die). The groups hooked up to D0/D1/D5/D6/D7 are 9 bits wide, while the ones hooked up to D2/D3/D4 are only 7 bits wide. One row in each group appears to be used for secondary OAM, while the other pairs of rows store the actual sprite data - since the flags byte does not contain any actual data in D2-D4, the corresponding rows are absent (and thus contain only 3 pairs of rows instead of 4 pairs); indeed, what appears to be a 4->9 decoder at the top of the die (just to the left of CPU D7) looks to convert the bottom 3 bits of the SPR-RAM address (and possibly the top 9th bit) into enables for offsets 0-7 and secondary OAM (for 8-15), and the enables for offsets 2 and 6 are not connected to D2-D4. --Quietust 18:23, 11 January 2011 (UTC)

In fact, the 4->9 decoder at the top also explains behavior I've seen elsewhere, where setting $2003 to a nonzero value would use the value of the upper 5 bits (instead of all 0s) to fetch the first two sprites (and cause the first one to trigger sprite #0 hit)... --Quietust 18:29, 11 January 2011 (UTC)

Perhaps this page could be renamed to something like "Sprites" and have some of the priority and evaluation stuff merged into it. A separate page just for the memory area seems a bit arbitrary to me. -Ulfalizer (talk) 05:05, 28 March 2013 (MDT)

One part of it says "It has not been determined whether the PPU actually drives these bits low or whether this is the effect of data bus capacitance from reading the last byte of the instruction (LDA $2004, which assembles to AD 04 20). "

This is not factual information and adds noise to the page. Has it been determined since this was edited in? Bregalad (talk) 08:19, 20 May 2015 (MDT)

PAL horizontal overscan masking?

The wiki currently says "[A sprite 0 hit will happen even if it is during] The PAL PPU blanking on the left and right edges at x=0, x=1, and x=254."—what PAL PPU blanking on the edges? Did I miss something? (maybe add a citation in the article?) —Lidnariq (talk) 21:06, 20 May 2015 (MDT)

It's the "Side borders" row in Clock rate. --Tepples (talk) 21:41, 20 May 2015 (MDT)

Doesn't that mean that the visible width is 260 pixels on PAL, with two pixels of black on both sides, not that the visible area is 256 pixels of which the NES blanks two pixels on each side?—Lidnariq (talk) 22:51, 20 May 2015 (MDT)

No. The left and right 2 columns are always black in PAL (even if the background colour is not black), making the "effective" resolution 252x240. Since everything is so badly worded and so confusing on this wiki it's no surprise there is no consistency how this phenomena is called and how poorly it is doccumented. By the way, you guys obviously are not used to work with technical documentation. Text should state facts only once, not 3 or 4 times sparkled around and using a different wording. If examples should be given to complement the text, they should be graphical, not textual.Bregalad (talk) 01:41, 21 May 2015 (MDT)

In this particular case, the Wiki describes this once, inadequately, and in the wrong place (clock rate??). That's probably on par with most technical manuals I've read, but most technical manuals are crap, and they have a very different target than our wiki (and often don't have the advantage of hypertext). Examples can be very useful to understanding, I have no idea why you came up with the bizarre idea that examples should be graphical only, but some graphical illustrations of how the PAL video is displayed would be very helpful. - Rainwarrior (talk) 11:31, 21 May 2015 (MDT)

It's briefly covered in Overscan#PAL, it looks like, and that's actually an appropriate place for it. - Rainwarrior (talk) 11:35, 21 May 2015 (MDT)

Thank you. If you find duplication, the first step is to figure out which shall be authoritative for each fact. For example, Myths and Errata are duplicative by their nature, but they link to the primary page for each fact. So I have added a note in Clock rate that the behavior is fully described in Overscan#PAL. --Tepples (talk) 10:37, 22 May 2015 (MDT)

I don't think a moderate amount of duplication is necessarily bad, except when they get out of sync. Hyperlinks are very helpful here. The issue with it being at clock rate was one of obscurity. (i.e. how would anyone know to look in clock rate to find that information?) - Rainwarrior (talk) 23:55, 22 May 2015 (MDT)

Well ideally the example should be graphical especially when talking about graphics. That makes sense, I don't think it's a "weird idea". An explaination like "a sprite with colour $12 will hit on a background with colour $32" or whathever is hard to understand and makes absolutely no sense for those who aren't already familiar with the NES palette. Even for me who am familiar with the NES palette this makes few sense: Why those values? Since the palette does not matter at all, I don't see why adding palette values is useful in any way, it is just downright confusing and stupid.Bregalad (talk) 01:27, 22 May 2015 (MDT)

I agree about that. Calling out two random example values like that was very strange to me, almost like it was suggesting there was something special about them. That whole sentence was a bit wonky to me (starting with the ambiguous term "pixel values") and I revised it the other day. Do you have thoughts on the current version, or what a suitable explanation graphic would look like? - Rainwarrior (talk) 00:01, 23 May 2015 (MDT)

I chose %01 and %10 for a reason: they AND to %00. I also chose palette colors $20 and $02 for a reason: they and to $00. Mostly I was trying to express in English how to create unit tests for an emulator's sprite 0 hit handling. How can we work this in? --Tepples (talk) 10:18, 23 May 2015 (MDT)

I don't understand the relevance of "AND to 0". Is this some common confusion about sprites that I've never heard of? The best way to guide someone to a unit test would be to make one and link to it. - Rainwarrior (talk) 12:26, 23 May 2015 (MDT)

Does what you call "3 or 4 times sparkled around and using a different wording" have anything to do with what Koitsu calls "provide multiple phrasing" in Nesdev wiki talk:Manual of Style/RFC 2119? --Tepples (talk) 19:45, 26 May 2015 (MDT)

No. Koitsu gives the explanation about attribute tables in his own document, nestech.txt, as an example. Attribute tables is not the easiest thing to explain, yet he does it very gracefully in my subjective opinion. First he explains what area it covers in term of pixels, tiles and metatiles, then he makes a graphical representation of the thing. This is both extremely clear and concise, and is a great example on how technical documentation should be done.

On the other way, saying, with only text, "A non-transparent sprite pixel will collide with a non-transparent BG pixel. For example if sprite pixel 1 collides on BG pixels 0, there is no collision. If sprite pixel 0 collides with BG pixel 2, there is no collision. But if sprite pixel 1 collides with BG pixel 3, there is a collision. Oh and if sprite pixel 3 collides with BG pixel 2, there is also a collision. If palette entry is %xx and the other palette entry is %yy, there is still collision. But guess what? If palette entry is %zz, there is also a collision (etc....)"

This is terrible because 1) it's long, 2) the examples are meaningless, 3) you assume the reader is a 3 years kid who cannot understand the original claim. "Nontransparent sprite with nontransparent BG" should be enough, given the "nontransparent" is proprely defined. All the rest is garbage, except a possible graphical example (in this particular case, the concept is so easy to understand that it's fully optional).

Bregalad (talk) 03:43, 27 May 2015 (MDT)

I'd really like something more authoritative (such as a photograph of a TV with a ROM that demonstrates the missing columns). The only thing I've been able to find is Bregalad blankly asserting that this is true: [1] —Lidnariq (talk) 12:24, 21 May 2015 (MDT)

The relevant thread in regard to this effects I don't know how to name is here: [2]Bregalad (talk) 01:27, 22 May 2015 (MDT)

Talk:PPU palettes

It says that the background palette hack can be used to display the unused palette data. Can the EXT pins also do this? --Zzo38 (talk) 22:30, 1 July 2013 (MDT)

Yes, I think so. While rendering background pixels, the palette index that gets looked up is simply 0<exp_in3><exp_in2><exp_in1><exp_in0>. -Ulfalizer (talk) 03:58, 2 July 2013 (MDT)
Interestingly, it looks like the background palette hack wouldn't work for output to the EXT pins though (bit 6 of $2000 set). The logic that causes the VRAM address to be used for the palette index while the background palette hack is active comes after the logic that outputs the index to the EXT pins. -Ulfalizer (talk) 04:15, 2 July 2013 (MDT)

Thank you for information. I suppose if you are using the master/slave, you can connect the EXT pins in reverse (EXT0 to EXT3, EXT1 to EXT2, EXT2 to EXT1, EXT3 to EXT0) so that this can be used to make extra colors. --Zzo38 (talk) 23:05, 2 July 2013 (MDT)

Contents

1 Source of palette
2 Parsing the palette
3 Browser compatibility of Drag's palette generator
4 Palette color format?
5 Platte display
6 Move the palette chart to the top

Source of palette

Where did the palette added by Lidnariq in this edit come from? --Tepples (talk) 18:56, 25 December 2013 (MST)

Screenshot from Nestopia running blargg's full_colors and nes_ntsc. Feel free to bikeshed. —Lidnariq (talk) 20:00, 25 December 2013 (MST)

Parsing the palette

The palette values from this table are read from left to right, then up -> down. Is this ok?

00 01 02 03 ... 0F
10 11 12 13 ... 1F
20 ...
(unsigned comment by Zepper)

Almost. They appear to go from $00 to $0D, then the next line from $10 to $1D, etc. --Tepples (talk) 06:42, 28 December 2013 (MST)

Browser compatibility of Drag's palette generator

It appears that Firefox 29 implements built-in validation for <input type="number"> such that said elements are expected by default to contain integers. This affects the default hue and saturation settings, causing the boxes to be given glowing red borders and explanatory tooltips, and preventing the values from being changed to other reasonable non-integers. The default settings still work (in that they produce the same palette as in older versions of Firefox) as long as they are not changed.

Relevant documentation can be found on various Mozilla websites (not bothering to link any of it here due to lack of login). --150.135.211.242 22:30, 18 May 2014 (MDT)

Maybe send this information to Drag? I don't think it does much good here. - Rainwarrior (talk) 11:00, 20 May 2014 (MDT)

How does Drag prefer to be contacted? I am not active on the forums (and therefore don't qualify for an account on the wiki either). The homepage of the domain on which the generator is hosted mentions that Drag has a Twitter account, but I'm not a registered Twitter user either (and I don't feel like registering just for this one issue).
I don't see how posting here is useless given that some other user could make a fixed version. For example, Tepples has some webspace which could theoretically be used for this. --150.135.211.242 14:46, 20 May 2014 (MDT)

You used to need a reputation on the BBS or IRC to qualify for a wiki account. You don't anymore; that ended 20 months ago with the transition away from Parodius. Feel free to register and jump right into the talk pages, and so long as your posts there show clue, you'll get autoconfirmed in no time. --Tepples (talk) 19:35, 20 May 2014 (MDT)

I'll take this into account if I decide to poke at my palette generator again. :P Thanks for letting me know about it though. --Drag (talk) 17:27, 26 May 2014 (MDT)
The number fields should now be fixed, I hope. I just needed to add a "step" property to the input field to specify that I expect decimals to 0.001 precision. --Drag (talk) 01:09, 28 May 2014 (MDT)

←

One more problem with the validation: Press the "Get current preset" button with everything else left at defaults. The Wx value of 0.3127 gets flagged as invalid because it has one more decimal place than the current validation allows. It's probably a good idea to allow four decimal places in all the custom colorimetry settings, based on the conventions I've seen. (I suppose I'm fine downloading a copy to run locally if you don't want to bother)

(Aside: My main reason not for registering at this point is lack of HTTPS support. Even if I were to ignore that, I'm a little confused why some accounts have needed to be confirmed manually recently.) --150.135.211.242 14:32, 21 April 2015 (MDT)

Palette color format?

What's the color format used in the palette entries? Example: 755,637,700,447... ??? How do I "decode" the 755 value in RGB? --Zepper (talk) 13:24, 29 October 2014 (MDT)

Those are RGB333 values, so 637 means 6/7 red (0xDB), 3/7 green (0x6D), and 7/7 blue (0xFF). --Quietust (talk) 20:36, 29 October 2014 (MDT)

The .PAL format should consist of the same color formatting as the Classic VGA Palette format so if you know how to program back then, you already know this. --Hamtaro126 (talk) 05:55, 31 October 2014 (MDT)

Why does this page show strange, nonstandard palettes first ?

Platte display

One version of the canonical, standard NES palette should appear at the top of the page. Other palettes used by RGB, playchoice or whathever are annecdotical and should only appear below. They should most certainly *not* appear first. Bregalad (talk) 14:29, 6 January 2016 (MST)

Move the palette chart to the top

I don't know about you guys, but most of the time I visit this page is because I want to see a chart which maps NES colors to their corresponding numbers. Strangely, the only chart on the page for this is found at the very bottom! The charts that come before it are for the 2C03, 2C04, 2C05 PPUs, not the 2C02 PPU which is what most people would expect.

Suggested change: Move savtool's NES palette to the top of the page, above any mention of the 2C03.

Pubby (talk) 11:20, 11 May 2016 (MDT)

Good point. Done. --Tepples (talk) 13:10, 11 May 2016 (MDT)

Talk:PPU pin out and signal description

EXT port description

Can the function of the EXT pins be described more precisely? I do not understand very well, there are four EXT pins, and the colors are six bits (selecting the palette entry is only two bits), so how can it decide the color from this? --Zzo38 (talk) 00:27, 21 January 2013 (MST)

I am having a doozy of a time figuring out how to rephrase it on the main page in an intelligible manner, so I'll just start from scratch: Assume the NES's palette has no gaps and thus is a {32 entry} × {6 bit} array. log₂(32)=5, so indexing this array requires 5 bits. The EXT port takes as input or output the bottom 4 bits of this 5 bit index. If the EXT port is used as an input, it replaces the "transparent" color in index 0 with any of colors 0-15, i.e. it's an extra layer of background and background-colored sprites underneath. —Lidnariq (talk) 01:59, 21 January 2013 (MST)

OK, thanks, that makes sense, now I can understand. --Zzo38 (talk) 03:37, 25 January 2013 (MST)

SYNC -> RST

Through analysis of Visual2C02 and cross-referencing of the Family Computer schematic, I've decided to rename pin 22 from "/SYNC" to "/RST" because that's clearly what it does (and I also renamed /VBL to /INT). However, there is still the matter of this comment: "(In a dual-PPU arrangement, the master /INT is also connected to the slave's /RST input)". This cannot be the case, because it would result in the chips becoming desynchronized - /INT goes high at the beginning of scanline 261 (pre-render), but /RST places the chip at the beginning of scanline 0 and forces rendering to be disabled for a complete frame. --Quietust (talk) 09:33, 31 March 2013 (MDT)

I imagine that the two chips' /RST inputs would be tied together. There'd also have to be glue logic to keep some semblance of synchronization between writes to $2001 on both PPUs so that neither PPU is put in a state where one skips the dot between pre-render and the first line of picture and the other does not. --Tepples (talk) 12:32, 31 March 2013 (MDT)
Yeah, the more dwe refined the functions of the pins, the less I trusted that comment.—Lidnariq (talk) 13:23, 31 March 2013 (MDT)

Rename some pins?

This wiring diagram calls the A2-A0 pins on the PPU RS2-RS0, which I'm guessing stands for Register Select. I think that might be a less confusing name for them. The /CS line is also called /DBE (prolly Data Bus Enable), which might be better than /CS since (I think) /CS might imply that the entire PPU would be disabled rather than just the CPU-to-PPU bit. Mind if I rename those pins? -Ulfalizer (talk) 12:04, 22 May 2013 (MDT)

What is more useful, to describe what the pins are known as in isolation, or what they connect to? I personally prefer the latter, especially for inputs.
I object to using /DBE. The "/CS" terminology is well established industry practice used by peripheral ICs (e.g. MC6845, YM2149), not just memories: it requires less explanation to someone who already has background.
If we are simply going to use Nintendo's terminology, we should also rename CPU pins 1, 2, 29, 35, and 36; furthermore they used different terms for CPU pins 3, 29, 31, and 35-39 in the Vs System documentation (http://nesdev.com/VSSCHEM.pdf) than the Famicom (http://nesdev.com/Ntd_8bit.jpg) —Lidnariq (talk) 14:07, 22 May 2013 (MDT)

What makes it confusing in this case is that some of the VRAM address pins are also called Ax. It's easy to think that e.g. A0 and A8 are related. I'd prefer to label the pins according to what they do and also explain what they connect to. (Well, except in cases where it's immediately obvious from what they connect to, like CLK, etc. :)
Looks like you're right about /CS. Maybe not as confusing/unexpected as it seemed coming at it as a beginner then. -Ulfalizer (talk) 14:18, 22 May 2013 (MDT)

Talk:PPU registers

Contents

1 Naming the registers
2 Palette
3 Emphasis bits
4 Allcaps vblank?
5 Immediately?

Naming the registers

Am I the only one being annoyed by those "PPUMASK" "PPUSCROLL" etc... names ? Because Mr Tepples often refers them as it doesn't mean everyone often refers them as it. I like to use plain $2000, $2005, etc... Personally I'd vote for removing references to those names from the Wiki but I don't want to force it if other people disagree. Bregalad 21:29, 24 February 2010 (UTC)

It depends. It's not only Tepples that promoted those names. I'm a firm believer that using symbolic constants makes the code easier to read. As long both are available in the wiki I don't see the issue.

I can give you an example as code. Which one is clearer when you read back the code?

This:

lda #%1010000
sta $2000

Or:

; In another file (nes.h)
PPU_CTRL_NMI %10000000
PPU_CTRL_SPRITE8x16 %00100000
PPU_CTRL $2000

...

; Somewhere in the code
lda #PPU_CTRL_NMI + PPU_CTRL_SPRITE8x16
sta PPU_CTRL

Once you know the convention, it makes the code easier to read. Of course for the registers only it could be argued for a while since there is not that much on the nes but it's always good to follow good programming practice. In a professional environment, I will always promote the second once since it makes the code clearer.

You don't know how many time I saw code samples for newb with no comments at all and you have to figure out what the hell was done with anonymous labels to make it worst. At the least those constants give some visual feedback on what you're trying to do. It's only a matter of getting used to the naming convention.

In brief, I think it's a good practice to use them but nobody is forcing you do to so. There's just there to try to make a convention and of course not everyone will agree with it (i.e. see how many linux distro..)

Banshaku 01:35, 25 February 2010 (UTC)

Well it's fun because I always do it like your "bad example" exept I write numbers in hex instead of binary, and I never had problems reading it. Symbolic names just makes the thing longer and more confusing. In fact I think it is the exact opposite of what you said - it makes things harder to read in my opinion. Then it depends if you remember best words or numbers - I know I remember numbers better personally.

Like you said, as long as there is both there isn't any problem... but my issue is that I found several pages on the Wiki which ONLY refers the symbolic names which are nothing official anyways. So my proposal would be to not touch this page, but change the others to mirror the numbers (e.g. $2001) instead of symbolic names that makes few sense (PPUMASK really makes no sense to me it sounds like carnival or something).

Again I don't want to force anything but I'd vote for at least replacing all instances which ONLY have the symbolic names to show the true register instead. Bregalad 08:20, 25 February 2010 (UTC)

I was not aware that some page of the wiki only refer to the name. In that case, yes it can be confusing since there is no official standard for naming them. To make both crowd happy, we could always put both at the same time too.

Which pages are like that?

As for using constants For the registers, the benefit is quite negligible since there is not that much but for flags or your own values in your game, it will save you from many headache when you use the same value many time. Of course, if you use long name and you have to remember all of them by heart, everybody will agree with you and say it's quite a pain in the butt (I do agree) but with a good editor, the editor will give you suggestion once you start to type a word. For example, in Visual Studio, Eclipse and many IDE, if I would type PPU, it would give me a suggestion list of all the words that start with PPU. In the case of nes programming this is an issue because there is no such editor that gives that functionality. I wanted to make one for that reason since I cannot remember all my constants, which is normal.

Banshaku 12:05, 25 February 2010 (UTC)

See GBATEK for the kind of style that I was attempting to follow when I instituted the PPU registers' names in the first place. The GBA community never refers to registers by their address. --Tepples 12:55, 25 February 2010 (UTC)

Tepples there is a big difference : The NES adresses are 16-bit and so you only have 4 digits per adress, which makes them much easier to remember. Another big differences is that all those names are made up - they are nothing official and probably aren't "often refereed as" as this page says Ian Bell uses the following definitions in his open source "tank demo" so if anything were to be official it'd look more like this (and again I doubt it's official it's probably made up by Ian Bell himself) :

VCR:		EQU	$2000	; video control reg base address
VIDEO0:		EQU	VCR+000	; CTRL0
VIDEO1:		EQU	VCR+001	; CTRL1
VSTAT:		EQU	VCR+002	; video general status register
OAM_ADR:		EQU	VCR+003 ; sprite attribute address register
SCROLL:		EQU	VCR+005 ; scroll h/v registers appear here
VRAM_ADR:		EQU	VCR+006	; video address register
VRAM_DAT:		EQU	VCR+007	; video data register

SPRITE_DMA_ADR	EQU	$4014
WRST		EQU	$4015	; DMA WRST/RDST

CONTROLLER1:	EQU	$4016		; Joystick and DMA
CONTROLLER2:	EQU	$4017		; Ports

So according to what Banshaku said, I guess I can go ahead and remove places where registers are refereed only by their GBA-style name and replace them with true adreses. If this cause problems someone can still undo the changes. --Bregalad 15:10, 25 February 2010 (UTC)

Game Boy addresses are 16-bit, yet the same fellow behind GBATEK also wrote Pan Docs. --Tepples 16:02, 25 February 2010 (UTC)

We should just be careful thought. It's not because there is no official naming convention coming from Nintendo that we cannot make our own in the first place. If we go that extreme, we could say that we don't agree with Loopy_V/Loopy_T naming convention because that is not official too.

There is nothing wrong to try to make a naming convention that seems simple for new users. The one shown above is not any simpler the the currently proposed one on the wiki. It's all a mater of preference. Don't forget that people have complained many time that the wiki was "not organized" so we shouldn't shoot down people that try new ideas. There is nothing wrong we that. You may have missed that Ddribin did some example in it's own sandbox for some possible formatting and naming convention here. I thought his idea was interesting and it passed under the radar of everyone.

Banshaku 23:46, 25 February 2010 (UTC)

I just noticed this mass-removal of named registers and it's ridiculous. The point of this Wiki is to make thigs clearer. Using numeric addresses everywhere adds needless detail and harms its primary purposes of educating NES programmers.

The point of using an assembler is to work at a higher level than machine code. The assembler allows you to use the names of instructions rather than their op codes. Likewise, it allows one to give addresses names and work with them. Labels in programs are one example, and named constants are another. If one really believed that using hexadecimal values instead of named registers was good, one would have to argue the same for labels and instructions, and thus use only .byte directives in the assembler.

New NES programmers have plenty to remember already. Being able to say PPUSTATUS instead of $2002 lightens their mental load, and reminds them of the register's purpose wherever it's used, without having to look anything up. Even an experienced NES programmer who takes a break will have to re-learn the values to some extent, and make more errors during the process.

All NES programmers make typos when programming. Making a typo on PPUSTATUS will result in an assembler error in almost all cases, rather than a program that misbehaves. Making a typo on $2002 can easily result in a program that assembles fine but fails to work, without any way to easily find the typo.

When a programmer is reading source, addresses like $2002, $2003, $2005 all tend to look somewhat alike, while PPUSTATUS, SPRADDR, and PPUSCROLL are more distinct, and can be set up as keywords for the syntax highlighter.

If one is used to using numeric addresses, he will have to learn the names for them, but this has none of the disadvantages listed above. The names are based on the function, rather than arbitrary numbers. And misremembering a name will be caught almost immediately. I can't help but think that the desire for removal of names is to avoid having to learn them, or make up for deficient tools or something.

Blargg 22:18, 28 February 2010 (UTC)

It's a battle of the B's, and I'm still the odd one out even after buying a copy of Bee-52 :-)

Martin Korth uses purported official names in GBATEK and Pan Docs, but he appears not to use names in Everynes. My early GBA header files used different names from the names in GBATEK. Part of this was to be different on purpose to avoid appearing to support the use of unlawfully acquired trade secrets. What are "official" names other than names in leaked Nintendo manuals? The other part was to take advantage of the various arrays implicit in the GBA register map. In fact, some elements of my naming scheme, particularly with respect to these arrays, eventually made it into devkitPro's libgba header file, which otherwise follows GBATEK. (See for example BGCTRL[].)

So, Bregalad, do you object to the idea of having the community invent a consistent set of names, or do you just object to the specific names I invented? --Tepples 02:44, 1 March 2010 (UTC)

I tend to agree to what Blargg said. Making a typo on a name will make the compiler fail but a typo on an address won't. By using constant you avoid that possible issue.

For beginners, those constants are a must. How many times when we look at the code sample they send that we can be sure that they really meant $200X and it was not a typo? With the constant, it makes it plain obvious and easier to correct them.

I think it will be hard to make everyone happy in that case. For now, we only have one person objecting to this naming convention. I just checked the updated page and since I didn't program the nes for a while it didn't make any more sense to me anymore. When you have to juggle with many platforms during the day, constants and the proper tools the way to go. If I could find an editor that do some intellisense with my own defined constant I would be happy. I need to check if Notepad++ can do it, that would be great.

Banshaku 03:57, 1 March 2010 (UTC)

Well I don't know. You guys says a newbie already have a lot of things to learn, but learning those confusing names just sounds like one more thing to learn to me. Remembering "PPUSTATUS" you have to remember 9 letters instead of 4 numbers in $2002 which is more complicated (you really have to remember 1 number, because the first 3 are always $200x). I also disagree about the typo things, you can't really do a typo when typing "$2002" without noting it immediately, however you can very easily do typos with words.

You are right tough about that there is no reason the community can't made up names - and I wasn't intending we should replace those names by more "official" names, just using the register is fine for me. My references to Ian Bell's code (which isn't really "leaked" since he did give it himself on purpose to the community) was misplaced - I didn't intend to use them.

About the argument that it would be less confusing when switching to from a system to another, I disagree. Every system has other registers anyways so it wouldn't change a thing.

I just think most of those name didn't make sense to me and are too long to be remembered, but I don't really care if you all like them go away and use them (and undo my modifications), I'll just not use them in my code and anyone is free to use them. It's just that I figured those names caused me trouble as I always had to had the registers page open in another tab to convert from those names to actual registers.Bregalad 07:57, 1 March 2010 (UTC)

- It's not ridiculous. I don't play very often with NES assemblers, but I suppose that those labels should be pre-defined in an header file perhaps? Really, it's pointless. The $2002 means PPUSTATUS; fine. Is this more educational than $2002? Do you know about ppu address mirroring, of address AND 7, just for the case?

- Personally, I prefer the numbered registers instead of labeled ones. If it's not part of a compiler, it's up to the user to define a couple of labels. Yup, it avoids errors, but I _really_ dunno you would do such mistake; probably, your algorithm or opcode usage has more chances to spot an error than a $200X "whoops". Zepper, 1 March 2010

As for number of characters to remember: "PPU" is a concept, and "status" is a concept, and humans are better at remembering concepts. It's easier to remember a name like "Jennifer" than a phone number like "903-5768". Otherwise, why do we even use assemblers at all? "LDA #" has more characters than "A9".

Different people have historically used different names. What MOS Technology, its second sources, and ARM call "EOR" everyone else calls "XOR". Likewise, Sony's highly-6502-inspired SPC700 CPU uses different mnemonics even for instructions that by rights should be the same. "MOV A,X" could have been "TAX" for familiarity to people who have programmed the NES and the other half of the Super NES.

Bare addresses have different purposes based on what bus they're on. Is $2000 the first PPU control register, or is it the start of the first nametable?

Register address mirroring is probably more useful to emulator developers and people trying to obfuscate or digitally fingerprint code than to developers of original NES software.

Yes, the constants should be predefined in a header file, and the header file should be on this wiki. I fully intend to make such a header file at least for ca65 once we standardize the names and other parts of the style guide.

--Tepples 17:07, 1 March 2010 (UTC)

You are right that concepts are easier to remember than numbers. However you say that if I don't use the labels you made up to assign registers, I might as well not use an assembler, which is absolutely not what I meant. I am not against labels as a whole - I am just against the fact that some labels one guy made up were used on this wiki instead of the real addresses of the register without any reference to the real address next to it, and that the name of the labels themselves didn't make much sense to me.

I completely disagree that this should avoid errors. Since I started coding for the 6502 I've had to deal with MANY typo errors, but they were always for other reasons (misspelling of labels, bad use of anonymous labels and confusion betwen X and Y should hold the top tree (X and Y are one next to the others here, unlike english keyboards)). So if you really want to use the labels on the wiki go ahead, but then also refer to the register name, or at lest link to it, so that people who don't make any sense from these names can have an idea what you are talking about.Bregalad 17:48, 1 March 2010 (UTC)

The comment about not using an assembler at all was a bit of hyperbole. I have a disability that sometimes makes it difficult for me to discern the line between what is acceptable and what is not. As a coping mechanism, I sometimes use hyperbole to establish lower and upper bounds for the discussion. But if the solution is to link to the article defining the labels from every other article that uses the labels, I have no problem with that. Redirects would help with that; it'd be as easy as, say, [[PPUSTATUS]]. --Tepples 18:44, 1 March 2010 (UTC)

- Quick question: perhaps other people want to debug or trace your code using a disassembler. Does it display $2002 or PPUSTATUS? ;) So, it's something fully optional, including empirical labels for such registers. Well, regarding $2000, it was silly. We have CPU and PPU addressing the things! How would you differ the labels? --Zepper 21:25, 1 March 2010 (UTC)

Quick answer: The disassembler displays whatever label set you have loaded in. It starts with just the 30 registers of the NES, but as I learn more about how a game works, the label set fills up with memory locations and subroutine entry points. If I really wanted to thwart disassembler users, I could have the assembler generate 10 random bits and make them different for every access to the PPU registers. This brings up another idea: if we make a header file for ca65, we could also make a label file for FCEUX. --Tepples 21:41, 1 March 2010 (UTC)

Actually, I don't know any disassembler with such feature. Plus, there are lots of good h4ck3r5 that uses only an hexa editor. ^_^;; But perhaps it's another story. --Zepper 21:56, 1 March 2010 (UTC)

Here's an example of what I'm using in all my nes project: CA65 constants. Yes, the name are verbose because I'm trying to find a naming convention that make sense. I'm still in a trial and error process. I always had that file open when I need to use them but I found out that with Notepad++ you can create a list of word that can work like intelissense in Visual studio. This mean I won't need to remember them anymore once I create that file for my editor.

Banshaku 23:34, 1 March 2010 (UTC)

The debugger in FCEUXD (and subsequent derivatives like FCEUXD SP and FCEUX) has such feature: NL files. --Tepples 17:16, 2 March 2010 (UTC)

Say someone discovers a new CPU architecture, but no official document about its instruction set was disclosed to the public. Examples include the microcontroller in the NES and SNES CIC and the CPU in the Pokemon mini video game system. What mnemonics should appear in documents about the CPU designed for an emulator author or in a debugging emulator's disassembler? --Tepples 21:21, 4 March 2010 (UTC)

Given all I said above, I have to say that the current names (PPUXX) are not that readable (to me at least), due to the repeated prefix.

PPUCTRL
PPUADDR
PPUDATA

Those just meld into a mess to my eyes. These are for some reason much more readable to me:

PPU_CTRL
PPU_ADDR
PPU_DATA

It may be that I'm partial to underscores, using them heavily in naming in all the languages I use. But I think visually it makes the beginning of the second part visually distinct so the eye can quickly make out the shapes of the beginning. Lowercase might of course be better as well, but I think that lowercase isn't the best idea to use for registers, as the uppercase makes it clear in code that it's not just some variable.

Remembering "PPUSTATUS" you have to remember 9 letters instead of 4 numbers in $2002 which is more complicated (you really have to remember 1 number, because the first 3 are always $200x).

Memorizing PPUSTATUS is just memorizing PPU + STATUS, for a register that gives the current status of the PPU. Remembering $2002 is remembering the base address of the PPU ($2000, an arbitrary value) and an arbitrary offset (+2). And when you recall $2002, you can't be sure you remembered it correctly without consulting something.

I just think most of those name didn't make sense to me and are too long to be remembered, but I don't really care if you all like them go away and use them (and undo my modifications), I'll just not use them in my code and anyone is free to use them. It's just that I figured those names caused me trouble as I always had to had the registers page open in another tab to convert from those names to actual registers.
[...]
So if you really want to use the labels on the wiki go ahead, but then also refer to the register name, or at lest link to it, so that people who don't make any sense from these names can have an idea what you are talking about.

So you're saying you have trouble remembering the names of registers, but not their addresses? This is an odd argument, because the whole point I'm making is that new NES programmers have to remember arbitrary addresses, which is more difficult. It seems your whole argument comes down to "I've memorized the addresses, but not the names, and I don't want to memorize the names, therefore names are bad."

I won't avoid admitting that the biggest problem with names is agreeing on them and then using them consistently. You don't have that problem with addresses, save for choosing the base (hex, decimal, or perhaps binary heh).

I completely disagree that this should avoid errors. Since I started coding for the 6502 I've had to deal with MANY typo errors, but they were always for other reasons (misspelling of labels, bad use of anonymous labels and confusion betwen X and Y should hold the top tree (X and Y are one next to the others here, unlike english keyboards))

How do you know you haven't ever made a typo for a register address? The whole point is that there is no way to reliably diagnose them.

The comment about not using an assembler at all was a bit of hyperbole.

Actually, I meant it somewhat seriously. There are probably some old-time programmers who prefer to write machine code instead of assembler, because they find the mnemonics confusing and obfuscating of the actual opcodes.

The main point was that the argument against symbolic names applies to mnemonics as well. In both cases, you don't see the actual value generated, just the name. The argument against symbolic names because they're confusing or hard to remember applies equally well to mnemonics. If the arguer is fine with mnemonics, it shows that he has not discovered his actual reasons for being against symbolic names. One likely explanation is that his argument is simply for things he's familiar with, and against things he's unfamiliar with. There's nothing wrong with that as a personal approach to things, but it's not suitable for community decisions.

And in case it's not clear, the idea of using symbolic names here is that the page describing the register shows its numeric address, and perhaps a register summary as well. Any other page mentioning the register just uses its name, which is also a link to the page describing the register (and thus giving its numeric address).

Blargg 17:07, 6 March 2010 (UTC)

As for the underscores, I always been using then in my CA65 constants since when you uses all caps, you cannot distinguish were the words end. If I define variables, you can always do zpJoy1Status and you can read it quite easily.

Banshaku 02:36, 7 March 2010 (UTC)

Well Blarg you're probably right, I remembered the address instead of the names just because that's what I used first. If the very first "hello world" program example I've used would have used the symbolic names instead, maybe things would be different. In all cases, I think it's good practice if any reference to a register is wiki-linked to the description to the said register - but I find it the most consusing where there is a symbolic name, no address and no wiki-link. Also I have to say it looks much better with underscores to me. Bregalad 19:12, 10 March 2010 (UTC)

I too remember the NES addresses better than the symbolic names, because I also started without names. Symbolic names should be used throughout the Wiki, but it should still make it easy for those who learned without the names to understand. I agree that mentions of registers should have links to the pages describing them, and any other minor things to help.

Blargg 19:34, 11 March 2010 (UTC)

I see we're coming to a consensus. I will see if I can find time and first change the name with underscores then revise the wiki so that all reference to them link back to the actual topic about it.

Is there any name that may still be hard to understand? For example, I didn't know why PPU_MASK was used. Maybe it's something in English that I'm not used to hear.

Banshaku 01:04, 12 March 2010 (UTC)

I understand the name because it masks out (hides) the left pixels, or non-red/non-green/non-blue/all colors, or entire layers. Since the functionality is enable, clip and color emphasis: I'm not certain what a better collective name is.

Lidnariq 14:28, 12 March 2010 (UTC)

Lidnariq was on the right track: see wikipedia:Mask (computing). When you mask off bits in the register, you mask off parts of the screen. When you turn on bit 0, it masks off bits 3-0 of each palette entry. And if bits 1-4 are the gobo, bits 5-7 are the gel. --Tepples 14:52, 12 March 2010 (UTC)

Well it still don't make sense to me. PPU is a integred ciruit in the NES, mask is something that is meant to be put on a head. "Video Control" or "Rendering Control", "Video Switches", or something like that would make more sense to me.Bregalad 11:07, 13 March 2010 (UTC)

You have the same reaction as me because maybe we share something in common: we're French natives. Maybe mask is used in English in other ways that we are not used to hear in daily conversation.

Banshaku 12:54, 13 March 2010 (UTC)

What we could do is use the name of each register's closest counterpart on a Nintendo platform for which the homebrew community has adopted "official" names. For example, on the Game Boy Advance:

$2000 is BG0CNT
$2001 is DISPCNT
$2002 is DISPSTAT
$2005 is BG0HOFS and BG0VOFS

But then it falls apart for $2003, $2004, $2006, and $2007. Unlike on the NES and Super NES but like on the Game Boy, the GBA's VRAM, OAM, and CGRAM are memory-mapped. --Tepples 16:19, 13 March 2010 (UTC)

This naming convention makes almost no sense just by looking at it. The PPU_SOMETHING makes more sense already. It doesn't mean that it's official that the naming is better.

Banshaku 02:57, 14 March 2010 (UTC)

I don't really have a problem with naming the registers, especially since I haven't seen any official sources come up with their own names for them. Also, Bregalad, it makes more sense to name $2001 PPUMASK (or some variation on that) if you think of masking in a broader sense. Like, one might mask their face by concealing it with a mask, but one might try to mask the foul odors in a room by putting in air fresheners, or mask their presence by camoflage. In this way, it becomes easier to consider that a programmer may mask or reveal sprites and the background by using the register at $2001.

And nobody is forcing anybody to use the names Tepples has provided, or any names at all.

--Doppel 20:25, 22 September 2011 (UTC)

Should mention that the overflow flag is cleared at the start of the pre-render line here. (Posting to get account activated.) -Ulfalizer (talk) 18:45, 15 March 2013 (MDT)

Palette

$3F00-$3FFF has no palette data. Well, I would understand "palette" as RGB entries, or similarly. What's stored in that space are color indexes, not palette data. --Zepper (talk) 18:21, 27 March 2013 (MDT)

Many other parts of the Wiki (e.g. PPU_palettes and the "palette" entry on Glossary) use "palette" when referring to the $3F00-$3FFF range though, and switching to "color index" might be confusing. To me, a palette is just a set of colors, regardless of representation. -Ulfalizer (talk) 00:33, 28 March 2013 (MDT)

I disagree. When you dump $3F00 region, there are no "colors" or palettes like in other systems, but a 256-bit number, or 32 palette indices. At anyway, that's me. :) --Zepper (talk) 18:20, 28 March 2013 (MDT)

There is no reason "palette" should imply "RGB". And they do contain HSL entries.—Lidnariq (talk) 18:51, 28 March 2013 (MDT)

One thing is the hardware palette. Another thing is the colour look-up table, that's what the NES does. --Zepper (talk) 20:24, 28 March 2013 (MDT)

You'll notice that this article explicitly refers to the CLUT as a palette. - Rainwarrior (talk) 22:24, 28 March 2013 (MDT)

I disagree. "Palette" means exactly a selection of colours. It does not mean "RGB data", not at all, unless that is the type of palette you are using. VGA has a 256-colour palette. EGA has a 16-colour palette. CGA has a 4-colour palette. NES has 8 4-colour palettes. This palette has 6 colours. The format of how a particular colour is specified is specific to the hardware, but ultimately the data is an index, yes, whether that index is RGB, RGBA, HSV, greyscale, or the NES' form. The larger selection of colours which the palette can be built from may also be called a palette (though for clarity's sake it's probably best not to call both the full gamut and the limited on-screen selection "palette" in the same sentence). What I am saying is that "palette" is the most precise, accurate, and common term to use for this. I think it is also a "color index", and a "color lookup table", but palette is the most useful thing to call it. - Rainwarrior (talk) 22:20, 28 March 2013 (MDT)

All about "palette" I mean RGB entries OR similarly. When a normal user dumps $3F00, he won't find colors (RGB or whatever format you wish), but just a lookup table, so that's what I meant and only that. Also, it IS a color lookup table, unless _Q says it isn't. AFAIK, there's no direct access to the hardware colors. --Zepper (talk) 14:21, 29 March 2013 (MDT)

It is a palette, of colors specified in voltage/phase format, not RGB. But it is a lookup table to select the color (in voltage/phase format) from the pattern table, nametable, and attribute table data, reading from the palette memory, and then output according to the voltage/phase (or using a further lookup table to a RGB palette stored in ROM, in the case of RGB Famicom). --Zzo38 (talk) 14:28, 29 March 2013 (MDT)
What do you consider "similar" to RGB? What is "whatever format you wish"? What are "hardware colors"? (Also what is a "normal user" who is dumping PPU contents but neglected to learn what they contain?) I don't understand what you think is special about the NES' colour data format that isn't equally special about every other possible way to encode colours. There is no "hardware" colour table hiding in the PPU that this is an index to, it is just a bit-packed number that gets translated directly into the video signal. There is no RGB data in an NES, you would only find it in an emulator that uses an RGB lookup table to translate for RGB hardware. - Rainwarrior (talk) 18:32, 5 April 2013 (MDT)

There's no RGB data in a frontloader or NES-101, but there is in 2C03-powered Famiclones manufactured by Sharp under license from Nintendo: C1 NES TV and Famicom Titler. In any case, there are two stages that could be described as "palette lookup": lookup in $3F00-$3F1F (under the program's control), and then lookup in either the NTSC signal generator or the RGB table (not under the program's control). --Tepples (talk) 18:52, 5 April 2013 (MDT)

I think the point of pedantry is that there is no "lookup" in the 2C02. The value stored in $3Fxx is the direct value written to the analog output stage, much as the values written to the 2600's COLUPx registers are, or the values written to the TG16's register at $FF:$0404 are the direct 9-bit values written to the video DACs. (Tangentially: are there a canonical set of register names for the TG16?) —Lidnariq (talk) 19:23, 5 April 2013 (MDT)

Actually, the real point I was trying to make is that "palette" is the standard term for what this is (and has been on every single platform I've ever developed for), and it's also completely consistent with its dictionary definition. Claiming that it's different because it's not RGB, and should be called a "lookup table" instead will only serve to obfuscate its definition. I think Zepper is confused about what palette actually means, and is arguing to change the terminology in the article to fit his confusion. As for the VS/Sharp PPU variants, yes they may actually have a hardware RGB lookup table. I don't think it's useful to call the NTSC signal generator a "lookup", but if you want to make an academic argument that it does the same thing, sure. - Rainwarrior (talk) 19:39, 5 April 2013 (MDT)

[Edit conflict] It is a lookup. To continue the pedantry: In the 2C02, there's still a layer of digital "decoding" after $3Fxx lookup and before the output stage. A hue of 8 might be decoded to 00111111, 11110000, or 00000011 depending on the phase, a hue of 0 to 11111111, and a hue of D to 00000000. How do I give a citation in Visual 2C02? --Tepples (talk) 20:16, 5 April 2013 (MDT)

@Rainwarrior: too bad you have fired me with a bunch of "why this?", "why that"... a sign of lack of respect, unfortunately. I really refuse to clarify anything. --Zepper (talk) 11:22, 6 April 2013 (MDT)

Then please clarify it to me. Definition disputes derail discussions. --Tepples (talk) 13:25, 6 April 2013 (MDT)

This discussion is about a definition. Ironically the stuff about what the hardware does internally was the more derailed part. My argument is that this data stored in the PPU is a palette, as this data directly specifies a "selection of colours" for the NES to use, and similar things have been called a palette on all sorts of other platforms. Zepper's argument is that it is not a palette, and all of my questions are asking what reason he thinks it should not be called so. - Rainwarrior (talk) 19:00, 6 April 2013 (MDT)

I asked a question about each thing I do not understand. If I did not respect you I would not ask. As I've stated, it is my strong opinion that "palette" is the correct word to use, and I think trying to avoid this term in favour of "lookup table" will make it harder to understand for others. Please do not confuse my opinion of how these terms should be used with my opinion of you. As I said earlier, palettes are more generally indices and lookup tables, and it is fine to mention that it is also these things, but this data is still a palette, and that word is the most useful one we can be using for it. - Rainwarrior (talk) 18:41, 6 April 2013 (MDT)

Emphasis bits

It says the emphasis bits are unused if the selected color is $xE and $xF. Is this true with RGB as well or only with composite? --Zzo38 (talk) 16:40, 23 June 2013 (MDT)

I PM'd Memblers to ask; he said that that behavior is only true for the 2C02/2C07; the 2C03,4,5 emphasis bits do not exclude those colors. —Lidnariq (talk) 16:08, 2 June 2016 (MDT)

Allcaps vblank?

Just curious as to why vblank has been changed to VBLANK across the page? I understand allcaps register names as a convention for a defined constant, but I have no idea what this is supposed to signify for vblank. - Rainwarrior (talk) 11:20, 17 March 2015 (MDT)

Just a guess, but it might be a progression from VBI (initialism for Vertical Blanking Interval) through VBL to vblank. --Tepples (talk) 15:57, 17 March 2015 (MDT)

FWIW, it was this edit. —Lidnariq (talk) 12:22, 18 March 2015 (MDT)

Immediately?

The PPUCTRL section contains this sentence:

To avoid this problem it is prudent to read $2002 immediately before writing $2000 to clear the vblank flag.

Which implies that all writes to PPUCTRL must look like this:

bit PPUSTATUS
sta PPUCTRL

But is that really necessary? It seems like reading PPUSTATUS at any part in the NMI handler would be sufficient, so long as it happens before writing PPUCTRL. That's not "immediate" at all.

The code below would work, no?

nmi_handler:
  bit PPUSTATUS ; read at the start of NMI

  ; ... do some nmi stuff ...

  lda #PPUCTRL_NMI_ON
  sta PPUCTRL ; write to PPUCTRL several hundred cycles after reading PPUSTATUS

Pubby (talk) 14:15, 2 June 2016 (MDT)

My reading on that section is that it's describing how to safely write to PPUCTRL outside of the NMI handler. —Lidnariq (talk) 15:58, 2 June 2016 (MDT)

Talk:PPU scrolling

Proposed Merge

I think it's high time we merged The skinny on NES scrolling into this document. This redundancy has been a problem for a long time.

Keep the lead and "The common case" from this article, discard the rest.
Keep everything from Skinny except the preface, and include it directly after "The common case".

I'm suggesting doing it this way because while I don't see anything incorrect in this article, the explanations in Skinny are universally more detailed, and there's nothing covered here that isn't explained more clearly there. I find the formatting in this article hard to read and the prose is difficult to parse (much like the original loopy document), so I don't think we're really losing anything by just going with the Skinny article version. Of course we shall continue to revise after the merge too, I'm not saying the Skinny version is perfect either.

Does anyone oppose this? Any additional thoughts on how this merge should be done? Since it's a topic a lot of people care about I just wanted to open a discussion before making a change like this.

- Rainwarrior (talk) 14:57, 24 March 2015 (MDT)

You have my thumbs up, but I don't have any particular ideas. Well, other than that the animated gif here seems like a good illustration. —Lidnariq (talk) 16:14, 24 March 2015 (MDT)

Thirded. I blew away everything after #The common case and replaced it with a link to Skinny. The GIF was part of #The common case, so I left it in. --Tepples (talk) 17:23, 24 March 2015 (MDT)

Yes of course keep the GIF! Keep that whole section. - Rainwarrior (talk)

I guess I'll just do it. Everyone seems in favour, and tepples already wiped the rest of PPU scrolling anyway. - Rainwarrior (talk) 20:40, 24 March 2015 (MDT)

I'm not so sure I like how the merged version feels. Beginners might feel tempted to read on before they're ready to understand the rest. I'd prefer reverting the merge, leaving just "The common case" here, so that we have a place to direct beginners who want a short and sweet summary of best practices for a game that does not use a split screen. True, "The skinny on NES scrolling" isn't quite the best title for the advanced parts, but that's resolvable with a rename to "Advanced scrolling". --Tepples (talk) 21:30, 24 March 2015 (MDT)

I've actually felt that a lot of people were daunted by the "advanced" stuff being kept tucked away separately, in a document with a weird name, especially with all the weird mystique associated with loopy's old hard-to-understand document. I honestly think that presenting it plainly here without the attached reputation, or undue separation, might make it more approachable in general. The old paths to this information were riddled with thorns, and I think it can be taught a lot more easily. It seems that every week or so a new emulator author comes to understand it just fine, perhaps new homebrew developers would have an easier time if we didn't make such a big initiation ritual out of it? ... Anyhow, with the current layout, the GIF makes a great visual division between the "easy" and "hard" stuff. I think as long as we keep it well organized, it'll be better than before. - Rainwarrior (talk) 22:17, 24 March 2015 (MDT)

Talk:Program compatibility

Passive-aggressive

How is this any more passive-aggressive than Game bugs? --Tepples (talk) 18:16, 28 July 2015 (MDT)

It's passive-aggressive because you have a direct way of dealing with the problem that raydempsey had a bug in his in-development game. I think it's quite rude to put it on a list like this given the situation. He's still working on it! Your edit said "namin' and shamin'", I presume as a joke, but I think it's an accurate description of what it was effectively doing. This is completely different than enumerating bugs in long-dead software by people who are not members of this community.

Yes, you did let him know directly on the board. That part was good. In light of this your actions weren't passive-aggressive as a whole. I was really just referring to the act of putting up a public notice about someone's bug, which by itself is a rather rude and passive-aggressive way of telling them to fix their software.

The other entries on the list are probably fine/useful. - Rainwarrior (talk) 21:21, 28 July 2015 (MDT)

Compatible and Incompatible

I'm not sure I understand the utility of the three categories. I think the approach taken by Game bugs is better. We should just be listing bugs in homebrew games, possibly with categorization by the nature of the bug.

The compatible category seems pointlessly incomplete. There is a great deal of homebrews software that should be considered "compatible". I would also suggests that all software has bugs; we just haven't found bugs in these ones yet. ;P I get that the word "compatible" is supposed to refer to emulators vs. hardware, but that's a moving target. Every emulator is different.

What does "incompatible programs" mean? Crash on boot? I'm sure each of these games has a different reason for failing to run. It's mildly useful to have a list of software that shouldn't be expected to run on a good emulator, but this form is rather poor information.

On a related note, does anyone else get occasional black squares in the world background when running the Super Bat Puncher demo on their PowerPak? I've always thought it had a bug, but I never tracked down what it was. - Rainwarrior (talk) 21:33, 28 July 2015 (MDT)

I investigated the four listed games, and have revised the structure of the page like I suggested. I think we should just put any homebrew bugs here, not just emulator compatibility issues, though obviously the compatibility is a big problem for homebrew in a way that it (mostly) wasn't for commercial-era games, so I've tried to make that prominently explained at the top. - Rainwarrior (talk) 22:33, 28 July 2015 (MDT)

Talk:Programming UNROM

NES 2.0 advocacy

Converting a ROM from original iNES to NES 2.0 isn't strictly necessary unless the mapper is ≥ 256 or the iNES header is ambiguous. For example:

Several VRC mappers are ambiguous as to which low CPU address lines are connected to the mapper's port select.
Mapper 1 is ambiguous between SIROM (PRG A14 from MMC1 output) and other SxROM boards using 32K PRG (PRG A14 from CPU A14).
Mappers 1, 4, and 5 are ambiguous among PRG RAM sizes. For example, SNROM vs. SOROM, MMC3 vs. MMC6.
A few games (notably Low G Man) require the PRG RAM to be absent.

What's ambiguous about mappers 2 (UxROM), 3 (CNROM), and 7 (AOROM), other than whether or not the ROM has a positive chip enable to avoid bus conflicts? --Tepples (talk) 22:19, 26 February 2013 (MST)

Two things-

the comment about PRG-RAM: due to iNES's shortcomings one can't distinguish between 0="no ram" and 0="unspecified ram"; and
the entire point behind NES2.0's backwards compatibility is the encouragement of its adoption without infringing on non-NES2.0-aware emulators. Creating mindshare makes it possible to say that it really is a solution.

—Lidnariq (talk) 01:50, 27 February 2013 (MST)

True, perhaps NES 2.0 might be warranted to keep programs from relying on an implied PRG RAM circuit that iNES emulators emulate but which is not present on official mapper 2 boards. I'll see how I can work it in. --Tepples (talk) 11:45, 27 February 2013 (MST)

Leaving the .byte $00  ;UNROM has no PRG RAM comment is explicitly misleading in light of the above.
In any case, because of NES2.0's backwards compatibility, I don't see an argument for why we should recommend plain iNES headers. —Lidnariq (talk) 14:51, 27 February 2013 (MST)

If old iNES headers are used, the emulator ought to assume 8K PRG RAM for any mapper that doesn't already have PRG RAM and doesn't use $6000-$7FFF for anything else; this way it is compatible if something does add RAM there. If the header version bits specifies NES 2.0 then it ought to assume no RAM if the NES 2.0 header specifies that there is no RAM. (For example, I might want to make some UNROM game that includes PRG RAM and lacks CHR RAM; even the old iNES header probably supports this, isn't it? Some emulator might not support it so how do you deal with such things like this?) --Zzo38 (talk) 00:30, 24 June 2013 (MDT)

Do you mean UNROM with 8 KiB CHR ROM, sort of like what Morita Shogi does on the SNROM board? Technically that should be supported but I don't see the point. For one thing, it's two custom mask ROMs, one for PRG and one for CHR, instead of one and a cheap 6264. --Tepples (talk) 00:39, 24 June 2013 (MDT)

Talk:Programming with unofficial opcodes

Contents

1 Stability of ATX
2 NOPs that discard reads
3 Bus conflicts serious here?
4 ARR and AXS instructions
5 Lot check for unofficial opcodes?

Stability of ATX

The reference I'm using lists ATX as "unstable"; I made a point of leaving "unstable" instructions out of a reference for programmers. Furthermore, it states that its behavior might differ between machines. It cites two references agreeing with you but also cites Adam Vardy's document, which calls the instruction "OAL", claims that it includes ORA #$EE as one of the steps, and further claims that different machines use different values instead of $EE. It might actually be ORA <line noise> AND #i TAX, and predictable only if i = 0 (in which case it's no different from LAX #0). --Tepples 16:25, 8 February 2011 (UTC)

On IRC, kevtris reported that he has seen a constant $FF as the value in the ORA step, which would put ATX with the LAXs. The difference between $EE and $FF might arise from the lack of decimal mode in the 2A03's ALU. But I'd still recommend against using this instruction because different NES consoles may still interpret it differently. --Tepples 04:05, 11 April 2011 (UTC)

http://visual6502.org/wiki/index.php?title=6502_Opcode_8B_%28XAA,_ANE%29 strongly implies weirdness with the $10 and $01 bits on all unstable instructions are due to a different period of analog feedback inside the 6502. Lidnariq 18:59, 11 April 2011 (UTC)

NOPs that discard reads

This was a thread in the forum in the past, but maybe we might mention the side-effect reads (There, the monikers DLD (dummy load) and LDN (load no-op) were suggested, other random possibilities include "LoaD and Discard"). Could one use 'LDD $20FF,X' where X is some multiple of eight to discard two bytes from CHR-ROM, or would that tight of timing screw up the PPU's fetch FSM? —Lidnariq (talk) 15:41, 24 August 2013 (MDT)

LDD a ($0C aa aa; 4 cycles)
LDD a,X ($1C aa aa, $3C aa aa, $5C aa aa, $7C aa aa, $DC aa aa, $FC aa aa; 4 or 5 cycles)
LDD d ($04 dd, $44 dd, $64 dd; 3 cycles)
LDD d,X ($14 dd, $34 dd, $54 dd, $74 dd, $D4 dd, $F4 dd; 4 cycles)
Reads from memory at the specified address. Discards the result. Affects no register nor flags. Only useful for side effects (e.g. PPUADDR increment) so on the NES the zero-page versions are only useful for timing.
LDD d,X reads from both d and (d+X)&255. LDD a,X additionally reads from a+X-256 it crosses a page boundary (i.e. if ((a & 255) + X) > 255)
Sometimes called TOP (triple-byte no-op), SKW (skip word), DOP (double-byte no-op), or SKB (skip byte).

Figured I'd format it. —Lidnariq (talk) 20:35, 24 August 2013 (MDT)

I'd call it IGN (ignore). --Tepples (talk) 21:04, 24 August 2013 (MDT)

Bus conflicts serious here?

Some distinction should be made between "bad" bus conflicts, e.g. CMOS high versus anything else's low, and benign ones, like a pull-up resistor versus anything. Here it talks of bus conflicts in the unofficial opcodes, but from the sounds of it it's no different stress-wise than how a normal NMOS output works internally when outputting low, where its in "conflict" with the pull-up current source. I think people are (rightly) concerned about intentionally causing bus conflicts, and might be wary of using techniques that cause what they think are the same thing. Maybe calling them stressful bus conflicts and benign bus conflicts would make it clearer. Blargg (talk) 21:36, 6 January 2014 (MST)

Yes, I agree that it should be made clear about how potentially damaging it can be or not (but I don't know how it works with unofficial opcodes). If there are resistors then it isn't really a bus conflict but is a default logic. --Zzo38 (talk) 22:22, 6 January 2014 (MST)

I have been told that the internal bus conflicts in the CPU aren't dangerous.--Zzo38 (talk) 22:58, 27 January 2014 (MST)

ARR and AXS instructions

Are these descriptions for ARR and AXS instructions correct? VirtuaNES doesn't emulate them exactly this way nor does any other documentation I can find specify that they work quite this way either. One file says this: "ARR: part of this command are some ADC mechanisms. following effects appear after AND but before ROR: the V-Flag is set according to (A and #{imm})+#{imm}, bit 0 does NOT go into carry, but bit 7 is exchanged with the carry." and "AXS: performs CMP and DEX at the same time, so that the MINUS sets the flag like CMP, not SBC." --Zzo38 (talk) 22:58, 27 January 2014 (MST)

The (only) reliable reference is Visual6502 and tests done on a physical NMOS 6502. With that it mind, I tested:
$6B(ARR): As far as I can tell, Visual6502 seems to be omitting the AND effect. The rest of the document here agrees with what Visual6502 is doing.
$CB(AXS): The document here agrees with what Visual6502 is doing.
For both, the writeups you've found are of dubious applicability. The former (ARR) is another way of phrasing the same claims on this page. The latter (AXS) doesn't actually describe the behavior at all, only what lines in the PAL are fired. —Lidnariq (talk) 23:44, 27 January 2014 (MST)

Of course, that is correct, that the physical NMOS 6502 is the best way to know what it is doing. Why is Visual6502 omitting the AND effect of the $6B instruction (is it a bug in Visual6502)? And you are correct, but I didn't realize it at first. I may have made some mistakes myself in trying it, but it is also possible that some emulators are also defective, or probably both. --Zzo38 (talk) 00:09, 28 January 2014 (MST)

A lot of the AND behavior in unofficial instructions arises from bus conflicts, which in NMOS act as AND (lower voltage wins). Perhaps some simulators are less likely to handle bus-conflict ANDs correctly than AND gates made out of transistors. --Tepples (talk) 16:43, 28 January 2014 (MST)

Lot check for unofficial opcodes?

"Using the CPU's unofficial opcodes could get your game rejected from Nintendo lot check" What reason do we have to believe that this is true?

I'm trying to imagine how this test would have been performed. Did they build a custom 2A03 CPU that generates an external signal on these opcodes? (Seems impractical.) Did they run your ROM on an emulator? (I doubt emulators at the time were suitable for testing an interactive game like this.) Did they require full source code disclosure? (That would be a highly unorthodox requirement.) I'm straining to think of a plausible method Nintendo would have tested for this. - Rainwarrior (talk) 08:14, 21 August 2014 (MDT)

If you want to explain the dearth of unofficial opcodes in licensed NES games, I don't think you need any extra reason beyond them being largely unknown at the time, and officially discouraged. Even today lots of us avoid using them for the sake of emulator compatibility. The same concern existed then for future hardware revisions. - Rainwarrior (talk) 08:21, 21 August 2014 (MDT)

I have no official evidence, but I do remember having read in Nintendo Power that Nintendo originally intended the Super Famicom to be backward compatible with Family Computer software. I was guessing that back when Nintendo still thought the Super Famicom was going to be backward compatible, it could have tested games with a 65802 (a 65816 in a 6502 pin-compatible package) instead of a 6502. --Tepples (talk) 12:58, 21 August 2014 (MDT)

Talk:Pulse Channel frequency chart

Merge

Isn't this the same as APU period table? --Tepples (talk) 20:27, 14 October 2013 (MDT)

Sort of, just a little more user-friendly. It's a simple reference for people who want to know which two bytes to plug into $4006-7 (et al.) in order to obtain a desired musical pitch, without getting bogged down in tables, calculations, formulas, ASCII diagrams, etc. Every reference I've been able to find seems to consist heavily of the latter, when all I want are those two little bytes! --Dr. Floppy (talk) 22:30, 14 October 2013 (MDT)

In my experience, someone developing a music engine doesn't want a pitch but instead a set of pitches to use for all the notes that will be played over the course of the program. Does your music engine store pitches in musical phrases as two bytes (a literal period) or as one (a note number)? I understand that the latter is more common in real music engines. --Tepples (talk) 07:58, 15 October 2013 (MDT)

Yes, my engine (which officially became "real" over the weekend) uses a complete set of pitches from A-1 to B-7, invoked by single bytes. My lookup tables are arranged in a nonstandard fashion due to the aesthetic design choice I made early on: #$C4 indicates "play Note-C in the fourth octave", so the two relevant bytes need to be the C4th entries in their respective data tables. It was this nonlinear approach that had me wishing for a cut-and-dry reference like the one I eventually created and submitted. --Dr. Floppy (talk) 23:37, 17 October 2013 (MDT)

Approaches that I've used to transcribe music in a readable text file involve either constants and macros (e.g. N_A0 = 0, N_AS0 = N_BB0 = 1, N_B0 = 2, N_C1 = 3, N_C5 = 51) or a domain-specific language translated by a PC-side program into music sequence source code. How would you do sharps and flats in your format? Or transpositions of a musical phrase? Or transpositions in an arpeggio envelope? --Tepples (talk) 13:33, 18 October 2013 (MDT)

I, too, want to know how to do the black keys (are they 1,2,3,4,5?). However from what I can tell, Retrodriver is done in entirely hex coding and does not use any assembler or MML or whatever. --Zzo38 (talk) 12:23, 19 October 2013 (MDT)

I assigned the five accidentals ("black keys") according to my synaesthesia. High nybbles 4-, 5-, 6-, 7-, 8- correspond to C-sharp, E-flat, F-sharp, A-flat and B-flat (respectively). As always, the low-nybble determines the octave. Rhythm offsets utilize high nybbles 2- and 3-, allowing for 32 different note-durations for any given song. The $1x-block is used for selective repeats within a part, and the $0x-block is reserved for special control codes (d7-d3 of the fourth register and timbre/volume changes for the pulse channels, hard rests, soft rests and jumps). --Dr. Floppy (talk) 21:59, 19 October 2013 (MDT)

What purpose is this user-friendly for? This table isn't good for someone looking to code an NES music engine. It can't be copy-pasted into code, and typing all of them by hand would be rather tedious and error prone. The other page provides both a ready-made code block and also a program to generate them for you, both of which are directly useful for that purpose. Having a table like this is maybe useful if you want to look up a single pitch at a time for some reason, but who would want to do this? - Rainwarrior (talk) 08:27, 15 October 2013 (MDT)

It's useful for those who are using a non-linear format for their frequency storage in order to make actual music coding easier. To illustrate, the C-Major scale in Retrodriver™ format is C4-D4-E4-F4-94-A4-B4-C5. --Dr. Floppy (talk) 23:37, 17 October 2013 (MDT)

I'm not sure how that makes it useful though. Any driver will need to represent the entire scale. With the table on this page you will need to copy-paste 84 individual values to make your driver. It is much better to write a program to generate the table for you- it reduces the time needed and likelihood of human error. At any rate, I would highly recommend revising your table into a grid with the octaves in rows or columns, which would make it much quicker to look up individual values. After doing that, I would suggest we merge that table into APU period table. - Rainwarrior (talk) 16:47, 18 October 2013 (MDT)

Another one to potentially merge with as well: Celius NTSC table - Rainwarrior (talk) 08:25, 17 October 2013 (MDT)

Tuning

If you're going to have a chart like this you should declare the nature of the tuning used. Presumably this is equal temperament using A-440Hz but this should be explicitly stated, as it is an arbitrary choice. - Rainwarrior (talk) 08:23, 15 October 2013 (MDT)

Also, when generating your table, consider rounding to the nearest integer, rather than rounding only down. The resulting error vs. target pitch will be smaller. - Rainwarrior (talk) 00:06, 2 November 2013 (MDT)

Talk:RTS Trick

Indirect vs. RTS

Is there an advantage over using JMP ($0200), where $0200 has been loaded from the same kind of jump-table? that's what I wonder, but I'm not gonna count up the cpu cycles needed for either method right now. --Memblers 20:21, 25 Jun 2009 (PDT)

Not sure. Seems like a pick'em to me. Here are some things that come to mind:

RTS Trick doesn't require any RAM.
I personally think the RTS Trick is more readable. If I see a table of pointers in my (or somebody else's) code and they all have a "-1" after them, I immediately know their purpose and how they are used.
PHA, PHA, RTS requires less bytes than STA, STA, JMP (3 vs. 9).

--MetalSlime 00:08, 26 Jun 2009 (PDT)

JMP ($0200) isn't re-entrant. The RTS/RTI approach uses the stack therefore can be done by mainline and interrupt code freely. Blargg (talk) 02:12, 23 January 2014 (MST)

Self-modifying

If you use self modifying code and assure that the table has to start at a page border (and store pointers to the routines, without the -1) then you can use a smaller and faster code:

tb_opcode_launcher_smc:
	; bytes, cycles
	asl ; 1, 2
	sta smc+2 ; 3, 4
smc:
	jmp (tb_opcode_rts_table) ; 3, 5
	; total 7 bytes and 11 cycles

tb_opcode_launcher:
	; bytes, cycles
	asl ; 1, 2
	tax ; 1, 2
	lda tb_opcode_rts_table+1, x ; 3, 4
	pha ; 1, 3
	lda tb_opcode_rts_table, x ; 3, 4
	pha ; 1, 3
	rts ; 1, 6
	; total 11 bytes and 24 cycles

--212.8.208.194 (talk)

Assuming that by sta smc+2 you meant sta smc+1 because 6502 is little-endian. But if you're doing any sort of nontrivial work in the NMI or IRQ handler, you would need separate 7-byte self-modifying trampolines in RAM for the main, NMI, and possibly IRQ handlers. And with the NES's 2048 byte RAM, 21 bytes might be a lot, though it's still not as bad as it would be on the Atari 2600. --Tepples (talk) 11:18, 21 May 2013 (MDT)

If you have extra PRG RAM in the cartridge, you could use that, too. Also, self-modifying code seems to be especially suitable for disk-based programs (although in many ways other than just this!). --Zzo38 (talk) 16:45, 8 December 2013 (MST)

Fast RTS Trick

You can make a bit faster RTS trick also if all of the jump targets are in one 256-byte page. Alternatively, you can align each jump target to a separate page and then not even use a lookup table. In addition, even when using the full addresses, I prefer to store the high bytes in one table and the low bytes in another table, instead of doing it together. This results in a smaller and faster code. --Zzo38 (talk) 16:45, 8 December 2013 (MST)

Talk:Standard controller

Contents

1 Microphone
2 SNES-in-NES reads
3 Bit deletion detection?
4 Open bus
5 Famicom 2nd controller missing Select and Start
6 Bit deletion in other input devices
7 Distinguishing hardware variant
8 A controller MUST NOT toggle the button states on each strobe pulse; that'll break any game that rereads the controller.
9 74165 compatibility

Microphone

How to do microphone? --Zzo38 19:18, 16 September 2012 (MDT)

Nevermind I found it on the other page it says $4016 bit2 is microphone. --Zzo38 19:19, 16 September 2012 (MDT)

SNES-in-NES reads

It says "all subsequent reads will return D=1 on an authentic controller but may return D=0 on third party controllers", and what happen on Super Nintendo controllers? --Zzo38 17:50, 27 September 2012 (MDT)

After the first eight bits, the Super NES controller returns A, X, L, R, four zero bits, then all 1. --98.226.71.46 18:22, 27 September 2012 (MDT)

Bit deletion detection?

Official controllers have the correct 8 bits, then all 1s. Couldn't you detect the absence of a bit deletion by seeing if the 8th bit is 0 and the 9th bit is 1? This only works while right is not pressed, but ... —Lidnariq (talk) 12:12, 8 February 2013 (MST)

Reading 9 bits to skip rereading if Right is not held could work provided that you're sure that the user isn't using a Four Score, an official Super NES controller, or an unlicensed controller that has all 0s after its report. The Four Score and Super NES controller have longer reports (24-bit and 16-bit respectively), but these reports likewise end with a transition from 0 to 1. In any case, in games that don't use players 3 and 4, it'd be quicker just to re-read than to look for the Four Score signature. --Tepples (talk) 13:34, 8 February 2013 (MST)

Open bus

Lidnariq: Some more details on the difference between 'x' and '0' in the $4016/$4017 diagrams would be nice, and on what M/F read as on NES. -Ulfalizer (talk) 01:22, 19 March 2013 (MDT)

Done, but my presentation is lousy. I'm not certain if it's even possible to reunify the diagrams anymore.—Lidnariq (talk) 02:05, 19 March 2013 (MDT)

Much clearer now at least - thanks! -Ulfalizer (talk) 02:13, 19 March 2013 (MDT)

Famicom 2nd controller missing Select and Start

The article says

Button status for each controller is returned as an 8-bit report in the following order: A, B, Select, Start, Up, Down, Left, Right. The Select and Start buttons are completely missing on the second controller of the plain Famicom.

So reading $4017 bit 0 on a Famicom returns which one of the following?:

a 6-bit report: A, B, Up, Down, Left, Right
an 8-bit report: A, B, 0, 0, Up, Down, Left, Right
an 8-bit report: A, B, 1, 1, Up, Down, Left, Right
something else?

--Bavi H (talk) 17:23, 19 March 2013 (MDT)

The 2nd of those three. I've updated the article to state this explicitly.—Lidnariq (talk) 17:58, 19 March 2013 (MDT)

Bit deletion in other input devices

Does bit deletion still do in controllers that don't use the shift registers (such as the light gun and keyboard)? From the instructions, it seems to me it is safe to use DPCM if using the light gun or keyboard, but I am unable to test this, and the article should probably be made clear. --Zzo38 (talk) 12:35, 25 August 2013 (MDT)

The article does say that the CLK line is what causes bit deletions; devices that don't use it (such as the zapper, keyboard, data recorder, Oeka Kids tablet, &c) won't be affected. I'm uncertain how to edit this to make that more explicit. —Lidnariq (talk) 12:53, 25 August 2013 (MDT)

Distinguishing hardware variant

It says bit3 and bit4 of $4016 is "Open bus on traditional Famicom, all 0s on AV Famicom". Does this mean that a code like this might be able to distinguish the traditional Famicom from other hardware?

   LDX #$17
   LDA $3FFF,X
   AND #$18

I don't know exactly know how open bus works though, but maybe someone is able to test this. --Zzo38 (talk) 12:54, 7 January 2014 (MST)

Yes, that is what it means. Well, not exactly that, because the page wrapping of the LDA abs,X should cause a read from $3F16 before the useful read, which will pre-seed open bus to whatever the PPU's internal open bus is. So I think something like

   LDX #$FF
   STX $2002
   LDA $3F17,X
   AND #$18

should DTRT.—Lidnariq (talk) 14:33, 7 January 2014 (MST)

OK, thanks. I forgot about that. (I don't know what "DTRT" means, but I think I can mainly understand your message nevertheless.) --Zzo38 (talk) 18:07, 7 January 2014 (MST)

Google says "Do the right thing". --Tepples (talk) 16:36, 8 January 2014 (MST)

A controller MUST NOT toggle the button states on each strobe pulse; that'll break any game that rereads the controller.

Is this wiki targeted at controller manufacturers? Or is it for emulators that simulate turbo controllers? In all cases this sentence comes out weird in this context, especially with the strong emphasis on the all caps 'must not'.

I agree, and have revised it. "MUST NOT" seems to imply enforcement of policy, of which there is none here. NesDev users can do what they like, the Wiki's job is just to keep them aware of the problems. I added an explanation of exactly why it can cause a problem, which is probably a lot more helpful than telling people IT IS FORBIDDEN. It's probably a perfectly sensible approach if you're building a turbo controller circuit for specific games. - Rainwarrior (talk) 10:37, 26 May 2015 (MDT)

It's for controller manufacturers. I have seen hobbyist controller manufacturers in both NESdev BBS and #nesdev on EFnet. As used in documents that cite RFC 2119, these strong words are "used where it is actually required for interoperation", and a homemade controller that toggles buttons every strobe will not interoperate with games that misbehave when the controller toggles buttons every strobe. --Tepples (talk) 16:57, 26 May 2015 (MDT)

74165 compatibility

http://www.raphnet.net/electronique/arcade_control/arcade_control_en.php "74hc165 wont work because they dont appreciate the clock being high when the latch is low."

I'd have to look closely at datasheets and test actual hardware to be sure, but it seems that the HC/HCT versions don't work for NES. Anyone actually tested this with custom hardware? If it indeed works on the 74HC(T)165 variants, we can revert this edit and put a note on compatibility. alphamule (talk) 01:28, 15 August 2015 (MDT)

http://privatewww.essex.ac.uk/~nbb/snes-technical.html Seems the 74HC works fine? "I have used two 74HC165 Shift registers to make a joypad adaptation, although I had to buy a cheap joypad to get the connector. " alphamule (talk) 02:13, 15 August 2015 (MDT)

Talk:Sunsoft 5B audio

Disch's Notes

Why was all of this added here? The noise generator is possibly useful (though I will need to verify it), but everything else is entirely redundant, and with a lot of speculative/weasel wording for things are now properly understood. The frequency calculation is also incorrect, and so are some statements that presume it to be an AY and not a YM. - Rainwarrior (talk) 01:00, 6 May 2013 (MDT)

I've removed all of the redundant or incorrect information, and moved the remaining new information into the article. - Rainwarrior (talk) 01:10, 6 May 2013 (MDT)

I moved it so that there was only one page we had to remove wrong information from. —Lidnariq (talk) 12:46, 6 May 2013 (MDT)

LFSR noise

By the way, someone made a program that will calculate the taps of a LFSR, given a recording: http://listengine.tuxfamily.org/lists.tuxfamily.org/hatari-devel/2012/09/msg00003.html —Lidnariq (talk) 15:29, 7 May 2013 (MDT)

Hmm, that program doesn't look -quit- that simple. I'd first have to decode the recording to a binary stream, but it looks like it could do the work from there. Most of the emulations I've checked are using the 17/14 tap configuration mentioned in that thread. Thanks for the link, though, I'll try to make use of it when I get around to testing my 5B. - Rainwarrior (talk) 14:09, 8 May 2013 (MDT)

YMZ284 vs YM2149

The datasheet for the YMZ284 claims that the top four bits of the data written to register $F must be 0 or else ... something. It'd be idly interesting find out what that something is, and if the 5B does that same something. —Lidnariq (talk) 16:54, 14 November 2014 (MST)

Is the "or else" a consequence that involves the I/O port? If so, how would you verify it with the 5B? If there's a test you'd like me to run on the 5B let me know, but I have no idea what I'd be looking for with this suggestion. - Rainwarrior (talk) 17:33, 17 November 2014 (MST)

The YMZ284 doesn't have any I/O ports, so I have no idea what the top four bits are. Just that the datasheet says "those bits must be 0" and that it "controls power", so it's clearly hooked up to something. So I guess the obvious test is writing non-zero to those bits and see if it obviously changes the sound? If it does, then it seems likely that we know the exact heritage used in the 5B. —Lidnariq (talk) 18:18, 17 November 2014 (MST)

Well, perhaps an emulator could be made to display a warning if it finds these bits to be nonzero. (It won't answer that question, but it would allow to test that a program isn't doing anything it isn't allowed to do.) --Zzo38 (talk) 14:50, 21 November 2014 (MST)

Talk:Sunsoft FME-7

2048KB of PRG ROM and 512KB of PRG RAM? The FME-7 only has 44 pins (2 of which are unconnected on NES-BTR), and the existing pins only permit up to 512KB of PRG ROM. Just because the data bus is 8 bits wide does not mean that the registers themselves are that wide, and there's also no guarantee that such amounts of PRG RAM are also supported - for example, the MMC3 PRG bank registers are only 6 bits wide, leaving the chip physically incapable of addressing more than 512KB of data, and while the MMC5 can address 1024KB of PRG ROM, it cannot support more than 64KB of PRG RAM. I'm only pointing this out because I don't appreciate my emulator being listed with a bunch of potentially erroneous compatibility errors. --Quietust 17:26, 17 April 2011 (UTC)

I meant no offense Quietust. I suppose I need to make clear that the extended ROM and RAM amounts are only for the NESDEV1 version of FME-7. I will change the page to reflect this. Nintendulator is 100% compatible with the real FME-7. --qbradq 19:45, 17 April 2011 (UTC)

Contents

1 PRG RAM on the original mapper
2 Sunsoft vs. FDS
3 NESDEV1
4 Disch Notes

PRG RAM on the original mapper

When PRG RAM is swapped into $6000, what does the original hardware put on the PRG bank lines? --Tepples 23:24, 20 April 2011 (UTC)

Sunsoft vs. FDS

This may sound funny, but it looks like FDS IRQs may be possible (with modifications) with the Sunsoft Mapper...

And Also the thing with ROM at $6000... It seems possible that this was meant for porting FDS using traditional ROM in place of PRG-RAM.

Can anyone help me test these to verify? --Hamtaro126 08:20, 18 August 2012 (MDT)

FME-7 might be a sensible choice for porting FDS. I doubt that it was designed with this in mind, though. There is ROM at $6000 because it gives you more addressable space. There is a timer IRQ because timers are useful. I don't think you need any more justification than that. There weren't any FDS games ported to FME-7. - Rainwarrior 16:51, 18 August 2012 (MDT)

NESDEV1

Qbradq disappeared from the forums close to a year ago. I'm tempted to remove most of the details about the nesdev1. --Lidnariq 19:46, 18 August 2012 (MDT)

Personally I don't see why there should be any info on the wiki about a proposed cartridge that's never had a public release/production. It benefits nobody and is only a source of confusion. - Rainwarrior 00:54, 19 August 2012 (MDT)

Disch Notes

Any new correct information from the Disch Notes should be merged into the article, and the disch notes should be deleted. There's not much there that I can see, but here are two tidbits that I don't know are accurate, that should either be added to the article, or discarded:

Note about open bus behaviour w.r.t. command $8
Are PRG select registers 8 bit? (commands $9-B)

Other than this, I think the IRQ section could use a little more explanation, but otherwise I don't see anything of additional value in the disch notes. - Rainwarrior (talk) 19:41, 1 March 2015 (MST)

PRG banks are 5 bits on 5a and 5b, and 6 bits on FME-7. But no games have more than 256 KiB PRG anyway. The open bus behavior is buried in our description of Reg:8 but probably should be made a little more explicit. —Lidnariq (talk) 20:10, 1 March 2015 (MST)

Okay, I think I've amended anything that was left, and trimmed the redundant disch notes. - Rainwarrior (talk) 08:47, 2 March 2015 (MST)

Talk:The frame and NMIs

quote "You can't keep the music updated during slowdown, or during bulk drawing transitions, because NMIs will be disabled"

Sure you can (while keeping NMIs enabled, I mean). I'm not sure if I should edit it in, I don't want to turning a newbie-friendly article into a technical dorkfest, but I was thinking of this: first instruction in the NMI would be 'inc nmi_nest_level', and last NMI instruction (before RTI) would be 'dec nmi_nest_level' the NMI routine would check the nest_level variable, if it is higher than 1, then you could could the play music, then exit. To avoid corrupting temporary variables in the music play routine, you would need to guarantee that the music routine can never be interrupted. Memblers (talk) 23:17, 6 October 2014 (MDT)

Pokémon Red and Blue for Game Boy Color appear to do exactly this. You can hear the music lag and then catch up. If that effect is desirable, you could edit it into the article. (Klax for NES and Tetris for Game Boy lag and don't catch up.) --Tepples (talk) 08:03, 8 October 2014 (MDT)

I think I mis-explained, I mean the point is the music wouldn't need to lag at all - during a frame overflow, the 'nested' NMI would do nothing but play the music. Similarly, during a bulk VRAM transfer, NMI can be left enabled as long the NMI routine is following a path/mode that doesn't touch the PPU registers. But yeah I'm still not too eager to add it to the article, I think it's better to encourage people to use the mainloop and NMI together, though I suppose the bulk VRAM transfer would still apply to that case. Memblers (talk) 21:23, 26 October 2014 (MDT)

Talk:The skinny on NES scrolling

Contents

1 Changes 1/08/2013
2 Temporary X?
3 hblank
4 Short writes
5 Actual timing for V/T updates during rendering
6 Split X/Y scroll simplification

Changes 1/08/2013

I made the following changes:

I removed the first example, since it appeared to be broken w.r.t. fine Y scroll.

I added a note about $2007 having side effects on v, please elaborate or correct it if anything is wrong. I note that nintendulator does a weird Y-1 thing if rendering is enabled when it is used? I'm not sure what is going on there.

Bit 14 of t was inconsistently sometimes referred to as bit 15.

Added a note about Y increment of v, which appears to occur on pixel 250 in nintendulator? I find this confusing, so I would appreciate if someone with authoritative knowledge could correctly explain the timing for the Y increment of v. Complete wrapping logic would also be helpful.

The imaginary bit 15 was removed from the examples at the top of the page, for clarity and consistency.

Added examples for simple scrolling, where only X, or no split is needed.

Revised the $2006, $2005, $2005, $2006 example to be a more practical example, explaining how to set the scroll for a specific X/Y/nametable.

Explanation of why the registers work this way, trying to make it easier to remember.

Please check for errors, and make corrections as necessary. We could also use some information on tile/attribute fetching, timings and which/whether can be changed mid-scanline.

- Rainwarrior 03:31, 8 January 2013 (MST)

Temporary X?

Does x also have a corresponding temporary/reload register that gets copied into x at the beginning of each line?

Correct me if I'm wrong, but can't I write $2005 anywhere in the scanline, and x should be reloaded to the expected value at the start of the next line. If there was no reload value for it, and x is immediately set by $2005, it would be absolutely critical where in the scanline I happen to set it, and I don't remember this ever being the case when trying it on an NES.

- Rainwarrior 05:01, 8 January 2013 (MST)

I guess this one doesn't matter. If it is reloaded we can just refer to the reload value as x. - Rainwarrior 06:42, 8 January 2013 (MST)

hblank

Making scroll writes during hblank... Some threads have suggested this, but is it possible, and how? When I've tried to do scrolling in the past, I could never seem to get timings that accurate, so it was always necessary to pull it back from the right edge and accept some amount of glitching on the end of the line. Glitches like this seem to be very normal for games with split scrolling... can it actually be avoided? Is it bad advice to suggest timing it during hblank?

- Rainwarrior 05:33, 8 January 2013 (MST)

Okay, enough information has been gathered on the forum to answer this. The article is updated. - Rainwarrior 18:03, 8 January 2013 (MST)

Short writes

Is it worth describing short sequences for quicker (and sometimes easier to calculate) but incomplete scrolling (i.e. 2005/2006, 2006/2006)? —Lidnariq 19:57, 8 January 2013 (MST)

I don't see why not. Maybe put them in an "advanced examples" section? - Rainwarrior 23:22, 8 January 2013 (MST)

Actual timing for V/T updates during rendering

Some of this was mentioned in the Visual 2C02 forum thread, but I've just double-checked it in the simulator:

Pre-render scanline, all dots 280 thru 304 - copy non-horizontal bits (yyyN.YYYYY.....) from T to V
Every scanline, dots 328/336/8/16/24/32/.../240/248/256 - increment horizontal bits in V
Every scanline, dot 256 - increment vertical bits in V
Every scanline, dot 257 - copy horizontal bits from T to V

Note that these are using the "revised" cycle timings mentioned here. --Quietust 20:49, 10 January 2013 (MST)

Wow that's some great information, thanks! I will integrate it into the article when I have some time, if somebody else doesn't get to it first. - Rainwarrior 02:49, 11 January 2013 (MST)

Split X/Y scroll simplification

The example given in the article for mid-frame X/Y scroll updates uses the write sequence $2006 + $2005 + $2005 + $2006, where both of the $2006 write values need to be calculated ahead of time. Since only the last write is necessary to make the Y-scroll update take place, you can replace the first $2006 write with a $2005 write (if the base nametable isn't going to change, otherwise you'd need an additional write to $2000) which can be a bit simpler to actually code since you'd only need 3 distinct values, allowing you to safely fit the entire sequence within HBLANK (STX $2005; STY $2005; STX $2005; STA $2006). --Quietust (talk) 14:18, 8 August 2013 (MDT)

On the one hand, now all four writes can fit in hblank. On the other hand, now all four writes have to be in hblank to avoid visible glitches. —Lidnariq (talk) 16:05, 8 August 2013 (MDT)

Correct. There's a window of about 20 CPU cycles when v can be modified, namely during sprite fetch. A sequence of n consecutive writes takes 4n - 3 cycles from the start of the first write to the end of the last: 4n because STA $200x takes four cycles, and - 3 because the first opcode fetch doesn't count toward the timing. The $2006-$2005-$2005-$2006 sequence requires only the last two writes cycle of to be in this window, resulting in a write sequence that occupies 5 of 20 cycles. The simplification requires the whole thing because of the immediate effect of fine X changes, resulting in 13/20, and 7-cycle jitter is at the very limit of what can be achieved with sprite 0 or NMI alone. --Tepples (talk) 12:28, 9 August 2013 (MDT)

Talk:Tile compression

Citing external sources for format details

On 2016-05-02, Bisqwit made this edit to "Spell out the format. Depending on external links for textual content is bad wiki practice." But I seem to remember about a year earlier, when I was making these edits about LZSS as used in GBA/DS BIOS, that someone was confused about the scope of this page, whether I was making a complete format reference or not, especially for formats not used on NES. This "someone" may have been on forums.nesdev.com or in #nesdev on EFnet; I don't remember exactly. --Tepples (talk) 07:24, 4 May 2016 (MDT)

I think it was me, and I believe my confusion was that comprehending the stuff on the wiki page depended on information behind the link (which already fully described it), which I felt made the wiki material either useless or redundant (depending on whether you'd read the linked page). I believe I was in favour of just linking it with a brief summary instead, but revising it to have fully formed ideas was an acceptable alternative. - Rainwarrior (talk) 12:21, 4 May 2016 (MDT)

Non-NES compression algorithms

Details about compression used in commercial games for another platform other than NES has nothing to do there, in my opinion. Only designs which are useful for either homebrew development or romhacking existing games or using them as inspiration for homebrew is useful. 178.196.73.155 14:25, 20 August 2016 (MDT)

Why would explaining how a compression format for another CPU of comparable computational ability not belong here? We're not describing LZMA. —Lidnariq (talk) 18:12, 20 August 2016 (MDT)

Compression formats are separated from the CPU encoding or decoding them, so there is no problem describing any format. However, explaining the details how a particular game compress its data do, in my opinion, not belong here, but to the data crystal romhacking wiki.

Bregalad (talk) 13:31, 22 August 2016 (MDT)

I should think that the note about GBA/DS video memory doesn't really belong here, because it is not applicable to NES/Famicom, even if the same format may be used. --Zzo38 (talk) 16:22, 22 August 2016 (MDT)

Talk:UNIF

Add UNIF board documentation?

What do people think of adding documentation on the various UNIF MAPRs that don't have iNES encapsulations? I randomly stumbled across Quietust's Drip game and it might be nice to have documentation that's not just part of (e.g.) Nintedulator's source.

Should they go in subpages under UNIF? e.g. UNIF/UNL-DRIPGAME ? If so, do we want to refile all the iNES mappers to subpages also? —Lidnariq (talk) 15:55, 29 April 2014 (MDT)

Dead UNIF, dirty CaH4e3

With the deprecation of UNIF, how do we denote the custom mapper used for Quietust's port of Drip (UNL-DRIPGAME) and CaH4e3's dumps of pirate games? Does this mean the East Asian plane of NES 2.0 will finally see some action? --Tepples (talk) 07:25, 11 April 2015 (MDT)

I have already wanted to assign a mapper number to UNL-DripGame (as well as Game Genie, but that's a completely different issue). None has been assigned yet. They didn't want to assign a iNES mapper number, therefore I recommend to put into plane 1 instead of plane 0, for this reason. (I also recommend not using plane 0 for any new mappers that require NES 2.0 features.) --Zzo38 (talk) 11:09, 11 April 2015 (MDT)

Personally, I think Koitsu's deprecation of UNIF—and let's be clear, this is his action, not anything else—isn't in good faith. If he wanted to mark it deprecated, that's news to the current maintainer of the standard, and clearly in reaction to zxbdragon's reverse-engineering work. To be perfectly blunt: making a complete GoodNES-like tool and database is a non-negotiable prerequisite to being able to consider UNIF deprecated. Anything else is just posturing.—Lidnariq (talk) 12:46, 11 April 2015 (MDT)

This seems like it's more à propos of the[/a] forum, but I agree with Lidnariq: this seems unilateral. If the current maintainer is someone else, and it's still in use in a meaningful sector (like these dumpers) then it doesn't really make sense for the original guy to be permitted to torpedo it, any more than it would make sense for Marat Fayzullin to be allowed to declare iNES format deprecated. UNIF seems like it has at least one point over [i]NES[_2.0]: there's less need for a central authority to decide where to place mappers, as one just uses the board-name. Myask (talk) 16:16, 3 May 2015 (MDT)

Talk:UNROM 512

iNES number

What is the iNES number for this? Do you need submapper numbers for one-screen mirroring mode and flashing configuration? What are the jumpers for configuring CHR RAM? --Zzo38 (talk) 06:30, 1 April 2014 (MDT)

Was planning on having this as iNES number 30. The flashing configuration is enabled by the iNES battery flag, and the one-screen mirroring is done by setting the four-screen mirroring flag. If the rom is using NES 2.0, then the non-battery backed CHR RAM field is used to specify how much CHR Ram is enabled.
As for the jumpers that configure the CHR Ram, there is 4 of them on the board. Two of them tie the respective CHR-RAM address lines to Vcc, and the other two tie the respective CHR Ram lines to the 377 outputs. Basically, for 8KB, both CHR-RAM lines are tied to Vcc, for 16KB, only one of them is tied to Vcc, and for 32KB, none of them are tied to Vcc. Caitsith2 (talk) 08:50, 1 April 2014 (MDT)
I have formed a [patch] for FCEUX that both puts the mapper as 30, and implements NES 2.0. Caitsith2 (talk) 09:01, 1 April 2014 (MDT)

OK, now it makes sense; no submapper numbers are needed. The jumpers would then be to make the board act as if there is less CHR RAM than there actually is (I suppose, it is in case you have a ROM image that specifies only 8K (or 16K) CHR RAM, and you will want to use it with the existing board). I further suppose, then, I would guess that you would set the PRG RAM sizes in the NES 2.0 header (at least one of which is zero) to put into $6000-$7FFF, which would seem to be the default specification of such a thing (although FCEUX and some others may not necessarily implement it), if not otherwise specified; since battery bit means something else with this mapper, these PRG battery/non-battery RAM would be separate from flashed ROM (although, probably you should not install battery RAM anyways, in case something is mixed up due to that). --Zzo38 (talk) 17:17, 1 April 2014 (MDT)

No wram is installed. Both of the NES 2.0 wram header fields are 0 on this board. Also, there is no means to battery back the CHR ram, so its battery field is set to 0. The only thing specified is the non-battery CHR ram size. It should be technically possible to make a board that uses wram. Just to highlight, the xmas 2013 board will play nicely with this mapper as well, as there is another 377 wired on the $8000-BFFF bank, to control the LEDs, with no conflicting effects on that boards self flashability. Caitsith2 (talk) 17:41, 1 April 2014 (MDT)

"one-screen mirroring is done by setting the four-screen mirroring flag." That seems perverse. Can we make hardwired 1scr a NES2.0 setting? Like, (4scr&vert) = (1scr)? Myask (talk) 00:15, 23 August 2016 (MDT)

Suggest responding elsewhere to keep this conversation in one place, specifically here: Talk:NES_2.0#Mirroring bits and one-screen mirroring - Rainwarrior (talk) 11:51, 23 August 2016 (MDT)

Name confusion?

I know the RetroUSB board says "UNROM 512" on it, but I feel there's confusion between this and just UxROM with 512k (which is a subset of features, maybe?). Maybe "Sealie UNROM 512" instead? Maybe it doesn't matter and we should just embrace the confusion. :P (Also funny to me: the Sealie UNROM 512 boards I have incorrectly say "ReproPak MMC3" on the back.) - Rainwarrior (talk) 13:16, 22 August 2016 (MDT)

I agree. For me "UNROM-512" would be mapper #2 with either 512 kbits (64 kiB, 4 banks) or with 512 kiB (32 banks), but probably the former since the number usually refers kilobits, as in NROM-128 and NROM-256. I know the confusion between UNROM and mapper #2, which are two different things, comes from very early days of NESDEV and has been going on since. (i.e. Crazy climber is not mapper #2 but is UNROM, Maniac Mansion (J) is mapper #2 and not UNROM). But this name adds yet another unnecessary confusion on an already confusing name. Bregalad (talk) 13:40, 22 August 2016 (MDT)

Talk:UxROM

@lidnariq : Seriously, this paragraph was a bunch of shit, it is speculatively mentionning non-existant oversize variations, speculatively mentionning a multicart that never existed and speculatively talked about a non-existing mapper that isn't even mapper #2, cloning the SUROM behaviour but without a MMC1. Why did you re-insert it ? Is it any valuable when it comes to doccumenting the existing games/hardware and mappers ? Is the goal of this wiki to doccument existing things, or to speculate about what could have been done ? Bregalad (talk) 05:09, 18 March 2014 (MDT)

By now I'm starting to agree with you that because emulators have standardized on the behavior with the additional 7432, SUROM-style behavior belongs in a separate page, just as other multicart mappers get their own. Let Farid do what he does best. --Tepples (talk) 11:37, 18 March 2014 (MDT)

The entire point was that the cost of the second 74'32 can be exchanged for having every 16th bank be identical.
This is no different in scope than using an inverter to prevent bus conflicts.
Since UxROM uses discrete logic, it continues to be a perfectly viable target for physical production.
Saying the sole purpose of the wiki is to describe what was is to say that the sole purpose of the wiki is for archiving details necessary for emulation.
Finally, if you want me to take you seriously, try not cussing. —Lidnariq (talk) 12:56, 18 March 2014 (MDT)

Even if describing only what was, if it was used in a known homebrew, that makes it relevant (though it is stupid that the "known" homebrew was not named in the text, which seems in contradiction with "known"). I do think it's worth mentioning practical extensions of a mapper, provided they are clear-cut and natural extension, and not merely one of a billion other irrelevant possibilities. In this particular case, I think 512k UxROM is worth mentioning, but I don't think it's good to offer 5 different recipes for building the hardware. That's more confusing than it is helpful. We should not give users advice and alternatives based on the potential cost of chips, for example. That's a discussion to be had on the forums for the benefit of someone who actually wants to build it. For the wiki, this kind of stuff is just noise inhibiting comprehension of the page. - Rainwarrior (talk)

What exactly do you think the sections of a wiki page are for? It's not like the average person visiting the page is going to care about the Hardware section.
For that matter, why leave the comments about the 7402 or 74157 if you're worried about confusing the poor little naïf of a reader?
Nintendo released three boards (UNROM, UOROM, UN1ROM, and m180) of the relevant type. All used one 74161 and one quad 2-input logic gate.
Emulator authors decided that the platonic ideal of mapper 2 is "one bank switched, one bank fixed to the last one". But this is emulator-centric thinking.
Because BK2 was developed in an emulator, of course it counts as works like the emulators say it does.
So it's equally plausible that the concept represented by UxROM is "one quad OR gate and one latch", the same as the vast majority of the other discrete logic mappers with more than 4 bits of state.
Note that I'm arguing about UxROM (hardware), not mapper 2 (emulators). —Lidnariq (talk) 21:08, 19 March 2014 (MDT)

My objection has nothing to do with preferring emulation information to hardware information. I think it's great to have good info about the hardware. My objection is to needless speculation and hypothetical implementations. The hardware diagram and description on this page is great, at least where it's describing the actual board used. The moment it starts speculating about different ways to build it are where I think we've gone off track. "A 74HC02 quad NOR gate can be used instead..." begins a hypothetical design situation (unless you are describing actual practice used by some games, in which case please say so in the text). "If an actual multiplexer (74HC157 quad 2:1) is cheaper..." is not relevant to how this board works. I would be similarly opposed if someone were to add to the page 4 different C++ implementions of the mapper, along with commentary about the strengths and weaknesses of each approach. The 512k variant is relevant, and it needs to be mentioned, but this is not the place to hash out all the permutations of possibly ways to design its hardware. Do that on the forums for the benefit of someone who is actually having trouble building it. - Rainwarrior (talk) 23:27, 19 March 2014 (MDT)

Also, maintaining relevance on the page is for naive and experienced readers alike, my statements about comprehensibility aren't about the skill level of the reader. Keeping the pages organized is important for anyone trying to find the information they need. For example, trying to incorporate and eliminate redundant Disch notes is important because a thorough author trying to implement a mapper correctly will read the entire page to make sure he didn't miss something. It wastes the time of all readers to clutter the page with redundant or irrelevant text, not just the inexperienced ones. - Rainwarrior (talk) 23:52, 19 March 2014 (MDT)

There is plenty of other advisory content elsewiki. e.g. Programming with unofficial opcodes, PRG RAM circuit, and 6502 assembly optimisations, and I see no reason this wiki should contain solely descriptive pages. —Lidnariq (talk) 12:15, 21 March 2014 (MDT)

These three pages are all exclusively about this kind of content, though. In that respect they are well organized. I think all of the mapper pages should primarily be descriptive reference. The PRG RAM circuit page is a good example of material that would be bad to insert into a mapper page, even though this is information about how to build part of a mapper. - Rainwarrior (talk) 23:17, 21 March 2014 (MDT)

So how do you answer a question that a person doesn't know they can ask? This is the kind of information for which to ask the question is to already know the answer. Saying that "that information belongs in the forum" is equivalent to saying "that information doesn't belong anywhere at all". —Lidnariq (talk) 19:14, 24 March 2014 (MDT)

I don't understand that logic. This wiki is full of links to the forums for content that is related but too involved or special-purpose for the wiki article. - Rainwarrior (talk) 20:23, 24 March 2014 (MDT)

So you're saying you're ok with something to the effect of "Other oversize variants are possible" which is a link to a forum post? —Lidnariq (talk) 12:42, 25 March 2014 (MDT)

Absolutely. I'd also be fine with a discrete logic mapper design tutorial as its own wiki article, or some other way to organize this content. I'm not opposed to the content, just its inclusion here on this page. Where there is a single canonical hardware implementation of a mapper, I think it's fine to have on a mapper page. When it becomes a how-to description of many possibilities, I think this belongs somewhere else. - Rainwarrior (talk) 10:14, 26 March 2014 (MDT)

Exactly what Rainwarrior said. Anything with the last bank which is not fixed in not mapper #2 and even less UxROM and have nothing to do on this page. "Oversize" variants are worth mentioning and they are already mentioned outside of this useless and confusing paragraph. Anyone with any tad of knownledge of electronics will know several ways of implementing them, there is no need to explain how to implement everything that "could be done" on this wiki.

Bregalad (talk) 01:07, 19 March 2014 (MDT)

Well, I think it's great time we find a concensus, about what exactly terms like SxROM, UxROM, AxROM means, what should be described on which page and how. I'm not caring about naive readers, I'm just caring about myself, as I'm a ego-centric person ^^ And, more seriously, yes, the average person visiting here *will* care about the hardware information. In my opinion (which is not agreed by everyone) the term "UxROM" refers purely to a set of hardware PCBs, while the term "mapper #2" refers to the concept you have one bankswitching register to bankswitch to switch $8000-$bfff, and the last bank fixed at $c000-$ffff. There is literally infinite ways to implement this on hardware, and anyone knowing digital electronics is going to be able to do it. I can do it with 74 series chips, a PAL, a CPLD, a FPGA, with a microcontroller which is a couple of times faster than the NES, or with plain transistors if I feel like it. I could even implement this with a non-power of two ROM size, the concept works just as well. Documenting how Nintendo (and possibly other companies) implemented the mapper is very relevant. Documenting every possibility of implementation is not, as you could always find another one.Bregalad (talk) 01:35, 20 March 2014 (MDT)

In fact I think that's a great idea : Let's put one wiki page with all the ideas to make discrete logic mappers, and leave other pages free of them. That way the info is on the wiki, and it doesn't interfere with software mappers or Nitendo's boards info. Bregalad (talk) 06:38, 28 March 2014 (MDT)

74HC02 in Metal Gear (USA)

I wonder why is an additional 74HC02 (quad NOR gate) chip doing on the PCB of Metal Grear (USA). My random wild guess would be it disables bus conflicts by inverting PRG-R/W, can anyone confirm or infirm this ?

Why not use only a single 74HC02 as the main OR gate (by reordering PRG banks to compensate the unwanted inversion after OR-ing adress lines) and to disable bus conflicts, then ? Bregalad (talk) 04:27, 6 May 2014 (MDT)

Talk:Visual circuit tutorial

Contents

1 Cross-coupled inverter
2 Some possible NMOS clarifications
3 Pictures
4 "Open" and "closed" terminology
5 Steady state and voltage vs. current
6 Redraws
7 PLA
8 Circuit notation
9 Sizing

Cross-coupled inverter

Is that actually an S-R latch? vis. http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/File:R-S_mk2.gif —Lidnariq (talk) 12:46, 24 May 2013 (MDT)

Some possible NMOS clarifications

It might be possible to make "in NMOS, transistors are placed in a substrate of n-doped semiconductor" clearer. Does "transistor" here refer to the entire diffusion + poly combo (so that diffusion + poly together are placed on the substrate), or does the n-doped semiconductor make up (or interact with) some particular part of the transistor (like the diffusion, or the polysilicon)? -Ulfalizer (talk) 23:43, 27 May 2013 (MDT)

I misremembered about the substrate; it's a lightly p-doped substrate, vis wikipedia:File:CMOS fabrication process.svg. So I fixed that. The transistor is the sum of all its parts: the substrate (or "body"), both the source and drain N-doped diffusion, the layer of quartz insulator beneath the gate and the layer of polysilicon that is the gate. Arguably it's also the metal or polysilicon vias to the source and drain. Also wikipedia:File:CMOS NAND Layout.svg. Because the gate is placed before the diffusion, the region immediately under the gate is actually not very doped— hence "substrate". —Lidnariq (talk) 00:51, 28 May 2013 (MDT)

I'm happy with the current description then. Gives the general idea without lying or getting bogged down in details (which might be overkill for someone needing to look up "NMOS" in an article like this). -Ulfalizer (talk) 01:03, 28 May 2013 (MDT)

Pictures

Sorry if the page is getting a bit heavy. I guess some of the pictures could be converted to JPEG or a lower bit depth with no big loss. As should be clear from some of the images I'm not exactly a professional illustrator, so recommendations are welcome :P. Thanks for sharpening up those pictures btw! -Ulfalizer (talk) 05:41, 28 May 2013 (MDT)

I think the Best solution is figuring out how to get SVGs out. Those would compress very well, given the subject matter. Next best (and hopefully slightly more practical?) is to figure out how to get firefox/chrome to stop antialiasing the polygons in Visual2X0X. Without the blurry edges, a palettized PNG will be both easy and compress a lot. Finally, I don't think converting to JPEG will help with this—it's best at large regions of comparatively smoothly fading surfaces.—Lidnariq (talk) 11:57, 28 May 2013 (MDT)

I played with it for a bit, and have a few answers. You'll need a locally-downloaded version, because you'll be making a few local changes to the source.

To fix blur on really deep zooms (= disable bilinear filtering), in expert.css, in the section "canvas.chip", add this line for firefox: image-rendering: -moz-crisp-edges; or the equivalent line mentioned here: https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Web/CSS/image-rendering for your browser (But! it's not working for me using chrome 26)
To reduce blur on diagonal lines (usually polysilicon), in wires.js, in the function "setupBackground", add these two lines after the "getContext" call: ctx.mozImageSmoothingEnabled = false; and ctx.webkitImageSmoothingEnabled = false
To increase the maximum zoom possible and even out irregular pixel spacing, in expertWires.js, near the top, change "grCanvasSize=5000" to some larger value. (for me 20000 breaks horribly. 10000 seems reasonable for getting pretty screenshots) —Lidnariq (talk) 01:43, 29 May 2013 (MDT)

Thanks for the tips! Planning to add a section on those PLA-like circuits (preferably after I figure out what they're actually called :P), but after that I might do a picture clean-up pass. -Ulfalizer (talk) 02:52, 29 May 2013 (MDT)

I've already increased grCanvasSize multiple times - Visual6502 had it set to 2000, and I initially doubled it to 4000 for 2A03/2C02 (because they're much larger) and then just recently boosted it further to 5000. Increasing it further has the side effect of drastically increasing memory usage - setting it to 6000 will make it use a gigabyte of RAM. Also, increasing the actual maximum zoom level is done by adjusting grMaxZoom. --Quietust (talk) 07:13, 29 May 2013 (MDT)

Well, that would explain why 20000 caused chromium to simply refuse and firefox to eat All My Memory... For whatever reason, for me using 10000 is "only" causing firefox to take (1.145g-240m) resident and (1.36g-692m) virtual; chromium eats (1.6g-60m) resident and (2.7g-1.6g) virtual (debian sid x86-64) —Lidnariq (talk) 11:55, 29 May 2013 (MDT)

Another thing that might help, although it does change the appearance a bit, is in "setupBackground", comment out if((c==0)||(c==6)) ctx.stroke(); (prepend with //). This makes the metal (and polysilicon??) be flat shaded without a border. —Lidnariq (talk) 15:55, 29 May 2013 (MDT)

By the way, what program are you using to add the labels? —Lidnariq (talk) 16:54, 30 May 2013 (MDT)

Ad-hoc in Inkscape. I just embed the screenshot and put shapes and text on top of it. I could make an archive of the .svg's if you want; then you'd only need to replace the background image. -Ulfalizer (talk) 20:28, 30 May 2013 (MDT)

I would definitely appreciate that! —Lidnariq (talk) 00:36, 31 May 2013 (MDT)

Here you go: https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/20047039/vis_tut_svgs.tar.bz2 . I removed the transparent borders some of the images had (I goofed up on those) and tweaked the text size a bit in vis_crossreg.svg. vis_oam_left.svg might be unnecessarily tall too... -Ulfalizer (talk) 01:13, 31 May 2013 (MDT)

"Open" and "closed" terminology

I switched it around after some feedback in http://forum.6502.org/viewtopic.php?f=1&t=2522, but I'm not so sure anymore. What's your take on it? Unless it's "wrong", I prefer the old version (since I'm used to it :P). -Ulfalizer (talk) 02:56, 31 May 2013 (MDT)

Switched back to the old version for now. -Ulfalizer (talk) 03:14, 31 May 2013 (MDT)

It kinda makes the definitions circular, but you could use "conducting" and "nonconducting"; or maybe "in saturation" and "in cutoff" since they're FETs (even if it's rather jargony). Having read the thread at 6502.org, it looks like you can't win with "open" and "closed", though. Alternatively, just define your terms at the beginning and blame the reader when they confuse them :p —Lidnariq (talk) 12:12, 31 May 2013 (MDT)

Or we could borrow relay terminology: a FET can be in a "make" or "break" state. --Tepples (talk) 14:45, 31 May 2013 (MDT)

So for something like "the diffusion area from which current will flow when the gate is <?> is called the source", <?> could be

"open" - Door analogy.
"closed" - Switch analogy. Kinda confusing (at least for me) given that "gate" is a door analogy.
"on" - Easier to confuse as part of the sentence - "on top of what?". Could use italics, but that's kinda ugly to have to do in lots of places.
"conducting" - Pretty long and specific word to use all over the place. "Open" feels better there.
"made" (?) - Sounds a bit weird. :P
"high" - Works decently, but you still need another form for stuff like "when the gate is opened".

I might be giving this too much thought, but I still kinda like "open". Could just mention the terminology caveat I guess. Can't find a clear winner on the Googles. -Ulfalizer (talk) 23:22, 31 May 2013 (MDT)

Steady state and voltage vs. current

Re. the change from

"if any of the gates in red circles are open (high), the current from the highlighted node will go to ground instead of to the gate in the blue circle on the top"

to

"if any of the gates in red circles are open (high), the voltage of the highlighted node will be pulled to ground instead of pulled high"

(with comment "in steady state, the current doesn't really 'go' anywhere."):

Is the first version really factually wrong? I realize that you can model it as the entire node having a single "state" in steady state, but isn't what actually happens as in the first description? As a beginner I find currents simpler to think about than voltages, and beginners are the target audience. -Ulfalizer (talk) 11:54, 1 June 2013 (MDT)

I guess "the current from the power source" might be more precise though. -Ulfalizer (talk) 12:10, 1 June 2013 (MDT)

The current doesn't "go to" the transmission gate. A voltage is present at the transmission gate. A current could go through the transmission gate while it's conducting. But you can't have a current of water "to" a glass meaning "sitting in". —Lidnariq (talk) 12:20, 1 June 2013 (MDT)

Ah, so the problem you had with it was that no current will flow through the pass transistor when it is closed, even if all the grounding transistors are closed? Yeah, that makes the old description a bit iffy for that case at least... -Ulfalizer (talk) 12:34, 1 June 2013 (MDT)

I guess you have to be careful when talking about current in general here, as you'll only have a current until the steady state is reached in cases where the current doesn't go to ground. Didn't think of that until now. -Ulfalizer (talk) 13:49, 1 June 2013 (MDT)

Should prolly keep the description for the inverter as-is though. Absolutely technically correct might be the enemy of beginner-friendly in that case I think, unless you have any ideas. -Ulfalizer (talk) 13:59, 1 June 2013 (MDT)

Describing things using "current" instead of "voltage" is sufficiently less wrong when you're talking about exclusively NMOS logic that I'm not bothered by it. Transmission gates or CMOS logic are where the pedantry starts actually changing meaning. —Lidnariq (talk) 14:47, 1 June 2013 (MDT)

Redraws

Thanks for (and sorry about) dropping the rewrite on you with the changed figure (Vis_crossreg.png) — I'd just finished and then had to run out the door. —Lidnariq (talk) 14:47, 1 June 2013 (MDT)

No problem. I just assumed you had forgotten (like I tend to do :P). -Ulfalizer (talk) 14:49, 1 June 2013 (MDT)

I like the combined DRAM picture by the way. Probably would've drawn it that way if I had been less lazy when doing the original ones. -Ulfalizer (talk) 01:09, 2 June 2013 (MDT)

I think I'm going to revisit some of the highlighting. I showed my partner the images, but they had problems picking out what counted as "highlighted" vs "not". —Lidnariq (talk) 14:40, 4 June 2013 (MDT)

PLA

The length counter lookup table is currently being described as a PLA with an AND and OR plane, but I'm not sure that's really correct - in the forum post on 6502.org (with regards to transistor open/closed terminology), several people pointed out that both "planes" are composed entirely of NOR gates. In reality, I don't think this is a PLA at all: it's just a 5->32 (N -> 2N) decoder followed by a NOR-based mask ROM. The defining characteristic of a PLA is its ability to implement arbitrary combinational logic circuits, and the instances of this pattern in the RP2A03 aren't really used in this manner - there are 3 lookup tables (length counter, noise frequency, PCM frequency), 1 address decoder ($4000-$401F), and a very specific 15->6 decoder (for the frame counter). The RP2C02's H and V decoders are a bit more similar to the state decoder in the 6502, but they still aren't really PLAs, and the others are also just ordinary decoders (2->4 decoder for luma, 4->13 decoder for chroma, and the $2000-$2007 R/W decoder). --Quietust (talk) 12:46, 2 June 2013 (MDT)

Yeah, wasn't sure of the right terminology here. PLA did seem a bit odd given that they're hardcoded rather than reprogrammable. I'll rewrite it in a while now that I know the correct terminology. -Ulfalizer (talk) 12:57, 2 June 2013 (MDT)

DeMorgan's law says a bunch of NOR gates are AND gates with inverted inputs. Since the AND plane is regular (a demultiplexer) instead of the OR plane does imply to me it's a ROM instead of a PAL, but the term "PLA" is apparently intentionally generic enough to mean both, and there is an established history of using ROMs as programmable logic. —Lidnariq (talk) 13:04, 2 June 2013 (MDT)

Yeah, my view when writing it was that it was an AND plane implemented with NOR gates. Perhaps that's not a common way to think about this particular circuitry though (I don't know). -Ulfalizer (talk) 13:22, 2 June 2013 (MDT)
I think I prefer the decoder + ROM mask version, as it introduces more terminology and might be a bit more correct (even if "PLA" might be colloquial). I could also point out the similarity with PLAs in a rewrite. The only downside is that the labels on the first image would need to be changed to say "5-to-32 decoder" and "Mask ROM". Would that be a lot of work? -Ulfalizer (talk) 13:40, 2 June 2013 (MDT)

Could send the image to gmail at ulfalizer (reverse :P) if you decide to redraw it, so it can be synched with the update to the text. -Ulfalizer (talk) 14:01, 2 June 2013 (MDT)

It is still an AND plane feeding into a NOR plane, regardless of where on the ROM/PLA/PAL spectrum it is. All the ROM word line selectors I have ever seen have all been implemented that way—anything else would be wasteful. Anyway, I've uploaded to File:Vis_len_rom.png a version with labels "Decoder" (5-to-32 wouldn't fit) and "Mask ROM". —Lidnariq (talk) 16:40, 2 June 2013 (MDT)

Circuit notation

I really like those equivalent schematic displays, as tying things back to electronics notation was one of the things I felt were missing. If there's a particular name for the notation used (with e.g. triangles for transistors), that would be good to mention too. -Ulfalizer (talk) 04:59, 4 June 2013 (MDT)

Wikipedia calls them "ANSI schematic symbols"… the triangle with a line coming in the side is the symbol for a tristateable buffer, which is vaguely misleading (because no buffering occurs). But it is the closest digital symbol equivalent. I originally drew that part with another multiplexer, but since apu_clk1 and w400e aren't strictly complements I thought better of it. —Lidnariq (talk) 14:40, 4 June 2013 (MDT)

Sizing

A high-level overview of diffusion and gate sizing would be nice to have towards the end of the article (after section six or seven or so). Often you see signals invert into others where it seems it wouldn't be necessary from a purely digital perspective, and mentioning things like that would be nice too (guessing it has to do with boosting the signal).

I'm moving on to some other stuff for a while, but feel free to jump in. :) -Ulfalizer (talk) 04:51, 5 June 2013 (MDT)

Could you give me a few node numbers/names to talk about? I haven't spent enough time staring at the simulators to have places in mind. —Lidnariq (talk) 14:18, 6 June 2013 (MDT)

Here's some off the top of my head:

CPU: The PCM mixer. Looking at pcm_out0 and pcm_out1, both have just one strip of powered diffusion, but the gate on pcm_out0 is thicker (presumably to create more resistance).
PPU: The superbuffers that pclk0_en and pclk1_en connect to, used to generate pclk0 and pclk1.
PPU: The thing used to introduce the different colors at the beginning of the article, also from the PPU, and also related to pclk0 and pclk1. Maybe it's to make really sure the signals stay nice inverses.

I don't have any examples from random logic off the top of my head unfortunately, as I haven't paid much attention while browsing around. At least the first one would probably make a good example at least. Might think of more later.
Some formulas would be okay too, if you know them and they're reasonably simple (stuff like how resistance relates to width and breadth of poly, etc.). -Ulfalizer (talk) 15:27, 6 June 2013 (MDT)

Talk:Vs. System

Is there a way to detect if the game is running on Vs. System or not (which also works in emulators)? In case I wanted to make up the game which can work coin-operated arcade game but also works without it if you put it in a ordinary cartridge? --Zzo38

You can always make a separate version for Vs. boards. It's not like you can plug a Famicom cartridge into a Vs. board or anything. But unless you're using Duck Hunt or Tennis, one problem with Vs. is that the colors are all scrambled, making it much harder to do decent fades. --Tepples 16:17, 7 October 2012 (MDT)

The page mentions that certain revisions of the PPU (RC2C05*) return a magic number in the lower bits of $2002 read. —Lidnariq 16:47, 7 October 2012 (MDT)

But then those are the ones that swap $2000 and $2001, so you pretty much have to make special builds for the 2C05. --Tepples 18:11, 7 October 2012 (MDT)

If they swap $2000 and $2001 then you might be able to detect that using sprite 0 hit, somehow. Switches might also be used to configure the palettes in case 2C04 is used. Does 2C04 have any differences from 2C03 other than the colors? I know you cannot put a Famicom cartridge in the Vs. boards, but you could replace the chips manually, or make a clone hardware with the same purpose of $4016,$4017,$4020 registers (I don't know if it might be possible to build such a clone hardware into a cartridge, controller ports, and expansions ports, to wire to the coin slots and so on?). --Zzo38 18:47, 7 October 2012 (MDT)

If you're replacing chips manually, and you know what kind of board you're replacing them into, why not just use a build specifically made for one Vs. board? I don't see the advantage of having one ROM image that runs on several fundamentally incompatible system boards. --Tepples 18:59, 7 October 2012 (MDT)

Well I suppose yes it could be made separate ROM images, one for not Vs. System, and other for the Vs. System boards. (Using conditional compiling, perhaps?). I still was interested to know if there is ways to detect it, though. --Zzo38 19:39, 7 October 2012 (MDT)

Between the part where you'll need 5 additional builds (4 palette scrambles, 1 $2000/$2001 swap) to accommodate all the different Vs hardware, and only have the ability to detect the last, it's not clear to me how to feasible autodetection (as opposed to different builds, DIP switch settings, asking the user, &c)—Lidnariq 10:36, 8 October 2012 (MDT)

I suppose best would be to simply have one normal ROM image and one arcade ROM image (using macros and conditional compilation), and to use either the switches (three would be needed, unless there is a way to distinguish 2C03 from 2C04 in general, in which case two is sufficient) or a service menu to select the palette? --Zzo38 (talk) 15:34, 28 April 2013 (MDT)

Coin acknowledgement

I finally noticed what seems to be the official Vs System schematic—http://nesdev.com/VSSCHEM.pdf —and noticed that the coin acknowledgement seems to actually only be NAND3($4000-$5FFF,A5,M2) (gate 4D, coordinates E5 or J5). Which means that the register 1- should react to reads as well as writes, and 2- is duplicated all over the place. I don't suppose we can get any kind of verification; should I just update the document?

Also, there's something funny involving $6000-$7FFF, OUT1, and IRQs in this schematic. It looks like the two CPUs have 2KiB of RAM that can be shared depending on the primary CPU's OUT1 pin. I guess Nocash already figured that out, though: http://problemkaputt.de/everynes.htm#vssystemcontrollers —Lidnariq (talk) 16:20, 18 April 2013 (MDT)

Service button

If anyone makes a new game using Vs. System, then instead of simply adding a credit, it can be used when held down, displaying a diagnostics menu (containing such things as number of games played since power on, idle time, palette test, $2002 readout, high score, last score, last game duration), and if other buttons are pushed while it is active, to do other things:

A and B = Change the colors. This can be used if the game is running on a different 2C04 variant than normal (altenatively, three switches can be used, especially if there is no save game file, then using the switches would be better). Sound test could also be done using these buttons.
START = Add a credit.
SELECT = Discard all credits.
Up/Down/Left/Right = Edit the high score.

This is just a suggestion and you can make the game do whatever you want with this; it doesn't have to be the above. --Zzo38 (talk) 15:34, 28 April 2013 (MDT)

Moniker

The kit manual (see link the Wiki page) refers to the device as the VS. UniSystem, not the Vs. Unisystem. Should we fix the character casing on the Wiki page?

Template talk:Infobox iNES mapper

Contents

1 Don't Repeat Yourself?
2 NesDB linking, non-1:1 issues
3 General improvements
4 Multi-infoboxes and suggestion about Overview purpose
5 CHR-RAM
6 Proposed field: Multicart mapper of...

Don't Repeat Yourself?

"If you provide nescartdbgames, it automatically inserts..." Is there a way to likewise automate/fold into the box Mappers with bus conflicts? Myask (talk) 16:52, 21 April 2015 (MDT)

Yes, once I figure out a bit more string manipulation to distinguish "yes" and "Yes" and "Y" from "no" and "No". --Tepples (talk) 19:26, 21 April 2015 (MDT)

NesDB linking, non-1:1 issues

I think it would be better if the template was just for "mapper" not "iNES mapper", simply because a lot of articles are organized around something other than iNES number (Nintendo board, multiple iNES, no iNES, etc.)

I think we need more comprehensive NesDB linking, as well. For each thing there are several relevant ways to search NesDB, and we should probably have all of them in the infobox. Also, there are much cleaner and succinct URLs you could be using, e.g.:

http://bootgod.dyndns.org:7777/search.php?unif=NES-CNROM
http://bootgod.dyndns.org:7777/search.php?ines=3

If an artice is about 3 different iNES mappers, it would ideally have a seachlink to each relevant iNES, should probably have a search link for each relevant board too. I dunno if the "number of games" is very useful either; not sure how often that changes, but if it's just copy pasted from the search result, it's easy to find it there. Seems like an annoying bit of extra maintenance; why do I need a number of games to create an NesDB link? I feel like the link text should have something to do with the mapper/board used for search, not some number you have to look up manually, maybe something like: NesDB [CNROM] -br- NesDB [iNES 001] -br- NesDB [iNES 185], I dunno.

Also, how come only the first iNES mapper number has leading 0s? - Rainwarrior (talk) 17:03, 21 April 2015 (MDT)

I dunno, just "number of games" seems a really strange thing to put in. I get that we want to have an idea of the relative frequency of the mapper, but the NesDB is full of regional duplicates, etc. it's really hairy to try and come up with a number that means what you might intuitively think it does. Actually following the link and using the database directly is a much better way to figure out what you need. The stats page is especially good for this: http://bootgod.dyndns.org:7777/stats.php - Rainwarrior (talk) 17:10, 21 April 2015 (MDT)

You technically don't need a number of games; you just need a non-empty string like "Few" or "Many". The query I'm using already removes region dupes. I'd put in support for multiple NesCartDB queries, but I'm still unsure of my skill in making variadic templates. And UNIF is officially dead. --Tepples (talk) 19:25, 21 April 2015 (MDT)

I don't think "few" or "many" is useful information. It's not information at all. It's useless. If you can't or won't meaningfully fill in a field, we shouldn't force nonsense into it. I also don't care at all what the status of "UNIF" is to you, but it's the search parameter for PCB names in NesDB, and it's a useful search parameter. Rather than making the template variadic, you could always just let the user type whatever stuff they want in that field and let them manually make links. This is one of the reasons I preferred the existing Overview section to an infobox: editing them for special cases is easy to understand. Adding all the special cases to the template is complicated and error-prone (i.e. anybody can edit wiki text, but probably only you should touch the complex template code you created). The other big reason is that we often need to make notes and qualifications about entries in the overview which are quite inappropriate for an infobox. I'm okay with the infobox, though, we just have to be careful not to sacrifice quality of information for the sake of the template. - Rainwarrior (talk) 20:07, 21 April 2015 (MDT)

"Few" or "many" is ideally something to put in when clicking "Show preview". And the special cases are why, for example, I left the free-text half of MMC5#Overview alone.

An alternative might be just to create a separate NesDB box, if that's easier than trying to wrangle it all into the infobox. - Rainwarrior (talk) 20:10, 21 April 2015 (MDT)

One more note, to search as 1-per region you can add "&group=groupid" to the search link, though I don't know if that's a good default. Different people would want different information, it's probably best to use the simplest (and most inclusive) form of the search. - Rainwarrior (talk) 20:17, 21 April 2015 (MDT)

I created a simple box for making multiple NesDB links. I have placed it on AxROM as an initial test with this edit. Please let me know if you have suggestions about it. Doing it this way might be easier than trying to work it into the infobox. I don't think the infobox can really handle multiple cases very well, most mappers have several relevant NesDB cases (various NES board types, one or more iNES mappers associated with the page, etc.) so it might be better to just have a simple "NesDB" box. It also automatically tags the In NesCartDB category as well. (Sorry if this is a duplicate of discussion at Category talk:In NesCartDB, not sure where the best place to ask is.) - Rainwarrior (talk) 14:11, 22 April 2015 (MDT)

General improvements

I fixed a bug in the template (prgmax check was looking at chrmax) - Koitsu (talk) 16:00, 22 April 2015 (PDT)

I disagree with some "assumptions" in the current logic in the template: 1) if prgmax is defined to blindly assume there's a prgpage default of unknown (recommended: don't bother printing the line at all if prgpage isn't explicitly set), 2) if chrmax isn't set to blindly assume 8K (I believe there are mappers which have no CHR) (recommended: don't bother printing the line at all if chrmax isn't explicitly set), 3) if chrmax is defined to blindly assume there's a chrpage default of 8K (recommended: don't bother printing the line at all if chrpage isn't explicitly set). Good examples of a couple of these are on the CNROM page which I've updated - Koitsu (talk) 16:00, 22 April 2015 (PDT)

I have made prgpage independent from prgmax and chrpage independent from chrmax. But mappers designed for use without CHR (Magic Floor, Game Genie) are such an edge case that chrmax=None ought to satisfy the template. --Tepples (talk) 16:23, 30 April 2015 (MDT)

Multi-infoboxes and suggestion about Overview purpose

Lidnariq is experimenting with multiple infoboxes at Namco 163: [1]

IMO this looks nightmarish, though it might not be so bad if the infoboxes could stack horizontally. However, I have a different suggestion.

It might be best to just keep the old "Overview" sections in addition to the infobox? PGCX864 made a series of Overview-to-infobox edits earlier that ended up erasing a bunch of subtle but important information, and a lot of this stuff it's hard to find a good place for when putting it back.

If we kept the Overview, sticking multiple mappers into a single infobox might not be such a problem. The Infobox would be just for a "quick overview" of what you're going to find in the article, and the Overview section itself can have the proper details.

For an example of what I mean, if we had a mapper article that has 3 mappers with different PRG-ROM capacities, the infobox would be inclusive with the information, and the overview section would resolve it in detail. The point of the infobox being a summary of the article, and the point of the overview being a detailed summary of all the mappers included.

Infobox:

PRG ROM capacity: | 64K / 128K / 512K

Overview:

Mapper A:
PRG ROM capacity: 64K
Mapper B:
PRG ROM capacity: 128K
Mapper C:
PRG ROM capacity: 512K

Alternative:

PRG ROM capacity: 64K (A), 128K (B), or 256K (C)

Whichever form seems to make more sense. Is this a sensible suggestion? Maybe the infobox isn't really a good alternative to the Overview sections, but rather a good supplement/addition to it. You know what I mean? At the same time, I think this would make it appropriate to move category tags back into the overview, rather than attempting to resolve all the cases with complex infobox code. - Rainwarrior (talk) 14:14, 23 April 2015 (MDT)

I'd be inclined to agree with leaving unusual Overview stuff in Overview. Notice that I left the Overview section in the MMC5 article because there was so much that would not fit in the infobox. --Tepples (talk) 14:31, 23 April 2015 (MDT)

CHR-RAM

I realize CHR-RAM is almost always an option via the iNES format, but on physical boards it's often not quite as trivial to go between ROM and RAM implementation. Shouldn't it be a line on this infobox? - Rainwarrior (talk) 19:18, 29 April 2015 (MDT)

Whether the PPU /WR line is available depends more on the board than on the mapper. Some boards have this pin on the cart edge, not connected to anything. This apparently includes all Famicom boards. As far as I can tell, modding these to take a 62256 in the CHR slot isn't harder than modding a game with Nintendo mask ROM pinout to use JEDEC flash in the CHR slot. Others, especially later NES boards, omit it to save some piddly amount of money per board. Hence the search for "full pin SMB2" (that is, early revisions of NES-TSROM) to mod into a TNROM-compatible donor for reproductions of translated Final Fantasy III. --Tepples (talk) 21:58, 29 April 2015 (MDT)

Okay, but my question was whether it should be included in the infobox. Some board-classes may have variants with and without CHR-RAM, but a lot of them were just one way or the other. It's a useful thing to know about a mapper (whether it is a single-board mapper, or a class-of-boards mapper) that it had CHR-RAM always, sometimes, or never. We've had Category:Mappers with CHR RAM for a long time, and I've thought it was good knowledge to have. - Rainwarrior (talk) 14:52, 30 April 2015 (MDT)

My fear is that emulator authors might misinterpret such a declaration in the infobox as meaning that a particular class of boards can never have CHR RAM, and any homebrew program that uses CHR RAM necessarily exhibits what the C programming language standard calls "undefined behavior". It'd have to be carefully worded to avoid this. I find this important because I'm working with another programmer on an NES project that uses CHR RAM with a mapper that had used only CHR ROM during the NES's commercial era. --Tepples (talk) 16:02, 30 April 2015 (MDT)

If you're afraid that emulator authors are going to do something stupid, you should advise them against it in a much more direct way, not with some passive organization of infobox article summaries. The iNES format makes CHR-RAM optional for every mapper, unless there is some structural conflict (maybe this should be stated explicitly on the iNES article, and possibly in the "mappers with CHR RAM" category text). This wiki is for more than emulator authors, it is for anyone involved in NES development, anyone who wants to do research on boards and mappers, and all sorts of other uses. Knowing which boards were used for CHR-RAM is important. - Rainwarrior (talk) 17:07, 30 April 2015 (MDT)

Also I might as well recommend a move to: Template:Infobox mapper since we don't (and shouldn't) organize the mapper articles per-iNES. - Rainwarrior (talk) 15:08, 30 April 2015 (MDT)

Such a naming would imply that this infobox shall be made no longer specific to mappers that have had an iNES number assigned. What would go in the mapper number entry for a mapper that lacks a number or has an NES 2.0 number greater than 255? --Tepples (talk) 16:02, 30 April 2015 (MDT)

Well, all of the infoboxes created so far are about a board-class rather than an iNES mapper specifically. Why shouldn't mappers that aren't iNES have infoboxes too? I don't really understand this restriction. It should be optional. Also, the decision to exclude "NES 2.0" from being an "iNES mapper" is tremendously pedantic and silly at face value. iNES mappers are easily categorized already by the mapper grid, the iNES mapper category, and the redirect pages for iNES mappers that are better described under some other category. I don't think the infobox actually helps this organization; the infobox is to make it easier to survey mappers at a glance. It's a page-summary, not a categorization or organization of pages. The content of the mapper articles should dictate the needs of the infobox, not the other way around. - Rainwarrior (talk) 17:02, 30 April 2015 (MDT)

In any case, it seems odd that there is no way to include this staple-of-Overview-section datum...and if a new variant is made with a different configuration, that's a new "board variant" (even if it's only on emulator), and the information can be updated. Until then, it seems prudent to stick to extant/used variants in our descriptions, just like we do with mapper numbers. Myask (talk) 15:41, 3 May 2015 (MDT)

Proposed field: Multicart mapper of...

An optional field to show which mappers a multicart mapper can encompass would be handy, I feel. (As would a category for multicart mappers.) Myask (talk) 16:12, 28 May 2015 (MDT)